[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Okay, well, welcome to lecture four of CS193P,
Stanford Winter of 2015.
So, I've been doing all demo up until now,
and now we're going to be doing all slides today.
So, I have a lot of stuff to talk about most of this,
although not all of it,
is covered in your reading assignments, mh okay?
But here I'm going to
try to highlight the things that are pretty important, and
also just show you some stuff that are not in
that reading assignment that you kinda need to know.
So this is definitely not a substitute for
the reading you'll still need to do the reading in order to
kinda get the, the details of a lot of this stuff.
So but this hopefully will kinda get you focused in on,
on the key stuff.
All right, [COUGH] so first, I wanna talk about
optionals and enums, so now that you know what an enum is.
I can tell you what an Optional really is okay?
An Optional is just an enum, okay?
It's a very simple enum it's a generic kind of like array.
You know, have an array,
you specify the type of thing in it,
Optional's exactly the same, okay?
It's a generic.
You specify the type of Optional it is.
And that type, which is T here in this little enum,
is just the type of the associated value, you know,
that enums can have associated values.
So that's just the type that, if the optional is not nil.
That's what you get so that's all an enum is and
so for example, this is what it would look like if we
used the enum notation to do an optional.
Saying you know, x which is an enum or is an optional string,
which nil would just be saying x equals optional,
angle bracket string dot none.
Okay?
Or, if you're sending it to not be know you
would say optional angle bracket string dot some,
parentheses, the associated value, which would be hello.
That make sense?
So Optional really actually super simple.
With a question mark and exclamation point,
I know that makes it seem like, it's just so
really complicated, but it's pretty simple really it's just
syntax sugar, syntactic sugar to do this Optional.
Now the unwrapping, really just looks like this It's just
a switch and the case of sum, you give the value back.
In the case of none, you raise an exception, okay?
And simple as that.
That's why it crashes when you unwrap something that's
nil, okay?
So that's optional all right, so array, I just wanna.
We covered this so I'm gonna really fast through this but
arrays, the syntax there is the same, right?
That square bracket thing,
that means exactly the same thing.
Also you can't append or modify in any way
an array that is a let, right, that's a constant array.
I just wanna make it clear that defining an array to
be a constant by saying let something equal
an array versus var something equal an array,
means that it's immutable, so you can't do append or insert,
or anything else that you could do on a mutable array.
Also, of course,
if you access an array with the square brackets and
try to pull out something that's outside the bounds of
the array, this array only has four animals in it and
I'm trying to get animal five that's gonna crash.
Array index out of bounds,
just like pretty much any language you've used.
How to enumerate an array.
If you wanted to go through every single item
in an array and look at it, you can use four in, okay?
So you just say four, some variable you want,
in your array, and then inside there,
that'll be your value, okay pretty obvious.
I put this here mostly to compare it to the next slide,
which is dictionary so dictionary again,
that's where a bracket thing is an alternate for
the exact same thing so if I had a nice
dictionary here I can create a dictionary.
Using this square bracket notation,
which is just square bracket, key colon value, comma
key colon value okay, you know that.
And you also know that if I access a dictionary with
the square bracket, it returns an optional and
that's because, for example here, I'm looking up PAC ten
team Ohio State obviously that is not.
It packed ten team so it's not in the dictionary.
So it's going to return nil, okay?
So, that's why when you access a dictionary,
it comes back it's an Optional.
To enumerate dictionary you use a tuple.
Okay, so you say four, the tuple,
key com of value in the dictionary.
And inside there, key and value will both be set.
Okay, that's really easy way to enumerate dictionaries.
Sent all right I'm gonna teaching about new struct that
you haven't seen called range a range is just two points.
Of a sensible type, so a starting point and an ending
point is exactly what you think a range would be.
Now I say a sensible type here because, you know,
the sensible type depends on what you're talking about for
an array, the sensible type is an int,
but for other things like a string, it's not, and
we're gonna talk about that in a minute.
Range is also a generic, just like array or
like that Optional enom.
And so it takes the type of thing so the range again that,
to specify a range in an array would be range, angle bracket,
int because ints are how you index an array.
So, if you were gonna specify a range in
an array they would be ints, okay?
And it's approximately what I put here it's
not exactly this, but as far as given what, you know,
so far this is the best I can describe it to you.
It's just a struck that has a start index and end index and
it is a struck you can go and get those values and
set those values out of there so
array's range would be a range of Int string it's,
you would think that string would also be.
You see sub ranges of strings would also be specified by
an int, but in not, it not.
There's a special type called string.index,
which is an index into a string,
I'm gonna talk all about that in a later slide, okay?
So ranges, just like arrays and
dictionaries, we don't usually say range, angle bracket,
int equals something we use this special syntax.
And the special syntax is this three dots, or
two dots and a less than sign.
Okay, so the three dots means a range from the first thing,
oh, no, on the left of the dots, to the other thing on
the right of the dots that's the start index and
the end index, and it includes them both.
Includes both the start and end, whereas the other one,
two dot dot less than means it includes the first one, but
it does not include the second one.
So it's an open-ended range, okay cuz those,
both of those kind of ranges are common.
So that's how we specify a range 99% of the time,
we don't use the range struct to do it
although you can you could create a range struct.
And you could pass it as an argument to anything that
takes these dot, dot, dots you could put an actual range in
there as well, okay they're the same thing.
It's just the dot, dot,
dots are syntaxed to create that range for you, okay and
the things on either side of the dot, dot, dot.
You know, it depends on
what kind of range you're trying to create.
If you're creating an Int range.
A range of angle bracket int, then they'd be ints, okay?
But if you're doing a string,
they have to be string.indexes.
And that's a little harder to create, because a string.index
can't be created from a numeric literal.
You have to create it programmatically, so
we'll talk about that.
In about ten slides or so okay and
you can enumerate a range using four end just like we
can with our raising dictionaries there okay?
All right,
other classes, besides araised dictionaries range NSObject.
So NSObject was the the base class for
all of Objective C classes.
In Swift we don't really have a base class for
all Swift classes.
however, there are some kind of advanced features in
iOS that require,
even your Swift class to inherit from NSObject.
I can't really talk about them,
because there's other things you need to know for
me to even explain them to you but
down the road that will happen.
It really doesn't hurt to make your swift class be
a subclass of NSObject, so we could have
made calculator brain be a subclass of NSObject.
Wouldn't hurt, and
in the future, once we learn these advance things,
it'd be nice to be able to do those advanced features with
calculator brain so it's kinda one.
Can feel free I'm not sure what to
say the best practice here is to always have your Swift
classes inherit from NSObject all the classes in iOS,
like UIViewController, and
all those, they all inherit from NSObject eventually.
It's the super class of all of them [COUGH] there's not
really much in NSObject anymore that matters.
But like I say, there's these advanced features but
then there's NSNumber,
you've actually briefly seen NSNumber NSNumber is
just a generic number holding class, it just holds a number.
That's all it does on it has a ton of methods on and I'm not
gonna go through and here you can look in the documentation.
But, the methods are things like Double value.
Int value which is give me your value of yourself as
an Int, as a Double etc.
In Swift, we don't really use this very much,
because it's strongly typed and,
so we're using types like Int and double.
But in Objective C APIs, there's no NSNumbers lying
around and so you kinda need to know about it.
I'm gonna talk a little bit later about the fact that
all those swift types are kinda magically bridged.
To NSNumber, okay those inits and doubles.
So, you really don't even have to worry about NSNumber.
Unless you use NSNumber formatter that we used in
the assignment, because that thing returns an NSNumber.
>> So it there's no like, NSObject parallel in Swift,
is there a way to make like an array that holds.
And kind of [CROSSTALK].
>> Yep, so the question is, if there's no NSObject, well,
it wouldn't really matter about NSObject.
But the question is can I
create an array where there are random Objects in there?
And we're gonna talk about that later.
Another class, NSDate, exactly what is sounds like,
stores a date, let's you get the current date and time too.
Pretty self explanatory has lots and
lots of methods in it.
And it has even more and more methods because there's those
three other classes mentioned here,
calendar, date formatter, and date components.
And if you're ever doing a date where you're gonna
put a date on screen as part of your application,
you really wanna look at all these classes and
read the documentation that talks about dates.
Because, dates are displayed very
differently around the world.
Different calendars different you know even
different languages, the order of the month, day, year even
if you're using the Gregirian calendar is different.
So, you really, really dates are tricky to get right if
you wanna build an app that can work around the world.
Okay, so I'm just kind of warning you if
you're gonna build an app like that some day you wonna really
understand date and all it's friends here.
There's NSData,
super easy class it's just a bag of bits, okay?
Could be gigantic bag of bits, small bag of bits, whatever.
But it's just untyped data that's just in there it's just
you can think of it almost like a point or two memory and
you just don't know what's in there.
This is how iOS will pass around untyped data,
raw data it passes are out, it around using this class it'll
be obvious when we start using this what it's for.
You're not gonna be using NSData much in this class,
cuz we're not dealing with raw data that much,okay.
All right, so, let,
I just wanted to mention some of those classes just so,
you know, they exist you can check out the documentation.
On all of them to find out more about it and
I'm gonna revisit a few of them like array and
dictionary and string because they, they're so important I'm
actually gonna talk about some of their methods.
But, I wanna talk a little bit about data structures in
Swift in general, okay?
There's really three fundamental building
blocks for your data structure that you
might build and you've seen them.
Two of the three of them in detail, but
they are class, struct, and
enum, okay they're the three basic building blocks.
And they look very similar their declaration syntax looks
very, very similar, right?
Just, the only difference is whether it's class,
struct, or enum, but otherwise looks the same.
They're also very similar in that they can all
have properties and functions, okay.
All three of them now enums they can't store any values
you store the values of your enum in that associated
information but they can have computed properties, okay?
And all three of them can have functions all right okay?
So, that's very important to understand so,
they are very, very similar in that way.
They're also similar at least strucs, and
classes in that they can have intializers.
And we're gonna talk about initializers in detail in
a few slides, okay?
So, they're similar in a lot of ways but
there's a couple ways in which they're very different,
all right?
Classes are the only ones where you
have inheritance, okay?
And it's pretty obvious,
that's kind of the main definer of what a class is,
it has inheritance.
And then, introspected, spection and
casting, which I'm also gonna talk about a little
later those are only for classes, so none of this
casting thing I'm gonna talk about can you do for structs.
And the most important difference to understand, and
we really went over this in the demo,
is this value type versus reference type.
Structs and enums are passed around and
stored in variables copied, okay?
Right?
And referenced and classes are reference types.
In other words, we pass round pointers to them,
they live in the heap.
And remember that class is their memory and
the heap is managed for us.
Okay, so there's nothing,
we don't have to do anything [INAUDIBLE] can free them.
We create them when we want, and
when nobody else, no one's using it,
it gets cleaned up and it's not garbage collection, okay?
Reference counting, automatic reference counting.
But, I wanna just have a slide on this
value type versus reference type again, because it's
a really important thing to understand it.
Cuz people get confused writing the code and
they don't understand what's going on,
but a value type struct means, you know, it's
mean that it's copied when you pass it into a function.
It's copied when you assign it to a different variable,
this one especially gets people.
I don't understand as I have,
you know let x equals array, and I say let y equal x.
That makes, essentially a copy of x,
now that copy might be lazy behind the scenes, but
as far as you're concerned it's a copy, okay?
And if you wanna to be mutable,
you could copy it into a VAR instead of a LET,
and now you could mutate it.
And if you mutate it you get,
you're mutating your own copy, you're not mutating.
What the other one pointed to, okay?
you, because of this, when you make a struct or an enum,
and you add a function to it that modifies it,
you have to mark it with this keyword mutating.
And that's so that Swift knows when someone else.
Gets you know, tries to use your enum or struct, if
they use one of these mutating functions it obviously has to
be in a var but not in a let type variable.
[NOISE] Okay so reference stored in the heap, reference
counted even if you have a constant pointer to a class.
Let something equals the class.
You can still send messages to that thing that can mutate it,
because it didn't the heap.
All right, so it being, you have a pointer to it.
So, and when you pass it to a function,
you're passing a pointer to that thing, so
if the function modifies it,
it's modifying the thing back where it was called.
Okay?
So which do you use between these two?
Well you know,
90% of the time, you're gonna use a class.
This is object-oriented programming language.
You're gonna wanna have the ability to do inheritance, and
overriding, and things like that.
Structs are really more for the basic fundamental types,
like double, int, array, dictionaries, string.
These are all you know, really fundamental things and
when we get into the graphics, you're gonna see the points,
sizes, rectangles, those are structs, okay?
But, most of everything else we build,
we build the classes, okay.
And since it manages all the memory for you and
all that, it's really no big pain to do, to use classes.
All right, so methods.
So, I wanna talk a little bit about methods, all right.
You obviously-
>> [COUGH]
>> If you override a method in a class,
you have to put the keyword, override in front of it, 'kay?
You can also mark a method final,
that means no one can override it.
So, if someone subclasses a class you wrote,
they can't override you if you marked it final.
You can also mark an entire class final, which means hm,
it's a, you know, this is the end of the line.
You can't do any subclasses of it basically.
Okay?
Both types and instances have methods and properties.
So, types, a type is like array,
that's the type and instance of an array is an actual array
with things in it.
Okay?
So let's look at this pili, piece of code, right here.
I've defined a double, 'kay?
This var which is a double, and I say,
if the Double isSignMinus, that means if it's minus sign,
has, it's negative.
Then I'm going to set the Double to be it,
the absolute value of the double.
So, isSignMinus is an instance variable,
an instance property.
You send it to a particular Double to ask it,
is your SignMinus?
Whereas Double.abs is a type function on double.
You pass the Double you wanna operate on to it, and
it works on it.
But your, and you're not sending abs to a particular
double, you're sending it to the class, or
the struct in this case, the type.
在这个例子中的结构体、类型
You see what I mean?
你明白我的意思吗？
So, some method you send to instances, particular
So, 一些你发送到实例中的方法
instances of some things you can send to the type.
特别是实例中的一些东西你可以发送到类型中
All right, so two different kinds of, of method but
All right, 所以两种不一样的方法
otherwise, the rules for them are about the same.
但是，他们的规则是一样的
It's just that, who you asked to do the work.
就是那种,要求你做这份工作的人
You declare a type method or
你声明一个类型方法或者或者一个属性
a property by using static in front of it.
其之前必须使用静态变量
So, like abs, there would static func abs,
So, 就像绝对值，那里存在一个静态的绝对值方法
takes a Double returns a double.
取出一个Double类型数据也要返回一个Double类型数据
And that makes it so you send it that to, the Double type
instead of sending it to a particular double.
In a class you use the word class not static.
在一个类中你使用非静态的文字类
Okay, cuz it's called a class function.
Okay, 因为它被叫做一个功能类
Okay?
So, I just don't want you to be confused,
So, 我不想使你感到困惑
when you start seeing methods like abs that are sent to
当你开始看见一个类似于abs的方法时
the Double type.
它会发送Double型数据
That looks kinda weird but it's perfectly normal.
那看起来有一点怪异的但是它很正常
Okay?
And what would you do with a ty, wh, when do
然后你会用一个 ty,wh 做什么，什么时候用？
you have a type function versus an instant function?
你拥有一个类型函数去和一个实例化的函数进行对抗
Well, if you're doing any kind of utility work, right?
很好，如果你正在从事任何一种实用型的工作，对吗？
You're not doing anything in
你不是针对一种
particular to a certain kind of double, but
特定的Double类型，
just in utilities, you would have those in there.
但是在实用型中，你将会拥有这些
Sometimes you would have type methods that create objects of
有时候你应该拥有类型方法
certain kinds and hand them out.
它可以创造特定类型的方法并且将他们分发出去
Maybe a shared object like if you had one,
也许一个共享型的对象就像是如果你有一个
only one instance of an object for
只有一个对象的实例
your entire app of a certain type, maybe you would ask that
为你的整个App 确定某种类型的，也许你会问那个类型
type, give me that shared instance, okay?
给我那个共享的实例，明白了吗？
So it's kinda before utilities and
所以他是那种在实用型和建立之前
creation, that kinda thing.
是那种类型的东西
And they're, now I wouldn't, I don't wanna say, they're rare,
而且他们，现在我不能也不敢说，他们是特殊的
they're not super common, you'll see them in, in iOS and
他们不是一个超级 common类，你不会看到他们在里面
you'll probably use them occasionally.
在iOS系统中，而且你可能只是偶尔的使用他们
you, you would use them really instead of global functions.
你将会使用他们代替一个全局的函数
You can't have global functions.
你不能拥有一个全局函数
In Swift, of course.
当然，在Swift中
But you'd really probably prefer to make it a type
但是你真的可能喜欢去穿件一个类型方法
method so that function is associated with you know,
以便那个函数关联到你知道的内容
the type and kind of, unless it's
类型和种类，除非它是
truly a global function that applies to the world.
一个真正的全局函数适用于整个工程
It doesn't, it's not about a particular class,
它不是，不是关于一个特殊的类
usually you would make them be a type,
通常情况下你将会把他们当做一个类型使用
a type function [SOUND] very well [SOUND].
一个类型函数是非常好的
All right?
So method, now lets talk about the parameter names
所以方法，现在让我们来谈谈
of methods.
方法的参数名
This is, this is a, this is gonna be the crash course,
这是一个将要崩溃的课程
you read all about this I hope in the documentation.
你阅读了我希望的在文档中所有关于这些的内容
But, all parameters to functions have an internal
但是，函数中的所有参数都有
name and an external name.
一个内部的名字和一个外部的名字
So, we're talking about the parameters.
所以，让我们来讨论一下这些参数
Okay?
明白了么？
So, down there,
所以，在下面
foo, the parameters the parameter to foo there.
foo, 参数foo在这里
'Kay, it has internal name and external name.
明白了么，它有一个内部命名和一个外部命名
So, the internal name, which goes kinda near
所以，内部的名字，和冒号有一点接近
the colon, is the name that that thing is gonna have as
是在方法中拥有一个本地变量的名字
a local variable inside the method, at this internal name.
在这个内部名称中
And then the external name is the name that
外部命名是一个名字
callers are going to use when the, to put before the colon.
调用者准备使用的，放在冒号之前
'Kay?
明白了么？
When they call the thing.
当他们调用东西的时候
So in bar there, I'm calling things, and
所以在这里，我要调用一个东西
in foo I'm defining them.
在 foo方法中我定义了他们
So, you see that here, I call foo with external colon 123.
所以，在这里你可以看到，我通过外部名称123调用了 foo 方法
Even though, internal to foo, that thing is called internal.
即使，foo的内部，那东西叫做内部
'Kay?
明白了吗？
So, you can have both external,
所以，你可以同事拥有外部的
internal names, they can be different.
以及内部的名字，他们是不同的
You can put an under bar,
你可以添加一个下划线
remember under bar is kinda the don't care thing in Swift.
记住，在Swift中下划线是不会被编译的
Even under bar if you don't want callers, so
如果你不想有调用者
use an external name.
所以使用一个外部命名
So now look at bar.
现在来看这条线
It calls foo,
它调用了 foo方法
it doesn't even put internal colon or external colo, colon.
它甚至没有添加一个内部的冒号或者一个外部的冒号
It just puts the argument there.
它只是把参数留在了那儿
'Kay? So, the under bar says,
Okay？所以，下划线说：
I don't wanna have an external name for this.
“我不想拥有一个外部命名”
'Kay, now that is the default for
Okay，那里只是默认的
the first argument to a function.
将第一个参数传入到函数中
So, foo only has one argument, so
所以，foo方法 只有一个参数
it's first argument, it's only argument.
所以，它是第一个参数也是唯一的一个参数
You can see that when you call it from bar,
你可以看到它当你从bar处调用它
you don't say internal colon,
你没有声明一个内部的冒号
as because that under bar thing is the default.
因为下划线的值是默认的
Now, if you don't want that to be the default,
现在，如果你不想让它为默认的值
you can force the first one to be required by
你可以强制第一个参数是必要的
putting a pound sign there, a little hashtag, okay?
通过添加一个井号标志，一个小的标签，明白？
And that makes it so you have to say internal colon-
这使得你不得不称它为内部冒号
>> [COUGH] >> 'Kay?
Okay？
For other parameters, not the first parameter but
对于另外的参数，不是第一个参数
other parameters.
是其他的参数
The name, the internal or external name,
他们的名称，内部命名或外部命名
is mandatory, 'kay?
是强制性的，明白？
Unless, you put the and you can change the name,
除非，你设置或者改变了它的 name
you can be you can, you can have the external name be
这个因人而异，你可以将 external name 区别于其他的参数
different for any parameter not just the first one.
这个不仅限于第一个参数
And you can put the under bar in there and make it so
还有，你可以在这里添加一个下划线
even the second one has no parameter name.
来让第二个变量没有 parameter name
This would be incredibly un-Swift like to do this.
我不建议这样做，因为这不是标准的做法
To have a function like this that takes two arguments, and
要想让这样一个接受两个参数的方法的第二个参数
the second one doesn't really have, a name.
不需要 name
Because in Swift you can kind of think of the name of
因为在 Swift 中，你一般会认为方法的名字
the method, as describing what the first argument is.
即描述了它的第一个参数是什么
The first argument's your method, it should always be,
你的方法的第一个参数，始终需要
kind of obvious based on the name of the method.
基于此方法的名字
Because the method does something,
因为方法完成了某些功能
it operates on something or whatever.
它在某个变量之上进行操作
That should be the first argument.
那个变量就应该是第一个参数
That's why it usually doesn't need a first parameter name.
所以为什么我们不需要第一个参数的 name
And then all the other arguments,
至于其余的参数
you wanna give them names, so
如果你理解了它们在干什么之后
if you understand what they are, 'kay?
你想要给它们命名
What they're about?
那应该怎么做呢
And in other languages a lot of times you'll have a real,
在其他的语言中，你经常会遇到
really long method that says you know, do this, and
非常非常长的方法命名告诉你某个方法
that, with this other thing, and
干什么、使用了那些变量
that, and then in parenthesis you have four arguments and
然后你就能够在圆括号中将这四个参数
people have to kinda match up what's what.
一一对应起来
Here, the name of the method really is kind of
这样的方法是根据
distributed out amongst it's arguments.
它的参数来命名的
So, it's really a lot easier to read and
所以他比较方便去阅读
a lot easier to understand, what the heck is going on?
也比较方便去理解，我们讨论这些有什么意义呢？
so, I don't recommend it,
显然，我并不推荐这么做
I don't recommend putting the under bar in, in parameters.
我不推荐在参数之前加上下划线
There, there are some exceptions, but
虽然有一些是特例，但是
I generally don't recommend that.
一般来说我不推荐这么做
'Kay?
明白了吗？
All right properties,
接来下是 properties
let's talk a little bit about properties.
让我们一起来看看什么是 properties
So, property observers are very important and
显然， property observers 是非常关键的
we're gonna use them a lot.
而且我们会大量地使用它
They are very simple,
它们使用起来很简单
you have a property like here I have some stored property.
在这里你有一个 someStoredProperty
It's an Int equals 42, and
它是一个 Int 类型的，并且它的值为 42
yes I didn't need to type there, I'm just putting there.
我并不需要在这里输入这些，我只是把它放在这里
okay, and throughout my slides by the way.
这些一直贯穿在我的 Slides 中
Green, I put things in green because I'm just trying to
绿色，我将这部分标注为绿色，因为
make you draw attention to the fact that this is code.
我想让你们注意到的是，这部分是代码
Okay? That's all green means, but
明白了吗？这是被标注为绿色的部分的意义
yellow usually will mean this is
黄色部分通常表示
the thing I'm talking about, right now.
这是我正在跟你们讲的东西
This is the thing to pay attention to.
它是你们需要关心的地方
So, you can al,
所以，你可以把黄色部分
almost think of yellow, as like highlighted.
认为是一种高亮
Okay?
明白了吗
So, here I have some stored property.
回到我们之前讲的，这里我拥有一个 someStoredProperty
It stores in Int 42.
它存储了 Int 类型的 42
And notice though, even though it's a stores property,
需要注意的是，这是一个
not computed, it's stored.
直接存储、不需要计算过程的 property
I still put a curly brace after it.
我仍旧在它之后放置了一对花括号
But in that curly brace instead of
花括号的意思并不是
saying get instead like a computer property.
说，这个 property 是通过计算得到的
I say, will set and did set, 'kay?
而是 willSet 和 didSet 来得到的，明白了吗？
So these are little pieces of code inside the willSet and
所以在 willSet 和 didSet 之后的
dill, didSet.
小段的代码
They get called when that property gets set by anybody,
会在设置或获取 property 的值时被调用
so it's called an a property observer cause I'm observing
这就是它为什么叫 property observer 的原因
with this code I'm observing this thing is being set.
因为这段代码 observe 这个 property 的设置或获取方法
And the willSet is called right before
willSet 这个方法会在设置 property 值之前被调用
the properties value gets set, and the didSet, right after.
同样道理，didSet 这个方法会在设置 property 值之后被调用
And inside the willSet,
在 willSet 方法中
you've got this special variable called new value,
你会有一个特殊的 newValue 变量
which is gonna be the new value that's going to be set.
这就是 property 将要被设置的新的值
And then inside didSet, you've got this special thing
同样，在 didSet 方法中，你会有一个特殊的 oldValue 变量
called old value, which is the old value.
这就是 property 要被设置之前值
Okay?
明白了吗？
Now, you use this in really kind of these two cases.
现在，你可以在这两种情况下使用它们
One is you have the stored property in yourself,
一种情况是你在自己的类中拥有
in your class.
stored property
And whenever someone sets it, you want to kinda notice and
当其他方法的设置它的值时，你想要获得一个 notice
do something, okay?
然后你可以根据这个 notice 做一些事情
And the other one is you inherit some property, and you
另一种情况是你继承了某些类
don't necessarily do anything with that property directly.
你并不需要对这些类中的 property 做什么修改
But you wanna know, when that gets changed by anybody.
但是你想知道它们被其他方法改变了
'Kay?
明白了吗？
So, you can even do willSet and
所以，你可以在某些继承的类之上
didSet on properties you inherit from somebody,
编写 willSet 和 didSet
from your super class.
Okay?
明白了吗？
Now, what kinda things would we do in here?
在这里，我们能够做些什么
Well, one extremely common thing to do in iOS is to
一个在 iOS 开发中非常常见的做法是
update the user-interface.
更新用户界面
So, you have some view controller let's say, or
举例，你有一个 view controller
you have a view, and you change some property in it and
或者你有一个 view ，你可以改变其中的某些 property
it, that changing that property means would change.
改变其中某些 property 意味着
So, in the didSet, you'll go update the user-interface.
在 didSet 中，你将对用户界面进行更新
That make sense?
这样说能理解一点了吗？
'Kay.
好的
So, the observers are really cool, they're a really good
所以， property observers 是非常酷的
way to kinda keep track of what's going on and
同时也是追踪哪些 property 被设置或获取的一种好方法
keep things in sync.
All right, lazy initialization so a lazy property,
接下来，我们谈谈 lazy initialization
if you put lazy in front of a property declaration, it means
如果你在 property 声明前加了 lazy ，这意味着
it does not get initialized until someone accesses it.
And that's true whether it's initialized with
equal something, so that equal something will not
happen until someone actually accesses that property.
Or you can actually initialize it by putting a closure there,
put parenthesis after it, and we'll execute that closure.
And that will initialize the property.
But that closure won't get executed until someone tries
to get it, 'kay?
And then you can even in a lazy property, you could call
a method to, to initialize it because it, normally you
wouldn't be able to do this if you didn't say lazy.
Because you can't call any
methods in your class until you're fully initialized, so
there's kinda a catch 22 there.
But in this case since,
you can't call any methods until you're initialized,
by the time somebody tries to get this property,
you'd be fully initialized.
So, you can call methods.
So, you see the advantage of lazy there?
'Kay.
This lazy thing still satisfies the rule that you
must initialize all of your properties.
'Kay, even though it doesn't actually initialize it
until someone accesses it.
It still satisfies that rule.
unfortunately, only vars can be lazily initialized.
Things that are let,
if you had constants in your class, those would have to be
initializing in your initializer.
You can't initialize them lazily, only vars, not lets.
This can be used to get around some kind of tricky
initialization dependencies.
Because of that rule that everything has to be
initialized before you can do anything.
Sometimes you can get into fights with your
superclass for example, about when something's gonna be
initialized, and you need your superclass to do something or
you can do something, but it needs you to do something
before they can do something, so you're kinda we're stuck.
And what you can do is one of the other of you,
make one of the things that depends on their lazy.
Okay. And then, as soon as
somebody wants it, it'll get initialized and off we go.
Okay? Any questions about Lazy?
Pretty cool feature.
All right?
And it's exactly, what it sounds like, just lazily waits
to initialize until someone wants this property.
>> [COUGH] >> Okay?
So, now let's talk about initialization, so
I need to get, I need a drink before the initialization,
cuz it's complicated.
Hopefully my, [NOISE] I'm just, I'm not, this is not,
just taking care of my voice here.
Okay, init, [LAUGH] all right.
So, when do you need an init method?
Well, you know what?
You actually don't need an init method that often.
'Kay? We showed,
had the init method in the CalculatorBrain.
Made sense there.
We needed it there.
But you don't need it that often,
because a lot of your variables and
constants in your class or
struct are set with equals, so you don't need them.
Or maybe the properties are optionals.
And so they can just start out nil and
you can set them later like the outlets in a storyboard.
Or you can actually initialize by using a closure.
Okay? As I showed in the previous
thing, that lazy thing, that you, you can do that for
non-lazies, put the closure thing there and execute it.
It'll get executed right away and
nothing inside that closure could refer to
other instance variables of, of course because it
would be executing before the initialization was done.
But still, you can calculate some things to assign things
in a closure, by executing a closure.
and, or you could use the lazy mechanism and
then to avoid needing an init.
So, there's a lot of ways to avoid init.
But if you do need an init then what,
what, how do we do init?
Because init has some kind of
interesting inter-dependencies,
it's not as straightforward as you might think.
Now you get some free inits-
[COUGH] 'Kay? Inits that get done for
you, one is that if all the properties in a class,
in a base class.
Not a co, this is something that has no superclass,
like CalculatorBrain.
If they all have defaults,
then you'll get an inits with no arguments for free.
So, if we haven't implemented CalculatorBrains, init,
of course, we still could have said.
>> You know, brain equals calculator brain parentheses.
That's because we get a free init in calculator brain,
这是因为我们有一个默认的init
cuz we initialized our default using equals something.
我们默认使用等于某值初始化
Okay. So you,
所以
that's one way to get an init.
这是一种得到init的方法
A struct, not a class, but a struct,
结构体，不是类，但是结构体
it will get a default one that has all the properties as
它将默认得到一个将所有属性作为参数的初始化方法
arguments only if you have no initializers.
仅当没有initializers时
So if you had a struct and you gave it no initializers,
因此，如果你有一个结构体并且没有initializers
you would get one for free, which would be init or
你会得到一个默认的初始化方法
all the arguments match all of the vars you have.
并且所有的参数和变量匹配，如果有的话
All the vars and lets, okay?
所有的变量和常量，明白吧？
So here I got a struct, it has two properties there, x and y.
这里我有一个结构体，它有两个属性，x和y
And you can see that I got this init, x takes an init and
你可以看到我这里有一个init方法，x是int类型
a y string for free, for free.
y是string类型
I didn't have to implement that at all, it just came for
我没有实现它，仅仅是默认的
free and so people can call that.
都可以调用
They can initialize MyStruct, by saying,
可以初始化MyStruct
MyStruct open parentheses and provide the x and the y.
MyStruct提供x和y两个属性
Okay?
All right.
So, what can you do inside of init?
你可以在init里面做什么？
Okay. We saw,
好，我们看到
what we did in calculator brain,
我们在CalculatorBrain里做了什么
we initialized some stuff.
我们初始化了些
But what can you do?
你可以做什么？
Well, you can set any properties value in there.
你可以在里面设置任何属性值
[COUGH] You can even set
你甚至可以
properties that have default values.
给属性设置默认值
So even if you have properties set equals 12.
即使你把属性设置为等于12
In your init, you can reset that thing to something else
在你的init里，你可以把一些东西重置为别的什么
if you wanted to, if you changed your mind in init.
如果你想的话
Okay?
You can do that.
你可以这样做
You can also set constant properties.
你也可以给常量属性赋值
So if you have a struct or a class and
如果你有一个结构体或者类
it has letx colon string, you can set that in your init.
你可以在init里这样设置 let x: String
Even though to let, it's gotta get set some time in your init
你必须得设置一段在你的init里
is when you can set it.
You can also say, equal something, but
也可以是等于其他什么
you can also set it in your init.
你可以这样设置，在你的init里
Okay?
So people sometimes don't understand, realize,
人们有时不理解
they're like, oh, I can have lets in my class?
他们肯定在想，哦，在我的class里可以有let？
Can have like, you know, constants for
可有一样，你知道的
my class that are created at initialization and
类里的常量在初始化和创建实例
stay the same for the lifetime of instance and
的生命周期里是保持不变的
absolutely you can and you initialize them in your init.
你绝对可以在init里初始化它们
Okay.
That's actually a good practice if
这实际上是很好的做法
you have something that's, you know, constant like that.
如果你需要定义属性，你知道的，可以用常量
You can call other init methods in your own class or
在你的类或者结构体里你可以调用其他的init方法
struct using self.init.
使用self.init
Okay?
Self.init, you can call the other ones with the ones that
self.init，你可以调用有不同参数的其他init方法
have different arguments.
Okay?
So that sounds good.
所以听起来很不错
And of course in a class, you can call super.init.
当然，在类里你也可以调用super.init
Call your superclass's initializers,
调用你父类的初始化方法
what their arguments whatever, they might be.
参数无论是什么，如果有的话
However, big old humongous, however on this one.
There are a lot of rules for
调用其他的init时有很多规则
calling other inits, especially in classes.
尤其是在类里
They instruct, it's not a big deal.
在结构体里，这并不是一个大问题
But in classes, there's a lot of rules and were gonna take
但在类里，有很多规则，我们将拿两个幻灯片
two slides here to go through these rules briefly.
对这些规则做简单介绍
All right.
So as part of these rules,
所以作为这些规则的一部分
what do you required to do inside of init?
你需要在init里做些什么？
What is mandatory for you to do?
什么是你必须要做的？
Well, as you know, you have to have initialized all
好，正如你所知道的，在你的整个类里
the properties in your entire class.
所有的属性都必须初始化
You can not start a class off with no value.
他们都必须有值
And remember, optionals, nil is a value for an optional.
记住，optionals，nil也是一个optional
So if an optional is nil, it is set.
所以，如果你有一个属性的optional是nil，这也算它有值
So, everything's fine there.
一切都好了
[COUGH] There are two times, type,
在类里，Swift提供两种类型
types of inits in a class.
的构造器来初始化
Not in a struct, but in a class.
不是在结构体里，在类里
One is called a convenience init and
一种是convenience init
then there's all the other kinds.
Those are called designated initializers.
还有一种叫designated initializers
So by default, an initializer is
默认的initializer
called a designated initializer, but there's also
是designated initializer，但是另外还有些
these things called convenience initializers.
叫convenience initializers
And we make this distinction,
我们得做出区分
because there's a little bit different rules about them.
因为它们的规则有一点点的不同
So lets talk about that.
我们来看看吧
A designated initializer, one that doesn't take
一个designated initializer，不能有
convenience in the front of it.
convenience在它的前面
It has to, and
他只能
can only call a designated initializer in its superclass.
调用其直接父类的designated initializer
It's a very important rule.
这是一个非常重要的规则
Okay. If you
have a designated initializer, initializer doesn't have
如果你有一个designated initializer，初始化时不能有
the word convenience in front of it,
convenience这个单词在它的前面
it can't call another init in your class.
在你的类里不能调用其他的init方法
It has to call a superclass in init and
在init里有调用父类的init
it has to be a designated initializer not
它必须是一个designated initializer
a convenience initializer in the superclass.
而不是convenience initializer
Okay?
Understand that rule number one?
理解第一条规则了吗？
That's your designated initial.
这就是你们的预设初始化（designated initial）。
This is all, by
这就是全部了。
the way in the documentation It's very elaborately.
顺便说一下，在文档中有详细的描述。
Drawn out with pictures and all that.
有图表之类的说明。
I'm just trying to summarize it here.
我这里只是大概提一下。
Okay. Hopefully,
希望，
you've read that already and this is review.
你们已经读了文档，这是复习。
But if not, hopefully you're understanding a little bit of
如果没有，希望你们能理解一点
what I'm saying.
我所说的。
Tonight when you read it, you'll be, oh yeah, I get it.
今晚，当你们阅读文档时，就会明白了。
Okay. So that's the rule for
这就是
designating initializer.
designating initializer 的规则。
You have to initialize all of your own
你必须在调用父类的初始化函数前
properties before you call your superclass's initializer.
先初始化你自己的所有属性。
Okay? This is for
只有 designated initializers 需要这样。
designated initializers only,
cuz they are the ones who call supervisors initializers.
因为他们调用 supervisors initializers.
So you have to be done with your own properties before you
所以你必须在调用父类的属性前
call your superclass's.
先处理你自己（类）的属性。
This one will trip you up, often.
这经常让你有麻烦。
Okay? You also have to call your
Okay？ 你要先调用
superclass's init before you assign a value to
父类的初始化函数，然后才能给继承自父类的
any property you inherit from your superclass.
属性赋值。
In other words,
也就是说，
you have to let your superclass's initialize,
你必须先让你的父类初始化它的属性，
it's properties before you can start setting them.
然后你才能给它们赋值。
So you get those three rules?
你们现在明白这三条规则了吗？
Okay.
That has to do with, so you're superclass, cuz it has to do
这和你们的父类有关，因为它必须处理
with designated intitializers and calling super.
designated intitializers 并调用它的父类（的初始化函数）。
All right. Now
a convenience initializer has different rules.
convenience initializer 有不同的规则。
Okay? First of all,
首先，
a convenience initializer must and
convenience initializer 必须
can only call a designated initializer in it's own class.
而且只能调用本类的 designated initializer。
Convenience initializer,
Convenience initializer，
initializer cannot call super init of any kind.
这类初始化函数不能调用任何父类的初始化函数。
And it can't call and it must call a,
它必须调用
a designated initializer.
designated initializer。
Now it can call that designated initializer
它能通过调用其他的 convenience initializer
indirectly through another convenience initializer.
间接调用 designated initializer。
Okay.
So one convenience initializer can call self another
因此 convenience initializer 能调用本类其他
convenience initializer, which called designated initializer.
调用designated initializer 的 convenience initializer。
But eventually, a designated initializer must be called.
但最后，有个 designated initializer 必须被调用。
Okay?
A convenience initializer must call that
一个 convenience initializer 必须先直接或
designated initializer, directly or
间接调用designated initializer，
indirectly before it can touch any values, obviously.
然后才能访问其他的值。
Okay?
You have to kinda get the main, your
你必须让主要的，
object primarily initialized before you can have
你的对象首先被初始化，然后你才能
the convenience initializer start hacking at properties.
让 convenience initializer 开始访问属性。
The calling of other inits, whether your a convenience guy
其他初始化函数的调用，不管是你的 convenience 初始化函数
calling your designator or whether your a designator
调用你的 designator ，还是你的 designator
calling up to your supers designator has to be complete
调用你父类的 designator，
before you can start accessing your properties and methods.
所有这些都必须在你开始访问属性和方法之前完成。
In other words, the class has to be initialized before you
也就是说，这个类必须被初始化，然后
can start calling methods and properties.
你才能开始调用方法和属性。
Okay?
That's why we have to use lazy if we want a property to
这就是为什么我们必须使用懒惰的方式，
set its value to be calling a method.
如果我们要设置一个属性的值则调用方法。
Because we can't do it non-lazily,
因为我们不能使用非懒惰方式。
because we wouldn't be initialized at that time.
因为那时我们还没被初始化。
We'd still be in the process of initializing.
我们还在初始化过程中。
It's kind of a two phase initialization.
这如同初始化的两个阶段。
You get fully initialized, now you can go do that.
完全初始化之后，你就能那样做了。
Okay? So these are the rules.
这就是（初始化的）规则了。
Question?
有问题吗？
Is there a way to set the constant then by
有没有这样一种方式，通过调用
by calling a method?
方法给常量赋值？
So the question is,
问题是，
is there a way to set constant by calling a method or
有没有一种方式，可以调用方法或者类似的途径
something like that?
给常量赋值。
And the answer is no.
答案是不能。
Okay.
You can only set constants either setting them equals
你只能给常量赋予等于的某个值，
something or in your initializers.
或者在你的初始化函数中。
Unfortunately, later we can't do it.
不幸的是，之后我们不能做这些了。
Okay.
Let's talk about inheriting init.
让我们聊聊继承式初始化。
Okay?
Cuz this is complicated, as well.
这也很复杂。
So here are the rules for inheriting init.
这就是继承式初始化的规则了。
If you do not implement any designated initializers in
如果你没有在你的类中实现任何 designated initializers ，
your class, any, then you'll inherit all of
那么，你将继承你父类中的
your superclass's designated initializers.
所有 designated initializers。
Otherwise, you'll inherit none of your de,
否则，你将不继承任何你的父类中的
superclass's designated initializers.
designated initializers。
Okay?
It's all of nothing on designated initializers.
如果你覆盖了你父类中的所有 designated initializers，
If you override all of your superclass's designated inits.
则 designated initializers 中就什么都没有。
Okay?
All, so your superclass has
你的父类中有
three designated initializers with different arguments.
三种不同参数的 designated initializers，
If you override all of them, then you'll inherit all of
如果你覆盖了所有这些方法，那么你就继承了父类中所有的
your superclass's convenient initializers.
convenient initializers。
Also, if you implement none of them.
同样，如果你没有实现它们中的任一个方法，
Because you'll essentially inherit all
在这种情况下，你将继承
the designateds and all the convenience in that case.
所有指定的、方便的类。
Okay?
So that's the inheritance rule.
这就是继承的规则。
This trips people up, too.
旅行的人也是这样。
They're like, oh yeah,
他们说，哦耶，
I implemented that one initializer, but
我实现了一个初始化
how come the other initializer doesn't work?
但是其他的初始化为什么没用？
Well, because once you initiali,
好吧，因为一旦你初始化
implement one designated initializers,
执行一个指定的初始化
you don't inherit the rest of them.
你就不必继承其他的
Okay?
So it's all or nothing on designateds.
所以指定不是全有就是全无。
And on convenience, it's kind of all or nothing too.
并且便利，同样也是。
Cuz you have to implement or not implement all of
因为为了方便，你要执行或者不执行
the designateds to get the conveniences.
指定操作。
Any init that you inherit by these rules that I just said,
你做任何初始化，继承了我刚才说的规则
count for all the rules on the previous slide.
包括之前幻灯片提到的所有规则。
I'm not gonna go back to the previous slide and go through
在这里，我就回顾之前幻灯片的内容了
them all, but you can satisfy a lot of the requirements in
但是通过之前的幻灯片里讲的的继承初始化
the previous slide by just inheriting your initializers.
可以满足你的很多要求。
Okay?
But you have,
但是你
you can only inherit them in these kind of restricted ways.
只能通过这种受限制的方法去继承它们。
But once you do,
只要你这么做了。
you can satisfy a lot of those previous rules.
之前的所有规则你都可以满足了。
It is possible to have what's called a required init.
可能有人问什么是 required 的初始化方法。
You just put required on it.
你只要给它设置 required 。
And if you put required,
如果你设置了 required ，
it means that subclasses must implement it.
那么它的子类就必须实现这个方法。
It is required.
这就是 required 。
Now they can inherit it by the rules above.
现在通过遵守上面的规则，你可以继承它了。
In other words, if they don't,
换句话说，如果没有遵守
if any designated negative initializers,
任何指定的负面的初始化
they'll inherit the required initializer, that's good.
它们将会继承 required 的初始化，这非常棒。
But if you implement any of the designated initializers,
但是如果你想实现其中得某个指定的方法
you must implement the required ones.
你必须实现它对应的 required 。
Okay?
Finally, there's failable initializers.
最后，这是失败的初始化。
Okay? So
明白吗？所以
some initializers are allowed to fail and return nil.
有一些初始化允许失败或者返回 nil 。
Okay?
You, you designate them by putting question mark
你在初始化完成后，可以加个注释
after the init, like this right here.
就像我这里一样。
Okay?
Now, this is pretty uncommon.
现在，这是很少见的。
Okay? You don't see
明白吗？你们不经常见这些。
these very often and the documentation last I checked,
我上次查文档的时候，
doesn't really show this very well.
它也没描述的特别仔细。
It doesn't put the question mark in there.
它没有把注释标在那儿。
I think it's just
我觉得是
a documentation generation problem.
生成文档的时候出现的问题。
It will say in, in the comment for
它会在初始化的时候提示
the init, this can return nil, if it fails.
这个可能会返回 nil ，如果失败的话。
But it doesn't put,
但是它没有放，
seem to put the question mark on there.
貌似把问题标注在那儿了。
But that's okay, because when you start using it,
但是没关系，因为当你用它的时候
you're gonna call this initializer.
你就会调用它。
And the thing's gonna come back and you're gonna try and
回调的时候你会
send messages to it.
给它发送一个消息。
And it's gonna say,
它会提示
this isn't optional, does not respond to the method.
这个方法不是 optional 的，没有对应的方法。
And you're like, what?
你会惊讶，我擦！
Isn't optional?
它不是可选的？
And then you're gonna know.
然后你就会瞬间反应过来
Oh, the initializer was failable.
哦， 初始化失败了。
So let's look at an example of this.
来，我们来看这个例子。
So UIImage.
关于 UIImage
Okay?
That's a class in UIKit.
它是 UIKit 中的一个类。
And [COUGH] it returns an image.
然后，它返回一个图片。
And you can ask for an image by its name.
你可以通过它的名称来获取图片
But of course, that image named that might not be
当然，如果你的项目中如果不存在图片的话
anywhere in your project, so this thing can return nil.
它就会返回 nil 。
So in this case right here,
那么在这里，
image equals UIImage named: "foo".
名为 "foo" 的图片赋值给 image
Image is an optional UIImage,
Image 是一个可选的方法。
even I'm calling initializer there, right?
甚至，可以称做 Image 的初始化，对吗？
UIImages initializer.
UIImages 的初始化方法。
It could be Usually,
可能这种叫法比较常见。
what we do in this case is we use if let.
这种情况下我们会用 if let 。
If we can let the image equal the image name foo,
如果 image = UIImage(name: "foo") 成立
then we'll do what we want.
那么我们就处理相关的事件。
Otherwise, we couldn't find it.
不成立，不能创建图片。
So, we'll do whatever we do in that case.
所以，我们可以做任何处理这种情况下。
Okay?
是吗？
So watch out for those.
所以，多注意这些细节。
There's a few of them, a few dozen at the most.
是啊。
Yeah.
So this is a replace like tricach?
-所以，这是一个取代，比如 tricach？（学生提问）
So the question is does this replace tricatch?
这是一个取代，比如 tricach？
And we're not even going to talk about tricatch in
我们不打算谈论 tricatch
this class.
在这节课。
Okay? That's how rare it is.
明白？ tricatch 非常少见。
You don't even really use tricatch in Swift.
甚至在 Swift 中也很少用到它。
You know, things are optionals make a lot of tricatch stuff
你知道，很多可选的事情让
just not necessary.
tricatch 变得不是必须得。
Tricatch, for
对于那些不知道什么是 Tricatch 的同学，
those of you who don't know is you can raise exceptions in
可以在你的项目中抛出异常
your program and they can percolate up the callstack and
它们可以贯穿调用堆栈并且
someone tries to catch them and handle them.
有些人视图抓住它们，处理它们。
Okay?
And that programming methodology is not one
that's really something that we use much in iOS.
Okay? In Objective C,
maybe it was used even a little more.
I'm not even sure about that but
certainly in Swift we're not gonna be using that.
I'm not, I'm not even gonna show it to your in this class.
That's how unneed, unnecessary it is to know that.
Okay.
So let's talk about creating objects,
then you know to do it by putting the type and
then parentheses and then the arguments to the initializer.
Okay.
It's completely obvious there.
You notice you don't always create objects by doing that.
Sometimes, you will ask a class method or
a type method to do it.
So here's one, buttonWithType.
You see that's being sent UIButton, the type.
All right. It's not being sent to
a UIButton, it's being sent to the type,
like we talked about before.
And so sometimes,
you'll be creating things that way very rarely.
They really, Apple's been moving away from that model
and more towards just using initializers and creating
things but there, there's some that, that do that.
Like remember UIImage on the previous page,
that wasn't UIImage dot image named.
That's kind of how it used to be in Apple, now it's UIImage
parentheses whatever, called a constructor.
Sometimes other objects will obviously create
objects for you.
So like here's a really cool method in string called join.
Okay?
Join takes an array of strings and it will separate them by
whatever string you send join to.
So comma.join up in array will give you a comma
separated string, a string with the things,
then the array comes separated.
And that's obviously creating a new array.
So this, this is kind of completely obvious.
But yes, some methods return objects to you that
are created.
okay.
So let's talk now about AnyObject,
this was brought up earlier.
AnyObject is kind of okay.
For the purposes of what you know so
far, you can think of it as a type.
Okay? It's not really a type, but
you can think of it as type, like Double or
array or whatever.
And it's used primarily for
compatibility with existing Objective-C APIs and iOS.
Okay. You're really not gonna use
any object to build your own data structures very much.
I suppose you could, but
it'd be kind of, it'd be, again, kind of anti-Swift.
Swift is very much into strong typing and type inference and
all that.
So you could, but I'm only gonna talk about it in the
context here of using it here as this compatibility thing.
All right?
So what is AnyObject?
Okay? And where will you see it?
So AnyObject, means a pointer to an object.
Meaning, an instance of a class.
Okay? That you
don't know what the class is.
So it's just kind of pointer to unknown class.
Okay? Which it seems kind of
weird and it is kind of weird.
And you, so we gonna have to play around to be able to
use it but that's what it is.
And where will you see this in iOS?
Sometimes, you'll see properties that are in
AnyObject, like there's a property on storyboard segues
which we're gonna talk about next week.
Called destinationViewController,
instead of being a UIViewController is a type,
it's AnyObject.
Okay, for historical reasons really.
And similarly u, in UIViewController,
there is a property called toolbarItems and
it would return to an array of the AnyObject.
Okay?
So basically, these properties are giving you back things you
don't even know what they are.
Kay?
You'll also see them as arguments to functions.
Like here is
a UIViewController method prepare for segue.
It takes a normal argument there, segue, but
then it also takes a sender, which can be any object.
Now in that case, it kinda makes sense because it
really could be AnyObject in that case,
cuz whatever's causing the segue to happen in a user
interface, could be AnyObject, so it makes some sense.
可以是AnyObject，这是一样对
But there's addConstraints, kay?
但这里是addConstraints，Okay？
Which is another UIViewController thing.
也是一种UIViewController
And you add the constraints, you think that would be
并且你加了限制，你认为
array of whatever class constraints are,
这是一个无关类型限制的数组
I haven't taught you about this, but
还没有教你们这些
these are the constraints that do all our UI shifting.
这些限制都是我们UI的移动
But again, for historical reasons, it's an array of
但是，由于历史遗留问题
any object and even in a appendDigit in calculator.
这是一个任意对象的数组，甚至是计算器里的appendDigit
Okay, remember, when we drag, control, dragged the button to
记住，当我按住control拖动时
make a appendDigit, and I made a big deal of of saying,
拖动按钮去生成一个appendDigit的，我们也会同时作出一个巨大的改变
change that from any object to UI button, okay?
把那个任意对象变成一个UI Button
Well, if you hadn't changed it, then you could've ended up
如果你还没改变这个，你就不会在结尾
with a appendDigit, sender any object.
用appendDigit传递任何对象
Kay?
It also can even be the return type for fun, for functions,
这甚至也可以给函数返回对象
like that button with type I talked about a few slides ago?
就像是前几张幻灯片中我说过的那个类型
It actually returns any object,
这真的会返回任意类型
it doesn't return a UI button, you would think it would, but
这不会返回一个UI Button，你可能想这会返回这样一个类型
it doesn't, it returns any object.
但是不会，他会返回任意对象
Okay, so, this,
就是这样
you're probably like what the heck is going on.
你可能会想这是怎么了
Why would you be passing around these pointers if
为什么你要传递这些
you don't even know what these things are, okay?
甚至你不知道这些是什么的指针呢？
Well we'll talk a little bit why we do it but
我们稍微讨论了一下为什么做这个
let's talk first about how we use it, because it's this
来说说我们怎么用这个，因为这是一个指向未知对象的指针
pointer to unknown object, so I can't really send any
所有我不能真的发送任何信息
messages to it because I don't even know what it is, okay?
因为我甚至不知道这是什么
And so to use it, we convert it to a type we do know, kay?
和怎么去用，我们把他转换成一种我们知道的类型
That's the only way we're really gonna use any object,
我们唯一的用任何对象的方式
is to invert it to some class that we do know, all right?
就是把他转换成我们知道的类
And we do that with.
我们通过
By creating a new variable, so we, we've got some AnyObject,
建立一个新的变量AnyObject来实现它
it's a, it was an argument to a method, or
这是一个方法的参数
it's a local variable or
或者是一个本地变量
something like that, and we wanna convert it.
或者我们想要转型的类似它的东西
So, we're gonna create a new variable of the,
所以我们要建立一个新
of the type we wanna convert it to, okay?
我们想要转换的变量
And we're gonna assign this new variable to be
然后我们要把这个变量申明成
equal to that anyobject thing converted.
我们需要转换成的那种
Now, of course,
现在，当然
we have to convert it to a compatible type.
我们需要转换成一个合适的类型
It actually has,
它真的有的那种
has to actually be one of those things.
必须要转换成其中一种
So, if we got a UI button back from buttons type and
所以如果我需要从按钮的类型中取回UI Button这种
it comes back as any object,
这就会返回成任意类型
we can convert it to UI button, cuz it is a UI button.
你可以把他转换成UI Button，因为他真的是个UI Button
Kay? But
但是
we can't convert it to a UI label, it's not a UI label, so
但是不能转换成UI label，因为他不是个UI label
that would crash our program actually.
这会让你的程序崩溃
So, how do we do that conversion?
那我们怎么去做这个转换呢？
yeah, see, it will crash our program if we do that.
看到没，这会让我们的程序崩溃
How do we do that conversion safely so
如何安全的去做这个转型
we're not crashing our program all the time?
这样我们就一直不会让程序崩溃呢？
So, there's two ways, and we call this casting, kay?
这里有两种方式我们叫它转换
You know what typecasting is, we're essentially casting
你知道类型转换是什么，我们
the type from any object to something else.
本质上是把一个类型从任意类型转换成其他的
And we can typecast forcibly using the as keyword.
我们还可以用as 关键词强行转换
A S, as.
用as
Okay swift as usual, very succinct.
通常Swift是非常简洁的
And so I'm gonna use that destination view
下面我要用destinationViewController
controller thing as an example so
来做个例子
I've got this property destinationViewController.
我得到了这个destinationViewController作为属性
It's in any object.
这是个对象
And, I know it's a ViewController.
我知道这是个ViewController
And I think it should be a calculator ViewController.
我想这应该是个计算器ViewController
So, I'm gonna be using in my
我要在我的
examples CalculatorViewController.
CalculatorViewController里面用
Imagine we had called our CalculatorViewController,
想象一下我们调用CalculatorViewController
CalculatorViewController instead of ViewController.
是CalculatorViewController而不是ViewController
I'm doing that in examples because it,
我因为这个才用在我的例子里
it's just going to make more sense, okay?
这样能让你们更好理解
So, I want to talk to this destinationViewController,
所以我想说说这个destinationViewController
which is any object.
这个对象
And I know that it's a CalculatorViewController.
我知道这是个CalculatorViewController
And if it's not a CalculatorViewController,
如果这个不是个CalculatorViewController
my program should probably crash.
这个程序就应该会崩溃
Because, in the context I'm using it,
因为在用这个的环境下
I want it to be that.
我需要他是CalculatorViewController
Okay?
So, I can just say, let calcVC equals
所以可以let calcVC ＝
CalculatorViewController as CalculatorViewController.
destinationViewController as CalculatorViewController
And now, calcVC, this new constant, its type is
现在，擦了擦VC这个常量的类型
not any object, its type is CalculatorViewController.
不是其他任何类型，而是CalculatorViewController
And so now, I've gotten hold of that AnyObject in
所以现在我可以这种方法获得任意对象
a way that I can actually do things with it,
然后用这个来处理
and I can send messages,
也可以发送消息
CalculatorViewControl messages, to calcVC.
CalculatorViewControl 消息给calcVC.
Now, you can protect against crashing if
现在你就可以防止崩溃了
you're not sure whether that destinationViewController is
你不确定destinationViewController是不是
a CalculatorViewController, but you're hoping it is.
一个CalculatorViewController，但你希望是
Okay?
You can use as question mark.
你可以用一个问号
And as question mark returns an optional.
as？会返回一个可选的
Same as as, right, as returns that any object thing cast to
跟as一样返回任意类型
be a different class.
转换到其他类型
As question mark does the same thing, but it's optional
问号做了同样的事，但是可选版本的
version of that, so we can return nil if that any object,
如果destinationViewController
destinationViewController cannot be
不能转换成CalculatorViewController
turned into a CalculatorViewController,
那就返回nil
because it's not a CalculatorViewController some
other kinda ViewController or something else.
All right?
And so you can say,
if let calcVC equals destinationViewController as
CalculatorViewController, and
then inside there, you've got calcVC set.
And it's, you know that it's a CalculatorViewController.
And any object is now in your past, okay?
Make sense? So, we have as and
as question mark.
You can also check beforehand if you just wanna see, is this
a CalculatorViewController, you can say is.
So, you can say if destinationViewController is
a calculation view CalculatorViewController,
then I'll go ahead and, then I can do the as, for example.
But usually we use the as question mark, you know,
check it and convert it all in one go.
Okay?
So that's how we're gonna use an AnyObject.
We're gonna have to cast it with as into something else.
Question?
Is there a way to check if it's not [INAUDIBLE] it
doesn't [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah. So the question is,
is there a way to kind of ask it what the type is and
get the answer back in some way?
And, the answer is, for the purposes of where you are, no.
Okay? You don't do that.
You, you, you ask it for
certain, whether it can be a certain thing.
You don't ask it, what are you?
And then try and figure it out from there.
Just, that's, we're not gonna use that paradigm.
Okay?
Let's talk about arrays of any object.
Cuz sometimes you're gonna get an array of any object back,
like that constraints one I was talking about.
Where it's going to be an array of constraints that
are going to be AnyObject, but I know they're going to be in
this layout constraint, but they're going to be an array.
So, you can do
some interesting things with casting there.
So, let's use the toolbar items one,
so that toolbar items it's a, that's a property on
UIViewController and it returns an array that's gonna
have UI bar button items in it.
But, for historical reasons it returns the square bracket
of AnyObject.
So, I can say for
item in toolbar items, then item is gonna be in AnyObject.
So, I'm enumerating those AnyObject.
And I'm actually having my variable item be AnyObject,
but then inside I'm saying,
if I can let the toolbar item equal, you know,
be a UI bar button item, then I'm good to go.
So, you see how I'm enumerating this array of
any object.
Then the objects, and
then inside I'm doing the as question mark.
But I can do it another way to.
Kay? Which is I can say, for
toolbarItem in toolbarItems as an array of UIBarButtonItem.
Another words, I can cast the entire array.
If I know that that array of many objects is
really an array of UIBarButton item, I can just cast it.
Now this one, you can't do question mark, because it
wouldn't make sense to say for toolbarItem in nil, okay?
So, that makes no sense.
So, you can't here,
you better be darn sure that that array has what you want.
But then inside, now toolbarItem is a tool,
UIBarButtonItem, cuz I've casted the whole array from
array of any object to array of UIBarButtonItem.
You understand the difference there between those two?
Okay another example of AnyObject and
where it appears.
So, if we hadn't changed, when we control drag to
make a appendDigit, what if we had left at any object?
Kay? So we had
a appendDigit sender colon any object.
How could we have dealt with that?
Well, we just would've said,
if we can let the sendingButton equal sender as
a UIButton, then do what we do, let digit equals
sendingButton.currenTitle exclamation point,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
Make sense?
But we didn't want to put that extra if let and
I hadn't talked to you about as, so
that's why I said be sure to put that thing UIButton.
All right?
Now you might ask, why is that even in AnyObject?
When I control dragged, why did he just put UIButton?
Why did it even offer any object?
Well, because you could have an action that is sent
by two different kinds of UI elements.
Maybe it's set by a button and also by a slider.
I don't know what that would be,
I couldn't even think of an example of that.
But you possibly could, It's theoretically possible.
And in that case the sender would be AnyObject.
And you would have,
say if the sender is a slider then do one thing, else,
if the sender is a button, then do something else.
And you would do that with as.
Okay?
So, the rea,
that's why I'm saying I think that default should not be
AnyObject cuz that's a pretty rare case, where two
different kinds of UI elements are sending the same thing.
So, why do the rare case, even though that's the more
generic or more general case, I agree.
It still just seems kinda error prone to me, but anyway.
So there's another a, AnyObject example.
So here's one more AnyObject thing.
Let's go back to that button thing.
So I told you
the buttonWithType returns AnyObject, kay?
And so if I got a button and I wanted to find out
it's title or something like that, I have to cast it.
So, I would call UIBut, I would call that button with
type and I can cast on the fly, right in line.
So, if I called that line green at the top,
then down here I could say the title of the button
equals button as UIButton.currentTitle.
So, I'm just casting that AnyObject,
that button AnyObject up there, to be a UIButton, and
then sending it a message.
So, you can cast on the fly.
Again, crasheroo [LAUGH] if that button is not a button,
but that's okay.
In this case,
button with type better darn well return a UI button.
Okay, now this casting business is not just for
any object.
You can actually cast any two objects.
For all non any object case though, obviously those two
objects will have to be in the same inheritance hierarchy.
Right?
Can only cast down you know,
down cast into your own inherit this hierarchy.
So, for example, if I had a local variable called vc
which was of type UIViewController, but I set it
to CalculatorViewController, okay?
I couldn't say vc.enter, right?
Enter is a method in our CalculatorViewController.
I couldn't say vc.enter because vc
is a UIViewController.
So as far as Swift knows, it doesn't respond to enter.
Even though it is in fact, a CalculatorViewController,
from Swift's point of view, that local variable is not.
It's a type UIViewController.
But I could cast it and say if I can let the calcVC equal vc
as a CalculatorViewController, now I can say vc.,.
. . calcVC.enter.
Okay.
So you can cast,
downcast through your inherit hierarchy as well.
We rarely do that but, you might occasionally.
All right.
So let's zoom on here to every,
any questions about that whole anti-object thing?
When you see it in action,
it'll make a lot more sense, okay?
okay. So now let's just
talk about some fun functions throughout all our classes.
And we're gonna start with array.
First of all that you know,
you know that array does plus equals.
Can do, say array plus equals.
But the argument plus equals is another array.
Okay, so if you just wanna add one thing to an array using
plus equals, you would have to put it in another array.
Just square brackets, put the thing inside, okay?
Some people get tripped up by this.
They do plus equals, you know, they have an array of ints,
and they say my array of ints plus equals an int, and
they're like, oh, why doesn't it work?
It's because plus equal only adds whole arrays to
other arrays.
It's an array concatenater, okay?
There's a couple of interesting variables,
properties in array first and last that will
return the first or last item in the array.
What's interesting about them is
that they return an optional.
So, they don't do array index out of bounds.
So, thay'll return nil if your array is empty.
Okay? So,
you should know, you should know about these because they
can make your code read really nicely sometimes.
so, for these next ones I'm
gonna have a little example array here,
this can be an array that's got three things in it.
I'm not even gonna say what the types of
those three things in there, they could be anything, okay?
Cuz array is generic, right?
Array angle bracket T.
You can assume for
the purposes of this, they're of type T.
Whatever the T is that I created the array with, right?
So, let's talk about, you know about append.
That's how you add something to array,
we did that in the calculator all the time.
There's also insert, so
you can inset something in the middle of your array.
You just specify what index.
There is also splice.
Kay? Splice will take
another array and splice it into the middle of your array.
Kay? So that can
sometimes be invaluable.
It's otherwise just like insert, it's just like
inserting another array inside the array.
Okay there's also removeAtIndex of course of
course its a var, if you've got you're array in
a var you can do removeAtIndex and
there's also removeRange, okay?
So you can specify a range with the dot dot dot thing or
the dot dot dot less than thing and
remove a range of your array elements.
And there's also replaceRange, and
when you replace a range, the thing you replace it with
doesn't have to be the same length.
So, I can have an array and replace a range that
spans three things with something that is six long,
and make my array it'll make my array longer, okay?
So you can replace range.
There's also sorting.
You can sort an array.
The sorting method in array takes one argument and
that's just a function to determine whether two
things are ordered before each other or not.
Kay? So, it's
going through the array and putting everything in order.
It needs to know, it pick, picks out,
however whatever sort, if it's Quicksort or
I don't know what sort it's using in there.
But it needs to be able to compare things so
you just provide a function desk comparison and
usually you're going to do it with a closure just like this.
You can see this is kind of the default sorting assuming
that this type can just be compared with less than.
I would just say a dot sort, closure, $0 > $1.
Make sense?
And that's gonna return yes, if $0 < $1, and
that's what sort wants to know and
it's gonna call that closure repeatedly okay?
As it's going through doing it's quick sort or whatever.
There's also another one call sorted.
So we're ta, this is an in place sort.
Right? Sorts the array in place.
They're sorted, will return a new array that is sorted.
Okay? A copy of your array sorted.
More array methods.
Okay, so these three are pretty cool.
This one's called filter.
So filter will give you a new array with all
the undesirable elements filtered out of there.
And the way you specify which ones are all undesirable is
with the argument which is a function,
that just returns a Bool,
whether something's undesirable or not.
Make sense?
And there's another one you can do by mapping.
So this will give you a new array where every single
element in your array is mapped to something else.
And the thing you map it to doesn't even have to
be the same type, so I can have an array of ints, and
I could map it to an array of strings.
And that's what I've done here.
So I have this array of ints, 1, 2, 3, and
I've mapped it using a closure that
returns the stringification of it to an arrayed strings.
Now, you can see, incredibly concise language swift.
I mean, to take an array of ints and turn it into an array
of strings, no for loops, no nothing.
Just, you know, running a dozen characters here.
So you really want to take advantage of some of
the things swift can do with closures, syntax and
things like that.
You can also reduce an entire array to, to a single value.
So this one takes an argument which is the initial value you
want to start with.
And then it just takes a function that
takes the value so far and the next element in the array and
you return what the combination is.
So you're just combining, combining, combining.
So for example if you wanted to add up an array,
you could say [1, 2, 3.]reduce.
Start with a 0, and then my closure just gonna add
the next element, which is the $1 to, so far which is $0.
Okay all right, string.
So string is a little bit complicated.
I can tell all the, by the way,
already I'm not gonna get to the end of this so
we'll finish this next Wednesday.
This whole slide package here but.
So string.
String is complicated when it comes to indexing.
You know, creating sub strings and stuff like that.
A lot of people are like, oh, I can't even figure out how to
make a substring of a string in Swift.
It's so complicated.
But once you understand that strings are made of unicode
characters and when you get a substring, you actually don't
want a substring of unicode characters.
You want a substring of
unicode characters that are on glyph boundaries.
A glyph is something you perceive to be a character.
But in unicode, it could be
multiple characters making up one glyph.
For example, an accent.
So you know, a lot of European languages, there's accents,
okay, maybe you know, in French, you have accent aigu,
right, which is the forward going top slash.
Well, that could be two unicode characters, E and
the accent character.
So two characters makes what you perceive to be one glyph.
So you can't index into this string which is
an array of characters.
That's what a string is,
a string is array of in essentially,
internally a collection or
collection of unicode characters.
You can't really index by Int or
you might be halfway through the e accent aigu, and
you're getting you know, either the ac, accent aigu or
the e but not the character.
So instead strings are indexed by this other type called
string.index.
Okay? Now how do
you get a string.index?
Okay, well, yes.
It's saying here.
Okay?
So you get a sting.index by getting the start index of
the string.
That gives you string.index that point to
the first character of the string.
And then you advance it forward,
however many times you wanna go.
So in other words, you have to look through the characters so
that it will jump over e accent aigu,
both characters to the next one, you see?
So you do that with this function,
it's not a method in string, it's actually just a function,
a global function called advance.
And you give it the index, okay, and
you tell it how many times you want it to move forward.
And it will give you back a new index.
So here's an example.
I have a string that says hello, okay?
I wanna get the index of the L, the first L.
Okay? So I say,
let the index equal advance,
the start index of that string, go forward two.
Okay?
So now it's pointing at the l.
It went forward one to the e, now forward one to the l.
And again, if that, it was e accent aigu,
it would have gone forward four Unicode characters, but
only three to the third glyph, as you perceive it, okay?
So now that I have a pointer to that L, I could use, for
example, a nice string function called splice.
So splice is just like the splice in array.
It will splice a string into the middle of another string.
Okay? And I'm gonna have a splice at
that index, and that's gonna make it be heabcllo.
Splice the abc right into the middle there.
Okay?
So, this startIndex is the magic behind making that work.
Also if I said, if I got two local variables star deck,
Index, and endIndex, which I made by taking advance of
the startIndex by one and six.
So this is going to be, I want it to be from index one to
index six, then I could get a substring and
I get a substring and in the string exactly the same like
an array, square brackets.
String, square brackets.
But inside that square brackets goes arrange.
And the range, the dot, dot,
dot thing has to have a string.index on the left and
a string.index on the right, not ints.
Okay?
So here I got string.index.
By doing this advance for the left and a String.Index on
the right, until the substring will be eabcl.
Cuz I went from index one,
which is the second character, index zero is the first, or,
to index six, not including index six, okay?
Everyone understand String.Index now?
It's all about advance, 'kay?
The advance function is the key to understanding how to
substring strings.
And, there's lots of other, once you understand this,
there's things like range of string.
Remember we used range of string in calculator, and it,
I told you it returned nil if it couldn't find it?
Well, what does it return if it could find it?
Well, it returns a Range of String.Index.
Actually, it
returns an Optional Range of String.Index.
Okay? That's how, if you used it for
your assignment, that's how you used it.
You used the Optional nature of it,
but now you can even use the Range nature of it.
So for example, if we wanted to
get the whole number portion of a string that had a number.
So I have, let's say, 56.25 as a string,
I wanna get the whole number part.
I could just say find me that decimal point.
Kay? And that's gonna
return a range if, if it can find it.
If there's a decimal point in
there it's gonna return that range.
And I'm gonna grab the part from the num.startIndex,
you see the num is the number, it's startIndex all the way
to where the decimal is, not including the decimal, okay?
Now I've got sub string which is the whole part.
Are we cool with that?
So sub stringing and strings actually,
once you understand this whole index thing pretty powerful.
We could even remove the whole number part.
'Kay, just by using removeRange of that same
range, num.startIndex, the decimal range.
Or we can replace the range with other things, etc.
Okay, so there's a lot of string methods there for
doing that and they're all based on that string index.
Okay, other string methods,
I'm gonna start blasting through a lot of this.
You could look these all up in the documentation.
Some of these it actually gets from NSString,
which I'm gonna talk about in a moment.
You can see that you can find the endIndex,
there is the join takura talked about before
notice that there's toInt but not toDouble.
Why is there toInt in string and not toDouble?
Anybody having any idea why it is?
It's because when you convert to a double,
you have to specify things.
How many significant digits do you want?
How many digits after the fraction do you want,
things like that?
And so there's really nowhere to specify that.
It would have to be toDouble with a whole bunch of
arguments to specify how you wanna do that conversion.
When you convert to an int, there's nothing inside,
you just convert it to the int, right?
So the whole number so but notice that toInt does return
an optional int, that's because if you say toInt,
if you send out to hello, it's going to be nil, okay?
So, string methods, all right?
Okay, there's kind of a hidden bunch of methods which you
don't even know about, which is conversions using init.
So for example, if I had a Double and
a float, I could say, let x equal Int of that double, and
I just basically create a floor and turned it to an int.
So I converted it.
So I know you convert things and
convert them from one thing to another.
It makes total sense with the number values like ints and
floats and things like that.
And you're gonna see CGFloat next week.
That's another kind of floating point number.
And you can convert using.
There's no toInt or anything.
You just create a new one with the initializer.
'Kay, so the numbers.
But you almost might be surprised.
Actually, if you read the homework carefully or
the reading assignment, you saw this.
Is that you can convert arrays and
strings using these intitializers.
For example, you can say array of a string, so create a new
array and the initializers argument is a string.
And it will return you an array of
all the characters in that string, right?
Unicode characters.
Or vice versa, you can have an array of unicode characters.
Right?
And it will, and you pass that to strings constructor and
it will return the string with those things zipped up.
Okay?
So there's kind of a hidden thing there.
Notice that you can't do string of 52.5,
but that's okay because you have that back slash,
open-parenthesis thing to convert.
Of floats to strings.
Okay? You can do
string of 52 though.
Cuz it has toInt, it kinda knows how to do that.
All right, assertions.
So assertions, really valuable debugging aid.
They basically take a closure as the first argument.
It's an auto closure,
which means you don't need the curly braces.
Is this just kind of funky think, okay.
So the first argument is what would be inside the,
the curly braces of a closure.
And the second argument is some string that's gonna be
printed out on your console because assert, if whatever
that thing that was in the auto-closure evaluates to,
if that's not true.
'Kay, cuz you're asserting that that's true,
then it's gonna crash your program.
Okay, and print that message out.
So it's a great way to make
your program crash when things that should be true aren't.
Now, asserts don't work when you build your program for
release, like to the App Store.
When you're shipping to the App Store, asserts don't work.
It doesn't even evaluate the closure, okay,
they're just ignored.
But for debugging, it's pretty good.
So I might have a function called validation that should,
at this point that I'm executing this assert
not be returning nil.
And if it does return nil then I'm going to crash here.
So I say the assertion is that validation should not be
nil right now.
'Kay?
So a lot of languages have assert so swift does too.
okay, other function, so there's a lot of function and
these do not appear to be documented anywhere yet.
So the slide might be your only documentation.
I'm sure you can find about them on the internet instead
of too but there's a lot of functions.
These are global functions, not methods.
They take arguments which are hard for
me to explain to you right now.
But basically they take arrays and strings, and dictionaries,
because they take other things that arrays and
strings, and dictionaries are, those things.
But you can look through this list kinda interesting things.
I can combine it with the thing I
was talking about at the end there with the string.
Passing in an array of characters.
I can actually take a string, call a reverse, which returns
an array of the characters reversed and then call string
to push it back and call it, create a string again.
All right?
Objective-C Compatibility.
You know what?
We are going to wait and talk about this next time.
Very important topic.
But I don't want to give it short shrift.
So, that is it for today.
Let me, quickly, show you, this slide.
Okay coming up, no Friday section this week.
Next Monday is holiday, no lecture.
Next Wednesday,
I might not be talking about auto layout next week,
I'm not sure.
Your homework one was due today, your homework two was
already posted, your reading assignment two was posted on
Monday, all that stuff is due next Wednesday.
If you have any questions, I'm here.
[SOUND] For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.