[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
>> Welcome to Stanford CS193P,
this is
winter quarter 2015.
And we're gonna dive right in
today to
some brief slide work.
This people at Stanford, you've
got a
document that describe,
describes all the grading and
all that
stuff so
I'm not gonna go over that in
lecture like
I often do to start the quarter.
Instead I'm gonna talk a little
bit about,
what this class is about.
Brief mention of the
prerequisites cuz
they're pretty important in this
class.
Then just the [NOISE] quickest
overview of
iOS.
I'm gonna assume that anyone who
is here
or is watching this, knows what
that is.
And then, we're gonna dive right
into a
big old demo.
It's gonna be a two-day thing,
where I'm
really going to try and
introduce you to Xcode and the
development
environment and
this language Swift, that you're
gonna
have to learn to develop for
iOS.
All right, so what is this class
about?
It's about building cool apps,
as we know.
Why are these iOS apps so cool?
Well, because the device you're
gonna run
them on is in your pocket or
in your backpack.
Either, if you write an app, you
can just
pull it out and show your
friends and
it's highly networked and
incredible
graphics with animation.
It's just cool all the way
around and I
think you guys all know that or
you wouldn't be here.
But you're also gonna learn in
this class a lot of real life
Object-Oriented Programming.
You're taking a lot of other
classes here
at Stanford on things like
graphics, and
networking, and databases, and
maybe
animation.
Things like that.
And we're gonna is kinda tie
that all
together into a real world
class.
'Kay?
You're gonna get to see all this
stuff.
Now, you know, it's gonna be
kind of a
survey course in that,
I can't go too deep into
networking.
databases.
I can't go too deep into
animation, but
you'll get to see it all in a
really real
world environment, where people
out there
building apps using that
technology.
For some of you who haven't seen
that
before that'll be a big bonus of
this class, I think.
The prerequisites of this class.
Number one thing is you have to
be a
pretty strong Object-Oriented
programmer.
If you're not a strong
Object-Oriented
programmer, and
you hit this class, you're
probably gonna
go under water, pretty quick.
Okay?
I'm gonna assume you know,
everything about Object-Oriented
Programming.
IOS is a completely
Object-Oriented
Programming envir,
development environment,
I just don't mean I'm not just
talking
about the language is
Object-Oriented.
But the entire design of it the
way you
use it if you're not
comfortable with things like
subclassing
and
stuff like that then you're just
really
gonna be behind the curve.
In iOS so at Stanford here that
means
CS16A and B or
CS16X, and then you know, CS107,
while
it's not really Object-Oriented
course,
at least it's a heavy duty
programming
course.
CS108 is a great Object-Oriented
course so
if you have, if you've taken
CS108 you'll
probably, be really well
prepped.
110, again not really too much
an
Object-Oriented program but
good programming course cuz
there's a lot
of programming in this class,
in fact, all the work in this
class is
programming.
You will not have, a little bit
of reading
the first couple of weeks just
to
kinda learn this new language,
but it's
almost all programming after
that all
the way til the end, including
your final
project.
So if you're not really
comfortable with
all these terms,
this Object-Oriented terms or if
you're
just not really comfortable with
writing big programs then this
class will
definitely be a challenge for
you.
okay, so what's in iOS, what are
the parts
of it?
You know, it's ha, it's such a
big system,
it's got so much in it.
It's impossible for me to,
like, encapsulate it into a
small little
summary but.
I do have this slide right here
that
divides it into these four
layers.
These four layers are
approximately down
near the hardware at the bottom.
Up near the user at the top.
Okay?
So at the bottom, so
a lot of people don't realize
that iOS is
basically a Unix-based operating
system.
'Kay?
It's very similar shares a lot
of
the core of Mac OS 10.
Okay?
Now, it's certainly optimized
for mobile
devices, which have
battery restrictions and things
like that,
but that is basically what it
is.
And so down at that layer you've
got
sockets, and
you've got you know,
permissions, and
things like that,
that have to be near the oh you
know,
hardware to, to work properly.
But above that there's kind of
an
Object-Oriented layer that lets
you get at
a lot of that stuff using
Object-Oriented
Programming.
'Kay?
And this stuff is not UI
oriented it's
more kind of accessing the
hardware
through Object-Oriented
Programming or
accessing networking through
Object-Oriented Programming but
it's a big layer there and so we
will
spend a fair amount of
time in this layer because we
need those
primitives to build at the
higher layers.
Then, there's this whole layer,
which I
wish we had more time to spend
on.
We only get ten weeks in this
whole class.
It goes by so fast, you'll be
amazed, as
you're probably,
used to with your Stanford
courses.
But there's a whole media layer
here, both
for
static images, as you know, JPEG
and
things like that.
And video both capturing video,
editing
video, all that.
Incredible audio, the frameworks
on this
device for
doing 3D audio for games and all
that.
I get to, unfortunately I get to
very
little of this layer.
But I'll try to let you know,
that it's in
there and then you'll know to go
out and
seek out, if you're building a
very audio
intensive app or
video intensive app, you'll seek
out that
layer.
But we'll spend the vast
majority of our
time at the Cocoa Touch layer.
So the Cocoa Touch layer, that's
where the
buttons and
sliders and things like that are
it's the
layer,
where you're gonna build the
interactivity
with your end user.
And so, that's where we probably
spend 70
plus percent of
our time in the Cocoa Touch
layer.
And this is a very powerful
You know, you've seen things
like the maps
app on the phone.
There's basically, an object
that does
almost the entire maps app, that
you can
just drop right into your
program, and now
you have maps in your program.
Same thing with web browser.
If you wanna put web browsing in
your app,
it's just boom, pop an object in
there,
call a couple methods and in
your, on your
way.
So very powerful, very high
level in
there's a lot going on in there
and
that's where we will spend most
of our
time, 'kay?
And by the way, if you have any
questions
I try to glance up, so
the bright lights over there
sometimes in
my way,
but, shout out or you know,
otherwise get
my attention.
If you feel free to interrupt.
Then there's the development
platform
itself.
'Kay?
With the tools we use to build
these iOS
apps.
What's in that?
Well, it's all pretty much now
been
funneled into this one
application called Xcode 6.
There are some little adjuncts
that it
calls out to but
Xcode 6 is everything, it's your
code
editor,
it's your compiler, your
debugger all of
that in one, pretty awesome app.
And so we'll be learning all
about Xcode 6
in this class, and
that's where you'll be spend all
your time
developing, you're not gonna be
at
a terminal typing in Emacs or
something,
you're gonna be in Xcode 6.
Languages I have there's
actually, two
languages in iOS now.
There are peers that you can
pretty much
use either one.
One of them is called
Objective-C,
that's the language that iOS was
originally developed for.
It's a language been around a
long time,
probably 30 years it's been
around or 25
to 30 years that's it's actually
been used
to build stuff that's on the Mac
today.
So, it's very mature language
but it's
also 25, 30 years old.
And so Apple last summer
introduced a
completely new language called
Swift, and
Swift, you can do pretty much
everything
in iOS with Swift and
that's the language we're gonna
learn
because it's a modern language.
Apple did a great job of kind
of, building
all the best stuff of
all the languages that have been
invented
over the last, you know,
25 years of this especially the
last five
or ten years into this language.
It's very concise it's a very
type safe
language but has type inference
and a lot
of things that make it so that
you get the
best of both worlds by having
type safety-
>> [COUGH]
>> And not have to
be constantly over specifying
everything.
So we're gonna go Swift only,
I'm not even
gonna really talk about
Objective-C,
I just don't have time to do
both
languages.
Yeah.
>> [INAUDIBLE] This is
a [INAUDIBLE] course [INAUDIBLE]
[COUGH]
[INAUDIBLE] doing iOS
development.
>> Yeah, so the question is if
I'm going
out into the world to do
iOS development in the real
world for real
companies.
Am I probably, gonna have to
learn
Objective-C?
And the answer is [NOISE] it
depends on
the company you're at.
Probably in the short term, yes.
But as the time goes by
probably, more and
more people switch to siff,
Swift.
>> [COUGH]
>> The good thing is the
underlying iOS
APIs are exactly the same for
both, its
just the syntax-
>> [COUGH]
>> Of the language a little bit
about how the language
approaches calling
the API is slightly different,
but any,
everything that you learn in
here about
the underlying,
lying parts of iOS will totally
work in
Objective-C.
All the methods are the same you
know,
it's just the syntax is a little
different.
>> [COUGH]
>> So, don't feel too bad about
not
learning both languages, and
once you've
learned this language,
learning Objective-C is gonna be
pretty
easy, too.
So.
Good question though.
All right.
Of course iOS is filled with
tons of
frameworks.
Frameworks are libraries,
basically, of
objects that you use,
as building blocks to build your
application.
And we are going to be covering
them.
UIKit is the main one.
It's got most of the user
interface stuff
in it.
Foundation is that most the
course
services layer that I was
talking about,
and but there's tons of other
ones, core
motion for doing the, the device
moving
around, you know, gyro and
accelerometer,
core data for Object-Oriented
database.
Things like that.
So I'll get to, as many as those
as I can,
especially the big ones.
But there's just way too many to
cover in
ten weeks.
And finally we I, I put this,
as a first class thing with all
the rest,
as a design strategy MVC.
I think, I usually ask, I'll all
ask this
year, too.
How many people have used MVC in
some
other class?
See, so it's half of you.
So I'll be teaching MVC, as if
you don't
know it, so
if you don't know it don't
worry.
But MVC is a way of designing
your
application so that it's a
little more
debuggable, reusable
understandable to you
and to anyone reading your code.
And iOS was designed with MVC
from the
start.
So it's just integral part to
building an
iOS.
Now, I'm gonna do the demo
today, and on
Wednesday I'm kinda not gonna
follow MVC.
But then next Monday we're gonna
apply MVC
to the demo I'm doing today and
Wednesday, so you're gonna get
the full
MVC treatment there.
And I'll be having some slides
on MVC on
Wednesday to prepare you for
next Monday.
Okay?
All right, so here's the demo.
The demo I'm gonna do,
is something I actually did a
few years
ago that really works well-
>> [COUGH]
>> With Swift, which is a
calculator.
So, we're gonna build this
And we're gonna build it from
scratch, all
the way.
And I like to do my demos, where
I only
type in stuff, I don't copy and
paste big chunks of code in or
whatever.
I know, I'd see a lot of laptops
open, a
lot of people like to try and
follow along with me.
I'm a fast typer, but usually in
most
demos you can keep, keep up if
you want.
I don't recommend it
necessarily, or
certainly I don't require it.
I am going to, you, you'll be
able to go
back and
watch this particular demo on
video.
Even Stanford people will be
able to do
that.
Because your first assignment is
gonna be
to reproduce what I do.
'Kay?
That is 90% of your first
assignment.
Reproduce what I'm gonna do,
today and on
Wednesday.
So I'm not gonna post the code
because I
want you to go through the
experience of
typing the code in, and if you
watch in on
video,
watching what I do again, and
and typing
it all in.
>> [COUGH] 'Kay?
And I'll explain that all on
Wednesday.
Okay?
So, I put on the slide a bunch
of things
that I'm gonna cover, but I'm
not gonna go
over it in advance, I'm just
gonna sit,
sit and soon I'll start doing
it.
So any questions before I dive
in here?
I know we're gonna little fast,
but I
wanna maximize your learning
time.
[INAUDIBLE]
[NOISE].
Direct of what?
Recommendation to which Xcode-
So the questions, which Xcode
should we
use, should you use?
Well, you should just use the
one on the
Mac App store.
So, just go to the Mac App
store, it's
free.
Use the one there, whatever the
latest one
is.
If a new one comes out in the
quarter,
well, let's all switch over to
it.
Okay, let's just always be using
the
latest Xcode.
'Kay any-
[INAUDIBLE] Beta [INAUDIBLE] No.
Not.
We're not gonna using a beta or
anything like that.
We'll just use whatever the
currently
published Xcode is.
Okay.
So, I'm going to start this demo
actually
by launching Xcode.
So, here it is, right here.
Xcode.
And when you launch Xcode, let's
hide
others here.
You're gonna get this splash
screen and
on this splash screen on the
right, this
is gonna be all your projects.
Now, since it's the beginning of
the
quarter, we don't have any
projects yet,
but they'll all be listed here,
so as the
quarter goes by this will fill
up.
You can turn this splash screen
off, if
you don't like it by the way.
This splash screen also lets us
do things
like playgrounds and
a source code management right
down here.
We're not gonna be doing that
for a while.
We're gonna be focusing on this
option,
right here.
Create a new Xcode project.
If you don't have the splash
screen, you
can go to File > New > Project.
Kay.
Same thing, those both the same
thing.
So I'm gonna click right here on
Create a
new project.
When I create a new project, it
wants to
know what kind of project you
want to
create, because Xcode is
actually used on
Mac OS 10 and to build
frameworks and
all that stuff.
But we're always gonna be
building iOS
Applications.
And in fact, we're always gonna
use this
template right here,
Single View Application.
'Kay?
That's kind of your basic MVC
starter
application and
we're gonna build very
complicated apps
out of that, but we're gonna
start here,
so you always click on that one.
Then it wants to know what you
want to
call your app, and
we're building a calculator, so
we're
gonna call our app, Calculator.
'Kay?
This organization name doesn't
really
matter that's just gonna appear
in
copyright notice and the code
that you
write at the top in a comment so
don't worry about that.
But this organization identifier
that is
very important.
'Kay, this uniquely identifies
you.
Okay?
So that on the next line we can
you just,
new uniquely idefy, identify
your
calculator.
So here if your a Stanford
student,
you'll wanna use this reverse
DNS notation
here edu.stanford.cs1983p.
And instead of instructor there,
you wanna
put your SU net ID.
'Kay?
Cuz nobody else has that but
you.
And that'll uniquely identify
As I said, we're using Swift not
Objective-C.
And we're gonna build an app
that works
be, equally well on iPad and
iPhone, that's called a
universal app.
You can pick to develop for only
one or
the other.
But we are going to go universal
here.
We're not gonna really be doing
the iPad
part of it for a couple weeks.
But it is our intent to
eventually build
an app that works on both.
Okay we're not going to be using
core
data,
that's object oriented database
stuff so
you just leave that unchecked.
And now it's asking where we
want to save
it, I strongly recommend saving
in your
home directory, this is my home
directory
here in a folder called
Developer, okay?
You could put other folders in
here if you
want to arrange it more,
but home directory Developer, I
highly
recommend that.
Source control, we will be
talking about
that at some point in the
quarter but
we're not gonna do it right off
the bat
here so
you can leave that unchecked as
well.
All right, so here's our first
project,
its been created so
this is Xcode that your seeing
right here,
this is Xcode's main screen and
the center is really what your
working on.
The left is, area here, is
called the
navigator, and the navigator
you,
you use to kind of choose what
you're
working on but you can also do
things over here like search
though your
whole project, that's this
little guy.
Look at all your break points
maybe, look
at previous builds that you've
done,
browse your project by class
hierarchy,
all that stuff.
But we're usually on the left
most one
here which is just all of the
files in
your project which can also can
be
organized hierarchically like
this.
And when you select something
here on the
left,
the middle will fill up with
what that
you've selected so.
Here I have the actual project
itself
selected.
So these are the project
settings of which
there are tons.
All along the top here you can
see tons of
settings.
We're, we'll go through them as
the
quarter goes on and
you've already seen some of them
like the
bundle identifier there and
the fact this is a universal
app.
We're not going to talk about
anymore of
this today,
this project settings business.
We're gonna focus here on some
of these
files.
And even some of these files,
like this
AppDelegate,
I'm just gonna move that down to
Supporting Files to get it out
of the way.
Same things with these image
assets,
LaunchScreen well get to this
later in the
quarter.
But I wanna focus on these two
files right
here.
Okay Main.storyboard and
ViewController.swift, okay?
In the MVC world by the way,
this is the
V,
the view and this is the C, the
controller
but we will talk about MVC on
Wednesday.
So what do these things contain?
So this Main.storyboard, if I
click on it,
you see it appear in the middle,
this is
our UI.
Okay, this is our user
interface.
So for a calculator this is
going to be a
little display,
this shows the number that we're
working
on or whatever at the top.
And lots of buttons down here,
number
buttons, times, multi, or sorry,
times,
divide, plus, minus, square
root.
That's all going to be here.
So we're going to build this
entire user
interface.
Purely graphically.
Okay?
We're not gonna be writing code.
Put button at this location.
None of that, okay?
We just literally with our mouse
are gonna
build this whole user interface.
So what's the code, what do we
need any
code for?
Well, we, this
ViewController.swift, this
is a Swift file.
This is your first look at Swift
for most
of you.
This controller is gonna control
that user
interface.
That's why we call it the view
controller
or the controller.
It controls user interface and
that means
it's gonna do things that
are specific to how this user
interface, a
calculator's user interface,
works.
So when we press the digit
buttons, it's
going to have update the
display.
When we press times, it's gonna
have to do
some multiplication and
then put the result in the
display.
So it's controlling the display.
Okay so we'll get back to this
code in a
moment but we're gonna start by
building our user interface and
by the
way, your user interface, you
can see I
have a low resolution screen
here so my UI
doesn't even really fit in the
space here.
You'll probably have maybe a
little higher
resolution screen then I do but
if you don't, you can zoom in
and out, I'm
just right-clicking,
if you right-click on the
background area
here, you can zoom in and out.
You can also do it by
double-clicking so
if I double-click on this,
it zooms it to normal, if I
double-click
on the background, it zooms out
so
that way I can see my whole UI.
Now when we build a complicated
app,
we're gonna have a whole bunch
of these
little square areas, we call
these scenes,
and a scene represents kind of
phone full,
phone screen full of
information.
Okay and as you you've used many
iOS
applications, you know that you
transition from one screen to
another as
the user goes through the app
and
that's how your gonna build your
apps as
well.
And this storyboard is
eventually gonna
have a big map showing all
the transitions between all
those scenes.
Okay, so this storyboard is
gonna get big
for
big apps, your really gonna see
your whole
application which is kinda cool.
So we're gonna start small
though, just
this one little screen right
here.
Which is gonna be our
calculator.
So let's start building our
calculator
with it's display.
So I wanna make a display.
So how do I do that?
Well that brings us to the right
side, the
right-hand side here,
this whole right side, this is
called the
Utilities area.
You can see that's it's got a
bottom and a
top, right?
We want to go into the bottom
and on the
third tab right here, which is
called
the Object Library, you'll see
that
there's tons and tons of objects
in here.
Okay, dozens of these things and
we're gonna get to a lot of
these by the
end of the quarter.
But these are the things you
build your
user interface out of.
So kind of towards the top, not
all the
way at the top, but towards the
top,
you'll start seeing things like
buttons
and text fields and things like
that.
Well this is what we need
obviously, to
build our display here,
is some sort of text field, and
there's a
couple of them here.
One, this one called Label is
static text,
you see?
And this one Text Field is
editable text,
in other words you can touch on
this one.
And the little keyboard would
slide up
from the bottom and you could
type in it.
So, the calculator, you can't
really touch
on the screen and
start typing so we want this
static text.
So, I'm just going to pick this
up with
the mouse and drag it out.
Now, when I drag it out into my
UI,
you're going to see a lot of
little blue
dash lines appearing.
You see these?
These are helping me put this in
the right
place.
So, I can put it right in the
center, for
example, of my view.
I could put it up in a corner up
here,
which is what I'm gonna do.
Mm-kay.
You always want your things that
you put
in your UI,
as much as humanly possible, to
be on one
of these dashed blue lines.
And you'll understand why in a
couple
weeks when we
starting talking about
auto-layout.
I'm gonna do a little
auto-layout right
here just to kind of
give you a feel for it.
But those blue, dashed blue
lines are
gonna be your best friend when
it comes to
building your user interface and
you'll
quickly see why that is.
Once you drag something out like
this, you
can,
these little things are rounded
that show
it's selected, right?
They also are little resize
handles so you
can grab them and resize them
when you
resize it also re-puts those
dashed blue
lines out there, okay?
So you definitely wanna, even
have,
when you're resizing, get those
things
lining up.
You can also manipulate it
directly, just
double-click on it, like a
calculator
probably doesn't want to come
up, this is
gonna be initial state of this.
Doesn't want to come up saying
Label, it
probably wants 0 or
something like that in it's
display.
There's also things you wanna
set about
this though or
anything you drag in your UI
that you just
can't direct manipulate and
that's what the top half of this
Utilities
windows is, is for, okay?
So if you look at the top half
here,
there's a bunch of tabs across
the top
including something like this,
the Size Inspector for setting
the size of
this thing.
And this tab right here, really
important,
this is the Attributes
Inspector.
And this is an object oriented
inspector,
depending on what you have
selected.
You'll have different user
interface here
in the top.
And this let's you edit
attributes about
what's selected.
So, for example,
a calculator, the zero doesn't
really want
to be on the left, right?
Calculators, the zero, the
numbers are on
the right and
they kind of grow out from the
right.
And so we can easily fix that
with this
alignment thing right here.
So I'm gonna click this and you
see the
zero move over to the right.
And, and maybe I want a bigger
font.
You see the font right here.
I can click on this, pick
different fonts.
I'm gonna just move it up to
like 32
point, it's a nice big font.
You can notice it kinda cuts
off.
I made it so big that it's too
small.
So I can always just resize this
larger to
make that fit.
So this is how we build our user
interface.
It's very direct manipulation
and very
object oriented as you'll start
to
see when we add different kinds
of
objects.
So, let's actually run this
application,
okay?
We haven't done, built any
calculaterness
about it, but
we have this one field, let's
run it and
see what it looks like.
So, how do you run things?
Well, you see right here where
it says,
iPhone 6?
This actually is a selector that
lets you
say where you want to
run your application.
So you can see you can run it on
an iOS
device if you have one
connected,
I don't have one connected
currently.
But you can do that.
And we'll talk in a Friday
section
probably in a week or
two about how to get your
devices hooked
up.
But also there's these plethora
of
simulators here, iPhone 6,
6+, iPhone 5, iPhone 4s, iPad
Airs.
And you can pick one of these to
run on
and
it'll actually simulate that
device right
here on your computer.
So I'm gonna run on the iPhone
6.
Okay,I'm just gonna hit Play,
see this
Play button right here?
That's how you simulate, so
Play.
Now it's launching the
simulator.
It's a separate process.
And it's going to run our app in
there.
And there it is.
Now you might say, whoop.
Big white square.
Oh that's not so good.
And the reason this is so
big is because the iPhone 6 has
a very
high resolution display on it.
Okay, the retina display, and
it's way
higher resolution than my
computer, okay?
So I actually have to scroll
around, you
see there's the top of it.
Scroll up and down to get to it
all.
Luckily if you go to Window,
this is not
in the simulator now, the iOS
simulator.
If you go to Window and Scale,
you can
scale it down to be smaller and
then it'll fit.
Okay, so if you have a low
resolution
screen,
you're definitely gonna wanna
use Window >
Scale.
Cmd+3 right there is another way
to do it.
Okay?
So here's our UI, but it doesn't
look to
good, okay, because where's
this?
We put this zero in there and it
just
never showed up, what did we do
wrong?
Well we didn't really do
anything wrong
and that zero is actually there.
It's just, here let me line up
these UI's,
this is not
necessarily exactly the same
scale but its
appropriate, approximately the
same scale,
you can see that the zero is
actually off
screen, [NOISE] okay?
So its there but you just can't
see it
because its over here off the
screen.
Okay, and that's a problem, but
that's a
problem we can fix.
So let's go fix that problem.
Why is that thing off-screen?
Well, look at this UI right
here, okay?
What shape is it?
It's square.
Okay, no IOS device is square.
There's not a single square iOS
device in
the world.
They're all, you know, tall and
thin, or, if you turn them
sideways, then
they're long and short.
Or even like an iPad.
You know the aspect ratio on an
iPad is
slightly different than an
iPhone so
their all slightly different,
but none of
them are square.
So why do we design our UI in a
square?
Because the way you design iOS
interfaces,
you design them in this square
and
you give everything inside the
square
rules, called constraints,
about what happens to them when
they get
squished down.
Either squished down vertically,
squished
down horizontally,
depending on what kinda device
their
getting put on, okay?
So you put these rules in there,
so, what
does it look like to put these
rules in?
Well again, it's all direct
manipulation,
so
I'm going to give some rules to
this label
right here to make it so that it
knows
what to do when this square gets
squished
down in any direction for any
device.
So, what do I want the rules to
be?
Well, I always want this thing
to use the
whole width.
However much width I have, I
want it all.
So I'm gonna pin this right edge
to this
edge, okay?
I'm gonna make it so all widths
are pinned
to each other.
And I do that with the Ctrl key.
I've turned on sticky keys so
you can see down in the lower
left here,
it's showing the modifier keys
I'm using.
So right now I'm holding down
Ctrl.
And I'm gonna Ctrl+drag from the
right
edge of this to the container
it's in.
See how it's showing me what I'm
dragged
to.
So when I drag to this
container, it puts
a menu up and says,
oh, okay, you want some rule
between that
label's right edge and
this thing's edge, what do you
want it to
be?
Well, I can do a lot of things
here.
I could center this label
vertically in
this container.
Up, you know, vertical up and
down.
I definitely don't want that, I
want my
label at the top, so I don't
want that.
I can make it the equal width,
so
I can make this label the same
width as
the container.
I don't want that either, cuz I
want this
little margin there, right?
But look at the top one,
trailing space to
container margin.
This lets me pin the trailing
space after
my label to the margin of the
container.
So that's the one I want, so I'm
gonna
click on this and it does it.
Now, see all these yellow and
orange lines
that appeared when I did that?
That's because the systems like,
okay,
you've started telling me the
rules for
this label, but your you haven't
told me
enough rules,
I don't know what to do with
this thing.
So now it's showing you all the
places
where it's like the system's not
sure what to do now when this
thing gets
squished.
Before it was like, okay, well
you weren't
telling me anything so
I'm not going to do anything,
but now your
starting to tell me.
So what do I do?
So we have to fully specify both
the what
happens horizontally and
vertically to this thing.
So we've only just started here.
So let's pin this edge also cuz
we want
this edge to stay on this side.
So I'm gonna hold down Ctrl and
drag.
And now I'm gonna pin the
leading space to
the container margin.
Okay, boom that did that.
Still have orange going on here,
that's
because I haven't specified
anything about
the vertical position of this
label so I'm
gonna pin the top to the top, so
hold Ctrl again, drag up here,
this is now
top space.
Notice that it realizes where I
am
dragging to and from, right?
So they can give me options that
make
sense,
like Top Space to Layout Guide
here.
So I'm going to do that.
So now I'm starting to get blue
lines.
You see these lines?
I hope you can see that there.
They're solid blue, not orange
or red.
Okay, that's because they're
okay, we are
okay horizontally here.
But we still have a problem
vertically.
Now I'm not sure exactly what
the problem
is vertically cuz I really don't
want the bottom of this.
I just want it to hang out
wherever it
wants to hang out based on the
size of my
font or whatever.
So I don't, I don't really wanna
specify
anything here so
why is this orange and how do I
get rid of
this?
Well any time you have orange
and when
you're doing this layout stuff
and
you don't know what to do.
You wanna go down to this button
right
here, okay?
This is the document outline.
And when you click this, a
little thing
will slide out, a little shelf
here.
And this is an outline view of
everything
that's in your UI.
Okay?
And they're linked, so
if I click the background,
nothing is
selected.
Then the background, the view is
what's
selected here.
But if I click this L0, which
means a
label with zero in it,
look it's selected my.
Zero label, and vice versa if I
click on
this here, it selects it over
here.
So this is this same thing in an
outline
mode.
This is really nice to have.
Sometimes you have views that
are
overlapping and they're kind of
in
each other's way, you can always
go here
to select the one you want,
okay?
And you can Ctrl+drag to these
over here
too it's just as much
Ctrl+draggable as
some of these other things.
But what we're, and we'll look,
we'll talk about top layout
guide, bottom
layout guide a little later.
稍后我们将讨论一下顶部和底部的布局指南。
But what I really want you to
focus on is
this little yellow circle up
here.
但是我想让你注意这个黄色的小圆圈
'Kay?
Any time you got yellow and
好的，任何时候，你都会在使用auto-Layout中看到黄色和橙色的警告
orange problems with this
auto-layout
business,
you're gonna get this little
yellow circle
appearing in your document
outline.
你可以在你的左侧文档中看到这个小黄圈出现。
And if you click it, it'll slide
in a list
of all the problems.
如果你点击它，它会展开一个列表，呈现所有的问题
And so here I highlight over
this and this
is where all the orange and
yellow is.
如果选中它，出现高亮的部分就是警告所出现的地方
It's saying the label with the 0
in it
expected the height to be 39 but
它提示这个label的高度应该是39，但
the actual height is 57.
真实的情况却是57。
Well that's because after I set
this font,
这是因为我在设置了这个字体后，
I just dragged this down a
little bit to
make space.
我向下的拖动了一部分，让它多出来一些区域。
All right, I, I wasn't very, I,
I didn't
know it was supposed to be 39.
好吧，我不是很，我不是很清楚它支持的高度是39。
I just dragged down.
我只是稍稍向下拖动了而已。
And so it's saying that's wrong.
这样，Xcode给了我一个警告。
Now, I could just try drag it
back up and
meet this dashed line.
现在,我可以试着将其拖动，和这个虚线重叠。
This dashed line, by the way,
强调下这条虚线，
is where it's kind of saying,
this is
really where this thing wants to
be.
它表明了这个标签真实的大小。
But the solid lines are where it
actually
is.
但是实线是我们希望的样子。
So I could kinda drag it up to
there, but
I, I could be off by a pixel or
所以我可能拖动到那里，但是我也许会相差1个像素或
something else.
出现一些其他的区别。
A much more reliable way is to
click this
little yellow triangle, 'kay?
现在有一个可靠的方法，点击这个黄色小三角，好了吗？
So I'm gonna click this yellow
triangle.
我将要点击这个。
It's gonna bring up this pop-up
window.
它会弹出一个窗口。
And there's three ways to fix
the
problems, okay?
这里给出了三个修改问题的方法，好了吗同学？
One way, Update Constraints,
this middle
way right here.
其中一个，更新约束，在第二个。
That's a way that says, hey, I
want this
thing to be,
这个方法是，我想要这样做，
this label to be right where it
is.
这个label这样才是正确的。
So just make some constraints.
所以只要做一些约束。
Make it up.
弥补上这个缺点。
Make it happen!
让它自己完成。
And it'll put some wacky
constraints in
there like 52 high, which is a
bad
它会把一些古怪的约束添加到这个52高度，这是一个坏的
constraint for it to be, 52
high, cuz this
label wants to be its natural
height.
约束，因为52的高度不是这个标签真正的高度。
It doesn't want to be 52 high.
它的高度不是52。
So this'll kinda force
constraint.
所以这里就可以用强制性的约束。
You'll almost never want this
one, 'kay.
当然你也许不希望这样。
Rarely do you wanna force the
constraints.
你很少想强制性的去约束。
Reset to Suggested Constraints
would
probably just work here.
这个就是设置label为建议性的约束。
I'm not gonna choose this one,
but it
would probably work.
我不会选择这个，即使它可能是正确的。
This one is going to make the
constraints
match the blue lines.
这个是将约束调整为蓝色的线条。
Those dashed blue lines that I
told you
always wanna meet.
那些蓝线，我告诉你是必须达到的。
Those are what's gonna help the
system
pick suggested constraints.
那些是系统帮助选择出来的约束。
So since we dragged that label
out to the
blue lines perfectly,
因为我们拖动的label是蓝色的，
I'll bet if I said Reset to
Suggested
Constraints, it might just work.
我敢打赌，我点击了重置约束，它也是能够工作的。
Okay.
But I'm actually gonna show you
this
好的。我想告诉你这个
last option up on top, which is
Update
Frame and what this says is,
take into
选项，它是能够更新框架和
consideration all the rules and
move this
label to where the rules say it
should be.
所有的约束规则，让label的按照规则进行移动。
'Kay.
And I like this option a lot
because it
好的，我喜欢这个选项
lets you kind of preview, do I
have my
little rules right, okay?
它让你能够预览，我有一个正确的结果，对吗？
So let's try that, let's see if
the, we'll
tell the, move this label, go
ahead and
我们尝试一下，看下移动后的标签是
move yourself and size yourself
to obey
these three rules we you put in,
and
遵守你自己的设定的那三个约束，
we'll fix the misplacement, so
let's try
it.
我们点击这个按钮，让我们尝试下。
And sure enough it did it, it
says there
are no auto layout issues.
果然做到了，没有任何问题。
If I go back to my document
outline, this
little yellow circle is gone.
如果你回到自己的目录列表，这个黄色的小圆圈已经消失了。
If I look in my view, everything
is
blue-lined, no yellow or red.
看看自己的视图，全部都是蓝线，没有红色或黄色的。
Okay?
So that's your
好了吗？这就说明你的
crash course on auto layout, and
we're
gonna talk a lot more about auto
layout,
自动布局已经完成，我们接下来讨论下更多的自动布局
in fact, even on Wednesday I'm
gonna do
another auto layout with all the
buttons.
在周三的时候我们将要尝试给所有的按钮进行自动布局。
Right?
The keypad buttons, and
真的？所有的键盘按钮
all that, which is a lot more
things being
laid out.
这听起来真的蛮多的。
But let's see if this fixes our
problem.
接着让我们看下如何修改这些。
Let's go ahead and run our
application
again.
我们再次运行一下应用。
So I'm just hitting that play
button.
点击这个运行按钮。
Here it, oh, we got our zero
this time.
此刻，我们现在可以看到这个0了。
You see how it pinned this zero
to that
edge?
你注意到这个零的边缘了吗?
And not only that, if we rotate
this
phoned,
不仅可以这样，如果我们旋转模拟器，
which you can do in the
Simulators menu,
Hardware > Rotate.
你可以在模拟器的菜单中点击Hardware>Rotate。
Look the 0, this got wider and
the 0 kept
pin, pinning itself over to
that.
看看这个0，它本身还保持着这个距离。
And it also stayed on the top
even though
this got, whole thing got
shorter.
它也保持着距离顶部的距离，底部距离变短了。
Okay.
And if I rotate back, the 0
stays there.
接下来，如果我旋转回来，0还是保持原样。
Question.
So what did it do at the bottom
there?
学生提问：是什么让它底部产生了变化。
Like what did the actual update
frame end
up doing?
就像你已经更新过那里的约束了一样。
What did the update frame in the
document
outline do?
在目录中的更新框架做了什么呢？
Yes.
It moved this bottom edge up.
是的，它改变了底部的边缘距离。
You see this is only 39 pixels
high now.
你看现在是39的像素高度。
It was 52.
之前它是52.
So, yeah, it just moved it up.
这样，它发生了改变，向上移动了。
It, it, and if other things had
been
yellow,
如果其他事情提示黄色，
it could have moved the whole
thing.
它可能移动整体了。
Right?
It would move that
好的，它将移动这
whole rectangle wherever the
rule said but
整个矩形达到约束的那样，但是
in this case, you can fi that
one problem
by moving it up.
这种情况，你能够向上拖动来修改这个问题。
Good question.
好问题。
Okay?
可以了嘛？
So that's good.
不错。
All right.
好的。
So that's it for auto layout.
让我们回到自动布局上。
Auto layout part one.
自动布局的第一部分。
So now let's talk a little bit
about
connecting our user interface
that we're
所以现在让我们来谈谈我们的界面,我们
building right here, up to the
code,
建立在这里，通过代码
cuz we want that code to be able
to talk
to the user interface.
因为我们想让代码能够告诉用户界面。
Otherwise how are we gonna have
the number
buttons,
否则我们如何拥有数字按钮，
make numbers appear up here in
the
display?
使数字展现在这里
Or the times button, give the
results of
the calculation up here.
或一些按钮，告诉计算结果在这里。
We gotta be able to talk to
this.
我们必须能够与之交互。
So how do we do that?
但是如何做到呢？
And the answer, first step is,
we need to
get both this co, this Swift
Code,
正确答案，第一步需要我们在controller中编写Swift代码，
the controller, and this view on
screen at
the same time, 'kay?
和这个视图相互对应。
Cuz we're gonna connect them so
we need
them on screen at the same time,
因为我们会连接他们,所以我们需要在屏幕上在同一时间
and there's a lot of ways to do
that, but
I'll do the simplest way right
here,
还有很多方面,在这里我要用最简单的方法,
which is this little button
called the
assistant editor, all right?
这个小按钮叫助理编辑，好了吗？
So I'm gonna click that and
look!
我要点击这个。
It put them both on screen at
the same
time, exactly what I wanted.
这时你能看到屏幕分成了两部分，这正是我想要的。
Now it's all a little crowded
here.
现在它这里是比较拥挤的。
Even if I expand my view a
little bit,
it's like it's all smashed in
here.
即使我放大整个界面，它看起来还是这么小。
Luckily the navigator and the
utilities
can also be hidden,
幸运的是导航栏这些都是可以隐藏起来的，
see these buttons up here, these
three
buttons?
看到这些按钮了嘛，这有三个按钮。
This left one, if you click it
hides the
navigator and
左侧这个，如果你点击它则会隐藏左侧导航，
this right one if you click it
hides
utilities, 'kay?
点击右侧这个，则会右侧右边的工具栏。
So now we have both my UI and
over here we
can still double click to zoom
out, but
现在我们可以看到他们都在视线中，我们可以双击缩放它，但
the thing is, anytime we're
actually
connecting our UI to our code or
事情是这样的,在我们实际连接UI代码或
trying to edit anything in here,
you need
to be zoomed to normal, 'kay?
尝试去编辑的时候，你需要把缩放比例调到正常。
For example if I tried to select
if I'm
zoomed out and
例如这个，如果我选择这个比例
I try to select this 0 I just
can't.
我就不能选中这个0了。
This is really kind of a bird's
eye view
just for seeing what your UI
looks like.
这个其实只是一个预览图，让你看看大体样子，而不能编辑。
If you wanna actually work on
it,
你只有这样才能够继续工作，
you double-click to zoom in on
this scene
that you're interested in.
你双击选择这个窗口即可。
Okay, so here's our Swift code.
好了，现在我们开始编写Swift代码。
I'm actually gonna delete these.
我将要删除这些。
We don't need them for the
calculator.
在我们的应用中是不需要这些的。
We will need these things for
future
application but we don't need it
for
我们需要一些计算功能，但这些不需要。
the calculator.
And this is your first look at
Swift,
'kay.
接着，你将要开始第一个Swift的编写。
So Swift, as I said, very
concise
language, but it's basically an
object
我说过，Swift是非常简洁的语言，但它还是一个
oriented language, it's gonna
look a lot
like C, some things look a lot
like Java.
面向对象语言，它看起来像C，有人说它有点像java。
It's kind of the, you know, best
of, of a
lot of different worlds at once.
你知道，最好的，很多不同的地方。
Now this import is just
importing the UI
portion of iOS.
这只是iOS导入UI的一部分。
You usually won't have to
specify import
yourself unless you start
你通常不需要指定导入，除非你开始
using frameworks that are not,
you know,
the base frameworks and we'll
get to that
不使用框架，你知道基础框架和我们将要
probably weeks into the quarter
where you
fi, finally have to do an import
yourself.
使用的一些会需要自己进行导入。
So this how it automatically got
put here
for us.
这里我们看到它自动的为我们添加了。
And so this is really your first
line of
Swift code, 'kay?
在这里要开始你的第一行Swift的代码。
Appropriately, it's a definition
of a
class.
这里是定义了一个类。
Cuz Swift is fundamentally
object-oriented
and here we're defining a class.
因为Swift从根本上来讲是面向对象的，这里是定义的一个类。
So what does the syntax look
like to
define a class?
这里的语法看起来像定义一个类吗？
You got the keyword class.
你看到类这个关键字。
You got the name of the class.
这里是这个类的名称。
Now this name ViewController,
pretty bad
name, [LAUGH].
现在这个名字看起来很糟糕。
Okay, very generic, really they
should
probably be something like
好吧,真的很一般,他们应该是类似
CalculatorViewController,
something
specific to
CalculatorViewController这样的命名
this particular scene that we're
working
on right here, that it's
controlling.
这样看起来就让人清楚他是控制哪里的了。
This is the default name it
gives you.
这是个默认的名字。
I don't want to spend the
valuable demo
time showing how to
我不想花费宝贵的时间去演示如何
rename this cuz unfortunately,
重命名这个，因为
I can't just type a new name
here because
I gotta keep the UI in sync with
it.
我不能在这里输入一个新名字,因为我要保持UI同步。
So I would have to do something
in the UI
as well.
所以我必须做一些事情在UI中。
But, for now, for your first
assignment or
two we're, we'll just
但是现在，你的第一个任务或两个，我们只会
call this ViewController, but
down the
road you're gonna wanna pick
better names.
叫他ViewController，但你最好给他更换一个好的名字。
And of course you're gonna be
building
multiple of
当然你可以创建一个
these scenes in this class in
the same app
in the future, so
新的类在其中，
of course, they'll all have
different
controller names.
他们都有一个不同的名称。
Okay, this :UIViewController,
that's
inheritance, that's its
superclass, okay?
这个UIViewController是告诉我们它的父类是谁。
Swift is single inheritance, so
you can
only inherit from one class.
Swift是一个单继承，你只能让他继承一个类。
It's perfectly fine in Swift not
to
inherit from a class if you
don't want to,
如果你不想这样，它是能够完整的继承一个类，
all right?
But here we have to inherit from
UIViewController cuz we
在这里我们有UIViewController，因为我们
want all this magic that allows
us to
control the UI,
想通过它来控制UI，
like that whole auto layout
business, and
there's a ton of mechanism in
here for
像自动布局功能，这其中有许多的原理
the, the allowing the controller
to
control this UI.
允许控制器来控制这个UI
So obviously we do that so all
ViewControllers, all controllers
of these
很明显，所有viewcontroller,所有控制器
little scenes always inherit
from either
from UIViewController directly
or they
这些小场景总是继承UIViewController或者它们
inherit from a class that
inherits from
UIViewController or up their
chain so.
继承的类的UIViewController或它们的链。
And then inside this curly brace
is simply
all the instance variables and
然后在这个花括号中所有实例变量和
methods in this class, 'kay?
方法在这个类中。
So very simple syntax to define
a class.
定义类的语法是非常简练的。
So let's dive right into making
some
instance variables and methods
so
所以让我们忙于做一些实例变量和方法
you can see what those look
like.
你可以调整下位置。
And I thought we, this was
segued to
because we're going to
我想我们，应该连接这个，因为我们想要这个
say we wanted to connect this UI
to this
code.
UI连接到代码中。
So let's do that.
我们现在就这样做。
Let's connect this label right
here into
this code, and
我们连接这个label到代码中去，
then we're gonna do that by
making an
instance variable.
然后我们会通过一个实例变量。
In Swift we call them
properties.
在Swift中我们叫它属性。
'Kay so if you hear me say
property,
如果你听到我说属性，
I'm basically talking about an
instance
variable.
那我其实就是在说实例变量。
Right?
A variable that is part of the
class.
清楚吗？一个变量是类的一部分。
Every instance of the class gets
its own
copy of it.
类的每个实例都有自己的拷贝。
Hopefully you all know what an
instance
variable is.
希望你都知道什么是一个实例变量。
If you don't, again, this class,
如果你不清楚，再说一次，这是类，
heavy object-oriented, you
should
definitely know that.
面向对象的，你应该清楚。
So I'm gonna make a property
here, an
instance variable,
我将要声明一个属性在这里，也可以说是一个实例变量。
that points to this label, so
that I can
update the label's text, right?
使用指针指向这个lable，这样就我就能够更新这个label的内容了。
I need to be able to talk to
this label,
and the way you do that in iO
eh,
我需要告诉这个label，
in Xcode is you hold down Ctrl,
just like
we did when we were making
在Xcode中，你按住Ctrl，像刚才那样
a connection to the edge, so I'm
holding
down Ctrl and clicking on the
label, but
连接边缘，我保持住点击Ctrl和左键在这个label上，但是
instead of going to the edge,
I'm gonna go
into the code, 'kay?
不是要添加约束，我是想让它到代码中去，
Now this is kinda wacky.
这是有点古怪。
I know a lot of you are like
what?
我知道很多你喜欢什么？
Into the code?
在代码中？
Yeah?
So we're going right into the
code here
and let go and it's gonna say
oh,
现在我们到右边代码中，松开鼠标。
you wanna make a connection
between your
UI and your controller.
你能连接UI和控制器了。
No problem, what kinda
connection you
wanna make?
没问题了，接下来需要做什么？
And we wanna make what's called
an outlet
connection.
我们需要设置outlet连接。
An outlet means an instance
variable or
一个outlet在实例变量或
property that points to this
thing in the
UI.
属性，这个指针指向UI。
And all it needs to know to do
that is,
what do you wanna call this
property?
接着你需要给这个属性一个名称。
And this is the display of my
calculator
so I'm gonna call this display
and it
它将出现在我的计算器，所以我将命名为了display，
already knows the type of the
thing is UI
label of course cuz we dragged
from here.
这是说它是什么类型的，因为我们是从这里拖出来的。
Don't worry about this weak,
I'll talk
about that in a moment.
不要担心这个弱连接，在后面我们会讲到。
And then we just hit Connect,
and it
creates an instance variable or
然后我们点击这个按钮,它会创建一个实例变量或
property, right here in our
controller.
称之为属性，完成后就出现在这里了。
So this is a great opportunity
to look at
the syntax in Swift for
在Swift中这个语法就是
creating a property.
创建一个属性。
And there's a couple of things
on here
that are not normally part of
it.
这里有几件事情通常都不是它的一部分。
This is you, the main syntax for
creating
a property.
这是你的主要语法创建一个属性。
Let's quickly look at this thing
to get it
out of the way.
我们快速的了解下这个get方法。
This is not really part of the
Swift
language proper.
这不是Swift真正语言的一部分。
This is something Xcode puts in
here so
这是Xcode将在这里
that this little circle, do you
see the
little circle in this gutter,
appears?
这个小圆圈，你可以看到这个小圆圈出现在这里。
This little circle when I mouse
over it,
look what Xcode does.
当我把鼠标移动到上面时候，看看Xcode的变化。
It shows me what this line of
code is
connected to.
它展示了我选中的代码所连接的UI。
'Kay?
So that's really cool, and
这看起来非常酷，
you're gonna see that's really
valuable
later in this demo,
在这个demo中这是非常有用的，
is being able to find out what
things are
connected to.
它能找到我们连接的是什么控件。
So that's all this thing means
here.
这个就是它所展示的意义。
You, you, you don't type this in
yourself,
that when you Ctrl+drag, it puts
it there.
当你Ctrl+点击拖动时候你不清楚是什么类型，它所说的。
This weak, all you, you, if you
come from
other languages,
这个weak，如果你从其他语言过来到。
you're used to things like
garbage
collection to clean up the heap.
你会使用过类似的垃圾回收机制。
Or maybe you even have to alloc
and
或者你也许习惯自己分配和
free things yourself manually in
some
languages.
释放管理在一些语言中。
None of that in Swift.
在Swift中是没有的。
In Swift, the, all objects live
in the
heap, 'kay.
在Swift中，所有的对象都在堆中。
All class, the instances of
classes live
in the heap.
所有类，类的实例都存在类的堆中。
And the memory for them is
managed for
you, 'kay?
替你进行了内存管理。
You allocate them as much as you
want, as
soon as there's no pointers to
them,
你分配他们尽可能多的你想要的，只要没有了指针指向它们，
they get cleaned up, and it's
not garbage
collection, 'kay?
它们会自动清理，不需要垃圾回收。
It's reference counting.
这就是引用计数。
It's actually counting
references to them
but it's all automatic.
它实际上是计算引用他们的次数，但这都是自动的。
The only thing you ever have to
be maybe
interested in is this weak
business which
你曾经也许唯一感兴趣的是这个weak的功能，
is less than a hundredth of a
percent of
the time.
在小于百分之一的时间。
And for the first four weeks of
this
class, forget about weak.
前四周的课程中，忘掉有关weak的吧。
It'll automatically happen when
you do
this Ctrl+drag, but just ignore
it.
当你使用Ctrl+点击拖动时候，它会自动完成，所以先忽略这个吧。
But the main thing to know is
that all
that memory
但是最主要的事情是知道有关内存管理
management is happening for you.
会发生在你身上的。
Also this, instance variable
right here,
同时，实例变量在这里，
which is a pointer to this
object, notice
there's no ampersands or
通过一个指针指向对象，注意到没有与符号或
stars or any other kind of
syntax that
says this is a pointer.
星或者其他任何语法说这是一个指针。
'Kay?
If you have a instance, variable
or
property or
如果你有一个实例变量或属性或
local variable that is an
object, okay,
局部变量都是一个对象。
it's always a pointer to it cuz
objects
only live in the heap, 'kay?
它总是一个指针，因为对象只在堆中存在着。
So you don't need all that extra
stars and
所以不需要多余的*和&，
ampersand, any of that business
from other
languages, okay?
不要从其他语言中借鉴。
This exclamation point, by the
way, I'm
gonna talk about in a few
minutes,
这个感叹号，顺便说一下，我要谈几分钟
has nothing to do with this
being an
object, okay?
这是和对象不相关的。
This is, this totally separate
thing.
这完全不相干的事情。
We'll get to it.
我们会得到它。
All right.
So let's look at this.
让我们看看这个。
This is the syntax for defining
a
property, 'kay?
这个语法是定义了一个属性，对吗？
An instance variable.
一个实例变量。
And it's very simple.
并且它是如此的简单。
You got var, short for variable
cuz that's
what this is, a variable.
你看到var，它是变量的缩写。
The name, this is the name of
it, display.
这是变量的名称，display
Okay?
That's just the name of this
property.
这个属性的名字是这个。
And then :UILabel!
紧接着就是UILabel。
Is the type, 'kay?
这个是它的类型。
That's the type of this instance
variable.
这个类似是这个实例变量的。
So again, I'll talk about the
exclamation
point later, but
我稍后会讲到那个感叹号，但
obviously this thing is pointing
to this
label so that we can talk to it.
很明显，这是指向label的，我们能这样说。
And we'll be doing that in a
moment.
我们能够这样去做。
'Kay?
Questions?
有什么疑问吗？
All right, let's talk about
another kind
of connection we may,
好的，让我们来谈谈另一种连接，
we can make, let's start putting
some
buttons in our calculator.
我们可以，让我们开始放一些计算器的按钮吧。
So I'm gonna go back to the
Utilities
window, 'kay?
我将要打开这个工具窗口。
By pressing this button over
here,
按下这个按钮，
go down to the bottom, go to the
third tab
over here, the object library.
找到下方的第三个选项的对象目录。
And instead of a label, this
time I'm
gonna drag out a button.
这次拖的不是label，我将要拖动出来一个按钮。
Okay?
I'm gonna put this button here
now.
现在我要把这个按钮放到这里。
Just to be different, I'm not
gonna
initially line it up with a blue
line.
有些不同，我没有初始化蓝色的线。
I'm just gonna put it kinda in
space out
here and
我只是想把它放在这个空间中，
I'll line it up with the blue
line later,
'kay?
将它放在蓝线的下面。
But I don't wanna forget to do
that
though, I always wanna do that.
但我不会忘记做，我总是期望这样。
What I'm gonna do later is to
show you it
can be done.
以后我要做的就是告诉你这是可以做到的。
So, this is gonna be, let's say
this is
gonna be one of our number
buttons.
接着，我们可以说这就是一个数字按钮。
Like the upper left corner of
our keypad
is a 7.
就像键盘左上角的数字7。
Okay?
Again, I have the same thing
over here.
我还需要其他的一些。
Okay?
With the attributes inspector I
can
通过属性设置，我能够
change things like the font.
修改一些字体大小什么的。
Let's make this be 24 point,
let's say.
让我们尝试下尺寸为24的。
I can resize.
我能够修改尺寸。
Notice that when I resize it
will actually
tell me the size,
注意，当我调整它时候，会显示尺寸。
see it saying there what size it
is?
看到它说这是多大的尺寸
I can also set the size maybe
with this
size inspector right here,
我还可以在设置尺寸这里修改，
type it in exactly.
类型的准备。
Maybe 64 by 64, something like
that.
也许64 x 64 看起来更合适。
We don't usually do that.
我们通常不这样做。
We want things to be kinda their
natural
sizes but
我们希望它能够是原始的大小，但
just want to show you that there
are other
inspectors over here.
这里只想向你展示有其他的方法。
So we have this 7.
所以我们有这个7。
Now when this 7 is pressed, what
do we
want to happen?
当7被按下的时候，会发生什么呢？
What we want.
我们想要的。
Numbers just start appearing up
here in
the display, right?
数字出现在需要展示的地方。
So that's something our
controller is
going to have to do.
这就是我们的控制器不得不做的事。
So, when we touch this button,
we kinda
want this button to send a
message to
当我们点击这个按钮，我们想让这个按钮发送信息到
our controller, and we do that
the exact
same way as we did this one,
我们的控制器，跟之前的方式一样，
we hold down control, drag into
our code.
我们按住Ctrl，点击，拖动到代码中。
When we let go though, we're not
going to
an outlet connection this time,
当我们松开时候，我们不想要outlet这个，
because I dont want an instance
variable
here, what i want is a method,
right?
因为此时我不想要一个实例变量，我需要一个方法。
A function on my class, a
method, everyone
understand the word method I
hope,
okay, so we want it to send an
[INAUDIBLE]
message to our control board, so
I'm going to pick" action",
[COUGH] losing
my voice here.
Bad time to have a little cold,
but.
[SOUND] So I'm doing an action
so
an action is a little different
than a
outlet, okay?
An outlet means an instance
variable or
property, action means create a
method for
me.
So again it wants to know the
name of the
method.
So what does this thing do?
Well when I press seven, it
appends a
digit onto the end of
whatever's already in the
display, so I'm
going to call it append,
I could call it append seven,
but I'm
actually going to call it append
digit,
because I want to have one
method that all
of my buttons use.
All right?
I don't want to, copy and
pasting a bunch
of methods, that would be really
bad code.
But if I'm gonna have one
method,
then I need to know which button
is
sending me this message, okay?
Luckily, when you haven't
actioned a
message being sent here,
you can specify that it has
arguments, you
see right here where it says
arguments?
And it can have no arguments or
it can
have the sender.
Which is the button here as the
argument.
The only tricky thing here is,
and I'm not
sure why they did this in Xcode.
Hopefully, they'll change it in
the
future.
By default, the type of that
argument,
which is right here, is any
object.
Now, we're gonna talk about any
object
next week.
But, we don't want any object
here.
We know that the sender is a UI
button, so
I picked, click this little blue
thing and
switch this to UI button.
When you're doing your homework,
if you
forget to switch that to UI
button,
you'll be sad, okay.
So don't forget.
And obviously the event that the
message
is gonna be sent on, touch up
inside,
just means the user touched on
this button
and the touch went up.
While it was still inside the
button.
That's all a touch up inside
means there.
All right so when I connect
this,
I'm gonna get a method with one
argument
which is a sender which is a UI
button.
So let's take a look.
So here's your first method
declaration in
SWIFT, okay?
Again it's got this little IB
action thing
which is kinda like IB outlet.
It puts a little dot in the
gutter.
Okay?
So that you can
see what this thing is connected
to.
So this is the normal, Swift
method
syntax.
Starts with func because
function,
basically that method is a
function in
class.
[COUGH] Here's the name.
Append digit.
And then in parentheses, all the
arguments
separated by commas.
We only have one argument,
though.
Here's the name of the first
argument.
That's the name we're going to
use to
access it inside of our method,
and
here is the type.
Okay?
It's a UI button.
I, notice no exclamation point
there, by
the way.
Okay if this had a return value,
if this
method returned something this
one doesn't
[COUGH] but if it returned
something, it
would look like this arrow the
return type
okay so that's how you specify a
return
type.
Okay, pretty simple the syntax
and then
inside here we just type,
well whatever we want this thing
to do
when one of these buttons is
touched.
So what do we want it to do?
Well, okay, first of all before
we do
that, let's go ahead and make
more of
these buttons because I need
seven, eight,
nine, four, five, six, all this.
So let's copy and paste the
button.
When I copy and
paste the button, notice I'm
using the
blue lines to put it perfectly
lined up.
Okay, also notice that it there
also
sending this message.
All right, see how their both
sending the
message, because when I copy and
paste, it copied that aspect of
it as
well.
So there's another one, I could
select all
three of these and
copy and paste, okay, I could
select all
six of these and copy and paste.
So I can quickly make, my entire
keypad.
Just need to edit the title.
Now, if while I'm editing these
titles,
sometimes you're clicking around
in
here and, you know, you're not a
very
accurate clicker.
[LAUGH] Or, you know, you just
get out,
out of control clicking here,
and oh,
you moved it out of the way.
Okay?
No problem, you can just put it
right back
in.
Okay, use the blue lines to your
advantage.
And we'll put our zero down
here.
And I don't need these buttons
so I'm just
hit, selecting it, hitting
delete.
That's how you can get rid of
something.
And I promised I was gonna put
these all
on blue lines, so I'm gonna do
that.
I'm gonna put it right
underneath the
zero.
So here's a blue line that means
underneath the zero, and
then I'm going to put at this
edge.
So now you can see that the blue
lines are
not just the edges, but
they are other objects, like the
other
objects in the keypad and
also now the title, the display
rather at
the top.
So I've got all these buttons,
they're all
sending this message append
digit.
So I need to figure out which
one is
sending it,
so that I can do the right
thing.
So let's start writing some code
inside
the method.
So the first thing I'm going to
do is
declare a local variable,
it's just a local variable
inside this
method.
I'm going to do that by saying
let digit
equal.
So I want this local variable to
be the
digit that was pressed.
Okay.
So, first thing that's quite
different
here is, what's let?
Okay?
Why isn't this var, right?
Cuz var means variable, what the
heck does
let mean?
Well let is exactly the same as
var except
it's a constant.
Which means you're going to sign
this
right off the bat, and
it's never going to change in
this method.
Now Swift makes a big deal about
this, and
I love this feature, because if
I'm
reading this code,
I know the digit is never going
to change
all, this might be, you know.
It might have a dozen lines of
code.
Which by the way,
you shouldn't have very many
methods, with
many more lines of code then
that.
Okay?
You want people to be able to
kind of see what a method's
doing.
You can use other methods,
call other methods if you need
to get more
code in there.
so.
Here I can de-,
rely on that not changing.
That's big for readability.
You'll be surprised how much
more readable
it makes the code, to know that
this is a,
local variable, but it's
constant.
Only set at the beginning.
Yeah.
Is there a reason, constants and
like, variables have the same
naming
convention.
Since [UNKNOWN] like Java there.
Like the naming conventions like
all caps
or lowercase.
Yeah.
So, yeah.
The question is, why don't I
call digit
like all caps digit, or
something like that, so I know
it's a
constant.
That would be a programming
style thing.
Generally in Swift they don't do
that.
And, I'll show you why that is
in a
moment.
Why you don't really need to do
that.
Because you can very quickly
find out the
declaration of
any symbol anywhere with one
click, and
you'll see that.
Good question though.
All right, so I wanna let the
digit, equal
the number that's on the,
the sending button.
So I'm gonna have to send a
message to
this button.
Okay?
Gonna have to somehow access
this button.
So I'm gonna have to do sender,
something.
Give me what your title is,
okay?
So this is a good time to talk
about the
documentation.
[COUGH].
Because being a good iOS
developer,
really demands that you are good
at
navigating the documentation.
Luckily, the documentation is
really well
plugged in to Xcode.
For example, if I wanna find out
about
button,
all I need to do is hold down
the option
key.
Okay?
And watch what happens now.
As I mouse over things,
everything, it turns blue with a
dashed
blue line under it, okay?
If I click on it,
it gives me a little blurb from
the
documentation about this thing.
So it's saying, you know,
here's, button
is a class.
Here's its inheritance.
Here's a little bit of what it
does.
And really awesome at the bottom
here,
here's a link that takes you to
the
detailed documentation.
So I'm gonna click this little
link right
here.
It's going to be up a
documentation
window, with UI button in it,
hello?
Did I not click that right thing
here,
oh I hope I don't have a network
issue
here.
hm, okay well, I guess I'm not
connected
to the network,
that's the problem, so it's
getting this
off the network.
Okay so.
Imagine that there were
documentation here
and, it would have along this
side here
on the left all the instance
variables or
properties and methods of u i
button.
And you could click on any one,
and
in there we'd have a full
description of
it here.
And all the types that it
referenced you
could click on it here, and
basically it's a hyper linked
documentation [UNKNOWN].
As you can imagine.
I'll try to get the networking
working on
Wednesday and we'll take a look
at this.
But if I was looking in here,
I'd look down in the section
that says
getting the button's current
state, and
I'd find that there is an
instance
property there called current
title.
Okay?
It's unfortunate I'm not going
to
link these things.
But.
So how do we access, property or
call a
method in another object,
will look exactly the same
whether you
call it a method or
accessing a property, which is
you use
dot.
Okay.
It's the same syntax that's used
in
a lot of languages is to, to do
dot.
And so when you do that, Xcode
is going to
say, oh,
well, here's all the things
button knows
how to do.
Okay?
And as you can see, button knows
how to do
a lot of things.
Because it inherits from a
class, it
inherits from a class,
it inherits from a class, that
all have
lots of methods in them.
So when I looked at that
documentation.
I've found that current title
was the
thing I wanted.
Now notice as I start to type a
c, it's
already cutting down
the things that could be
starting with a
c, and then c u, they cut down
even more.
I can type tab, to get to the
first
ambiguity point, then I can type
t.
Okay?
And then tab again, and I'm here
at
current title and then I can
press return.
Okay?
So there it is.
Digit equals sender current
title.
so, what's going on here in
terms of did,
descender title.
Let's go ahead and print this
out to the
console just to see what's going
on.
So I'm gonna print lin.
At which is a function, a global
function
that takes a string.
So I give it a string.
And inside that string, I'll
type mm,
digit equals and now I wanna
embed the
value of digit in this string.
And Swift has a really cool
feature which
is backslash open parentheses
close parentheses.
If you put that in a string, and
then
inside there you put some
expression, then
it will evaluate that expression
turn it
into a string, and embed it in
the string.
Okay, so its really easy to
print lin
values by
using this backslash
parenthesis.
Okay?
So let's go ahead and run and
see what happens when we press
these
buttons to see what kind of
result we get.
It's not going to be quite what
we expect,
but let's see.
Alright so, here's our BUY we
got our
buttons that's a good start.
And now, and console, where's
the console?
Watch this.
I'm going to press a button
five.
The console appears at the
bottom here.
See this down here.
This is the console.
And it's saying digit equals,
hm, optional
five.
Okay.
How about a nine?
They're all optional.
What the heck is going on here?
Okay.
This is crucial to understanding
Swift.
This is probably the most
important thing
to understand that
people don't quite get right
from the
start.
So we're really going to focus
here on
understanding what
optional means right there.
Okay?
So let's go back to our code.
And look at this, oh and by the
way it,
when the console appears down
here,
you can make it go away with
this little
button, or
you can just drag it out of the
way okay?
But sometimes it's nice to have
that
console still there, so
you can look at your output
while you're
you know reacting to whatever
you found,
in fact we will leave that up
there, so
you can see the optionals.
Alright, so, what's going on
here?
Well, what's happening here is,
well,
first of all,
don't you find this a little bit
odd, let
digit, I didn't put a type.
You see that?
How, what type is digit?
Okay, well there's no type in
there, no
type information whatsoever, so.
Does Swift have untyped
variables?
No, it's exact opposite.
Swift is very strongly typed.
Okay.
All variables have a type.
You have to specify type.
But, Swift is also incredibly
good at
what's called type inference.
So it can infer the type from
the context.
So here I let digit equal
whatever this
is, this current title, and
so it just made digit be the
same type as
this.
Okay.
Now back to the question
earlier, so what
type is that?
Well, if I hold down option,
okay, just
like we used option to
go look into the documentation,
we can
also option click on our own
variables.
To see are they constant?
Are they variables?
And what type are they?
So watch this.
Option click.
It says digit is of type string
question
mark.
Okay?
String question mark.
That question mark means
optional.
So there is a type in Swift,
it's a type,
called optional.
Okay.
Optional, that type can have
only two
values.
One value is not set.
Okay, this optional is not set,
there has
never been set or someone has
set it to the not set state,
they unset it
if you want to think about it
that way.
So optional one value is not
set, we call
that there's a, symbol for
it in here called nil, N, I, L,
okay?
That means not set, that's the
value of an
optional not set.
That's the only thing nil means
in Swift
is option this is an optional,
the value of an optional that is
not set.
What's the other value that an
optional
could have well the other value
is.
Something, it's set to
something, okay.
And the type of that something
is what,
is specified next to the
question mark
string.
So really you can almost think
of the
question mark there, that's the
type
optional, and that string to the
left is
just saying if this optional is
set,
what type of thing is it set to,
in this
case a string.
So we would call this an
optional string.
But it's really an optional,
it's not a
string that can be nil,
it's an optional that can be a
string.
Everybody cool with that
sentence?
That's an important sentence to
understand, okay.
So, this got to be an optional
because
this current title method right
here,
returns an optional string,
let's look at
that.
So I'm going to Alt+Option down
here,
click.
Look at this, this is the documentation for it.
看这里，这里是它的文档。
It's an instance variable a, a,
property
on UI button.
这是一个实例变量，UIButton的属性
Name is current title.
名字是current title
The type is string, question mark.
类型是string，问号标记。
And this little get means it's read-only.
而这里的“get”表示这个是只读的。
I can only get the current title.
我只能获得current title。
I can't set it, there are other ways to set a button's title.
但是我不能设置，有其他方式进行设置。
You can't set it with this method or this property.
你不能通过这个方法或者属性进行设置。
So it's an optional, so that's why this ended up being an optional all right.
所以这是一个选项，这就是为什么最后是一个选项。
Well, that's all wonderful.
嗯，这非常不错。
How do I get the string?
我怎么获取这个string呢？
I don't want it optional, I want that button's string.
我不需要它的选项，我要的是这个按钮的标题。
And the way you do that is you unwrap the optional, meaning you look in there and
方法就是你可以打开这个方法，意思是你正在
get the val, the associated value, with exclamation point, okay.
用“!”从里边获取关联的值。
What happens if I put that exclamation point there?
如果我把感叹号放在这里会怎么样？
Well first of all, let me show you that when I put that exclamation point,
首先我先会展示给你们看，我把感叹号放在这里
look what happened to digit, I'm Option-clicking on digit.
看看会有什么变化，我现在点击数字。
It's not an optional anymore.
它不再是选项了。
Digit turned to a string because I unwrapped the optional that
数字变成了string，因为我打开了选项
came back from current title, got the string out of there.
从当前的标题里的到了string。
But what happens if this is nil?
但是如果这是个nil值会怎么样？
What happened if this optional is nil?
如果选项是nil会发生什么事情？
In other words the button option has never been set, crash, 'kay,
换句话说，就是这些按钮选项没有设置会怎么样？对的，会崩溃。
crashes your program, so if you use exclamation point to unwrap an optional,
所以如果你使用"!"号来打开一个选项的时候。
and that optional's current value is not set, nil, then it will crash your program.
并且这个选项没有设值为空的时候，你的程序会崩溃。
Now a lot of you might be like whoa, I'm, my products are gonna be crashing all over
现在你们中的不少人肯定在想，怎么我的东西老是崩溃？
the place and, because there's a lot of optionals in iOS, I mean a lot, okay?
这是因为iOS有着非常多的选项，记住是非常多。
Most things are probably optionals, because most things, it make sense,
多数东西都是选项，因为这些东西都是有意义的。
they can be in an not set state at some point.
他们能在一些情况下出于不需设值的状态。
And yeah, in this case though, maybe you want your program to crash, okay?
在这个情况下，说不定你就希望你的程序崩溃？对不对？
You might want your program to crash, because if you had a button, that never
你也许就是希望自己的程序崩溃，因为你有一个按键，
had its title set, and it's sending a pen digit to your controller, you probably
但是它的标题从未设值，并且它传了一个数字给你的控制器
wanna have that crash, so you can find that bug, before you ship your program.
在你分发你的程序之前，你就能找到bug，所以你希望它崩溃。
You see why sometimes fra, crashing is good?
现在你知道为什么有时候程序崩溃是个好事吧。
Now if you don't wanna crash, there's a way to get around that as well.
现在如果你不想你的程序崩溃，这里有一个方法来解决。
And I'll show you that a little bit later.
我等一下就和你们说。
But for now understanding that that's what this exclamation point does.
但是现在，先弄明白这个感叹号是干什么的。
It unwraps that optional and crashes if it's nil.
它打开了选项，如果它是nil就崩溃。
But if it's not nil, it gets to the string or
但如果不是空，它是得到string还是
whatever the optional type is out of there for you.
给你其他的选项类型？
So now let's go ahead and run again and
所以让我们继续，重新运行一次
we're gonna see that digit equals is gonna say the number, 'kay?
我们将看看是不是能得到相等的数字？
It's got the string off the current title, no more optional in there, okay?
我们得到了当前的标题，没有更多的选项了。
Good?
看上去不错。
All right, so, now, what are we gonna do with that digit?
好的，现在，我们要用这些按钮做什么呢？
We got the digit,
我们已经能得到数字。
we want to append it onto the end of this display right here, okay.
我们希望按的数字能显示在这里的末尾。
And so let's just do that by saying display, dot.
所以让我们输入display.
Now, again, if we have the documentation,I'd go look in the documentation and
现在继续，如果我们查文档。
it would say oh, there's a property on UILabel, which is what display is,
它会告诉我们，UILabel有一个属性
display is a UILabel.
负责显示UILabel应该显示的什么。
There's a property and it' called text.
这个属性叫做text
See it right there?
就在这里。
And actually, you can even see right here, the type of that, it's an optional as
而且实际上，输入这个，你能在这里看到，这是一个选项。
well, because this label's text might not have been set either, okay?
所以这个label的text还没有设值。
So it has to be an optional string, okay?
所以这里是选项string。
So I'm just gonna set that equal now, display that text as an optional, so
所以我现在要用等号设值，显示的text作为一个选项
what values can I send it to,set it to?
什么值可以设给它？
I could set it to nil, that would be legal because it's an optional,
我可以设成nil，因为它是一个选项，是完全合法的。
see, no warnings, no errors.
看，没有警告也没有错误。
That would clear out that display.
这将什么也不显示。
It would not be set to anything, or
它不能设值成其他东西
I can set it to a string because it's an optional string.
我能给它设一个string值，因为它是一个选项string。
So I'm going to set it to a string and the string I'm going to set it
所以我将把它设值一个string
to is display.text, what's currently in there, plus digit, okay?
这个string我设置成display.text，这里加个数字。
So I'm going to append that digit on.
这样子就能增加数字了。
Let's get rid of that.
让我们摆脱删掉这句。
Okay, now, this has an error here.
好吧，现在又有一个错误。
Why does this have an error?
这个错误是为什么呢？为什么这里有个错误呢？
Anyone volunteer why this is an error?
有谁自愿回答这里为什么有个错误？
See it's pointing right here.
发现错误指向这里。
There's an error, back there.
这里有个错误，后面那位同学回答。
The display.text is an optional string.
display.text是一个选项string。
Bingo. Because display.text right here is not
答对了，因为这里的display.tex它不是个string。
a string, it's an optional, and you can't add a string to an optional.
你不能将一个string加在一个选项上。
You can only add strings to other strings.
你只能将一个string加在另外的string上。
So we need to turn this into a string by unwrapping it.
所以我们通过打开选项，将选项转变为string。
And again, yes, this would crash if the display currently has nothing in it,
对的，这个东西会crash，如果display没有值。
it's not set, okay?
现在还没有设值。
Are we cool with that?
大家都了解这个了吧？
So let's run again.
再让我们运行一次。
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[背景音]
All right.
好的。
So now 5, oh, it put the 5 on there.
所以现在点击5，噢，5显示在这里了。
6, excellent.
点击6，好极了。
It's kinda working.
它能够工作了。
I don't really like that 0 though.
这个0在这里我很不喜欢。
That's kinda weak, 0, 5, 6.
这里就有点不对劲了，5和6前面有个0。
That should not,
这样子是不对的。
that 0 should've gotten cleared out, right, when I first typed that 5.
这个0应该在我按下5的时候就清除掉。
And that's because we really need some way in our controller to know whether we're in
这是因为我们确实需要一些方法让我们的controller知道我们是否在
the middle of typing a number right now.
一个数字膻中输入数字。
Because if we're in the middle of typing a number, we want to append, but
因为如果我们在一个已有数字中部输入数字，我们是希望数字加在输入的地方的。
if we're not in the middle of typing a number,
但是如果我们不用从一个数字的中部进行输入。
we want to start a new number, right?
也就是我们想要从头开始输入一个新的数字。
So, let's do that, and I'm going to do that by adding a property, okay?
所以，让我们通过添加一个属性实现这个效果。
Var userIsInTheMiddleOfTypingANumber , which you might say,
设个叫做“userIsInTheMiddleOfTypingANumber”的变量，你也许会说
oh my God, that terrible variable, now I have to type that over and over.
天哪，这么糟糕的变量名字，每次都得这么输入还不得累死？
This is the last time I'll ever have to type that, okay?
其实下次用到这个变量我可不需要输入这么多的。
Because Xcode is always going to escape complete it for me, okay?
因为下次用到Xcode会帮我自动补齐的。
So long names are perfectly fine, in terms of typing load anyway.
所以这么长的名字没有问题。
So I like this name so I'm gonna keep it.
我就挺喜欢这个名字的，就这么用了。
And it's a bool, okay.
这是一个布尔型数值。
So I'm typing its, giving its type.
所以输入它的类型。
So here's var name type, and notice, look at this little error right here, 'kay.
命名完变量的名字和类型，注意看这里，有一个小错误标记。
Okay, sometimes you're gonna get errors in Swift that are completely incomprehensible
好吧，有时候你用Swift会遇到难以理解的错误。
to you because you haven't learned enough of Swift.
但是这是因为你对Swift的了解不够深入。
This one's kind of like that.
这个错误就是因为这个。
You see, it says, class view controller has no initializers.
你看，这里说类视图控制器没有初始化。
And that's because, and pay attention, in Swift all properties
请注意，这是因为，在Swift里
have to be initialized when the object is initialized.
一个对象没有初始化，那么对象的属性都不会初始化。
Okay, you can't have a property just sitting around not initialized,
所以你不能用没有初始化的属性。
they have to have a value.
它们需要一个值。
Now if they're an optional,
现在，它们是一个选项。
their value can be nil, but they have to have some value.
它们的值可以为空，但是它们必须有值。
So we can't have this have no value.
所以我们不能在它们没有值前使用。
Now there's two ways to give it a value.
有两种方法给它设值。
One is, with an initializer.
一种就是用初始化。
Unfortunately, I'm not gonna teach that to you until next week, so
但是不幸的是，这个方法要下周才讲。
you can't do it that way.
你还不能用这个方法。
Another way is just to say what it equals right here, okay?
所以另外一种方法就是对其直接赋值。
And boom, gets rid of all our errors, obviously we don't start out in
一下子，  所有问题都解决了。
the middle of typing a number,so we're good to go here, all right.
很明显用户不会从中间输入数字，所以从这一点出发
So now we have, we know whether the use is in the middle of typing a number.
现在我们知道了用户是否会从中间输入数字。
We can go down here and say if the user,
我们能从这里继续深入，如果说用户
now again, I'm just gonna hit Tab to jump past this, maybe a couple times.
按一下Tab，可能要花点时间，找到这个
But if the user's in the middle of typing a number,
但是如果用户从中间输入数字。
then we'll do what we were doing before.
那就和刚才我们已经做得一样处理。
Otherwise, we're just gonna set the display.text equal to the new digit we
另外，如果我们计划设置display.text为一个新的数字
just typed, 'kay?
只需要输入这个：
And we're gonna say that the user is now in the middle of typing a number.
这句表示用户现在在数字的中间输入数字。
Question?
什么问题？
Why would we have to do
[INAUDIBLE] to
display it?
Initialize?
Why did we not have to initialize this?
为什么我们部初始化这个？
That's a fantastic question and
这是个不错的问题
I'm gonna talk about that on Wednesday cuz there's only one minute left.
我将在下周三说这个问题，现在只剩下一分钟了。
But that is a great question and it'll also, when I talk about it,
在我下次说到的时候，这依然是个很好的问题。
I'm gonna tell you why this is an exclamation point and not a question mark.
我说一下为什么这里是个感叹号而不是个问好。
Because I told you that optionals are made with question marks.
因为我之前说过选项都是用问号标记的。
So why the heck is this optional?
但是为什么这个东西是选项
Cuz that's what it is, an exclamation point, so we'll talk about that next time.
因为可是个感叹号，我们下次课再说这个问题。
All right, so let's go ahead and run one last time here.
所以让我们下次课继续。
And hopefully this is gonna, this 0 will be cleared out, it is and
我们之前希望这个0可以正确的清除掉，看来没问题，看看这个
hopefully this will continue to append, it is.
希望这个可以正常的增加，看来也没问题。
So we're in a great spot right here, we've got a calculator,
我们今天已经有了一个不错的开始，我们将会做一个计算器。
we can enter numbers in it, next step is, we gotta make it do some calculating, and
我们已经能够输入数字了，下一步我们将让其能够计算。
we're gonna do that next time so I will see you then.
我们下节课再做，大家下节课见。
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.
想浏览更多？请访问stanford.edu。