[MUSIC]
Stanford University
[BLANK_AUDIO]
>>> Welcome to Stanford CS1933P, this is winter quarter 2015
And we're gonna dive right in today to some brief slide work.
This people at Stanford, you've got a document that describe,
describes all the grading and all that stuff so
I'm not gonna go over that in lecture like I often do start the quarter.
Instead I'm gonna talk a little bit about what this class is about.
Brief mention of the prerequisites cuz they're pretty important in this class.
Then just the [NOISE] quickest overview of iOS.
I'm gonna assume that anyone who is here or is watching this, knows what this is.
And then, we're gonna dive right into a big old demo.
It's gonna be a two-day thing, where I'm really going to try and
introduce you to Xcode and the development environment and
this language Swift, that you're gonna have to learn to develop for iOS.
All right, so what is this class about?
It's about building cool apps, as we know.
Why are these iOS apps so cool?
Well, because the device you're gonna run them on is in your pocket or
in your backpack.
it's highly networked and incredible graphics with animation.
It's just cool all the way around and I think you guys all know that or
you wouldn't be here.
But you're also gonna learn in
this class a lot of real life Object-Oriented Programming.
You're taking a lot of other classes here at Stanford on things like graphic. and
networking, and databases, and maybe animation.
Things like that.
And we're gonna is kinda tie that all together into a real world class.
OK? You're gonna get to see all this stuff.
Now, you know, it's gonna be kind of a survey course in that,
I can't go too deep into networking.
I can't go too deep into databases.
I can't go too deep into animation, but you'll get to see it all in a really real
world environment, where people our there building apps using that technology.
For some of you who haven't seen that before that'll be a big bonus of
this class, I think.
The prerequisites of this class.
No.1 thing is you have to be a pretty strong Object-Oriented programmer.
If you're not a strong Object-Oriented programmer, and
you hit this class, you're probably gonna go under water, pretty quick.
OK? I'm gonna assume you know,
everything about Object-Oriented Programming.
iOS is a completely Object-Oriented Programming environment,
development environment,
I just don't mean I'm not just talking about the language is Object-Oriented.
But the entire design of it the way you use it if you're not
comfortable with things like subclassing and
stuff like that then you're just really gonna be behind the curve.
In iOS so at Stanford here that means CS16A and B or
CS16X, and then you know, CS107, while it's not really Object-Oriented course,
at least it's heavy duty programming course.
CS108 is a great Object-Oriented course so
if you have, if you've taken CS108 you'll probably, be really well prepped.
110, again not really too much an Object-Oriented program but
good programming course cuz there's a lot of programming in this class,
in fact, all the work in this class is programming.
Your will not have, a little bit of reading the first couple of weeks just to
kinda learn this new language, but it's almost all programming after that all
the way til the end, including your final project.
So if you're not really comfortable with all these terms,
this Object-Oriented terms or if you're just not really comfortable with
writing big programs then this class will definitely be a challenge for you.
OK, so what's in iOS, what are the parts of it?
You know, it's ha, its's such a big system, it's got so much in it.
It's impossible for me to
like, encapsulate it into a small little summary but
I do have this slide right here that divides it into these four layers.