[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> All right, well,welcome
to Stanford CS193P,
winter of 2015.
This is lecture number two.
I apologize upfront for my
terrible voice, we are going
to try to get through this
as best we can today.
Our topics are two fold.
[COUGH] We're going to
continue the calculator
demo that we started, in last
lecture and then we're gonna
have some slides about this
model view controller,
object-oriented design pattern
that we're gonna use in
everything we do.
When we build applications
in this class.
All right?
So let's get started
with that demo.
Again, here's a slide with
the summary of kind of
the important things
we're gonna talk about.
You don't need to read
those in advance here,
it's more for reference.
My slides in general,
I post them,
it's mostly intended to almost
be note taking for you.
To be able go back and try and
figure out, whoa, when did
he talked about that day?
Oh yeah.
What's important, et cetera.
So my slides do tend to
be a little bit dense.
I tend to put a little
more on them, than,
than just bullet items.
But that's because I want you
to be able to look back and
kind of get just a little
bit more depth to
remind yourself what
I talked about.
Okay?
All right, so
this demo, if you'll remember
last time, where we left off,
we had gotten the keypad
fully working.
All right, and we were talking
a little bit about properties
and instant variables and
how we had to initialize them.
And so I'm gonna ask
a question right at
the end of lecture,
perfect timing.
What about the little
outlet that we dragged out
that display UI label
exclamation point, how come we
didn't have to make that
equal to something, to start.
And that's where this
demo is gonna pick up.
Okay?
>> Okay.
[COUGH] Well, let's dive back
into this demonstration,
where we left off.
Which it was this
line of code, here.
And, we had just talked about
the fact that we have to
initialize all of our
variables [COUGH] in a class,
in any class.
And, so that's why we need
this equals falls here.
They wanted the equal falls
too but we needed it and yet
it didn't seem like
we needed one here.
And why was that?
Well, it turns out
that this right here,
even though it doesn't quite
look like one, is an optional.
And, optionals automatically
get equaled nil, given to you.
So, you don't actually have
to put the equals nil here.
So that's why, so this one
here is getting initialized.
It's just being done
automatically for you.
But, let's talk about
the look of this thing.
It's got this
exclamation point here.
And, if it were an optional,
you'd be used to it
having a question mark.
For example, we look at
this optional right here,
current title,
you see it's string question
mark not exclamation point,
question mark.
So what's the difference
between a question mark and
an exclamation point here?
And the answer is,
it makes no difference to
the actual type, it's still
an optional whose value
here could be a UI label.
But it matters on
the usage of it.
[COUGH] And
this is purely just kind of
a compiler helping
you out thing, here.
But if we look at
when I change this to
a question mark you see that
some errors appear down here.
So then let's click on one of
these errors, like this one,
and you can see
the errors that UI label,
question mark does not
have a member named text.
In other words you
can't send text.
UI label question mark,
which is what this is and that
makes sense because UI label
question mark is
an optional and
obviously an optional
doesn't respond to text.
UI labels do, but
optionals don't.
So, why are we getting
this error now when we
weren't getting it before.
And how would we get
rid of this error?
Well, you could
certainly get rid of
this error by just putting
an exclamation point here,
that would unwrap
this optional.
And now this would be
an UI label right here and
we can send a text.
And we do the same
thing up here.
We can unwrap it there and
we can unwrap it there.
And that gets rid of
all of our errors.
But [COUGH] this kind of an
interesting property in that
even though it's
not initialized in
the very beginning of
a colossus creation starts out
as nil not set.
As soon as as this user
interface gets loaded up
by this new controller.
Then this gets wired up,
alright, so, that gets
wired up, and this is set, and
then this it's set forever.
So it's really, kinda would
be sad if we actually,
every time we used it had
to unwrap it all the time.
So these kind of
properties that.
Get set very early, maybe
not right at creation like
this one, but very,
they get set very early, and
then they stay
set all the time.
You can, instead of
putting a question mark
in their decoration.
We're talking about
their decoration here.
You can put
an exclamation point.
And what that says is.
This is just an optional, but
always automatically unwrap
it so that you don't have to
put this exclamation
point in here.
So I take this
exclamation point out.
You can see, it's not
generating any errors.
And it's still going to
unwrap this display and
turn into a UI label.
And.
It's still gonna crash
your program if for
some reason
the display were nil.
If you tried to execute
this code, that may
be impossible because this
is the button sending those.
So the button wouldn't be here
if this hadn't gotten already
loaded up in the set.
But if somehow you had some
place in your controller or
you were accessing display
before this UI got loaded.
It would crash,
because it is unwrapping this,
it's just that you don't have
to put the explanation point,
it's kinda like auto
explanation point.
And, this is called a
implicitly unwrapped optional.
Okay?
Implicitly unwrapped optional.
And it's really only useful
for this kind, of property,
that's, set very early, and
then stay set, forever.
It's kind of sugar, really.
Okay, so let's move on
to the next button in
our [INAUDIBLE] here.
Which is going to
be an enter button.
Now our calculator does
not have an equals sign.
So you're probably used
to calculators where you
say six plus three then when
you hit equals it shows you
the result.
This calculator is
a little more like
a scientific calculator.
Has an enter key.
And so, instead you put
the numbers you want to add or
divide or multiply or whatever
onto a stack and then when you
press the operation keys it
pulls them off the stack.
So that looks like this,
6 enter 3 times.
Four, six, enter,
three, enter, times.
So the times is going
to pull the six and
the three off the stack.
You could even go six, enter,
five, enter, four, enter, and
then go times plus.
That would multiply the top
two on the stack and
then add the last one on.
So we need an enter key
here for our calculator.
Now, I'm gonna create that
enter key in a way that's
actually gonna cause a problem
for me in a moment, but
I wanna show you how to
resolve that very problem.
So I'm gonna create this enter
key by copying and pasting.
This digit key right here.
And I'm just gonna
put it in here.
Notice that I'm lining these,
blue lines up
absolutely perfectly.
I don't want them to be, like
it's lined up with that one,
but not that one or
vice versa.
I want them
perfectly lined up.
Cuz later I'm gonna spread
these out over the whole UI
and if I haven't lined these
up just absolutely perfectly
then Expo's not gonna quite
know what I want here in
terms of the relationship
between these.
All right so we don't want a
three on here, we want to have
a,enter symbol so I'm gonna go
up here to special characters.
This is on in most
Mac applications.
You can go to the edit menu
to get special characters.
And I'm going to search for
this one actually, I think
that's called a return.
Yeah.
And these are just
Unicode characters right here.
And so
I want this one that looks,
kind of like a return or
enter key.
So I have this.
And I'm gonna use the same
mechanism we used before,
which is CTRL+drag.
So I'm just gonna
CTRL+drag out here.
And, we're creating an action,
of course, cuz we want this
button to send us a message.
I'm gonna call it Enter.
That's what it is
the answer key.
Now one thing is
different about this one,
if you'll remember when
we wired this action up,
we had the button that was
sending it as an argument and
we don't want that this time.
Because there's only
one answer key we
really don't need to talk
back to the answer key, so
we're going to say
none right here.
It also doesn't really matter
about this type because we're
not going to have
an argument so
it doesn't matter
what this type is.
So disconnect that.
As you can see right here.
We have Enter, and
it has no arguments.
Now, what are we gonna
do inside Enter?
Well, the main thing
we need to do is,
put whatever number is
in this display up here,
okay, onto our internal stack.
So, we're gonna need
an internal stack,
in a moment, here.
Another thing we
might wanna do, is.
Set users in the middle of
typing the number to false.
Because we might have
been typing a number, but
as soon as we hit enter,
we're putting it on the stack.
Next time we type a digit,
we're going to be
starting a new number.
[COUGH] All right, so we'll
call that user [NOISE] in
the middle of
typing falls there.
Now, let's go ahead and,
and actually run this and
see how this is working.
Because there's going to
be a little problem here.
So, run this.
Alright, so
let's try eight, enter.
Oh.
What's that?
Oh, my god.
Six, enter.
Well it's, it's kind of
working because after we
press enter the user is in
the middle of typing numbers.
Starts over.
So that's good, but
I had no intention for
this to be showing up on
the end of my display.
This little enter.
What the heck is
that doing on there?
Why is that happening?
Let's take a look here.
The problem here, has to do
with the messages being sent.
So, when we wire this up,
that's good.
We got enter.
The problem is that button
also sends a pen digit.
That's because we copied and
pasted this three, remember?
And the three sends a pen
digit, until we copy and
paste it.
Now, this one sends,
sends a pen digit.
So this is both.
Okay, sending two.
Now, that's a common
mistake to make.
You know, you only think
about that when you copy and
paste it.
And how do we fix this?
Well if you right click, so
I'm going to right
click on this button.
You'll get this
window that comes up.
And it shows you all
the connections from this
UY element to your code.
And you can see here
both appendage and
enter are connected.
The great thing is I can just
click this little X right here
and it'll take this
connection away.
So now I only have enter.
So now if I go back here.
See it's,
it's not sending appendage,
it is sending enter.
And you can do this right
clicking for anything.
Like we need to do it for
our label up here.
See there's the display
connection we have right here.
So don't forget right click
to disconnect things.
Now if you forget about
this and you don't do it.
Or maybe you have it wired to
some thing that you change.
For example, if we have
accidentally put an argument
here to enter, if we had made
it do descending button trick,
kind of like this.
You can't just say, oh okay.
I'll fix that.
I'll just delete that.
Because that would
not work because,
enter with an argument
is actually a different
message than enter
with no argument.
And so, if you just deleted
that when you were running
your program it
would crash and
it would say, couldn't
send message enter colon.
When you touch this button
cause enter colon means enter
with an argument, only for the
purpose of this tour It doe-,
we don't see enter
colon in our code.
That's just something that's,
this story board here.
So if that happens, you need
to right click on here and
disconnect the enter colon,
that happened in there and
then you just recontrol drag.
When you recontrol
drag it's nice it will.
Kind of let you try to
grab onto something, so
its easy to reconnect.
Kay?
All right, so now we want to
actually implement enter here.
We want to enter
the guts of it.
And so we are going to need
another property here which is
going to be that
internal stack that these
numbers are going to go on.
And so that's gonna
be a var just like
this var up here that
we've created and
I'm call it operand stack
that's a good name for it.
And it's gonna have a type,
it's type is going
to be an array and
just like in other languages
like Java when you specify,
when you create an array
type you have to specify.
What kind of thing
is in the array.
And so, I'm gonna put
doubles in my array.
And that's, even though you
might say, well we can't
enter doubles, because these
are all integers, basically.
But if I were to say,
3 enter 6 divide, I get .5.
So than a double would appear.
So that's why I'm
going to use double.
Now, you can see that we've
got this error up here again.
It says stored property
operandStack does not
have initial value.
So we have to give
this an initial value.
So I'm going to give
this an initial value of
an empty array.
So now you're seeing for the
first time how you actually.
Create an instance of
a class or of a data type.
And you do that just by
specifying the type and
then use parenthesis.
Now, we're not,
again we haven't talked
about initializers.
A class or
a data structure can have
multiple initializers.
Some of them might
have arguments in here.
But most, if it's possible
they'll allow you to
create them with no
arguments and in a case on
our right it's very
obvious what to do.
No arguments just creates
an empty array right,
with no elements in it.
Now, one thing I want to talk
about is this right here.
This type, you know?
It's kind of annoying that
we have to type this and
then we have to type
it right again.
And the answer is,
we don't have to do that,
because in swift,
swift is very strongly typed.
You know there's all
the variables, but
the properties
are strongly typed.
But they, there's also
a lot of type inference.
So swift can infer.
This type in the exact same
way that digit had no type and
it inferred it from here.
OperandStack, we don't have
to specify they type, and
it can infer it from here.
And if we option click on
operandStack you'll see that
indeed, it's figured out that
that's an array of double.
And in fact,
putting the type in here
is considered bad form.
If it can be inferred,
you should let it infer, so,
if we didn't have this blue up
here we shouldn't that either,
because, false, and true are,
can only be blue values so,
we're gonna take
that off as well.
Okay, so, now, our brand
stack right here what
do we wanna do with it?
Well, when we press enter,
we just want to append.
So, append.
This is actually the first
time we're sending an actual
message to an object
looks just like when we
accessed a property.
The dot and it's just the name
of the method that we're
trying to invoke
in our arrays.
Just an array, an array method
right here called a pen.
I think you see the arguments
as newElement: T.
This : T means it has
to be of this type.
Type of things in the array so
this has to be a double.
So that's kind of a problem,
cuz really what I want to
append onto my stack is what's
up here in this display text.
And, you know, I'd like to
say something along the lines
of display.text.
Okay?
But what type is this?
I can type display.text.
Now that's not string.
That is an optional.
Remember that display.text
is an optional.
So we can unwrap
it even though
that's not gonna
solve the problem.
This is still a string and
you're still seeing
an error here.
The same string is not
convertible to double [COUGH].
Because we're supposed
to be putting doubles in
this array putting strings.
So, we have a problem here.
We have somehow to convert
this string into a double so
we can put it on this stack.
I'm gonna use
this opportunity.
Just show you another
feature which we
call Computed Properties.
So I'm gonna create another
property display value and
it's gonna be a double.
And what I want this to be
equal to is, I always want it
to be whatever's in this
display converted to a double.
Okay?
And I want to
be able to set it or get it so
I'm gonna be able to get
the value of this double.
I just want to be able to
set it as a double and
have it turn into text.
Well, that kind of
property really is tied to
some data somewhere else.
So, I don't ever want to set
it equal to some initial value
or something.
Really, I want it to always be
calculated and we can do that.
Instead of saying
equals something,
you just put curly
braces after.
And you say, get,
and we say, set.
Okay?
And inside here we are gonna
compute the value of this.
Which is we are gonna
convert this display text
to a double and then inside
here, we are, someone said,
display value equal something
and we are going to
somehow compute,
not really compute it, but.
We're gonna de, decide,
what code we need to put that
number that they tried to set
the display value to in here.
'Kay, so
let's do the set side first.
It's actually
a little simpler.
Inside this set,
there's a magic variable
called new value.
It doesn't, it's not purple
for some reason, but.
New value in this,
this is the new value.
So if someone says
somewhere in our code,
display value equals five,
this new value will
have the five.
And so all I really wanna do
here is say display text
equals the new value.
But again, of course this
is an optional string.
You can't set it to a double
because displayValue equals
five, this new values
going to be a double.
But we know how to convert
something to a string by
using backlash parenthesis.
And this is the same
thing we did when we
printed out [COUGH]
our digit up here.
We just use the back
slash parenthesis.
It tries to convert
this thing inside here,
which is a double into
a string of doubles.
You know how to do
that themselves.
And so bingo,
we've got our display text and
that's all that necessary.
also, every time someone sets
this value and then we're
clearly not in the middle
of typing a number anymore.
[INAUDIBLE] Say that.
[INAUDIBLE] All right,
what about the getting?
Now in the getting
all we have to do is
return this display value.
So it's do something
to calculate what this
display value is here.
And then return it.
Now this one I'm not
gonna take time to go
through the details here.
And actually I've made it an
extra credit item that you can
do, which requires
you to figure out
what I'm gonna type here
using the documentation.
But I'm not going
to explain it here.
I'm gonna use a class that's
in this number formatter.
I'm actually gonna
create one and
I'm gonna use a method on it
called number from string.
And I'm gonna give it
this string which is
the display values text,
unwrapped of course.
The result is acting optional
so I'm gonna unwrap that.
And then I'm gonna get the
double value of the thing I
get back [COUGH].
Number gives me this
kind of generic number so
I am gonna take it and
turn it into a double.
So there we go.
So you can go
the next spread and
look at that later
if you want.
But surprising to say we
now have a property display
value that when we set it and
get it, it's gonna be
setting and getting.
It has a string here, so
that is really convenient.
Especially for
right here, where we
wanna say display value.
'Kay?
So let's see the double.
No problem.
We're pinning that
onto operandStack.
So let's print in our
operandStack here.
Just so, I mean we can do the
same thing here, operandStack.
Okay?
And this worked because
operandStack is an array, and
arrays know how to turn
themselves into strings.
You'll see how they do that in
the console in a moment here.
So let's go ahead and
see if our application is
actually putting things on
our stack properly here.
[NOISE]
All right.
Let's try here.
Let's try 56 enter.
And look, operandStack
equals 56 doing good.
Seven enter.
All right, 56.0 and 7.0.
So, you can see that arrays
turn themselves into strings
by doing open square bracket
and then they turn each of
their elements into strings
and separated by commas.
Now this is good.
So we got our operand,
operandStack building here.
So all we need to do is have
some times, and plus, and
minus buttons, et cetera.
I'm gonna put them right here.
That will operate on these
items uh,on the stack.
So, if I pressed
plus right now,
it would pull the seven and
the eight off the stack.
Add them together,
it would be 15.
Show that 15 here, and
it actually will put
the 15 back on the stack.
So then, we'd have 56 and
15 on our stack.
Then we could, maybe.
Plus those together and
we wanted by it plus again.
All right?
[COUGH] Okay.
So how are we gonna do that?
Well, we would make
our buttons here.
And I'm gonna make the buttons
again by copying and
pasting a digit button.
But this time I know
about that problem,
so right off the bat I'm
gonna right click on it.
And disconnect appendage it.
Okay?
So
now this button sends no
messages, yet anyway.
And then we could
put a type on here.
So here I'm gonna have my all
my operations buttons use
mathematical symbols so if we
go down here to math symbols.
See there's a bunch
of math symbols here.
So let's do times, right here,
first, we'll put times right
there, and we can wire it up.
I'm just gonna hold that
Ctrl and drag out here.
We're gonna call
this action method.
Operate.
And because I'm gonna have
multiple operation buttons and
they're all going
to send operate.
Just like I did
with append digit,
I am going to use the sender.
So I'm gonna be very
careful to change this any
object to be button.
Do not forget that.
'Kay, so action,
we are gonna have it centered.
UIButton.
Call it operate.
There it is.
That's method doing operate.
We can copy and
paste this button now, right?
We got this one, so
let's copy and paste and
make some more of these.
We'll start out with
four of them, let's say.
'Kay?
Let's get back our
special characters here.
[COUGH] All right, so
let's make this one be divide.
Let's make this one plus.
And this one be minus.
All right.
So we've got these
buttons [COUGH].
And they're all sending,
if we look at this here,
they're all sending operate.
Luckily, they're not sending
anything except operate, so
that's good.
And when they send operate,
we're gonna figure out
which one is sending it by the
same exact way we did above.
We're gonna say what is
the sender's current title?
We're gonna unwrap it.
So operation here is
gonna be a string.
And it's going to tell us
the title of the buttons so
we know which one
to use there.
Now I'm gonna show you a
control flow operator here in
Swift that's very powerful,
much more powerful than
this operator is in
other languages.
And also very,
very important to switch.
I'm only gonna show you the
simplest usage of it here, but
you're gonna see on
Monday's demonstration and
later in the quarter how
important this operator is.
But, it's switch, okay, and
switch looks like switch
in other languages, like C.
You switch on something.
In this case I'm gonna
switch on this string.
This is the string.
Then you just specify
the case of each thing.
So for
example here I have a case.
Let's do the multiply.
Okay, so we've got
multiply case right here.
And then we just put
the code that we want here
for multiply.
And we'd do that for
all the other cases here.
So let's copy and paste.
And we'll do this
be our divide case.
And we'll have this
be our plus case and
we'll have this be our,
make sure we're doing the same
[INAUDIBLE] here, plus case.
Again, you've got to be
a little careful here.
You know, this minus is
slightly different from this
minus which might be slightly
different than the minus
you type with the keyboard.
So, when you're putting
the symbols here,
you wanna use exactly the same
symbols here in your case.
Now, one thing about Switch
on Swift though is it
absolutely requires that you
have every case covered.
Now since this is a string,
obviously can't have case of
,
every single string
in the universe.
That is almost infinite,
but luckily there,
,,
you can take defaults and
just break out of the switch.
default,breakswitch
That means if it's not one of
these cases by default just
,
break out of the switch.
switch
You could put code
here as well,
but breaking out of it is
what we wanna do in our case.
break
now, in here, we're just going
to put the code for multiply.
,,
So, what do we need to do for
multiply?
,?
For the moment,
I'm gonna comment this out.
I'm gonna use command, slash,
command + /
which is a really
nice feature.
.
You do command slash.
command + /,
And then command slash again,
to uncomment.
command + /.
[INAUDIBLE] real quick cuz I
just wanna focus on times.
,
Now any time I
press any operator,
,,
I probably wanna give
the user an automatic enter.
enter
That's so that six enter,
three enter,
6,enter,3,enter
times is the same as
six enter three times.
,63
Okay, so six enter three times
is gonna do an automatic enter
,6 enter 3  enter
on that three.
Cuz obviously,
I intend to have six and
,,6
three be multiplied
in that case.
So for all of these
operations, I going to say,
,
if the users in the middle
of typing a number.
,
Then hit enter for
me, right here.
enter.
Okay, so [COUGH] what
do we need to do in
,
this specific case of times?
?
Well, really we just want
to set our display value.
.
Remember we have our nice
display value down here.
,.
And we can do setting
as well as getting.
,
So I set that display value.
,.
Up here.
.
Equal to multiplying the top
two things on this stack.
So I can actually remove
something off our stack.
,.
We're representing our
stack as an array.
.
Of course,
they are stacked as an array.
,.
And so a stack is something
you push things on,
,
you pop things off.
And with an array, we're just
gonna add something there at
,
the end to push something on,
and
that will just remove it
from the end to pop it off.
So there's a nice.
.
All right.
This is an array, right?
,,?
Operand stacks.
.
There's a nice method
called remove last.
:
And if we option click on
remove last, you'll see here
removelastoption,
that it removes an element
from the end of the array.
:
Now, it does require
a count greater than zero.
.
So if our array were empty
this would crash our program.
,
So let's put a little
protective thing here.
,.
If the operand stacks.
There's a nice property
here called Count on that.
Count
It is greater or
equal to two actually because
multiply takes two operand so
2,2
there better two
things on this stack.
Then we can do this and so
,,
we're gonna multiply that
by and remove the next one.
,
Okay?
?
So here we got-
,
We're just taking the last two
things off of this stack by
,
removing them from
the end of the array and
just assigning it
to display value.
displayValue
And we probably also
want to do an enter here,
enter,
because [COUGH] if I go
six enter three times,
6 enter 3 ,
well then I want to be able
to say then nine plus and
have it add onto
the six times three.
So we want an automatic
enter here, as well.
enter,
Okay?
?
So, that's pretty much
all we need to do here.
.
Let's go ahead and run this,
see how this works.
,,,
And so, six enter, or
three enter, six enter.
6   3  6
Now we've got them
both on the stack.
Times and you can see
we put our 18 here.
,18
It also put it back
on the stack and
,
we can say five times.
,5
That put a five
on the stack and
5,
then multiplied them,
took it off.
,,
So that's working nicely.
[COUGH] Now what about our-
,
Other buttons, here.
,,
We gonna make those work.
.
Let's do that.
Now, they do a very
similar thing, here.
,
So, one temptation would
be to just copy here.
,,
Let's uncomment these out.
,
And then just paste it,
repeatedly.
,,
So, put it there.
.
There, there and then just
changes times in here.
.
D note to plus for
example on this one.
,
But his is pretty messy code,
look at all this
,,
incredible amount of
duplicating code, in here.
,
We really probably wouldn't
to write our code like this.
.
People would think we were
terrible programmers I
think if we did that.
.
Really what would be
nice is if we had some,
?
could write some
kind of function.
Maybe we could call it
perform operation or
perfomOperation
something like that.
.
And if the argument
to that function.
,
Remember that
arguments have names.
,,
Here's the name.
.
And then we have the type.
The argument were something
which basically was this
little operation in here, or
,
some sort of function that
would do this operation.
.
So if this could be some
sort of function that
,
would be cool.
.
Then, maybe we could.
,,
I take this code out of here,
put it in here.
,
Let's call it perform not
pre-form, perform operation.
perform,pre-form
[LAUGH] Put it in here and
.
instead of doing,
you know, multiply here.
,.
Let's go ahead and we can
do this operation some how.
,.
I guess, well maybe operation,
operation,
call it like a function
with two arguments here.
.
Okay.
That would be
,.
cool because we'd be sharing,
you know, this check.
.
We'd be sharing this enter.
enter
[COUGH] We'd be sharing
the removal of the operator.
removal.
We'd be sharing
the same display value.
displayValue.
We'd be kind of sharing
a lot of code here and
,,
then up here if we could
just do something like,
,,
perform operation,
and, somehow, specify,
,
multiply, as the operation
we wanted to do here.
,
And then we wouldn't need
all this stuff here, right?
,?
So this is gonna be cool.
?
Now, can we do this?
Well, yes,
the answer is we can.
,.
And so, types, functions.
,
Can be types in Swift,
just like any other type.
Swift,
So, you know, we have
a double here, oops, double.
double,
That's a type.
,
You can also have
a function type.
.
So how do you specify
a function type?
,?
Well multiple I or
multiple,
whatever function I'm
about to perform here.
,
This is a function that takes
two doubles as arguments.
double
And it returns a double.
So, I can just say,
I want operation to be
,
a function that takes two
doubles and returns a double.
double,double
I can express that right here.
,
This is a type,
the type of this.
,.
Argument right here that you
can click on and say yeah
,
that type is double takes two
doubles and returns a double.
:2double,double.
So, just simple as that.
.
So all we need now
is a function here
,,
called multiply that
takes two doubles and
multiply,2,
returns a double and
does multiplication.
double,.
So we could go down here and
say okay multiply and
,,
you'll have op1 which
is double and op2.
,double,,
[COUGH] A double and
it returned the double.
double,double.
And it's just return
one times out two.
Okay?
?
And that worked great.
!
Back out again so we can
see if this actually works.
,.
But there's no arrows here.
.
Right?
It seems to work.
?.
Multiply seems to be
a function to take the $2 and
turns it double.
And that's what this
argument here is and
,
I'm passing it along.
It should all work so
let's give it a try.
,.
So here we go as
it takes enter.
enter
54 times and
sure enough it's working it.
54,,.
It's doing that
multiplication.
.
Works great and so what about
all of our other cases here?
,case?
Well we would just
need to take this same.
.
Piece of code right here and
put it for all of them.
case,,
And of course we need a divide
method, so we have to
,,
come down here, and copy and
paste that, and make divide.
,,,divide
Oh wait a second,
,
this is starting to be just
as bad as I had before.
,.
Having to make all these
extra functions, multiply and
,,
divide and all that.
,.
Well [COUGH] it
turns out it's so
,
common to pass functions as
arguments in Swift, that it
Swift,.
allows you to put a function
like multiply right in
,multiply,,
here without having to create
a separate function like this.
And all you do is
you just pick it up.
,,
So I'm just going to cut
that from down here and
I'm going to paste
it right in here.
The only thing you have to
change syntactically when you
,
do that is this curly brace,
okay.
.
Instead of being after
the declaration of
the arguments in the return
value, it needs to be before.
,.
So, you move the curly
brace before.
.
And then where
the curly brace was,
.
you gonna put in, the word in.
in
And so that allows us to just.
.
Come and do that again to
eliminate some of our errors.
,
And we can get rid of
function multiply down here.
mutiply
So that allows me to just put
that multiplier right in here.
.
Right in line.
Write as the argument
to this function.
.
And this things kind of wacky.
For those of you
who don't know it,
,
user programming languages
that allow this kind
,
of thing to happen
are called closures.
.
It basically allows you to put
a function right in there.
.
And this, okay here, looks
okay, I mean we can certainly
,.
you know, now we can copy and
paste this and put it here.
,,
You know, here and
change this and
put it here and change this.
,,,
But it can even be
better than this.
,.
So we know that Swift
is really good at
Swift
something called
type inference.
.
Where I can kinda
figure out the type,
,
of something,
from the context.
.
And you can do
the same thing here.
.
Because its looking
at perform operation.
performOperation
It knows you're calling
perform operation.
performOperation
It knows this argument is
a function that takes two
,
doubles and returns a double.
2double,double.
So you really don't have to
specify all the types in here.
,,
Cuz it knows all of this.
.
So you can actually get rid of
all these type decorations,
,.
right here, even the return.
.
And, again,
seeing no warnings, no errors.
,,.
It knows that this has
to be a double, and
double,
this has to be a double.
dobule.
Because it knows you're
calling perform operation.
.
So it knows the argument
to that is like that.
,.
Okay, and you can even make
this look a little nicer.
,.
We can move this all
up onto one line.
.
Really nice for
readability here.
.
But, we can actually do
even better than this,
,.
because Swift knows that
perform operations argument
Swift
returns something, you don't
need this return key if your
,return
whole is just an expression
like this return key word.
.
You don;t need that key word
because it knows this is
return,
going to return something so
.
this is just an expression
it's going to return it.
.
But it's even better than
that because a swift does
,
not force you to name
these two arguments.
swift.
If you don;t name them it
will use the names Dar0.
,$0
Dollar 1, and
$1,
if you have more arguments,
dollar 2, dollar 3, dollar 4.
,$2,$3,$4.
So you don't even need this.
,.
Okay?
?
So this is a function
right here.
.
It takes two doubles,
dollar 0 and dollar 1, and
double,$0,$1
returns a double.
double.
Now Swift knows that they're
doubles because it knows that
Swiftdouble.
you're passing them to
perform an operation.
.
If you were passing this to
some other, a function that
,
took different kind of
function as an argument, then,
,
you know, these types might be
different but in this case it
.
knows that's what it is and
it knows that it returns once
Swift
it knows it's going to return
what this calculation is.
.
All right.
Now one more cool syntactic
thing you can do is if you
,
have a function like
performOperation, and
performOperation,
it has an argument which is a
function like operation here,
operation,
if this argument is
the last argument, okay, so
,
if I had other arguments
before it, and
,
this was the argument, then
you can move the function.
,
Outside the parentheses,
so other arguments,
,.
if there were other arguments
before, they would go in here.
,.
But this last argument,
.
which is this operation, gets
to go outside the parentheses.
,.
And if there are no other
arguments, if this is
,
the only argument, you can
actually get rid of that.
,.
Okay.
.
So, we're cutting down
to incredibly concise
,
language here and we can
do this exact same deal,
.
of course with these
other form operations.
.
We just need to change the.
Nothing here.
.
This one, we be a little
careful with the order of
,,
operations here,
we wanna do this because we
,
click the thing that we're
dividing by on the stack last.
.
And that's the first thing
that comes off the stack.
And same thing here actually,
,
the subtraction
minus dollar here.
,,$,
Okay, so, this is our
entire operate, and
,.
you can see that it's
incredibly concise.
,.
Very readable.
.
TImes is clearly
doing this function.
.
And very extensible.
If you wanna add
more functions,
,
we just one liners here,
.
but more these [COUGH] binary
functions that have two So,
.
let's go ahead and make
sure these are all working.
,.
All right.
.
So, 6 enter 5 times,
that's 30, that's good.
65,30,.
How about 47 plus 77,
excellent.
4777,.
How about 2 divide.
38.5.
38.5
[INAUDIBLE] number there.
,.
Working, you can see the stack
doing all the right things.
,.
Okay?
Make sense?
??
Now, I'm going to do
one more thing, here.
,.
Which is to add
another operation,
.
this is going to be a slightly
different operation.
.
So, I'm going to copy and
,
paste these operation
buttons here.
.
Again, I'm going to make sure
they are lined up really
.
nice with as many of these
blue lines as I can get.
.
I'm actually going to
leave these buttons here.
.
Because you're going to need
them for your homework.
But we gonna change this
button right down here to be
a different operator.
Which is going to be,
square root.
Which is right here,
square root operator.
All right?
And, so, I'm going to go back
her to do square root, and
it's just another case, right.
Case square root.
And, maybe I should just
be able to use the same
mechanism, right?
Let's see if that works.
Place that in there.
And instead of this bracket
here, let's use the built in
function in Swift to do
square root called sqrt.
And a dollar there.
Looks good.
And then we're ready to go.
Let's just work, call it,
what's going on here.
They have some sort of error,
what's the problem.
I don't understand.
Let's take a look at this.
Now this error is a little
hard to understand but
basically what it's saying
is that you're calling
performOperation here with an
argument which is a function,
it only takes on argument.
Goes Swift looks here and
it's used that it's only
using a dollar zero so
this is a one argument
function this whole
curly brace thing is a
function that is one argument.
Well four operation
takes a function that
has two arguments.
So that's a mismatch
that doesn't work.
So how can we fix this.
Well actually believe it or
not we can just make a copy of
form operation of another
method, same name.
This one we are gonna
have different arguments.
It's gonna have a,
an argument which is
a function that only takes one
double and returns a double.
And then inside here,
obviously we don't need to
pull two things off the stack,
just one.
And obviously we only need to
check to make sure there
is one thing on the stack.
And look,
all error warnings gone, okay?
So it automatically
figured out that this
performer operation
must be this one,
because this is a function
that only has one argument.
And so it matched it up
with this version of it.
So in Swift, you can have
functions with the same name.
As long as they have
different arguments.
And that Swift will
automatically pick
the right one, if it can.
There are sometimes
when it's just like,
I can't really tell
which one you mean.
And it will certainly
complain, in that case.
But most of the type it's
gonna be on [INAUDIBLE] from
the types involved,
what's going on.
So, just gonna run this
one again real quick.
[INAUDIBLE] 36 square root.
Looks like it's working,
9 times square root.
Excellent.
Okay.
All right.
So,
the last thing I'm going
to do here is work on
the layout of these buttons.
So that's all I'm gonna do for
the code.
You can see that we
really didn't have to
write that much code.
To make this work and
we got to do a lot of
stuff in our UI here.
So, let's go ahead and make it
so these buttons spread out.
Cuz right now you see all this
space is wasted right here.
And on an iPhone
in portrait mode.
Whole bottom space is wasted.
And an iPhone on
landscape mode,
this whole size can be wasted.
So I really want these
buttons much bigger, and
stretching out.
Now, when you do something
like that, you have to think
a little bit of kind of what
your strategy is gonna be.
You can't just kinda root
four start, you know,
control drag it
between things.
And trying to set up
the horizontal spacing,
and maybe line up the, make
the equal width and height.
Oh my gosh, you'd be control
dragging all day long,
by doing that.
So I'm not going to use
control drag to do this.
I'm going to use these buttons
down here which will kind of
bulk out a layout buttons.
Let's go ahead and
use the whole screen here.
Document outline.
So what is going
to be my strategy?
Well, my strategy is I'm going
to make a perfect grid here.
So, I almost have one, except
for there's one missing here.
So I'm actually going to take
a button, copy and paste it.
Okay, just kind of be
a dummy button here actually.
With no title.
I'm going to right click on it
also because I don't want it
sending appendage or
anything else, So
its not going to
send any messages.
But it's just a dummy,
so I'm kind of using.
A little bit of brains
over brawn here to do
this perfect grid.
Now if I have this perfect
grid, then if I had a rule
where all these buttons had to
be the same size, and they all
had the same spacing between
their neighbors, not just.
Between each other but the
same spacing to this edge and
the same spacing
to this top edge.
Okay, if I had a rule like
that then they would get
big and of course the spacing
is facing from this edge
to edge and
this edge to this edge.
If it was all the exactly the
same, which I'll make it be
whatever this is, whatever the
dash for the lines gave me.
If that was the same then they
would all have to spread out.
Okay, they'd get bigger but
they'd all stay the same
size because I'm going to
make a rule that they
have to be the same size.
But they would move
out to this edge so
that this nearest neighbor
would be the same, you know,
this distance would be
the same as this distance.
So that's my strategy,
I'm going to try to do that.
Now to make that work,
all these buttons need to know
who their nearest neighbor is.
Well, these all know their
nearest neighbor here,
the other buttons, because
I made sure I used dashed,
blue lines when I
dragged them in there.
So, that's what kind of
teaches them their
nearest neighbor.
And I'm also going to make
sure that the entire grid
knows that the left edge and
just under the label there,
our nearest neighbor.
So now it knows on the top,
the nearest neighbor
is the label, and
on the left is this edge.
And it's going to
pick this edge as
the nearest neighbor for these
buttons and the bottom edge,
cuz that's all there is and
nothing else out here
that's gonna become,
that's the only neighbor there
is, it's gonna pick those.
So now that I've
used my dash for
the lines it makes
this all quite easy.
Now, if you don't use
the dash for the lines, or
if you make some mistakes
then it's not going to work.
This strategy won't work and
I've made doing this part of
this demonstration
be extra credit.
And so if you can't get it,
don't worry about it too much,
just keep all your buttons in
the upper left corner here
and that's fine.
But if you want to give
this a try, the key is to
use the dash lines to
make the perfect grid.
Make sure that you set
the nearest neighbors here by
dragging the whole grid to
make blue lines appear on
the sides.
And then, we are going to
set these rules in bulk and
we do that with these
buttons down here.
So there's this button right
here the left most button and
it let's you set things like
lining up leading edges or
the tops or the centers.
And you could imagine there
might be a way to do this by
doing that but I am not
going to use that strategy.
My strategy is just make
them the same size and
make the space in between
them, be the same.
But, I bet there's
probably a way to do it by
lining up their centers, or
something like that, too.
So I'm not going
to use this one.
The next one over,
right here, is the one that
has the things I want.
And so you can see
that it'll ask you to
make all the buttons
equal widths and heights.
Okay, not width and
height, that fixes them
at a certain width and
height, this means that there,
they can be any width and
height they want, but they all
have to be the same width and
height all these buttons.
Of course I had these all
selected by the way, if you
don't have them selected
it doesn't make any sense.
And then up here, you can
see there is spacing to
nearest neighbor, so this
is where I am going to set
that spacing between all
these, to be the same.
And you can see that
it's put eight here.
That's because when I
did the the dash lines
to the top eight seems to be
kind of a standard number of
points between elements.
These are all multiple because
some of these buttons,
their nearest neighbor is
way over here and it's huge.
All right.
The bottom or their right.
But all these buttons,
the thing on top,
whether it's another button or
whether it's this label,
all of them happen to be this
eight points right here.
So I want all of
these to be eight.
So I'm just going to turn this
bar on right here, which says,
yes please enforce, and
make the rule that all of
these are 8 points from their
nearest neighbor to the top.
And also, 8 to the left,
8 to the right, and
8 to the bottom.
Really wanna make sure
these beams are on,
if these beams are off,
even if there's a number here,
then it's not gonna
add this rule.
So we wanted to add this rule.
So this adds up to
87 different rules.
All these equal widths and
heights and all these So
if you don't have 87 in here,
if it says a hundred and
something,
probably you don't have
everything lined up right.
It only takes 87 constraints
to express all these rules.
All right.
Now, when I click this
Add 87 Constraints it's
going to add these rules
to all these buttons, and
watch what happens.
So, I get all kinds of,
first these blue lines
are showing me the rules.
'Kay?
A lot them are saying here
that things are equal
widths and heights.
So these are what
equals rules means.
But there's also tiny little
I beams right up here.
That are showing this basing
to nearest neighbor, and
also like there's a yellow,
yellow here.
This yellow,
remember, means yeah,
there's constraints on these,
but they're not actually where
they're supposed to be
based on those rules.
So we really want to move
them all to be in their
proper spaces based
on these rules.
That's what these dashed
yellow lines mean.
So we can do the same
thing to do that,
that we did at the beginning
with the label on the top
which is go to our
document outline here,
in the lower left corner.
Okay these are document
outline when we last saw it,
it only had this
one label in there.
Now we got all these
buttons added.
And you can see
they're all selected.
All selected here as well.
And, we've got this little
yellow thing up here.
Now, if this is red, okay,
if you do all this and
this is red, well that means
that you've got not just
warnings that your constraints
aren't in the right place, but
you've got errors, usually
conflicting constraints,
where you've asked
auto layout to
enforce two rules that
conflict with each other.
So if you get to that red,
this is not going to work.
So, you'll want to start over,
and
I'll show you in a minute how
you can start over if things,
or not going your way, but
if it's yellow that just means
things were in
the wrong place.
So no problem,
we click the yellow.
Here's all the things that
were in the wrong place.
This is all the buttons,
you can see they highlight
as I mouse over them.
And you can really pick on
any one of them to fix this
because there's a nice little
switch here called apply to
all views and containers.
You don't have to
click on each one and
have it to frame update
to the proper thing.
You can just click quite
obvious in container and it's
going to move the frame of all
the buttons top fix the fact
that they're in the wrong
place based on their rules.
So let's try that.
I'm gonna hit this button
here, Fix Misplacement.
And it moved them all.
There's no more yellow.
There's no auto layout issues.
Okay.
All looks good here.
We can close our
document outline.
We zoom out, we can see,
wow, it spread them all out.
Okay?
Because,
maybe it's obeying
those rules I gave it.
Okay?
So let's now run this on
some devices here and
see what this looks like.
So turn off on an iPhone 6,
which is a pretty tall device.
It's made, you know,
kind of tall and thin.
So if this still
works fine enter.
69874 times 5 divide maybe
square root something like
that, it all seems
to be working.
Now, not only is it working
here in this portrait mode,
tall and thin.
But if we go over here to this
we can rotate the device.
Okay, so
I'm going to rotate left and
right and use the command
keys to do this.
And we rotate it right and
you see it
may the buttons spread out
to this new location and
we can rotate back using
the command keys here.
And it looks good in
either orientation.
And in fact, it can look good
on other devices as well.
So let's go over here and
instead of doing iPhone 6,
let's try it on an iPhone 4S.
Okay so,
gonna switch the simulation
here, let's run that.
Now the iPhone 4s, you can
see is a little shorter,
it's not quite as tall.
A little lower resolution,
obviously.
But it relayed out the buttons
to look good in that case too.
9 times 9, divided by 8,
square root, et cetera.
And same thing here
we can rotate and
look at this one as well.
Okay.
All righty.
So the last thing I just want
to talk about briefly is if
you try this extra credit and
it doesn't work for you.
Get all messed up, you can
kind of start over by clicking
on this and using the third
button over here on the right.
And this allows you to
reset your constraints and
you can see the top section
here is the selected views.
I don't have any
selected here so
this wouldn't do
anything right now.
But the bottom is all
views in container and
I kinda recommend going
down here to all views
container and clearing
the constraints entirely.
Reset to suggested
constraints and try and
make some sense of your dashed
lines but if it's not working,
you're probably, you're
dashed lines are off anyway.
So you can just go here and
Clear Constraints,
that'll clear them all.
Now that's gonna clear
not just your buttons but
also it's gonna
clear your labels.
So you'll have to reposition
your label with blue lines and
use control drag to say
your top space, and, and
all that stuff, you know?
If your buttons are really
huge, they got really huge,
but they're not in the right
place, you can actually change
the size of all your buttons
in the utilities window.
You can go to the size
inspector right here,
that's this one, you can
actually type in the width and
the height you want
the buttons to be, make them
smaller again, which,
you know, maybe 64 by 64.
That might make them easier to
re-drag them into position so
the blue lines are working.
And don't forget the very
important blue line dragging,
which is you want to take
the whole grid and drag it,
so that it's sitting
underneath your label.
If you have problems dragging
the whole grid underneath your
label, sometimes it's
a good idea, clear all
your constraints, kind of move
your buttons out of the way,
just kind of move them down
to the bottom here and then
just for your label, do reset
to suggest your constraint.
This top one selected view
Rest Suggestion Constraints
cuz that will work for
the label if you move it
into position as long as
the buttons aren't too close
and it thinks that, you know.
Those buttons are near
neighbors or something.
And sometimes resetting it to
suggest the constraints will
make it so that, that bottom
edge of your UI label will
be attainable when you drag
your buttons into position.
But again, not to
worry too much about
this auto layout stuff.
It's extra credit
in assignment one.
It's not going to be extra
credit in assignment two,
so you're eventually
going to have to do it.
I'm going to be giving a big
lecture on this in a couple of
weeks, on auto layout.
I've really just shown you
just kind of what it can do,
I haven't really
taught you how to do
auto layout in particular.
Auto layout is very important
because we work in this
square area and
we want our UIs to work on all
kinds of different devices.
That's why we're
starting off in the very
start with some
experience with it.
All right.
So that is it.
Now, later today,
I'm gonna, in this lecture,
I'm gonna give you a talk
about this design paradigm
called model-view-controller,
and we actually designed our
calculator kind of poorly,
because all of
this code here is really
nothing to do with UI.
This is all calculator brain,
calculator engine code.
And this really wants to
meet a different object and
that's what NBC is all about.
And so I'll give a little
talk about NBC later today.
And then on Monday, we're
going to fix our calculator
to obey MVC and be a proper
citizen in the iOS world,
where all apps need to obey
model V controller paradigm.
>> So let's try and
understand for, I mean half of
you said that you already
know MVC or you've seen it
somewhere else so, this is
going to be mostly review.
But the other half of you,
this will hopefully give you
an idea of what
MVC is all about.
So MVC is basically
a mechanism where we divide up
all the objects in our
application into one of
these three camps.
Okay?
So, the three camps.
On the left there
you see the model.
So, the model camp is gonna be
all the objects that are what
your application does.
So, for our calculator its,
it calculates.
Okay, that's what it does.
So, all the parts what we're
doing perform operation, and
all that stuff, that's all
kind of calculator stuff.
That should be in a calculator
object somewhere else,
it shouldn't be in
our controller.
And then the second camp is
the controller, the controller
controls how the model
is presented on screen.
And the view is the minions,
the classes that
the controller is going
to use are kind of
like the the building blocks,
the Lincoln Logs,
I know maybe that's
before all of your time.
But, you know, these things
we're gong to do to build our
UI, we're going to
use in the view.
So the stuff that's in the
view is pretty generic, okay,
generic UI elements.
The stuff in the controller
is very specific to
how your UI works.
And the stuff in the model
is completely independent of
how your UI works.
Okay?
So doing MVC right is about
knowing where things go but
also about how to communicate
between these three camps.
And so we can try and
summarize how
the communication works
between these camps, and
I've used road markings, you
see the double yellow line and
then the dashed white line.
So that's like you're
driving in your car.
Try to use them as an image
for how this communication
happens, where it's allowed,
where it's not allowed.
So let's talk about
the Controller talking to
the Model.
Going from that side of the
road over to the Model side is
a dashed white line,
in other words,
you can head right
across there.
You probably want to
look before you go, but
you can go right across, okay?
The controller has to know
everything about the model,
and it has to have complete
ability to talk to
the model, use its public
API as much as it wants
because the controller's job
is to present the model to
the user using its
view as its minions.
So it has to have this access.
That full, unrestricted access
the controller has talking to
the model.
This is a one way arrow.
Control, or
one way arrow, from
the controller to the model.
And similarly, from
the controller to the view,
is also unlimited
communication,
because the controller
is responsible for
talking using
it's own minions.
The view is, the controller's
new meaning is
to lay out the user interface
and all that stuff.
So, the controller can
do anything it wants.
I put that little green word,
outlet,
up there because when we have
a property of a controller
that points into the view,
we call it an outlet, okay?
And you're gonna see that
in the demo on Wednesday.
I'm gonna say, oh let's create
an outlet from our controller
to our view so
our controller can talk
to it's view, all right?
What about this communication?
Model to view?
Never.
And why is that?
100% obvious, the model is
completely UI independent.
So, there's absolutely
no way it could talk to
a viewer object or
anyone in that camp.
Because the view objects
are fundamentally UI objects.
They're kind of generic, but
they're still
fundamentally UI objects.
Similarly, since the view
objects are kind of generic,
they can't be talking
to any specific model.
They need a controller
to interpret a model
for them, okay?
So there's never any
communication this way.
That's why it's
a double yellow line.
That's why these
lines are red.
That's why there's fire, okay?
Never go across that line,
ever.
What about the view talking
back to the controller?
You got these generic view
objects, like buttons.
Can they talk to
the controller?
Well, yes, they can.
But, they have to be careful
because the view objects
are generic.
So they can't really know
much about the controller.
So, they can only communicate
back to the controller
in a blind way where they
don't know the class of
the thing they're talking to,
and in a structured way.
A way where we all agree we're
gonna communicate this way
between the view and
the controller.
So, whats an example
of a structured way?
Well one is called
target action.
So, the controller basically
drops a target on itself, and
then it hands out an action,
which is like an arrow,
to the view and
says to the view,
okay, when you do what you do,
like you're a button and
someone touches you or
your a slider and
someone moves you,
send me that action.
Okay?
So, in this way,
the generic button or
slider is communicating
back to the controller.
It has no idea that it's
a card game controller or
a space game controller.
It doesn't know what
kind of controller it is.
All it knows is that when
something happens in itself,
boom, it sends a message
to the target.
So that's a blind, simple,
structured way for
the view to communicate
with the controller.
Okay?
But what about more
complicated ways?
Sometimes the view, things
are happening in the view
that are somewhat complicated,
and
the controller needs to be
informed of what's going on,
synchronizing what's
happening.
And one way to think about
this is these words I
put up here, will,
should and did.
When the view is kind of like,
let's say I am in
the scroll view and
I am scrolling around, and
I want to let the controller
somebody know that
the user just did scroll.
Okay?
Or
the user puts down the touch
and is about to scroll, I want
to let the controller know the
user will be scrolling, okay?
Or, the user puts
the touch down and
the scroll viewer
wants to know,
should I allow the user to
scroll here, is that allowed?
All those things, the scroll
view itself might not
have enough logic to know
the answer to those questions.
So what it does is,
it delegates the authority to
answer those questions
to some other object.
Now, it doesn't know
the class of that object.
All it knows is that
other object can
answer these questions, will,
should, did, this, that, or
the other thing like,
should allow scrolling.
Did scroll to point.
Things like that.
So those are the kind of
methods you are going to see
in these delicate protocols.
Now, I know this here is 1,
6 a and b,
do not teach protocols.
How many people know what
the word protocol means an
object during a programming?
I can see very few of you.
So, I will be teaching that.
A protocol is just a blind way
to talk to another object.
When I teach it,
you're gonna be like oh,
yeah, I know what that is.
So we can really call it
protocol or whatever.
But that's how we do
delegation, okay,
this blind communication.
Also another
important thing is
that views should not own the
data that they're displaying.
They should not own it.
In other words, it shouldn't
be a property inside of them,
where that's the truth
of that data.
And the easiest example for
this is, all the songs in
your iPod, on your iPhone or
your iPad, right?
You might have 10,000
songs in there.
So, if you have some kind
of generic list view in
your view, you can't transfer
all 10,000 songs to its
instance variables, and
expect it to hold 10,000 songs
so it can list through it.
A, that would be inefficient,
and
B that information, those
10,000 songs belongs where?
In the model.
Okay, because your song
database is a model.
It has nothing to do with UI.
It's just a list of songs and
artists and albums and
all that, it's in the model.
Some controller has to
look at that database and
tell a view how to
display all those songs.
Okay?
So, we need that communication
to happen here and the view is
displaying some sort of list,
and you're touching down and
you're flicking on the list
and trying to see more songs,
how does that
communication happen?
And the answer is, we have
another special kind of
delegate, which we
call a data source.
Now the data source doesn't
do the will did should.
It's gonna be asking
questions like count,
like how many songs are there?
And the controller
looks in the model,
10,000 response to the view.
There's 10,000.
The view
makes space internally for
10,000 things.
It doesn't know what they are.
Moves the scroll bar
indicator a little bit so
that you know where it is.
And then you start scrolling,
flipping through it, and
it starts sending the message
to the controller,
give me the data at
line 150 next 10 items.
You see what I mean?
And then you flick
down some more.
Now it's saying 250,
10 more items.
And so the control is going
back to the model and
saying give me more,
give me more data.
And it's providing it to
the view in this blind way.
So to see how the view is
getting data from the model
through the controller in this
kind of blind structured way.
Okay?
That makes sense to everybody?
So data source is just
a kind of delegate,
it's a specific kind of
delegate for getting data.
So you're gonna see that there
are classes in iOS that have
a data source, and they
usually also have a delegate.
Most sophisticated classes in
iOS have a delegate, the will,
did, should, kind of things.
Some of them have
a data source,
it depends on whether they are
showing a lot of data or not.
Now simple data, like if I had
a view, if I invented a view
for my card game called
playing card view and
playing card view
it just has a suit and a rank.
Okay, we're not going to
do count data app for
just suit and rank.
We are going to set
those properties.
And so the view then would
have that data set in it but
view
it wouldn't be owning it.
Right?
The model would still be
model
owning the suit and
rank, the view is just getting
that data to present it.
view
'Kay.
So simple data,
we might transfer to
the view but it's merely for
view
it to display it.
Okay.
This all adds up to
the controller's job being to
controller
interpret and format
the model's data for the view.
viewmodel
That's the controller's job.
controller
And when we do our demo,
deomo
I'm going to be marking like,
oh see I'm writing this code.
This is to make the controller
perform its job,
controller
which is to take
the model data and
model
using its view minion
to put it on screen.
view
Okay?
That's what
the controller does.
controller
What about this communication?
Can the model talk
to the controller?
modelcontroller
Again, obviously that's
verboten because model knows
modelUI
nothing about UI, so
it couldn't possibly talk to a
UI object like the controller.
controllerUI
But sometimes things
change in the model, and
model
the controller needs to
know about it, okay?
controllerOK?
Data changes,
a database changes or
the model is some
network database, and
model
somebody changes something on
the network and it changes.
And the controller
needs to find out.
controller
So, how do we do
that communication?
We do that using kind of
a radio station model.
Okay?
So, the model, a radio station
concept, the model will use
model
this concept to essentially
broadcast information to
model
anyone who's interested.
Okay?
And the mechanisms for
doing this in iOS are called
iOS
Notification and Key Value
Observing, KVO we call it.
NotificationKVO
And so, the model can
just say, oh, anytime
model
something changes in my model
I'm just gonna broadcast on
my radio station, and then the
controller simply tunes into
controller
that radio station, and he can
find out things are changing.
And when he finds out
something changes,
it's gonna communicate via its
green arrow to the model and
model
say, okay, give me
that data that changed.
Right?
That make sense?
So, towards the end of
the quarter we'll start seeing
a little how to do
notification to find out, for
example, if the data
in a database changes.
We'll get a notification,
the UI can then, you know,
UIcontroller
controller can then go talk
to the model to get the info.
model
Okay?
Some people have asked,
can a view tune into
the radio station?
view
They probably could, but
you probably wouldn't
want to do that.
That would probably be
a violation of MVC.
MVC
All right.
So we do this.
We have all this nice
communication and
all these rules,
and we can imagine building
something simple using this.
But what if we wanna build
a big complicated app?
An app that has multiple
screens on our iPhone, or
iPhoneiPad
an iPad, it's got three or
four different areas on screen
where things are happening.
How do we do that?
Well, we're
essentially going to
combine multiple MVCs, okay?
MVC
Because an MVC can use as part
of its view, another MVC.
MVCMVC
Okay?
So an MVC,
an entire MVC can be one of
MVC
the minions of
some bigger MVC.
MVC
'Kay?
And by doing that and
cascading it down,
we can build more and
more complicated applications.
So, an example of this is, you
might have your calendar app,
and it's showing you
the entire year.
And you click on a month, and
now it shows you a month view.
Well, a month view looks a lot
different than a year view.
A month view just has all
the days and maybe some circle
that tells you where you have
an appointment on a day.
And then when you
click on a day, and
now you get a day view, okay?
And the day is showing you
the hours and what all
your appointments are, and you
click on the Appointment now
you get an appointment view
and it showing the detail of
where you're going and
when it is et cetera, okay?
Well, each of those views,
year view, month view, the day
view
view, and the appointment
view are their own MVCs.
MVC
Okay?
But you can see how
the last three, okay,
view,
are used as essentially a
minion of the top level view,
year view,
to show more detail, okay?
So the year view,
you click on a month,
it's going to use the month
view MVC to show more detail.
MVC
So it's part of its view,
okay?
So, you see this also
in iOS with tab bar
iOS
controllers, right?
You have the tab bar at
the bottom, I have four or
five things you can choose.
Well there's some MVC at the
top whose has four pointers to
MVC
four minions, which are the
four MVCs that are each going
MVC
to appear in a tab bar, okay?
We'll be doing that for
example, in assignment
number two or
three where we'll be
making a tab bar and
you're gonna have to do
multiple MVCs, okay?
MVC
So, that basically results
in a picture looks kinda
MVC
like this.
All right?
Where you got this MVC, and
MVC
you see the purple one that's
like underneath the word
'together'
together there, and
it points to three other MVCs
outside of its view thing.
viewMVC
Okay?
That's how we're
going to build it, so
that might be a tab
bar control and
those might be the three tabs.
Okay, and
each one is its own little MVC
completely independent,
operates on its own.
MVC
Doesn't even know,
it's a generic reusable view
like thing at this point.
view
Doesn't even know that
it's in a tab bar.
Okay, it just knows that
it's supposed to do
whatever it does.
And so
it's modular in that way.
You can also see that there's
no communication between any
other, there's no other
arrows, except for
some of the models.
You see some of the models are
communicating with each other.
You know a big
application might have
a single shared model.
Or the models might be split
off into pieces to be used by
MVC
sub MVCs.
Okay?
But
that's the only kind of
communication you have there.
All other communication is
either the structure view
communication we saw on MVC,
MVC
or it's using MVCs as part
of the view of another MVC.
MVCMVC
Any question about that?
So we definitely don't want
to be having designs that
look like this, okay?
Where everybody's
talking to everybody.
We can't tell who's
talking to what.
It's just impossible to debug
a program like this, and
it doesn't scale.
You can't build really
big programs this way.
It just becomes impossible to
know how touching anything
would break everything, right?
So we're definitely not
going to be doing that.
All right so that's MVC and,
MVC
like I say, on Monday we'll
apply MVC to our calculator.
MVC
So what's coming up?
I always try to get to
this slide every lecture.
Sometimes I forget but
it's posted in the slides.
It says tomorrow is Friday.
No, day after
tomorrow is Friday.
And people who
are watching on iTunes U,
iTunes U
these Friday sections will
not be on iTunes U so
iTunes U
don't go looking for
them only the normal Monday,
Wednesday lectures
went on iTunes U.
But, for Stanford students,
Friday we have this debugger
section we talked about.
And then next Monday,
your reading assignment
is gonna be due.
In other words,
you should be done with that
reading assignment before
the start of Monday's lecture.
And I'm gonna assign you
another reading assignment.
It might be your only
other reading assignment.
Perhaps there'll be
a reassignment three,
but it won't be any
more than that.
And then on Wednesday I'm
really gonna dive into
swift and foundation.
SwiftFoundation
I'm gonna talk a little bit
about the Objective C legacy,
Objective-C
and then your assignment
one is gonna be
due a week from today.
It's been posted for you, and
your assignment two is gonna
go out next Wednesday and be
due the Wednesday after that.
Just for a little bit of
advanced planning for
all of you.
Okay?
Any other questions?
Okay, thank you.
>> For more, please visit
us at stanford.edu.
>>  stanford.edu