[MUSIC]
音乐
Stanford University.
斯坦福大学
Okay, well welcome to
CS193p, Winter 2015.
好的,热烈欢迎来到CS193p 2015 冬季课程
This is Lecture NO.3.
这是第三堂课.
This is gonna be all demo.
这节课将全部是演示.
today, my voice is mostly
recovered from last week,
跟上周比我今天的声音基本上恢复了,
not 100% as you can tell.
但如你们听到的, 我并没有完全恢复.
But it's getting there.
但是差不多了.
So what we're gonna be doing
today is a demo.
好的, 我们今天将要进行一个演示.
We're gonna extend our
calculator a little bit,
我们会给计算器加点东西
we're gonna make it more
powerful.
让它功能更强大.
But more importantly, we're
gonna have it obey this MVC
更重要的是, 我们将会让它遵从MVC
design paradigm.
设计范例.
'Kay?
好么?
So it's good, a pretty good
example of showing how
因此, 这是一个演示如何把(计算器里的)内容
we're gonna separate the stuff
into the camps here.
分配到这里列出的区块的好例子.
Now, we're gonna cover a bunch
of other things,
现在我们要讲讲其他的, 比如
language features and stuff as
I always do.
语言特性和用法这些惯例内容.
That's really the primary goal
of these first three lectures
这是前三节有演示的课的最主要目标.
with the demo.
我之所以向你们实时演示
So I just mean for you to see
it in action because you can
我之所以将要向你们实时演示
read all you want about swift
or, about iOS, but until you
是因为虽然你们能读到所有你们想读的关于swift或者iOS的内容
actually see it act, turning
into an app, it's not real.
但直到你看到代码如何成为应用，才融会贯通.
So I'm just trying to make it
real for you.
因此我会试着将应用的编写的过程展示给你们.
I'm going to go to my last
slide, because,
我会讲完最后一张幻灯片, 因为,
once I go to the demo, I'll
forget to come back.
我一旦开始做演示就停不下来了.
Which is just the what's
coming up in this class.
这张幻灯片仅仅是说明接下来这门课要讲什么.
On Wednesday, it's gonna be no
demo, it's gonna be all
本周三没有课上演示,全是幻灯片.
slides, it's going to be one
of the few lectures where it's all slides
这种课不会多，但这节是其中之一.
But what I'm gonna try to do,
我会在周三的课上尝试划出
on Wednesday, is give you the
highlights of this all
划出你们
this reading that you're doing.
现阶段所学重点.
Okay?
Because you're
可以么？因为
reading a lot of stuff and
it's sometimes hard to
你们要读很多的东西,有时候区分
tell what's really important
in there and what's not.
哪些是重点哪些不是会比较困难.
So I'm gonna kinda give you
the highlights so
因此我会给你们划重点.
you can get an idea of what's
important.
这样你们会对重点内容有些概念.
And then I'm also gonna start
talking about some of
接着我会开始讲一些
the foundation layer API in
IOS that's the non,
iOS中基础层的非
user interface layer basically and
用户界面 API, 大体上讲.
kinda what some of the classes
are in there.
和其中包含的一些类.
And then also just a little
bit of how we use the language
接着是一点点关于如何使用iOS中Swift
features of swift, and
foundation, in iOS so
和Foundation 框架的语言特性.
that you can kinda get this
kind of your
这样在一定程度上
next Wednesday's lecture ,
本周三的课
is gonna be your baseline lecture,
会成为你的当做奠基课程.
can kinda get you grounded in
how to do all this stuff.
你在一定程度会获得如何做这些东西的根基.
And then next week we'll start
diving in,
然后接下来一周我们开始深入,
to build a more sophisticated
iOS application.
写一个更成熟高端的iOS应用.
Okay, I know this is kind of a
whirlwind in first two
好的, 我知道头两周会有些吃力,
weeks, you're learning a new
language, all new system.
你们将在其间学一门新的编程语言, 一个全新的体系.
But hopefully by the end of
this week and the end of your
但是希望在这周以及
second assignment which will
go out on Wednesday you'll be
将在周三布置的第二个作业结束之后,
pretty confident that you'll
at least,
你能够比较确信,至少自己,
you know, have a, solid ground
foundation to build from,
额...有一个的坚实的基础.
no pun intended there.
我不是在说笑.
There's a holiday weekend this
weekend no Friday section and
这周末有公众假期, 所以这周五没课,
no class on Monday until we
resume next Wednesday, and
下周一也没课,直到下周三重新开始上课,
the primary thing I'm gonna do
next Wednesday,
下周三我的首要任务是
not day after tomorrow but
不是后天的周三
the next Wednesday, is talk a
little more about auto layout.
是下周周三, 是讲一些关于auto layout的内容.
Cause you've only just seen
kind of a glimpse of auto
因为到目前为止你们只是瞥见了一点关于
layouts so far and
auto layout的内容.
I haven't even really told you
how to do auto layout and so
我实际上并没有告诉你们如何做auto layout
you're kinda just fumbling
around and trying,
你们差不多只是在摸索和尝试
trying to reproduce what I do
so next Wednesday we'll
重现我做过的内容. 所以下周三
talk about how to really do
auto layout hm, and all that.
我们会讲如何做真正的auto layout和相关内容.
'Kay, any questions before I
dive into this demo?
好的,在我开始演示之前还有没有问题?
Hopefully my voice will hold
out I can already hear it
希望我的声音能坚持住, 我已经感觉到
starting to not hold out but
we will see.
嗓子有些挺不住了, 但是...看吧.
All right.
好的.
So, I'm going to just go to
Xcode here, launch Xcode.
嗯,我现在点这里的Xcode, 运行Xcode.
And we're gonna leave off
right where we, were,
我们将继续上次课程
last time, in the calculator.
计算器程序的编写.
There it is right here, and so
these are UI.
都在这里了, 这是UI.
Hopefully you recognize that
and you did,
希望你们都认出来了并且
did your homework.
做了作业.
I hope.
我希望.
And here is this area that I
selected at the end,
这是我在代码尾部选中的区域,
which is this area that's
really has not,
这块区域并不是,
this is not about how, how the
calculator gets presented on
并不是负责计算器如何在屏幕上呈现的.
screen, this blue area is
about how the calculator is
这块蓝色的区域是关于这个计算器
a calculator, okay?
为什么是个计算器, 可以么?
This is where all our
calculations are and
这里是存放运算的地方
this blue area really
shouldn't be in this class,
这个蓝色区域不应该出现在这个类里,
this view controller class
because this is the C
这个视图控制器类. 因为这是我们MVC模型的
of our MVC, okay.
控制器(Controller), 好么?
And our MVC, this is the C,
this is the V, the view,
我们的MVC模型, 这是控制器(Controller), 这是视图(View),
these are the minions that
this controller's using.
它们是控制器使用的小兵们.
And today we're gonna create
the M.
今天我们将构建计算器的模型(Model).
Okay?
The model.
好么?模型.
The model is gonna be what our calcu,
这个模型将会决定我们的计,
what our application is, which
is, it's a calculator.
我们的应用是什么, 也就是一个计算器.
'Kay?
好么?
We're also going to enhance
our calculator the primary new
我们将会加强这个计算器, 我们将赋予
feature we're gonna give our
calculator is that
它的首要新特性是
our calculators model is gonna
remember every operand and
我们的计算器模型将会记住所有我们要求的
operation you ever asked it to do.
运算对象和运算.
Okay, so right now as we do
operations we consume all
好的, 现在当我们做运算的是时候我们假设所有
the operands.
运算对象.
'Kay, they consume, kinda,
they're gone.
So in this case,
we're going to actually
collect all the operations and
operands in our, in a stack
and then we can
ask the model to, evaluate
that stack of operations and
operands at any time we want.
And the reason we're adding
that ability is because your
homework, assignment number
two, you're gonna add two
major features where having
all the operands and the
operations in a stack is gonna
be really valuable to you.
So you'll be starting your
second homework with what I
do today cause you'll need
this capability to do what I
ask you there.
Okay, and I'll talk about that
at the end.
If I forget to talk about
that, remind me.
Say, tell us about assignment
two.
Okay.
So, how do we create a new
class.
Because we're gonna put our
model, 'kay, the calculator,
kind of, it, it's the guts, in
a different class.
So how do we create a new
class, in Xcode.
We do that up here from the
File menu.
We go, New > File.
So, you're gonna do File menu
> New > File for a lot of
different things you're gonna
add to your project.
Not even just, new classes or
whatever, but, when you click
that you're gonna see
there's a lot of different
things you could add.
And, we're in iOS, so
you're gonna click on this iOS
thing at the top.
And we wanna add a source
file.
And over here we're gonna be
doing this later in
the quarter, this is how we
basically add subclasses of
iOS classes, Co, Cocoa Touch
classes.
But we're gonna do today this
one Swift File,
you can see it's an empty
Swift File.
And since our model is
completely UI independent it
doesn't inherit, it doesn't
subclass any IOS class or
anything, it's just a basic,
Swift File.
So I'm gonna pick on this
Swift File,
click Next, and now it wants
to know the name of
it and where we wanna put it,
and we're gonna put it in
the same place that all our
other swift files are.
Here's our Controller and
this AppDelegate, we moved it
out of the way at the very
beginning of the very first
lecture but it's in there too.
So we want to put it in this
same directory.
And we're gonna call this new
class CalculatorBrain.
Now, you don't have to have
the name of
this Swift File here be the
name of the primary class but
we always do that.
It would be kinda confusing to
people a little bit if the
name of the Swift File
was different than whatever
the primary class is in there.
But it's certainly legal.
All right.
And Swift, the name of
the file really doesn't mean
anything.
It's what's inside that
matters.
But, CalculatorBrain is gonna
be the name of our class,
our model.
I'm calling it that cause it's
the brain of our calculator,
I'm trying to pick a
descriptive name.
Notice the capitalization
here,
types in swift, we always
capitalize them.
And we do not put underbars
and other stuff in there.
Okay?
We use what's called this
camel notation here, where
every word gets capitalized,
including the first name, word
for types.
Everything else, we don't
capitalize.
So property names and things
like that, function names,
those all start with lower
case,
they still do the uppercase
and the other words.
That way we, in our reading
our code we
can really quickly pick out
what to type and what to not.
'Kay?
So please adhere to that.
If you don't, you're gonna
look like a newb out there.
'Kay.
Calculator brains what we're
gonna call it, I'm gonna
create it.
Here it is right here.
I'm gonna make it my whole
screen.
You can see that the import
here is not import UI kit,
it's import Foundation.
Foundation is that layer, that
kinda core services layer I
talked about in the first
lecture.
It don't have many UI stuff in
it which is good because our
model is UI independent so
there should be no UI in here.
So we would never be importing
UI kit into a model class,
'kay?
You can feel free to stop me,
by the way,
if you have any questions.
All right, so we're gonna
create a new class,
you already know how to do
that.
We just type class and
then the name of the class,
it's gonna be CalculatorBrain.
Now, this class is not going
to inherit from any other
class, 'kay?
Just gonna be a basic swift,
class.
Now sometimes your model might
inherit from a class called
NSObject, and
I'll talk about that a little
later maybe on Wednesday even.
You'll get a little bit if you
inherit from NSObject, but
we're just gonna have it be
basic swift base class, 'kay.
It doesn't, doesn't need to
inherit any functionality.
Okay.
So what's gonna be our data
structure of
our calculator brain.
It, it has to be a little
different than the data
structure we used in our
controller to
capture the operand because we
gotta capture operand,
operations and operands both
into this.
So we want it to be a stack,
I'm gonna call it opStack and
but the type can't be array of
double.
Okay, because operands are
doubles but operations
are like a combination of a
syn, a mathematical symbol
like plus, times and then also
a function.
Function that actually does
the thing, 'kay?
So obviously we can't do that
so
we're gonna have to need some,
some new data structure I'm
gonna call that data
structure op and we're gonna
define that in a second.
So op is gonna be something
that could be an operand or
maybe it could be an
operation.
'Kay?
It could be either or.
Now a couple of things about
this here is of course I
have to initialize this so I'm
gonna do
the exact same thing that I
did in the controller which is
I'm just gonna create an empty
array of op.
'Kay?
And
I'm even gonna use a little
different syntax, 'kay?
We've been using this.
I like this syntax because
especially for
people who are first time to
swift it's very clear,
this is an array and inside
the array are these ops but
this is evidently not the
syntax that is preferred.
The preferred syntax is
actually to do [Op] 'kay?
So this is just an alternate
syntax, putting square
brackets with the type in the
middle for declaring an array.
It's exactly the same thing
just different way of
typing in, identical in every
possible way,
it's exactly the same.
Okay.
I think this is a little bit
preferred because if
you ever initialize an array
which will see later.
You use this syntax to create
the array and
put things in it.
So I, I can understand why
they do that.
Okay?
So this is an array of op.
That make sense?
Now, let's talk about op.
What kinda thing should op be?
Well, we could make op a
class.
An op could have a property
for op,
for an operand, which would be
the value of the operand.
It could have another
property, which is the,
symbol, mathematical symbol
for the operation and
another property, which was a
function, which does it,
and obviously, if the operand
is set,
then the other two would be
not set and vice versa.
But that, that's a little bit
weird to have a class that
has properties that sometimes
they're set and,
and if other things are set,
they're not set.
It's really not what we want.
What we really want is an
enum.
Okay, so you're probably used
to enums in other languages so
I'm gonna create an ema,
[UNKNOWN] enum, it looks very
similar creating a class.
I just use the word enum
instead of class,
obviously no inheritance for
enum, sorry.
But enums can have functions,
just like the class,
they can also have properties
but only computed properties.
'Kay, the Camry's stored
properties.
So you know enums are kinda
for basic types and
enums are really great when
you have something that can be
one thing one time and a
different thing another time.
And never both at the same
time,
that's kinda what enums are
right,
they're enumerating different
possibilities so
we could say you know case
operand and we could have
a case operation, to have the
different things that we have.
Now, in other languages, this
would be as far as we can go.
And this would be pretty
useless.
Because if we had an array
that just said whether it
was an operand or an
operation, that doesn't help.
I need the actual operand.
I need the operations
mathematical symbol and
its function.
I need them, they have to be
in this e-mail.
And Swift has a really cool
feature where you can
associate data with any of the
cases in the e-mail.
So for an operand I'm gonna
associate the data double.
So if my enum is an operand
it'll have this
double associated with it,
that's gonna be the value of
the operand.
And similarly for
operation I'm actually gonna
do unary operation first,
that's a single argument
operation.
I'm gonna have a string which
is gonna be the symbol,
the mathematical symbol for
it and of course I'm gonna
have a function.
Okay again functions are just
types in swift,
it's no different than string
'kay we're just saying this is
a function, put a function in
there.
A lot of times we'll do the
curly braces and
put a closure use closures to
create our function but
we could create actual
functions and
pass them in there, that's
fine.
So, and we'd also want a
binary function here that
takes two arguments.
Binary operation and
just those two arguments here
in it's function.
Okay?
So now we have the stack.
Okay.
Which is an array of ops.
And these ops are either each
op in this, is array is either
an operand or it's one of
these two kinds of operations.
Okay so so this is great.
We got this op it's either an
operation or an operand.
How are we going to, you know,
put things into
this op stack for example and
something like that.
So let, let's go talk about,
the API.
A, API stands for application
programing interface.
API is kind of the meth, all
the methods and properties
that make up your class, the
description of them.
So I'll use that word a lot,
API.
And we really need to be able
to put an operand on there and
stack, and we need to be able
to put an operation on.
So I'm gonna have a function
called pushOperand, and
it's gonna take an operand,
which is a double.
Okay it's not gonna return
anything yet anyway.
And to push an operand on my
stack, could not be easier,
I'm just gonna say
opStack.append,
you'll remember that append is
a function in array and
the thing that you put on,
obviously has to be this
little type T.
T is whatever you put in here,
so op in this case.
So we have to have an op here.
How do you create an enum
item?
You just Op.Operand and you
give it the associated value.
'Kay?
So, very simple kind of way to
create these enums and
associate the value with them.
Any questions about that?
Okay, and then how about
operations?
We'll have instead of push,
we're gonna call this
performOperation.
And I think when I do
performOperation, what I'm
gonna have is, my calculator
brain is going to have
a bunch of known operations,
things it knows how to do.
And when you perform an
operation,
you just specify the
mathematical symbol of it.
So the argument here is going
to be symbol,
which is a string.
Okay?
So, to append an op on here
that is, an operation,
I'm gonna need to have these
known operations.
So, how am I gonna do that?
Well, to have known
operations, I'm gonna create
another instance variable here
called knownOps, so
my known operations.
And it's gonna be a
dictionary.
Okay, now, you read about
dictionaries in
last week's reading
assignment.
That's why I have the reading
assignment due today.
Cuz then I can know you've
read about them.
I hope you have.
And so, how do I create a
dictionary?
It looks like this,
Dictionary.
And it's the same kind of
thing with these angled
brackets, because you have to
say for the dictionary,
what type are the keys, what
type are the values.
And our dictionary is gonna
have keys that are strings and
it's gonna have values that
are ops.
Oops, sorry, ops.
Okay, and I'm gonna create
one.
'Kay?
Everyone understand this?
Now, this knownOps, I'm just
gonna put all of the ops that
I know in there, where the key
is the symbol and the value is
the actual op, and then when
someone says performOperation,
I'm gonna look it up in the
knownOps.
And when I find it, then
that's the operation I'm
gonna push onto the stack, all
right?
Make sense?
But I have to load this
knownOps up.
Oh, but first of all, so let
me talk about this syntax.
Just like array has a special
syntax with the square
brackets, so does dictionary.
So to have a dictionary like
this with this kind of
special syntax, we're gonna do
open square bracket.
And then a colon in between
the key and
the value type, so it looks
like that.
So it looks very similar to
array, but
you've got this thing where
you've got the key and
the value separated by a
colon.
'Kay?
Same thing, though, exact same
thing.
Just a dictionary, strings,
looking up in strings to find
ops.
All right, so how am I gonna
initialize this knownOps?
Well, this is a great time for
the first time for you see an
initializer, okay?
So far we've been creating
classes like right here, okay,
just by putting these
parentheses.
And I told you that was
calling an initializer in
Dictionary, okay, and
this one was calling an
initializer in Array.
And so we're gonna have our
own initializer in
CalculatorBrain, and
we just do that by saying
init, like this, okay.
Now any time someone says
something like let brain equal
CalculatorBrain, with the
parentheses, okay?
It's going to call an init
that
matches the same arguments.
In this case, no arguments, so
it's gonna call this init.
Okay.
Couldn't be simpler there.
So what are we gonna do in
this init?
We're just gonna initialize
this known op, so
I'm just gonna start putting
some known ops into this
knownOps dictionary.
We need our friend special
characters here for that.
So let's go ahead and
put, well, let's put times
here first, I guess.
Okay, and we need to create an
operation.
How do we create an operation?
Very similar to how we created
this enum.
Op, dot, and times is a binary
operation.
And you can see that it's
typing this for me.
I'm just pressing Tab to get
along.
This is the symbol, which is
this thing here.
Now, this is kinda bad code
that I ended up
typing this twice in the same
line.
If I accidentally use the
wrong x,
like some x from somewhere
else or the x just from my
keyboard might be different
from this x, than this x, ugh,
we could get in trouble where
these things don't match up.
So later, in the, right at the
very end of the demo,
I'm gonna show you how we
could do this in
a way where we don't have to
type this x twice like that.
Okay.
But now we just need the
function.
We know how to do that with
closures.
We say $0 times $1.
End the closure.
And yes, I could put this
closure outside,
since it's the last thing
here.
That is also legal to do when
you're creating
the operations like this.
'Kay?
So that's kinda nice.
Let's do our other three
binary operations here.
We'll go divide.
And this is where it really
gets annoying to have to
type it twice.
But I have to show you
something else before I can
show you how to do that right.
Let's go here.
And there we have minus.
You can see there's two
different minuses there, so
hopefully I clicked the same
minus in both those spots.
And then we change these
things.
We know that divide is 1
divided by $0, and
this is plus.
And this is 1 minus 0, $1
minus $0, okay, so
everyone cool here?
These enums are really easy to
create.
The API of them is really,
really nice, simple.
And then we have our other
operation,
which is our unary operation,
which is square root.
So let's put that in here,
square root is right here.
And we'll put it right here.
And square root is not a
binary operation it's
a unary operation.
Oops, look at all this.
'Kay?
And of course, inside here,
it's square root of $0.
Okay, you remember that from
last time.
So this is good.
Now, while I'm here,
I wanna show you a couple
things more about closures.
Okay.
This, what is this curly
brace?
It's a function that takes one
argument and
returns one argument.
And we know that
it's doubles because we're
creating a unary operation.
And so, it's inferring the
type here, right?
Everyone understand that?
Well, there's another function
that returns a function, or
there's another function that
takes a double and
returns a double, that does
square root,
it's called square root.
So inside here, we could just
say square root.
Okay, we don't even need this
business.
Just wanna emphasize that
we're just passing a function
here.
And it can be a named
function, or
we could use these curly
braces.
Now, this is really gonna
freak you out, cuz watch this.
For times, there's a function
that does times called times.
Okay.
So in Swift, all these
operators, times and
all these things, are just
functions.
They just happen to be
specified in a way that says
that they can be infix, right,
between the two
arguments instead of taking
the arguments in parentheses.
And we do the same thing here
with plus.
All right, plus.
Now, we can't do it with
divide and
minus because the order is
backwards.
Right, we put the things on
the stack,
we pull them out backwards, so
we can't do it with those,
but.
I just wanna emphasize, that's
what's going on there.
Okay, so now we have this nice
knownOps.
So we have this thing.
It's loaded up.
It gets loaded up whenever the
CalculatorBrain gets created.
So that's all good.
Now we can use that down here
in performOperation.
All right, so how are we gonna
use this in performOperation?
Well, we basically wanna let
the operation equal
knownOps sub symbol.
Okay?
Someone passed us a symbol.
They're trying to perform this
operation.
So this is either a plus or a
times.
Hopefully an operation we
know.
And we're gonna look it up in
knownOps.
And the way we do that is with
the subscript notation with
the square brackets.
Okay?
That's how you
look something up in a
dictionary.
But what might be kind of
surprising to you,
what type do you think this
would be, operation?
Any guesses, yeah, some people
are saying the right thing.
You'd think this might be an
Op,
because I'm looking up in
knownOps right here, a string.
And so hopefully I'm getting
an Op, but this is not an Op,
this actually is an Optional
Op.
Okay, now why is that an
Optional Op, because you
might be looking up something
that's not in there.
And it has to return, oh, nil,
sorry, couldn't find it,
so that's why it has to be an
optional, is returned.
So a dictionary,
whenever you look up something
in a dictionary,
it always returns an Optional,
okay, either nil or
the type of thing you said was
supposed to be in there.
So I'm gonna if let here, I'm
gonna say,
if I'm able to look up my
operation in my knownOps,
then I'm going to push it on
to my op stack.
Okay.
Are you cool with that?
Make sense?
Okay.
Now, what's next?
Well.
Now we have.
Oh, well.
I'm gonna take a pause here to
talk a little bit about access
control.
Okay?
Access control is about public
and private.
Okay?
What methods in this class
are public, in other words,
other people can use them,
other classes in my code
allowed to call them?
And what things are private?
My internal data structures
that I
don't want people messing
with?
Okay, so the way public
private works in
Swift is kind of interesting.
You basically specify the
things you want to
be private by putting the word
private on them.
If you don't put any word on
them,
then they're public inside
your program.
'Kay?
And you only use the word
public if you're shipping out,
like, a framework of objects
to other people, and
you want stuff in there to be
public outside the framework.
So I'm making some framework,
a bunch of objects that I'm
trying to sell to people or
I get people to use to do
something, and
of course I'm gonna have
things where my objects inside
my framework can talk to each
other.
There's no keyword needed for
that.
Then I'll have things inside
certain objects
that are private only to that
object, I'll say private.
And them some of them might be
public that the customer who's
buying my objects, my
framework, can use.
Now, in this class we're not
gonna be doing frameworks,
we don't really have time to
get to that, so
we're not gonna be using the
keyword public,
we won't ever use that,
because we don't have any
frameworks.
But we are gonna use private.
And, starting with assignment
two,
it's one of your evaluation
criteria is gonna be,
make private things private.
'Kay?
So that is important to do.
And you could just say,
well, I like everything to be
public.
Well, that's bad.
Okay?
If you make your
internal structure public, and
some other object in your
program starts mucking with it
and breaks your object, and
then you come to a new version
of your program, and
you change something, and now
everybody's breaking.
That's bad, okay, that's
chaos.
So the only things that want
to be not private are things
that you're committing to sign
up to support.
So in this class, the only
public things so
far are the initializer.
Obviously, we want to allow
people to
create a CalculatorBrain.
That's clearly public.
Also pushing and performing
operands and operations.
That's public.
Okay?
Everything else, for now, I'm
gonna make private.
So I'm gonna make this
private.
Notice that if I make this
private,
it's gonna start saying, whoa,
wait a second, this can't be
public, you know, it can't be
non-private because this is
private and it uses it.
That's what this warning's
gonna say right here, see.
Property must be
declared private because its
type is private.
Okay, that's the type of this.
But I want this to be private
anyway,
this is my internal data
structure, opStack.
Now, knownOps is kind of an
interesting one.
Maybe I would want that to be
public one day,
because maybe I want people to
use my calculator brain and
teach it new ops.
That wouldn't be that
unreasonable.
However, I'm not ready to
support that functionality in
my CalculatorBrain.
I'm just not sure I wanna do
it this way.
Maybe I don't want this
property to be public,
I might want to just have some
functions to learn an op or
something like that, so
I'm just not sure, so I'm
gonna start out private.
And that's really, when you're
designing APIs,
you wanna kinda start out,
make it private first, and
then open it up as you're
willing to support that
functionality.
Question?
>> Is the common view in
Swift to make most instance
variables private and
use getters and setters, or is
it to make them, if,
if they are supposed to be
public, or
make them public and then let
the?
>> All right.
So the question is, is it,
is it kind of part of the
Swift way to make
most instant variables private
and
then have getters and setters
that are public to get them.
That doesn't really even make
sense in Swift.
That's more of an Objective-C
thing.
In Objective-C, you had
instance variables, and
then you had properties that
would get and set them.
And Swift has kind of merged
those a little bit
closer together so that
properties are really kind of
the public or private getters
and setters.
So, if you have a property,
you just have to
decide whether you want people
to access it or
not, and if not, make it
private.
And if so, make it public.
And that, you know, don't make
it non-private, basically.
And that's, just that's all
you need to think about.
I wouldn't even think in Swift
in terms of instance variable
versus the property.
Now, it is still possible in
Swift to do that,
because you have computed
properties.
And those could be setters and
getters that are setting
private properties.
But we're gonna see on
Wednesday, even,
I'm gonna talk to you a little
bit about a way that when your
properties get set, you can
intervene,
you can check them to make
sure the value is okay.
So if you have a public
property,
you can still protect it by
intervening a little bit
when people set it or try and
get it.
So it is possible to still
have some protection there,
we'll see that.
All right, so these are our
only public things.
Now, there's only one other
public thing we need to do in
our CalculatorBrain, which is,
we need to let people evaluate
this stack.
So people are pushing operands
and performing operations,
now they wanna know what's the
result.
Okay?
They
pushed an operand of a five.
They pushed an operand of a
four.
They performed operation plus,
they want to see four plus
five.
Where's that nine, okay?
They need the result.
So we need another public
method here,
which I'm gonna call evaluate.
'Kay?
And evaluate,
we could have it return a
double, for example.
And it would just evaluate
this opStack and
return the value.
But I really can't make this a
double.
Really, this has to be an
optional.
'Kay, why does this have to be
an optional?
Well, that's because someone
might get my CalculatorBrain,
and the first thing they do
is,
they say, perform operation
plus.
Okay, well I have no operands.
Okay?
And
you're asking to evaluate
plus.
I can't do that.
So, I have to return something
to you, that lets you know,
I could not evaluate what you
ask me to evaluate.
So, I'm gonna return nil in
that case,
so valuate here really needs
to be an optional.
'Kay, so you can see some of
the thinking,
when do you make something an
optional when not.
'Kay, so this is a classic
case of that,
where you got sometimes you
wanna return it and
you can't do it, so you have
to return no.
All right, so how we going to
implement evaluate?
Okay, how many people in the
class,
raise your hands don't be shy,
are you comfortable with
the computer science concept
of recursion?
Okay.
Excellent, that's about 80 or
90%, so I'm gonna explain this
really fast then.
And if you don't understand
recursion,
if you didn't raise your hand,
that's something you should go
review.
Okay?
[LAUGH] Recursion is
something, you should know by
the time you take this class,
so that's something you
definitely wanna know.
So, how are we going to use
recursion to
evaluate this stack?
All right, looks like this.
I'm gonna do a sample stack,
right here.
So, let's say I put a 6 on the
stack, and then I put a 5, and
then I put a plus, and then I
put a 4, and then I put times.
Okay?
So here's our stack, and I'm
gonna evaluate this,
I'm gonna recursion.
How am I gonna do that?
Well, really, what I'm gonna
do is I'm gonna
have a helper method here, a
recursive helper method.
I'm gonna call it evaluate
also, actually.
And it's gonna take a stack,
as an argument,
a stack of things to evaluate.
And it's only gonna evaluate
the top thing on the stack.
That's it just gonna value the
top of the stack and
return it, but the top thing
of the stack might
involve looking at every
single of one of these, right?
Cuz, this times needed to two
operations.
So, lets look at this, this
recursive evaluates gonna come
in here, it's gonna try and
evaluate the top of the stack,
which is a times.
Okay?
So it's like,
okay, I'm doing times.
Now for times it needs two
operate,
two operands here for times.
So, it recursively calls,
itself to say give me to first
operand for time.
And so recursively, comes in
here, it finds a 4 on
the top it's like, I know how
to evaluate 4, it's 4.
So, it just returns.
Okay, so now I have my first
operands.
'Kay?
Now,
I take the rest of the stack
and
evaluate it, to get the second
one.
And when I do that, I get
plus, 'kay?
So, plus says, oh, I have to
evaluate plus.
It needs operands.
So, I come over here, I'm
getting a plus.
And I gotta go recursive
again, to go get its operands.
I get the 5, that's good.
I'm gonna go recursive again,
get the 6, over here.
And I've evaluated the whole
stack.
So, you see how I have to keep
going backward recursively to
my evaluate-
>> [COUGH]
>> To get the operands for my
operations.
Once, I get to an operand I
can stop,
okay number, I got it and I'm
out of of there.
But every time I encounter
another operation,
I have to keep going
recursively to
get all my arguments, any
questions about that?
'Kay, so it's actually gonna
be pretty simple recursion.
When you see the code, you're
gonna be, that makes sense.
So, I'm gonna have this
separate I'm gonna put this up
on top for scrolling reasons.
Oops.
Didn't mean that.
The separate evaluate.
And this evaluate is going to
take a stack of ops,
as its argument.
And why does it take a stack
of ops?
Because as it's recursing,
it's using the rest of the
ops.
So, you see what I mean?
It's not,
it can't be looking at the big
opStack in our brain.
It can't look at this.
'Kay, cuz it's kind of
consuming it.
Right?
And every time I call it
recursively, I'm gonna get
fewer operands to work with.
So this is what I'm doing.
Now, the first time I call it,
right here, I'm gonna give it
the full opStack.
So, I'll call my recursive one
from here.
Now, what's this thing gonna
return?
'Kay.
That's interesting and
here's a big new thing for you
to see.
You've read about it I, I
can't remember I
even asked you to read about
this but I think I.
No, I guess I didn't.
Which is tuples, 'kay?
So in Swift, you can combine
multiple things together
into one kind of really te,
mini data structure called a
tuple, 'kay?
Don't let the tu [LAUGH] sound
in there fool you.
It's not just two, it's any
number, okay?
And you just put them in a
parentheses, okay?
And, and that's it.
So you can use this for return
values.
So I've gotta function right
here,
and I actually need to return
two things from this evaluate.
'Kay?
One thing I
need to return is the result
of a evaluating it.
But the other thing I
need to return is the rest of
the stack that I didn't use.
Cuz as I'm working my way down
here and I take off that
times, and the 4 and the 5,
okay, I'm consuming things but
then I'm leaving the rest of
the stacks, so
I have to keep returning
what's left of the stacks,
while we keep consuming it.
Okay?
So, I'm gonna return this in a
tuple.
Tuples could not be simpler
syntax,
just open parentheses, not
nine, open parentheses.
Open parentheses, and just all
the types that you,
of things that you want in
here.
So, I'm gonna return a double
question mark,
that's my results.
'Kay?
That's what's eventually,
gonna be
returned out here after all
the recursion unwinds.
And then also I'm going to
have the ops that are left
over.
Now, a tuple could look just
like this, unnamed.
Did you see how these things
are not named,
each of these things in here.
But you can also put names in
here as, if you want, as well.
So maybe I would call this one
the result.
Okay?
And
I would call this one
remainingOps, 'kay?
And I kinda recommend putting
those in there, and
you'll see why in a second
because there's two ways to
call a function that returns a
tuple and get the results.
And one of the ways requires
that you name these, 'kay?
So, it doesn't hurt to name
the, you might, as well.
It's good documentation.
Someone looking at this now
knows, oh, yeah,
this is the result of the
evaluation, and
these the ops that were left
over.
'Kay?
All right.
So let's dive in here.
The first thing,
line of code I'm gonna put in
this recursive function
is the failure line of code,
which is return nil, ops,
okay?
So if I fail, okay, I'm gonna
try and
do my best in here to evaluate
these ops you passed me, but
if I fail I'm just gonna
return my result of nil.
'Kay?
And that's gonna be my default
is to return nil so
I know I failed.
So, if I run out of operands
or
I run out of stack can't find
it for
example, it's just gonna fall
out here and return nil.
Okay?
So that's good.
So, what do I need to do here?
Well, first thing is I need to
make sure I have some ops.
So I'm gonna check to see if
the ops is not empty.
Okay, if you've handed me a
stack of no ops to evaluates,
I can't do that.
So I'm just gonna return nil.
'Kay?
So
that's the very first thing,
I gotta make sure I have some
ops to work with.
Now, I'm gonna grab the first
op of the stack, so
in this example, I'm gonna
grab that x off of here.
'Kay?
I'm gonna do that,
I'm gonna try to do that by
saying, let op equal ops.
'Kay, ops is this argument,
right here.
'Kay, that's the ops, you told
me to work on.
And we know how to removeLast.
Remember, removeLast from last
time?
Removes the last thing off an
array.
And when we are trying to make
an array look like a stack,
that's how we do it, okay?
We push things by putting
these on the end of the array.
We pop things by, by pulling
it out.
But you can see I got an error
there.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And it's very important to
understand why I
have an error here, okay?
So I'm gonna click on it.
We're gonna read what it says,
it says, immutable value of
type array of op,
only has a mutating member
named removeLast.
Okay, well this is kind of a
formal way of saying,
you can't do removeLast on ops
because ops is immutable.
It's read-only.
You cannot mutate it.
You cannot change it.
Okay, why is ops read-only?
Well, there's two things to
think about here.
One is, when you pass
arguments into functions,
unless it's a class that
you're passing,
unless you're passing an
instance of a class.
The thing you pass is copied.
'Kay?
It's very important to
understand that,
that's passed by value.
You're used to it in other
languages,
most languages do this, pass
by value.
Arrays and dictionaries are
not classes.
They're not classes in Swift.
They're structs.
You know, like a C struct?
'Kay?
Arrays and dictionaries are
structs.
Structs in Swift look a lot
like classes.
They have functions,
they can even have properties
that have storage.
They're almost identical to a
class, really.
The only two huge differences
between structs and classes.
One is that classes can have
inheritance.
And structs cannot, okay?
But number two is that structs
are passed by value and
classes are passed by
reference, okay?
Very important that you
understand that distinction.
So structs are usually only
used for basic.
You know, components like
arrays and dictionaries.
Even doubles and ints are
structs in Swift, okay?
>> [COUGH]
>> And that's great because
that means doubles and
ints can have functions on
them and things like that,
which we will see as the
quarter goes by.
But those things are all
passed by values.
So that's the first thing to
understand is that this ops,
when I call evaluate, whatever
array of ops I pass to it,
it's gonna be copied.
Okay?
The second thing to understand
here is that they're kind of
an implicit let in front of
all things you pass.
In other words, they're
read-only.
Make sense?
And a read-only array can't be
mutated.
I can't append things to it.
You can't remove things from
it cuz it's read-only.
Now, I can actually put the
word var here, okay?
If I, sorry.
If I put the word var here,
then ops inside here look no
error.
Ops is a mutable array.
It's still a copy though.
So they copied it, made it
mutable.
And now inside here, I have a
mutable copy to work with.
Now, I'm not a big fan of
doing that, 'kay?
Putting var up here.
I think it's a little
confusing for
readers of the code,
to understand exactly what's
going on there.
So, I'm not gonna do that,
instead, I'm gonna make a
local variable here, which I'm
gonna call remainingOps and
I'm gonna set it equal to ops.
Now, when you set equals like
this,
that copies it if it's not a
class.
Classes are all by reference.
It's exactly, what you would
think.
>> [COUGH].
>> But anything else,
strucks or enums or anything
else.
When you do equals here,
this is actually going to make
a copy of this, and
put it in here.
And since it's a var, it's
going to be mutable.
Okay?
So now I have a mutable array
of opts and
now I can say remainingOpts.
Remove the last one.
And now I truly do have the
remainingOpts.
I've removed the first thing
in there.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Did everyone understand that
little tidbit there?
Yeah?
>> So there's a,
like a, a unseen let in sort
of the opts?
>> Yeah.
>> Why isn't that like in
front of doubles and
like ends or straightened
>> It is.
So, the question is why is
there not a kind of unseen,
let in front of all arguments?
Pretty much all arguments to
functions kind of
have that unseen let in there.
They're all read on, 'kay?
So and you could put var in
front of any one and
turn it into a mutable copy of
it,
that you could use locally.
But if you only use it
locally,
it's not that great a thing.
Okay?
Now, there is a way to have,
to pass by value things back
out, but I'm not even gonna
talk about that.
Okay.
You can read about it.
It's this in out thing.
I'm not even gonna talk about
it.
I really think it's better to
stay within the value,
pass by value, pass by
reference parameters.
I think you can get more
readable code that way.
But there is a way, there is a
way I'm not going to talk
about to do in out basically,
prime numbers that go in out.
Yeah.
>> Is there any way to
[INAUDIBLE]
>> Yeah that's what I just
said.
There is a way to pass it kind
of by reference in out.
You know, you pass it in, you
modify it,
and then it'll come back out
when it's done at the end.
So, it's kind of like by
reference.
But the other thing you said
is,
oh this is terrible I'm making
three copies of
that dang thing, this must be
super slow.
And the answer is no.
Swift is super smart about not
actually copying it,
until you actually make a
change to it.
So here when it passes a copy
in it didn't really
copy it, it just kinda passed
a pointer in but it knows that
pointer is by, you know, not
by reference it's by value.
And then when I copied it
again here.
It still didn't really copy
it.
Even if this array had 10,000
things in it,
it didn't make 10,000 copy of
it.
It was only here where I
actually mutated,
now it had to make a copy.
And it may not even have made
an entire copy.
It might have just kept track
of the changes, for example.
So, it's super smart behind
the scenes.
Sweet to very smart.
So, don't worry too, about
much about oh,
I'm copying these things over
and over.
Swift is making the minimum
out of
actual copying going on.
Okay?
All right, so now I have
remainingOpts here,
which truly are my remaining
opts.
'Kay.
Because I've
removed the top one, the x,
off the top.
So now I've got all the
remainingOps,
in this local variable here
called remainingOps.
Okay.
Now, what am I gonna do with
this op that I pulled off,
this one on the top, x?
Well I'm gonna get the
associated value from
the enum.
'Kay.
Either this or these or this.
And how do I do that?
I use Switch.
'Kay, I told you that Switch
is really important.
And now you're seeing that
Switch is really important.
Switch is how you pull things
out,
associated values out of
enums.
So I'm just gonna switch on
the op.
'Kay, this is the op that I
pulled off the top,
that x from the thing we did
on the board.
And I'm just gonna look at the
cases, so
I have the case operand, okay.
Notice that it puts a little
dot here because it's
really Op.Operand and it's
using type inference to
know that it's Op.Operand,
right.
Op.op, Op.Operand but it
doesn't need the op there.
And here it's asking in this
space, what do you wanna do
with the associated value if
you're handling this case.
Where the enum is operand.
'Kay?
Well I want to let that
associated value
be assigned to a constant
called operand.
'Kay?
And yes I could put var here,
which would do the same thing,
except for I could then change
the thing in here.
But I almost never wanna do
this, almost always let.
So let operand means that
inside the handling of
this case, 'kay, this case of
the switch.
Inside here, operand is gonna
have the associated value of
the operand.
'Kay?
Oh, that's exactly what I
want.
I'm just gonna return right
now I have to return this
tuple right here.
So I'm gonna returned the
operand.
That's the result, 'kay.
When I go here and
I encounter that next one down
which was a four, I got a four
I can just return that result
to evaluate this one.
And I also though have to
return the remainingOps.
'Kay, so I'm just returning
the two values of this tuple,
notice I don't have to put
result colon and
remaining opt colon in here it
knows that those match and
so it's still doing it.
All right, makes sense.
That's it for operand that's
all I have to do.
It's kind of a, in the
recursion,
it's kind of an end case.
Yeah?
>> Is remainingOps part of
the stack or heap?
>> This one here, or this one
here?
>> What in general
[INAUDIBLE].
>> Okay so, so the question
is,
when I do something like this,
where is remainingOps?
Is it in the heap?
Is it on the stack?
And the thing is, that's
implementation detail.
So, you, you don't know, but
you don't care.
All right, so that's operand.
Operand was really, really
easy.
How about our operation,
that's you, you,
UnaryOperation right here.
Now when we handle the case of
the unary operation,
we don't need that first
associated value,
that's the symbol, like plus.
Okay well I'm evaluating here
I don't care what this
symbol is, I only care what
the function is cause I'm
gonna evaluate the function.
So we can actually ignore this
by putting in underbar, 'kay?
Underbar in swift is kind of
the universal I don't care
about this thing.
Okay and we're gonna see it
other places we use it
where it's kinda like, I don't
really care about that.
So you just put an underbar
there.
That way you don't have to
declare a variable with
some dumb name or something
like that.
Just put an underbar it
ignores it.
'Kay?
But I do care about this.
I'm gonna let that equal the
operation that I'm doing.
'Kay?
Everyone, make sense there?
So I'm ignoring the string,
but
I'm grabbing the operation.
So here, what I wanna do is
return and I'll try to do it,
but I'm not gonna be able to.
I'm gonna say, return this
operation with
its operand which I don't
have.
And there's some remaining ops
that are leftover after I
get the operand.
So I'm kinda, I need to do
some stuff here to
be able to return what I want.
The first thing I need to do
is get the operand.
'Kay?
So, I did a unary operation
let's say it was square root.
I need to go back to the staff
and
pick off the next thing but I
can't just
assume that it's a number it
might be more operations so
I have to recurse, so here's
where the recursion comes in.
And I'm gonna show you how to
call a function that
returns a tuple.
And get it's value up so this
is important little example
here, so there's two ways to
do it.
I'm gonna do it one way here,
which is,
I'm gonna let
operandEvaluation,
which is just a local variable
that I'm inventing, equal call
evaluate with the remainingOps
that I have.
'Kay, so here I've recursed.
Okay, I'm recursing.
And I just set it to
operandEvaluation.
Now, let's look at the type of
this thing.
If I look at its type, you can
see that it's a tuple.
That's its type.
It's a tuple result
remainingOps.
It's this tuple right here.
That is the type of this
operandEvaluation.
So now that I have that tuple,
it's the result of evaluation
how do I get the result and
the remaining op out of it
well I can get the operand by
saying operand eval, [UNKNOWN]
operandEvaluation.result.
'Kay?
So that just pull this is the
tuple here I'm
getting this value of the
tuple out of there.
Now what type is this?
Anybody?
It's an optional.
You're pretty safe saying
optional when I
ask what type it is, aren't
you?
It's almost always an
optional.
Cuz I usually don't ask if
it's not.
But it is indeed an optional,
an optional double.
It's this type right here,
okay?
So we need to turn it into a
double if we're gonna pass it
to this operation right here.
So I'm gonna use if let to
turn that into a double.
'Kay?
Now, I can actually do this
because I have the operand.
Just got it right here.
'Kay?
This is now a double, see?
And I can call this operation
right here.
And this is the remaining ops,
but this has got to
be the remaining ops after we
recursed.
So it's gotta be the remaining
ops in this operandEvaluation.
So that
operandEvaluation.remaining-
Ops.
Everybody cool with that?
So that's it.
It's just recurse, we just
recursed to evaluate that.
If this fails if, if this
recursion returned nil,
then this is, this, if let's
not gonna happen this
return's not gonna happen,
gonna fall all the way out and
return nill which is what we
want, 'kay.
We failed in any of our
recursive attempts to
get the operands we need,
we gotta fail all the way up
to the top level.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay now binary operation.
Also okay, let's do yeah,
binary here case.
Binary.
Obviously same exact thing
here.
We don't care about that.
And here we're gonna let
operation.
And we're gonna do the exactly
the same thing we did
here but we just have to do it
twice because we have two
operands to do here, through
here.
So let's let opp1Evaluation =
evaluate(remainingOps).
'Kay.
And then if we can let
operand1 =
op1Evaluation.result.
'Kay, then we got op1, that's
good.
So now let's let op2Evaluation
=
evaluation(op1Evaluation.rema-
iningOps).
'Kay?
And if we can let operand,
oops, if we can let operand2
= op2Evaluation.result, then
we can
return (operation(operand1,
operand2).
'Kay?
And
we'll have
op2Evaluation.remainingOps) as
our remaining ops.
Okay?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Make sense?
All right.
What's our.
We have an error here.
What is it?
okay.
Yeah,
this is a good error to cover
here.
See this it says method must
be declared private because
this parameter uses a private
value.
And sure enough op is private
so this has to be private.
'Kay?
Now notice by the way,
I don't have default: break
here in this switch.
And why do I not have that?
Because I've handled every
possible value of op.
'Kay?
There are only
three kinds of op.
I've handled them all.
So I don't need any default.
It wasn't like in the other
one where we had a string and
we only handle a few strings,
we had a default break.
You don't put default break in
when you handle every thing.
And it's really bad programing
style to
put a default break in every
single switch.
'Kay, you should only put them
in on the ones where you
truly are breaking because you
can't handle every case.
'Kay?
All right.
Now, the last thing we have to
do is just call this recursive
version from here.
And I'm gonna call this one
and
get these tuple values a
little differently.
I'm not gonna call it in the
same way here.
I'm not gonna say, let
something equal.
Instead I'm gonna say let a
tuple which has let's call it
say (result, remainder) =
evaluate and
I'm gonna pass my whole
(opStack) here, okay.
So this is a different way to
call a function that returns
a tuple here you actually let
a tuple equal the result.
Instead of letting a single
thing equal result and
then using the dots to get it,
you let the tuple equal it and
notice that these names don't
have to be the same as these
names so result is the same,
but here I
use the word remainder instead
of the word remainingOps.
Okay they do not have to be
the same.
And then here we just return
our result.
Okay?
So we learned a lot right
there, okay.
We learned about tuple,
passing you know things back
tuples in
different ways you know how to
ignore things in enums and
when we're getting associate
values all that stuff.
So hopefully, you got all
that.
I see a few people still kinda
catching up on their typing.
So I'll break for second here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] So that's it that's
the entire implementation of
our calculator brain.
It wasn't really that bad
actually, right?
Pretty simple little data
structure here.
Just have to say what our
known ops are.
And have this recursion which
you know,
actually is quite simple,
powerful code.
If you're not comfortable with
your recursion I
can see how it might be a
little bit disturbing.
But go stare at it for
awhile and you'll, you'll get
it, how it works.
Okay.
So, now that we've got this
new calculator brain,
we have to use it in our old
controller.
Okay, yeah question?
>> Do we have to let like the
op stack equal the remainder?
>> Do we have to let the op
stack equal the remainder?
Here, you mean?
>> Yeah.
>> well, we're not gonna use
remainder, so
actually, even I could put I
don't care here.
I only put that remainder
there to show you could have
a different name, but I'm not
using the remainder.
I only want the result.
You see.
>> Won't the op stack contain
what was previously in it
before you evaluate it?
>> Yes, the op stack will be
unaffected by this because op
stack is an array.
Arrays are passed by value so
a copy of it gets passed into
here.
So this would be untouched and
which is what I want.
I don't want evaluate to
consume my op stack.
I wanna be able to call
evaluate over and
over and over.
'Kay?
Especially if,
I let's say introduced
variable operands and
that's what you're homeworks
gonna be, then I wouldn't
want to change the variables
to different things and
be calling it over and
over with different values for
the variable for example and
then maybe next week I can
have an assignment where I'm
gonna make your graph such a
thing, which I'm going to do.
Okay?
So that's why I wanna do that.
So anyway, yeah, remainder
here can just be anything.
I'm actually gonna put this
here because we're
gonna print one this in a
second just so
we can get a better look at
what's going on.
But first, let's go back to
our controller and use this
calculator brain, this nice
model we just invented.
Let's use it.
Now,
I'm gonna show you how to get
two things on screen at
the same time.
That aren't necessarily
directly related.
Before we have the story board
and then I went up and
clicked this system editor
right here and
it showed me the controller.
Because the system editor
figured out that, oh,
if you have the story board up
you probably want
the controller for the scene
you have selected.
But here it's like, I don't
know what to show you.
So I'm gonna show you a
different way to
get something in here, two
ways actually.
One is if you go to this top
bar where
it says counterparts, you can
mouse down and
you can find all kinds of
things about this
like subclasses of this class
on the left.
Superclasses of this [UNKNOWN]
class on the left.
Of course it has no
superclasses or subclasses.
But other things, things it
includes are included by it.
You can also just manually go
in.
We can go over here for
example and
find our view controller and
load it up that way, but
I'm gonna show you a different
way than doing that
which is to go over here to
your navigator.
If you hold down Option and
press on
a file like ViewController it
will appear on the right.
'Kay?
So Option clicking in here is
another good way to
put things on the right.
Okay?
So now here we have our
calculator brain on the left
and we have our controller on
the right,
we are going to rip out all of
the stuff in our
controller that had to do with
being calculator.
Okay, so that's all this stuff
right in here.
'Kay.
All this calculating stuff, we
don't need any of this
because those were only called
from there.
'Kay, so our controller's
getting quite simple,
our controller hardly has
anything left in it.
And that's because the UI only
needs this to be controlled.
'Kay?
We also don't need our operand
stack because the brain is
gonna do that.
However, we do need a new
instance variable here
which is the calculator brain.
Okay I'm just gonna create one
like that,
this is extremely common okay
this is
the green arrow that goes from
the controller to the model.
Remember that in our MVC talk
that I did last time I
said that the controller has a
green arrow to the model,
it can talk to it all at once,
say anything it wants.
This is essentially that green
arrow.
This is our model right here.
And this is the controller
this is how the controller
talks to it through this thing
we call the brain.
Thing you can call it anything
you want and
of course this might be much
more complicated green arrow,
it might be a network database
that is connecting to you to
get the data.
Okay?
But in our case it's this very
simple little brain.
Okay.
So now we don't need this
either down here.
This is where we're appending
onto the op stack and
printing it out.
So we don't need that.
But we do need an enter to
push the operand onto
the stack.
Okay.
So here I'm just gonna say,
that I'm gonna say I'm just
gonna
say brain.pushOperand(display)
value.
'Kay?
That's the main thing I need
to do, is just do that.
One thing though is, I also
need to update my display.
Because when I push this
operand,
that's gonna change the brain.
I need to call that evaluate,
right?
And get the value.
So I could call evaluate here,
but
actually, I'm gonna go back to
my brain, and I'm gonna change
pushOperand to return the va,
the result of evaluating.
Typing today.
From it, from its, from
internally, so
I'm gonna return evaluate
here.
So that every time you push an
operand,
it'll just return the
evaluation.
Now one could argue whether
this is the best thing to do.
Because, you know, you might
not be interested in
the result of evaluating that
right now.
But it kind of feels to me
kind of good.
And it's not gonna be,
there's not gonna be that many
things on the stack.
You're not gonna usually have
calculator brain
have 1,000 operations and
operands, although you could.
But you're not usually going
to so
it's probably not a
performance issue.
To have it just return this
and it'll make caller's code,
you know, look a little
simpler.
And if they don't want this
return value,
then they can just ignore it.
They don't have to use it but
I am gonna use it.
So, when I push this operand
right here,
I'm gonna say, I'm gonna if
let the results equal that.
Okay, because it's an
optional.
And if it's not nil then I'm
gonna
set the display value to the
result.
So in other words, every time
I push an operand,
I'm gonna up my display value
with the evaluation.
Make sense?
Okay, what if this comes back
nil?
So, I push something on,
this is not gonna happen
probably with Push Operand,
but it might, and after your
homework it might.
So, what if I push and it
comes back nil?
Well, now I'm kinda stuck,
okay?
This is why, in your homework
assignment, I suggested, wow
wouldn't it be cool if display
value took an optional.
Right, if display value took
and returned an optional.
You could put something
sensible in the display when
you had something that
couldn't be evaluated.
So in assignment two making
display value into
an optional is gonna be
required task.
So you might as well do it for
homework one,
cuz you're gonna have to do it
for homework two anyway.
Okay.
Just wanted to give you more
time because I didn't
really teach you the things
about NumberFormatter and
stuff in time for assignment
one.
But it's going to be required
and that's because the best I
can do here is maybe say
display value equals zero.
That's really lame but that's
the best I can do.
I really wanna say, display
value was nil, okay.
I really just wanna set
display value equal to
the result of this.
And I wanna have nil, you
know, clear out my display or
in assignment two,
extra credit, maybe it puts an
error message in my display.
Now that's extra credit, but
that would be an even better
thing to put there.
Okay?
But same thing for, for
forming the operation.
Here's our operation right
here.
And I'm just gonna say,
if I can let the result equal
brains perform operation of
the operation that I got off
the button, then I'm going to
let my display value equal
that result.
Otherwise I'm going to do the
very lame thing of
saying display value equals,
whoops, value equals zero.
Okay?
Unders,
people understand why that's
kind of lame?
All right.
Okay.
So that's it.
Look at how simple our
controller is here.
It has almost no code in it,
okay.
And that's really iOS is great
about that.
It really is pretty good about
making it so
that you can build your UI
mostly graphically so
that there's very little code
to control what's going on.
And then even our model,
which is a pretty powerful
calculator right now,
we could add as many functions
as we wanted to.
It's just one liners here.
And it would be capable of,
you know, evaluating any se,
series of them that's
evaluatable.
And it's also set up to do
your homework, okay,
which is to add those
variables,
to be able to push operands
that are variables.
The other thing your homework
is gonna ask you to do is to
eval, to draw this, okay,
the contents of it in a human
readable form.
Using infix notation like this
with parentheses when
necessary, things like that
and
that's gonna be a lot easier
here too.
Cuz you can recur,
use recursion, use recursion
to build this as well.
Okay, so that's the main two
things of
your homework that's what they
are.
All right, so let's see if we
broke anything here all right,
so we're gonna go up here and
run.
See if this all still works.
Our UI has not changed.
You notice I never even opened
the storyboard here.
Didn't even open the
storyboard.
Okay all these changes were
pushing things out of
the controller into the model.
Okay?
The co,
communication between the
controller and
the view has not changed here.
So hopefully this is gonna
work let's try 85, and
our number entering is still
working in
our controller that's good,
Enter.
Okay it still says 85 that's
good,
how about 41 plus seems to
actually be working.
Square root,
that's also working, nine
times, excellent.
That's working.
Now what if we do something
that's not evaluatable?
I'm going to press times a
whole bunch of times.
Right?
Times, times.
Oh, times no, zero.
See that's not really great
feedback.
Okay?
But, it's not really zero but
it's, it's not good either.
So your homework is going to
be printing out what's on
the stack in a nice form so
you'll be able to see that you
have times, times,
times, and it's gonna equal a
blank display.
And that's gonna make sense
that it's blank.
'Kay?
All right.
Now, I wanna do one other
thing here, though, just so
you can really visualize
what's going on,
which is, I wanna print out,
when we evaluate, I wanna
print out this stack.
I wanna print out the thing
we're evaluating,
I wanna print out the result,
and I even wanna print out
the remainder here so we can
see what's going on.
So, I wanna say print ln.
And I'm gonna say I'm gonna
use my backslash thing here.
Op stack equals result with
how did I say this?
With [NOISE], oh, yeah.
With our remainder left over.
Okay.
So wouldn't it be cool if I
could just do this.
Just say, okay, the op stack
evaluated equals this
result with the remainder left
over.
Okay?
Let's run that.
Do you think that's going to
work?
Maybe.
Let's see.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay.
So let's try putting eight on
the stack.
Okay?
Let's make so we can see this
over here, where is it,
it's this probably right
there, there it is.
We don't need that one okay,
so
here is our okay it's gonna be
that, it's this.
Okay, so it said here hm, enum
value in, in an array, equals
result of optional 8, that's
good, optional 8 is good.
With nothing left over.
Okay, that's good.
Let's go 6, Enter.
Oh, now we have enum enum on
the stack equals optional 6,
with enum left over.
Well that's not so good.
Times enum, enum, enum equals
it with, this is terrible.
This is, I can't understand
what the heck is
going on here.
Why is this happening?
Okay, when you put something
in parentheses like this,
it tries to convert it to a
string.
Okay, well the thing that's in
here is an array.
Arrays know how to convert
themselves to strings.
What they do is, they put open
square bracket.
Then they ask every single
thing in the array,
convert yourself to a string
'kay, and it puts them here.
Well our op is converting
itself to this string.
Enum value 'kay?
That's because the system
doesn't really know how to
convert it any other way so
it's just saying that's an
enum value.
It doesn't know how to convert
itself to a string.
So, you see, see what's going
on here?
So, I'm going to show you how
to teach a type to
turn itself into a string.
Okay, cuz that's really
valuable for debugging and
also might be valuable for
your homework.
So, how we gonna do that?
All right, the way you do that
is,
you have to add a computed
property to your type.
And enums, just like structs
and
classes, can have properties,
okay?
Only computer properties in
enums, structs and
classes can have properties
that are values.
Like these, like this over
here, all right.
But they can only be computed.
You remember a computer
property looks like this, var.
The name of it.
It has to be called
description because
it's gonna be a string
description of it.
The type has to be string.
It's a string description of
it.
And then of course you want
your get here.
And, whoops, your get and your
set set.
But it has to not only be a
computer property.
This description thing to make
this work.
It wants to be a read only
one.
So we're not going to put the
set,
so there will be no set, just
a get.
So this get just has to return
this op as a string, so
I say someone turned it into a
string.
Well how would we turn our op
into a string.
Well for the operations we're
just gonna return the symbol.
Okay if this is a plus
operation turning into
string is I'm just gonna
return a plus,
cuz that pretty well describes
a plus operation, a plus.
For the operand,
I'm gonna have to turn this
double into a string.
And return that.
Okay so how am I gonna do
that?
I'm gonna do that using
switch,
I need to switch on myself.
Okay cuz I'm gonna do this
switch so that I can get these
same things out here, and you
do the same thing I did here,
see how I did this switch.
So I could get these
associated values out.
I'm gonna do the same thing
here.
So how do I switch on my self?
I say switch self.
'Kay?
And then I just have to say
the case for operand.
And I'll let that be the
operand.
And I have to do the case for
unary operation.
Now when I do the case for
unary operation, I want the
symbol.
But I don't care about the
function.
Cuz I'm not actually gonna
compute anything.
I'm just going to return the
symbol.
And then for binary options
same,
same thing I want the symbol
but I don't want this.
So that's the, the don't care.
And what am I gonna do in each
of these cases?
Well in the operands case I'm
gonna return a string that
is that operand.
Oops, don't like the way it
puts that extra thing
on there.
Okay.
And then in the unary
operation case I'm
just gonna return the symbol.
And in the binary operation
case I'm also just
gonna return the symbol.
And we have, oops, don't want
the parentheses there.
Kay and we've covered every
case of this switch.
So not only does it know that
this switch is covered but
it knows that we for sure have
returned something out of
here, because we only have one
expression here which is
this Swift and switch and we
know that covers every case.
So there goes so we have this
nice description.
Now this is not quite enough
'kay?
You have to implement this
property,
this computer property
read-only.
But if you do one other thing,
which is up here, you have to
put, colon printable.
Now, I told you enums and
structs have no inheritance.
So you're like what, wait a
second, there.
You're telling me op inherits
from printable?
And the answer is no, does not
inherit, okay, it's an enum.
Enums don't have any
inheritance, only classes do.
What this colon printable
means is, and
this can be true for classes
or structs or whatever.
You can put after the colon
here.
This is called a protocol.
And all this means is you're
telling Swift that this
enum implements whatever is in
this protocol.
And this protocol happens to
just be one computer
property called Description
that returns the string.
Okay?
Now we're going to talk about
protocols in depth.
Because protocols are very
important for
explaining how things work
'kay?
But we're not gonna cover it
today, though.
Okay, so if you do those two
things, put description in
printable, now when we run,
you'll see, I'll go 5 enter.
Six, and you see it's put a
five in there.
There's a 6.
Times, it's even putting the
times.
If I hit times again, now I
get nil and
i tshows me the whole thing is
leftover, okay.
Let's go another thing here,
what if I go 6 Enter 5 Enter 4
Enter.
Now if I do times it says
times of 4 and
5 is 20 with the 6 left over,
exactly right.
Kay now notice I had to rerun
there to do that,
you're gonna have a clear
button right,
that you do in assignment one,
you're gonna have to
make that work in assignment
two as well.
Okay the last thing really out
of time but I'm gonna show you
the last thing really quickly
that I was gonna do is use
this description to fix this
problem I said right here.
Which is what if I had a
function called learn
op 'kay and it took an op as
an argument here.
And it just said known ops ops
description equals that op.
You see, now these could all
just be learn op this.
Okay which is a lot nicer, I
only have to type this thing
once, and I just use the
description here.
The other thing about this,
notice where this function is.
Inside the init.
Okay you are allowed to
put functions inside other
functions.
If this is only called inside
here, you can put it in here.
If if I put it outside in fact
I'd have a little a problem,
because it would have to be
private.
Because it uses op, and that's
what this error right here is.
All right I'd have say private
func, but I don't want to do
private func, instead I'm just
gonna put this right down
here, okay and obviously I
would do that one last.
Okay that's it, hope you
learned a lot and
stuff elsewhere for that and I
will see you on Wednesday,
I'm here if you have
questions.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.