[SOUND] Stanford University.
>> Okay.
Welcome to Lecture 10 of Stanford CS193P.
This is Winter 2015.
Today, we really only have one big topic.
And I've got one little small topic
that I'm gonna talk about.
At the beginning which is text field.
But the main topic today is going to be table view, okay?
And so, table view is a really powerful object is iOS, and
it uses a lot of the things you've learned already like
delegation.
And you'll get a chance to see how,
once you kind of have the basic concept,
you can build this powerful user interface features.
But let's take a minute or two to talk about text field,
because I actually used a text field in the last demo.
Okay. A text field,
it's kind of like UI label, but it's editable.
Text fields are not a big deal on the iPhone because
you want to try and build your UIs to not use them,
because that keyboard is so small on a phone.
On an iPad, a little more useful to have TextField,
but even there users would rather just be click,
touching on things and
things without having to, you know, hit that keyboard.
And when you're building a UI and you pull, put a TextField,
it'll seem like oh, this is great.
That's because in the simulator you can use your
keyboard on your computer.
And it seems like, wow I really like this UI.
But then when your users get it,
they're like, I hate this UI.
Okay?
So, be careful with UITextField.
But there's sometimes when you just absolutely
need an arbitrary string from the user and so you need it.
Now, the keyboard,
that little software keyboard appears whenever your
text field becomes what's called the first responder.
When a text field becomes a first responder,
the keyboard will slide up from the bottom.
Okay.
You can make the keyboard appear, and
cause the little blinking carrot to start by sending
become first responder.
That message, to a text field.
Or if you wanted to make the keyboard go away,
you can do that by saying resign first responder.
So it's that first responder thing.
That's what decides whether they keyboard's up, and
whether the blinking caret is there.
Okay, very easy.
The text field, unlike UI label,
does most of its communication with the UI via delegation.
That's why I don't really
teach it to you until you've already learned delegation.
One of the most important text field delegate methods is text
field should return.
And that happens when someone on the little keyboard presses
the Return key,
which sometimes says search, sometimes it says go.
Sometimes it says return.
Just depends on what kind of keyboard you have configured.
And a lot of times in that should return, you are going
to resign first responder, because the users hit Return,
they want you to take the text they type in and
do something with it.
You can make the keyboard go away.
This does return a Boole.
Actually, I didn't really show that on the slide there, but
it does return a boule.
And that boule is whether it should do what it normally
does when the user hits return,
which is usually going to be to do target action.
Because UI text field is a UI control, so
it can also be set up to do target action.
But usually, we get involved with the delegate because we
want this resign first responder activity going on.
So you can find out that the editing has ended.
Either by the person who didn't return,
by the text field did end editing delegate method, or
you can also just set up target action Ctrl+drag to
have it in action when it ends.
The keyboard, so the keyboard,
you'd think that there would be a class like UIKeyboard or
something and to do things with, but really not.
The keyboard appears because as a side of effect of
a protocol called the UI text input traits protocol so
objects like UA text field that implement this,
they get to configure the keyboard.
What type it is,
what auto-capitalization it's doing.
You know, whether it's secure text we saw.
We use secure text entry when we did the demo before.
So all these actually are not methods that are on text field
natively.
They're actually because text field is implementing this UI
text input traits.
And that's how you configure the keyboard.
All right?
And of course, text field implements that, and
the other object it implements is UITextView, which is a very
powerful text editing object, multi-line, multi-font, etc.
The keyboard, when it comes up from the bottom,
it comes up on top of other views, okay?
So you are responsible, when that keyboard comes up,
for moving anything out of the way that needs to still be
visible.
Especially if, for
example, the text field the user clicked on that caused
the keyboard to happen is at the bottom of the screen.
It will just get covered right up, so now the user's like,
whoa, where's that thing that I was typing in?
So you're responsible for moving that.
A lot of times, you're gonna put your text fields at
the top so that you don't have that problem.
Or your text field might be in a static table view.
I'm gonna talk about table views today.
In which case,
TableView will automatically scroll it up out of the way.
You don't have to worry about it.
But, if you have a UI,
where you have a text field down at the bottom, and
the keyboard comes up, and you have to move it,
you're gonna have to learn how to do this NSNotification
business.
Because the way to find out that
the keyboard appeared is you get this notification
called the UIKeyboardDidShowNotification.
So, not really gonna go into notifications today.
You're not gonna have to do any of this for
any of your homework assignments but
when you get to your final project just know that this is
how you're gonna have to deal with the keyboard.
If you have a text field or some text
typeable thing down towards the bottom of the screen.
Okay?
Other properties on text field I'm not gonna go into but
we'll see a couple of them in the demo today cuz I'm gonna
do text field again.
But you can look them up in the documentation.
Obviously just things to configure the way
the text field inputs or displays.
Text fields also have left and right overlays for
little things like search.
You've probably seen text fields that have a little icon
for search that you can click on there.
Or like a little icon that says whether you're doing find
or find and replace or something like that.
That's all in there too.
So it's pretty powerful.
The little control.
The keyboard, it gets enhanced by this inputAccessoryView.
So that's, again, a method in the UITextfield.
And you set a view, the UIView.
And when the keyboard comes up,
that UIview will appear along the top of the keyboard.
So you can add extra buttons there or
any kind of mechanism.
So that's how you enhance the keyboard.
All right, so that's enough text field.
Again, I'm going to be using the demo today, so
you'll see a little bit more.
But today mostly we're going to talk about UITableView.
So, UITableView is very important class for
displaying data.
Especially when you have a large amount of data
to display.
It's essentially a one dimensional table.
A list if you want to think of it that way, some people think
it maybe should have been called List View,
but you'll see that Table View ends up being
a pretty good name for it.
But it's a one dimensional list,
it's a subclass of UIScrollView, so
it has all the things that scrolling can do of course.
And it's very efficient with large sets of data.
So you can imagine having a list of all the songs in
the iPod part of your phone showing in an app,
even if you have tens of thousands of them, okay?
TableView knows how to be efficient with that.
Now, what about multi-dimensional tables,
tables that have rows and columns?
Well we usually do that with multiple table views inside
a navigation controller.
So you'll pick something from column one and it's going
to show you column two that matches column one and
you pick something there, and it's going push over,
show you the next one.
So that's basically how you get through,
how you build multi-dimension tables which.
Kind of have to do it that way on a small device like
a phone, unless the fonts going to be really tiny
because you can't build a big actual two-dimensional table.
So, the combination of table view and
UINavigation Controller is pretty cool for
building multi-dimensional tables.
Now, there's different kinds of table views and
I'm going to show you pictures of them.
You want to configure the table view to display in a way
that matches your data.
So let's take a look at some of these different
kind of looks.
One is a plain style.
You can see that one on the left.
And the other one is a group style.
Now a group style you can actually see that the little
rows are kind of grouped so like in miles,
in kilometers is grouped into the distance as a group.
And then driving and walking is grouped into the preferred
directions group there.
Whereas the plain style is just a big long list.
That can be divided into sections as well, but
it's mostly just a big long list.
Usually the plain style is for
dynamic data, like all the songs coming out of your iPod.
The group style is more for fixed data like
the settings app, you know, in your iPhone the setting app.
If you look in there,
a lot of table views in there, all with the group style,
and what's in there is kind of fixed, more static.
So let me talk about some of the words we used to describe
the parts of a table view.
This part at the top of the table view is called the table
header, it's a UIView.
I'm going to put along the bottom here,
is just going to be the code.
Like the name of the property or
the function that accesses this thing.
But you obviously don't know any of that yet.
So this is morely for
reference when you're looking back at the slides later.
So there's the table header,
it's at the top of the entire table, it's a UIView.
You can put things in there like a text field if
you wanted to add searching to your table, things like that,
we'll do that in the demo.
There's also a corresponding table footer, at the bottom,
that's also UIView.
It's at the very bottom of the table.
If you had 10,000 iPod items it'd be way down at
the very bottom,
you'd have to scroll all the way to 10,000 to get to that.
Then, all the information is divided into up into
sections, okay.
So you can have any number of sections in the table view.
And each section has a header,
a section header like that, okay.
And of course, each section also has a section footer.
The section footer and
the section header are usually just strings but there's also
a way to make them be UIViews as well, if you really wanted
complicated headers and footers.
And then you have what are called the table cells,
so that's the actual data.
This would be the actual songs in your iPod would be shown
here in each row.
And these table cells are highly configurable to show
all kinds of information for
each piece of data in your table.
Okay, so that's basically the terminology we use.
So that's what it all looks like in plain style.
We use the exact same terminology in group style, so
it looks like this, okay.
See the section headers are kind of the names of
the groups.
All right, here's what a table looks like,
I hope that shows up.
It look a little washed out,
but the version on the right there has sections.
You can see, like above the word Tokyo,
there's a little word there, says Japan.
And above Amsterdam, there's a little Netherlands there.
Those are the section headers.
Those are the names of the sections.
And the one on the left has no section title, so
all the things are all just listed not grouped, okay.
Now each cell can have one of five different types, okay.
Here's four of them right here.
So you got the Subtitle type,
which just has some big texts and little text underneath it.
You got Basic, which has no little text underneath it.
You've got the Right Detail and the Left Detail,
which is the big text and the little text,
just kind of arranged a little differently, okay.
So the type of cell that you choose determines how
the big text and the little text are going to appear.
There's a fifth kind of cell type, though, which is custom.
Which allows you to build whatever you want by dragging
in UI labels and UI text fields and image views,
whatever you want to do to build your own custom cell.
And that's what we're going to do in the demo today.
Okay, so that's the cell type.
All right, so how does this whole table view
business work?
There is a class in iOS called UITableViewController,
it's a subclass of UIViewController.
And it is kind of a prepackaged way to
use table view that I highly recommend you use if it's at
all possible in your UI.
The only real limitation of UITableViewController is that
the entire view of the MVC, has to be a tableView.
So if you had some view where you had a tableView and
then some other stuff around it, you would not
be using UITableViewController for that.
You'd build your own viewController, and you'd just
drag in a UITableView, which is just a UIView, okay.
You can add a UITableViewController to your
app just by dragging it out of the object palette there.
You can see a TableViewController and
it'll pull the whole MVC out, okay, a UITable, MVC.
So, here's UITable UMVC that I've dragged out.
It's controller is usually a subclass of
UITableViewController, and its view is the tableView, okay.
Ultra simple little MVC here.
But like any UIView controller you're probably going to want
to set the class of the controller to be some subclass
of UITableViewController.
So when you do new file to create your subclass make sure
that you pick subclass of UITableViewController,
if that's the kind of view controller you're making
there, okay.
And then once you do it,
same thing as any other view controller,
you set the class in the identity inspector, okay.
Everyone cool with that?
Now, the way that we're going to kind of connect
our code to the UITableView
is via two delegates that the UITableView has.
One's called delegate and one's called data source.
Okay, and I'm going to talk all about those later in this
presentation.
But just know that when you drag out one of
these UITableViewController's,
it's going to automatically wire up the controller itself,
as both the delegate and the dataSource.
And in fact,
if you right clicked on the TableViewController there and
you looked at it's connections,
you'll see dataSource and
delegate will be connected there to the TableView, okay.
Now, if you don't use a UITableViewController,
you just use your own ViewController and
you drag out a UITableView,
you will have to wire up the dataSource and
delegate yourself.
Again, usually to your controller, but
you could wire up something else but 99% of the time you
make your controller be the delegate in dataSource for
things in the view, just like you did in your calculator.
Okay, so you can also edit the attributes of the table view
if you just click on the table view, now,
when you're clicking on things in a table view sometimes you
want the cell, sometimes you want the table view,
sometimes you want the controller.
So you want to remember that trick I was telling you about,
Ctrl + shift and left-click will let you pick something
under the mouse, multi-layers deep, okay.
I'll show you again in the demo.
But you want to remember that trick when you're working
with table views.
So, if you click on the table view, not the cells,
not the controller, but
the actual table view, then you can obviously inspect it.
And so, you can look in there and
see all the various things that you can inspect
about the table view.
One thing that's important to set about the table view
is whether it's plain or grouped.
Okay, so this one that you're seeing is plain.
Here I'm going to switch it over to be grouped.
Now it's grouped,
you can see in the storyboard it will look grouped,
all right.
Another really important thing you can set about the table
view is whether the cells in it are static, or dynamic.
So let's talk about static first.
So here I'm going to switch to static.
Static means that these cells in here are determined in
the story board.
So you can drag in buttons, and labels,
whatever you want in there.
Just like, almost like it's just an open area view.
You can just drag them in there,
the table will help group them for you.
But you can then set outlets to your controller from them.
It's really almost just like it's partitioning the space
for you, okay?
So that's the static table view.
And so whatever cells you see here in story board,
that's what you're going to see in your UI,
no more cells than that because it's static.
Okay?
So it's almost just a way of grouping things.
So again, this is like the settings app.
In the settings app,
pretty much it's always the same thing in the UI,
that's not, you know dynamic.
It can be that some settings let you set.
Does things for different apps.
And so maybe the list of apps can grow.
So that may be a combination of the things going
on in there.
But usually static table view is static.
Okay?
Now, the other side is dynamic table view.
Now in a dynamic table view, these cells that you see.
Oh by the way, we almost always use dynamic in plane.
In the plain style.
These rows that you see are not, what you build in
the storyboard is not what's gonna appear in that one row.
You're actually building a template or a prototype.
And if it needs 10,000 rows to show your iPod things,
it's gonna make that row 10,000 times.
Okay?
You see what I mean by you making a template out of it.
You're making a prototype that's gonna be
replicated, okay?
So that's a very big difference there,
between static and these prototypes, the dynamic mode.
In either case, the cells themselves can be selected.
You click on those.
And you can see that cell's selected.
You can barely tell because it only has the small little
square there.
Resizing square that chose this selected.
But when you select the cell, you can choose its type.
Like here I'll change this cell to be subtitle type.
So now it's that subtitle style.
Okay?
You can also change the little symbol that appears on
the right side of the row.
Here's a very special one called
the Detail Disclosure symbol.
Okay? There's also,
you can put check marks over there and other things.
We'll talk about Detail Disclosure a little bit later
because it's one that, if you click on, it can actually do
a different thing than if you click on the rest of the row.
So it's kind of, add a little ancillary UI to that row.
So I'm gonna go back to non detail disclosure there.
Now we talked about the cell style, subtitle,
and all those.
But let's talk about this custom style.
What if I wanna build a custom prototype that's gonna be
replicated for my entire table view?
And you select the style to be custom.
See up there in the upper right?
And now it can just resize this cell to whatever size I
want and I can go grab, you know, I don't know,
a label let's say and pull it out, drop it in there.
You definitely want to use auto layout here because I'm
gonna talk about how you can make the height of the cell
adjust to whatever content is in there, but if you don't
set up the outer layout constraints, it's not gonna
know what it can squish down and what it can't, et cetera.
So you drag it out there and,
now you have the UI that you want.
And you can have multiple labels,
whatever you want in here.
Text fields.
Anything you can put in your view you can put here.
But when it comes to wiring up the outlets,
you can see that I can't wire up an outlet or action
to my controller, because I might have 10,000 cells.
Okay, so the way that that works is you actually create
a custom subclass of this cell.
So this cell is a UI table of U cell.
UI table of U cell is just a special subclass of UI view.
Okay, that's what the cell is, and so if you want to have
outlets and actions per cell, you're going to create
a custom sub class of this UI table view cell and
that's where the outlets and actions are going to be.
Okay and then for every row that's visible,
you're gonna have this UI.
Table view cell and you'll be able to get actions
from buttons in there, or have outlets to set things.
So, you do that with the identity inspector just like
you set the class of something else, right?
I select a cell and I go over to identity sector.
I need to create a UITableView cell subclass.
So I go to new file, and here I want the subclass
of to say UITableView cell, not UITableView controller.
Okay so I create a subclass of UITableViewCell.
I set it at in the identity inspector to be my table view
cell and now I can wire up these outlets and
actions in here two outlets and
actions in my custom subclass of UITableViewCell.
Okay.
And so I just bring them up side by side and
assistant editor just control drag over to them.
Sometimes it's a bit of a pain to get the table of U cells
subclass in the right-hand side of the assistant editor.
Automatic, seems like it eventually figures it out and
starts working.
But a lot of times it won't.
So you have to do manual to get that cell on the right.
This is where you bring up your.
Subclass code.
Then you can just control drag to create,
for example here, an outlet to this label.
And again, remember that you're doing this for
a prototype here, these are dynamic.
And so this whole thing,
it's going to be replicated over and over for every row.
Okay? Each row is
going to have it's own UI table U cell instance.
And thus its own outlets.
And when it sends an action,
it's gonna send an action just to its instance.'
Okay, now you might be freaking out a little bit
about that, thinking well I've got this UITableViewCell,
it's a UIView, what if I have 10,000 of them?
That's gonna be a problem.
But we're gonna talk about how that's
not a problem in the UITableView in a minute here.
So how do we hook up to this stuff in code?
How do we load those cells up?
How do we tell it how many iPod songs I've got?
And you do all that with this data source and
delegates, okay?
The data source is the one that's responsible for
the data.
In other words, what's in the cells.
And the delegate is really responsible for
how it's all displayed,
the configuration of the table, et cetera.
UITableViewController also, as I said,
it sets itself as the data source and delegate.
It also has a property called TableView,
which is the table view inside itself.
So you can, at any time inside your controller
get at the TableView with tis TableView thing.
Okay? [COUGH] All right, so what do
we need to do in implementing this data source protocol?
Well this data source protocol you're gonna implement
any time the table is dynamic, okay?
And there's three really important questions that
are answered by this protocol.
One is, how many sections are in the table?
The next is, how many rows are in a given section?
And the third thing is, give me a UITableViewCell, or
subclass thereof, to display this row.
Okay those are the three main things.
There's other things in the data sort of protocol but
these are the three main ones, It makes sense, right?
That we're trying to load up our table.
Data sources providing the data
that's the way it does it.
So, the first two are exactly what you would think, so
those are easy, so let's talk about how do I give
the table view a UITableViewCell to draw.
A given row.
And you do that with this method.
I was telling before, 10,000 rows, don't worry.
The UITableViewCells, the reason 10,000 is going to work
is because we're only going to create UITableViewCells for
the visible rows.
If I've 10,000 iPod songs, I can only see seven or
eight of them on screen at a time,
I'm only gonna have seven UITableViewCell instances.
But what that means is they're getting reused.
As you scroll down, they're getting, the ones that
are scrolling off the screen are getting put into a reuse
cue basically.
And when a new one comes on screen, it reuses it.
Okay?
It either eases it or creates a new one by copying that
prototype in your storyboard, okay?
But it's not gonna make 10,000.
It's only gonna make enough for the visible rows.
Now that has ramifications for multi-threadedness.
Because if you have a row, and it appears, and
you need to go fetch something on the network to draw it,
and you start to fetch, and then the user scrolls away,
when that fetch comes back, that you're no longer,
that row no longer wants that thing, cuz that row is gonna
be reused to display something else, understand?
So be careful with multi-threadedness
in TableViews because those rows, the UITableViewCells,
are being constantly reused.
All right, so
here is the method that the UITableView is going to send,
it's UITableViewDataSource implementing protocol object,
which is gonna be your controller,
to say give me UITableViewCell.
It's called TableViewCell for row at index path, okay?
And you can see it returned to UI table use cell.
Obviously, it could return a custom subclass thereof.
And the argument there, index path, and
in this index path, it's just a simple little container
that contains the section and
row that it wants the table view cell for, 'kay?
So you're gonna use that information like this.
You have some internal data structure that's arranged
by the sections and rows, 'kay.
I don't know what it looks like, but you're just going to
get the data for this row by accessing that internal data
structure, might not be as simple as this,
this is like an array of arrays, sections and rows
although the demo I'm gonna do is gonna do it that way, but
it could be anything that lets you get your data.
Once you have your data, then you're going to get a cell,
a UITableViewCell or subclass there of and you're gonna load
it up with that data and it's gonna display, make sense?
So let's talk about how you get that cell.
'Kay how am I get that cell that I wanna load up with my
data at that indexPath.row.
So to do this I'm gonna bring the UI back but
I'm gonna keep this code there too.
Okay, so let's have both the code and the UI on screen
at the same time here so you can see what's going on.
So, the way I get a cell
is I'm gonna call this function in table view, called
dequeueReusableCellWithIdenti- fier, 'kay?
Now, this is going to reuse the cell if possible, or
if not, it's gonna create one by using your prototype
in the storyboard.
Now you tell it which prototype to use, because your
table view can actually have multiple prototypes.
So you tell it by using the argument there,
the first argument the identifier, which you also
need to fill out in the UI, in the storyboard.
And you just inspect the cell, and
there'll be a field there called identifier.
And you just fill in that identifier and
that's what's using your code so
this is what links your code to which prototype
cell your going to make a copy of to use,
'kay, but it's only going to make a new copy if it can't
find one to reuse that went off screen.
Everyone make sense there, good?
Okay, so that's how I get the cell that I wanna use.
Notice that that cell comes back as any object, 'kay, even
though it's a UITableViewCell, it's historical reasons it
really should come back as a UITableViewCell.
But you're gonna have to cast it to a UITableViewCell, or
subclass thereof.
So, for example, if this prototype cell was,
you know, like, subtitle or basic or something like that,
it wasn't a custom one, then I'm gonna dequeue it
as a UITableViewCell, and then I am gonna use the API of
UITableViewCell to load it up, and if you look at
the UITableViewCell doesn't have a lot in it.
It has a text label, which is the big text, and
a detailed text label which is the little text.
It also actually will let you put in an image there,
it has image view property, and
you could just load this up.
So here I've loaded up the big text with the word title and
the little text with the word subtitle.
That would happen in every single row, but
usually I would put my data in there, 'kay?
From my internal data structure there.
Now what if I have a custom cell?
Well if I have a custom cell, then that dequeue thing,
okay, here I'm hooking up the custom cell there with
the identifier, the dequeue thing would be my
UITableViewCell subclass, right?
And instead of doing cell dot text label dot whatever,
I would call the public API of my UITable of UText, UTable,
UCell subclass, right?
It has some public API to set its, whatever,
it's displaying and you would call that, make sense?
Question about that?
Okay, so, that's how you get the cell.
How does the data source report how many sections and
rows to use?
Really simple, these two data source methods number of
sections in TableView and number of rows and
section, so you just implement those methods, and
you return the value, the appropriate value there.
The number of sections by default is 1, so
if you don't implement the number of sections in table
view you'll get 1 section, and
1 big section with as many rows as you want.
However, there's no default for
the method number of rows in section.
This is the required method in this protocol,
you have to implement it.
Obviously, the table,
you have to know how many rows are in each section, 'kay?
Cell for row in the next path also is required for
dynamic tables.
If you have a static table,
you don't have to implement any of these cuz a static
table it knows how many rows and
sections there are, cuz you set it up in the storyboard.
It doesn't need the cell for row in the next path,
because it can get it right out of the storyboard and
there's now reuse happening or
any of that stuff in a static table, okay?
All right, so, in summary, the way you load up a UITableView
is you implement the data source, almost always in your
controller, you just say how many sections there are, and
how many rows in each section.
Then, you implement cell row and
index path by dequeuing cells, loading them up with the data
at that section and row and returning it, that's it.
That's how table view works.
It's pretty straightforward.
But you can see the power of this simple protocol
delegation based API allows you to handle 10,000
cells because you've got that reuse going on,
without a lot of work from you, the programmer.
'Kay, all your work is really just manage your model,
get your data ready so that when the section row is asked
for you can load up the cell.
Okay, section titles, you know, like when I showed you
the one that had Japan and the Netherlands, those titles
are considered part of the table views data and so
it is the data source that provides them by implementing
table view title for header in section or title for foot or
in section, and it just returns a string.
If a string is not sufficient to show your title you can
delegate involved then, not the data source, but
the delegate, and it can provide a UI view.
Even if it provides UI view probably you're gonna use your
data sources as your model to load up that UI view anyway,
so since the data source and delegate are pretty much
the same thing, it's a fine distinction there,
but you should be clear about it in your mind.
So, there are a bunch of other methods in the protocol,
most of them are about deleting rows or
inserting rows, or moving rows.
Now, why would the data source be involved in those things?
Well, if I delete a row,
I have to delete that data in the model right?
If I move the rows around and
the order of the rows is reflecting something in
the model, then I need to move it in the model as well, 'kay?
So that's why the data source gets involved there,
and you can look that up in the documentation there.
All right, how about segueing?
What happens when someone touches on a row?
Well, if I'm in a navigation controller especially,
I'd like to segue way off to some other view controller,
and you do that just by control-dragging.
So you just Ctrl+drag from the prototype, or
in a static thing, you can control from a static one, but
you Ctrl+drag from the prototype, and then you
just set the segue type, show, or show detail, whatever.
[COUGH] And then you, oh, yes, if you have that little detail
disclosure I told you about, that special little
right-handed icon, you can Ctrl+drag from it, as well,
and you'll see that you can choose the accessory action.
So each row can actually send two different segues.
One if you click on the row, itself, and
then one if you click on that little round circle, 'kay?
[COUGH] Either way, you just set the identifier of
the segue as usual, and then implement prepareForSegue.
But let's think about as we prepareForSegue, cuz I've got
this prototype row and I've got 10,000 of them,
when I segue I've got to know which row caused that segue,
which of the 10,000 rows, so how do I do that?
So let's look at prepareForSegue.
This is a typical prepareForSegue in
a table view controller, [COUGH] and it looks,
all the stuff in green is all the same as any other one, so
you don't even really have to look at that code.
But the yellow there, the sender
is the first time we've used the sender in prepareForSegue,
and that sender is going to be the UITableViewCell of the row
that you're segueing from, 'kay?
That's the magic.
Now it's any object, so
you're going to want to cast it using as to be either
UITableViewCell or your subclass thereof, right?
So now you've got the cell that you're segueing from.
Now a lot of times you'll want to get the index path
of it now, the NSIndexPath to section and
row because your data, your model is going to be
indexed usually by section and row.
So you're gonna use this method,
indexPathForCell, which you pass the cell to, but
you have to cast it first, you can't pass it as any object,
you have to pass it as a UITableView cell.
And now, once you have that thing, you can do your normal
segueing, so, you're gonna get the destinationViewController
that you're segueing to, as whatever class it is.
Then you're gonna use the publicAPI of that scene you're
segueing to, to set it up using the data at this section
and row of the cell that was clicked on, right?
Okie-doke, all right, so
that's all the UITableView data source, that's getting
the data into the table, segueing, all that business.
Let's talk about the UITableViewDelegate, okay?
So UITableViewDelegate controls how the thing is
displayed, not the data but how it's displayed, so
obviously common for
them to both be the controller of the table view.
The delegate lets you observe what's going on inside
the table.
For example, you could find out when a row was clicked
on with the delegate.
When a row is clicked on, you could segue or
you can just find out from the delegate tableView,
didSelectRowAtIndexPath, and
it's gonna tell you the section and row.
Index paths give you section and row,
remember, of what you clicked on.
You can do whatever you want at that point, 'kay?
You could manually segue in code here, for example, or
you could do something else.
That little detail disclosure thing,
you can segue from it, or the delegate will get a message,
accessoryButtonTappedForRowWi- thIndexPath, and
you can find out about it that way too.
Okay, so clicking on rows whether you click on
the little detail thing or the row itself, you can just
find out about if you don't want to segue directly.
Tons of other stuff in the tableViewDelegate,
you can just look in the documentation.
It also can be involved in the editing part,
especially the re-display part of editing.
So you can take a look at that.
All right, back to UITableView itself,
what if your model changes?
You've done all the stuff to implement the data source, you
loaded up your 10,000 cells, what happens if new songs got
added to your iPod library and you need to re-display?
Well, you can send a message to your table view,
reloadData.
And it will go and send numberOfSectionsInTableView
and numberOfRowsInSection for each section and
call cellForRowAtIndexPath for all the visible cells and
reload up all your data, 'kay?
Now that might be a lot of work for 10,000 iPod things so
you might wanna just reload a small part of it if you can,
and then you can use things like reloadRowsAtIndexPaths.
You just give it an array of index paths and
it'll only reload those cells, 'kay?
So that's what happens when your model changes.
What about the height of rows?
So the height of rows, the rows are gonna be the height
they are in the story board unless, in your code,
you change the height to be UITableViewAutomaticDimension.
If you do that, then it's gonna use the autolayout to
figure out how high each row is, so
every row could be a different height.
'Kay, if you use that automatic dimension,
you're gonna wanna set an estimatedRowHeight,
because the table view is a scroll view, and
it kinda wants to know how big its content size is, right?
'Kay, remember, from scroll view,
the content size, so, it kinda wants to know that.
So it really helps to have an estimatedRowHeight so
it can kinda guess at what the size is and
then as you start scrolling down, it'll adjust it.
It's very good at doing that.
So if you ever use automatic dimension,
use estimatedRowHeight, 'kay?
Now you can also have your delegate report,
calculate and report the height of each row
using heightForRowAtIndexPath, 'kay, or there's also
estimatedHeightForRowAtIndexP- ath.
You can implement either of those.
And that's a way that maybe you can calculate the row
height without having to do the full auto-layout
calculation or something.
Or you can estimate it better than just a fixed estimated,
your delegate might be smarter than that, so you can do that.
Okay, so, dozens of other methods in UITableView itself,
things like scrolling to a row,
you wanna scroll right down to a row or you want to manage
whether multiple rows can be selected at the same time.
Those kind of things are all controllable by methods in
UITableView itself, not in the delegate or data source.
Okay, so that's it.
As usual, a demo's worth 1,000 words, so
let's do a little UITableView demo here.
What we're gonna do is we're gonna build an app
that searches for something in Twitter and
shows us all the tweets that match, 'kay?
Should be easy.
Let's see if there's
anything else here to talk about coming up.
Oh, yeah, your Assignment 4 is gonna go out,
might post it right after lecture today, probably, but
you have until next Wednesday on that one.
It's gonna be a table view-based thing.
On Wednesday of this week, I'm gonna go over the requirements
for your final project.
And then also, I'm gonna cover a whole bunch of other
things like alerts, unwind segues, timers and if I have
time on Wednesday, I'll actually start on animation,
which is gonna be our next major topic.
Friday's section is an awesome one for
this week which is UICollectionView.
So UICollectionView is kind of like a tableView, except for
instead of them being in a strict list,
it can be kind of arranged how you want on screen,
'kay, could be two-dimensional grid or whatever.
So it's a much more flexible version of UITableView.
And then next Monday, remember, no lecture,
we have a holiday.
Okay, so let's go to building new apps,
I'm gonna say create new project.
Single view, I'm gonna call this Smashtag, 'kay?
Put it in our normal place here.
I'm gonna move this stuff out of the way as I always do,
we're not gonna work on any of that today, okay?
So I just have my storyboard here.
It's got this one controller and
I'm actually gonna delete this controller.
All right, so
now we have a completely empty storyboard, and
I'm gonna start by dragging in a UITableViewController.
So let's go grab a UITableViewController.
It's right near the top.
Of our object palette here.
So I'm gonna drag this out.
There it is. I'm also gonna embed
it in a Navigation Controller.
Okay?
Because someday I might want to click on my tweets in here
and have it show more information,
like maybe in your assignment four, perhaps.
All right, so we have this table, your controller.
It really doesn't make sense to have a controller without
a custom view controller subclass, of course,
as you well know from all your assignments so far.
So let's go ahead and create a custom subclass here.
So we'll do File > New.
And hit iOS > Source > Cocoa Touch Class.
Here I'm gonna be very careful to say I want
a UITableViewController.
And I'm gonna call this TweetTableViewController.
Cuz that's what's gonna show.
It's gonna show tweets.
Okay? And we'll put it in
the normal place where you put everything.
Here it is.
I'll actually leave the code in here,
all this commented out stuff.
Because some of this stuff is kinda interesting, for
you to learn about how to do things like deleting rows, and
stuff like that, in the table view.
So, in here is the data source methods and
we're gonna go implement those.
So I'll leave this stuff in here.
I'm just gonna get rid of didReceiveMemoryWarning,
because we're not gonna deal with that.
Okay?
So here we go, here's our code right here.
Let's talk about the model of our, oh,
sorry, one more thing before we do that.
Let's go back to our storyboard and
make sure we set this to be a TweetTableViewController.
Okay, so I'm just in the identity inspector here.
That's a common thing to forget to do.
You'll notice immediately when you start trying to
wire things up.
Oh, that's not gonna work.
But anyway, common thing to forget there.
All right, so
let's talk about the model of this table view controller.
And what it's gonna be is,
it's actually gonna be an array of tweets.
But it's really gonna be an array of array of tweets.
Okay, why am I gonna make this an array of an array?
Okay, it's because I'm gonna have multiple sections.
Each section in my table view,
they're not gonna have headers or anything.
Each section is just gonna be a new batch of tweets, okay?
So, every time I get a new batch of tweets,
because you know how Twitter is,
things are always happening on Twitter,
there's always new tweets being put on there.
You want to be able to constantly be seeing
the latest ones, and so
I'm going to be fetching them every once in a while and
I'll just throw them in to my array of array of tweets.
That's why I'm making an array of arrays.
Everyone understand that, why I'm doing that?
So each array inside is a different section
in the table view.
Now what's a tweet?
'Kay, I got this thing tweet here.
What is that?
Well, I'm gonna give you the code to do that.
I'm gonna give you these Twitter files right here so
you can just drag them in to your project here.
And, what do these things look like?
Let's take a look at them.
So there's these four classes in here.
TwitterRequest is the class you use to actually request
tweets from Twitter.
And I'm gonna show you how to use that in this demo.
Tweet is the things that come back.
So, Twitter
requests are gonna give you an array of tweets, basically.
You're gonna tell it what to search for,
it's gonna give you an array of tweets.
It could not be simpler.
Tweets have some, you know,
things like the text of the tweet, when it was created.
It also has things like, the hashtags and URLs and
users that were mentioned inside the tweet, okay?
So things like the user has its own little class here,
User, that just has screen name, et cetera.
So these classes, you don't really
need to call any methods in any of them except for
TwitterRequest to actually do the search.
The other ones are just like bags of
things that are holding things like about the users,
user name, things like that.
Okay, so it's pretty easy to use this little thing.
So, now we have tweets in here so this makes sense.
We've got our nice model.
So, let's go ahead and make a request.
Let's see what the code looks like to make a request to
Twitter.
And I'm going to do that here in my viewDidLoad.
Okay?
Let's go ahead and leave the rest of the comments in there.
And, so all I need to do, to do this is create a request.
So I'm gonna let a request equal TwitterRequest.
So I'm gonna have to use one of TwitterRequest's
constructors here.
And I'm gonna use the one that lets me specify a search.
Okay?
So, I'm gonna search, let's say,
we'll start out just searching for #Stanford.
That's a good one to start with.
And, a count is how many tweets I want to get
in this request, so I'm gonna just do 100.
And these other things are optional, so
I won't even specify them.
Whatever they are is what they are.
Okay?
So now I've got my Twitter request.
I'm just gonna execute it.
I do that by calling this method in the Twitter request
called fetchTweets.
Now fetchTweets takes one argument which is a handler.
Okay? A closure basically,
we're gonna specify here, okay?
That gives back the array of tweets.
You see how it's giving the array of
tweets as the argument?
So that's going to be the argument in a handler.
So, I'm actually gonna use the trailing closure notation here
to do this.
And so, this is asking me, what do you want,
I just double-clicked on that by the way, it's asking me,
what do you want to call this variable?
So this is my new tweets that are coming back.
Okay? And so, inside here I can
just do whatever I want with my new tweets.
Well, what I want to do is very easy.
If there are any of these new tweets,
because maybe it couldn't find any, but if there are any,
then I'm just going to say self.tweets.
Now I have to say, if I don't say self, you know it's gonna
complain because this is inside a closure.
I'm going to say tweets.insert the new tweets atIndex 0.
So I'm going to put it as the first section
in my table view.
Okay? Remember, Tweets is
an array of arrays, and each one is a section.
So I'm going to put it in section zero
of my tweets right there.
You can see it's complaining because this is
inside a closure, and it wants me to put self in front so
that I'm clear about the fact that I'm capturing self.
Now that's not gonna be a problem in this case, but
it's always something you should think about, as whether
you're capturing something that points back to it.
Then I'm gonna reload my table view, okay?
So I'm just gonna say, tableView.reloadData and
that's gonna cause my whole table to get reloaded.
Now again, I could try and just reload this one section,
section zero, that probably would be better but
I'm just doing a demo here so
I'm gonna reload my whole table.
Its not that expensive to reload my table anyway.
Okay?
It's that simple.
That's all that's necessary.
Now, can anyone see what might be a problem with this,
conceptually?
When do you think this is called?
Sometime later, right?
I'm requesting tweets, I don't want to block my main queue.
So fetchTweets goes off and fetches it on the network and
when they come back, it calls you back later.
Not on the main queue, okay?
So, we cannot actually execute this code like this
because this is UI code and so
it can't be done off the main queue.
So, here we have to dispatch this back to the main queue.
Okay, I may do the same thing here.
My trailing closure notation.
Like this, so I'm gonna put this inside here, like that.
Okay, everyone understand why I had to dispatch this back to
the main queue?
Because this is an asynchronous API.
FetchTweets is an asynchronous API, and
you're gonna see APIs in iOS that are like this one.
This is an API I wrote, but.
IOS is going to have them too, where you're going to give it
a handler and it's going to call that handler back off
the main queue, sometime in the future.
Okay? So this is a multi-threaded API.
Okay, but that's all I need to do.
Simple as that.
When it comes back,
I'm just going to dispatch it back to the main queue and
reload my data.
Question? >> Sorry,
what would happen if you didn't have the [INAUDIBLE]?
>> Yes, so the question, what if I didn't put this in here?
And the answer is strange things.
Your UI would draw weird, things would get out of sync,
probably your app might crash, lots of bad things, okay?
So don't ever do it, it's bad.
Okay, so now, we have our data loaded up into our model.
Okay, in view did load we loaded up our model with some
data from a search, #Stanford here.
How did we get our model into the table?
Where we're going to go down to this UI table view data
source here.
By the way,
I'm going to change this to UITableViewDataSource.
I like doing that.
I don't think I've shown you this comment, // MARK:.
Have I showed you that?
Okay, if you put a // MARK:, then up here,
see where it says TweetTableViewController?
If you click on this, it will show you all your methods and
it will arrange them into groups.
See this?
This is this word right here.
Okay? So it's a really great
way to kind of organize your code using these marks.
So like, for example,
I've put another mark up here, this is a common one I do.
Which is, View Controller Lifecycle.
Okay now, when I click in here, see?
I got View Controller Lifecycle.
I got my data source.
Pretty cool, huh?
All right. So
here's my data source methods.
Here's number of sections.
So how many sections do we have?
Okay, number of sections is tweets.count.
Because tweets is an array of arrays, right?
In each array in there is this different section.
So how many sections are there?
However many things are in the tweets,
my tweets model up here.
Okay? So that's easy.
How about this?
How many rows are in each section?
Okay, well that's just tweets[indexPath.section].
Actually not even indexPath,
they just put maybe the section, [section].count.
All right, so it's asking me, for
this section, how many rows are there?
Well, I'm just going to get the tweets
that are in that section, and tell you how many there are.
Okay, so far this UI table,
it's pretty easy to implement, huh?
Okay. How about this one,
cellForRowAtIndexPath.
So we've got to do this dequeue reusable cell,
it automatically puts it in there.
We need a reuseIdentifier here.
I'm going to be a good coder and
say private struct Storyboard static
let CellReuseIdentifier equals and
we'll say "Tweet".
And then I'm going to put that here instead of this thing.
Storyboard.CellResuseIdentif- ier.
Okay so, but we have to put this string in the storyboard
for the prototype we want to use to build this cell.
So let's do that, let's go back to our storyboard here.
Okay. Here's our table view.
I'm going to click to select this row and again,
I can use control shift and click to pick the controller,
the table view, the cell, or even the views inside.
So I want this cell here, so I have this cell selected.
I'm just going to inspect this, and
right here you see identifier.
I'm going to say tweet.
And that says whenever I dequeue a reusable cell's
tweet, this is the kind of cell I mean, okay?
We'll configure that in a second.
So here we have the cell that's been
reused or pulled out of there.
Now we just need to configure it.
And since this is currently a normal cell,
just a regular cell not a subclass.
I'm going to use those things textLabel.text to set
the title.
Let's set the title to the actual tweet, okay?
So we'll have the big text be the tweet.
We'll have the little text.
Let's go back, let's go back to our storyboard.
This cell, let's make this cell's type be subtitle.
Let's make this be a subtitle style, right?
Where you got the big text and the little text.
So I'm going to make the big text be the text of the tweet,
and the little text be the user who tweeted it.
It's not very good UI,
but we'll make it better in a minute.
All right, so probably want to do question mark here in case
that's nil because it's optional.
So, I need to basically have find the tweet
that's in this row, and then just specify the tweet's text.
So, how do I get the tweet that's in this row,
let tweet equal something?
Well, that's just going to be my tweets[indexPath.section]
[indexPath.row].
Okay, this is my model and
I'm just indexing into it by section and row.
Right, this is the index path that I was asked right here to
get the cell for row in next path.
So now I've got the tweet.
So make its text, and now I'll say detailTextLabel?.text is
the tweet.user.screenname, or
that's actually their real name, what the heck.
Okay?
Everybody understand what I'm doing here in
cellForRowAtIndexPath?
Just return a UI table U cell that's
going to use to draw that row.
So that's all we need to do.
So let's go ahead and run, and hopefully this will work.
Oh, okay.
So here is the unreachable
entry point in your storyboard, okay?
That's because we need to have the entry point come in here,
so I'm going to select this navigation controller and
go over here to.
Sorry.
Select it as the initial view controller,
put that little arrow there.
Okay, now it will probably work a lot better.
All right here, so it wants to access my Twitter account,
sure, go for it.
There it is.
Wow, that was super easy.
We got all our tweets there now.
This is a pretty bad UI.
I mean, Twitter's already pretty limited,
140 characters.
This is not even that many, okay, so
these are all cut off.
So this is really not a good UI.
What we really want is to be able to build a nice,
custom UI in here for every tweet to show the screen name,
maybe the image of the person who posted it,
that kind of stuff in here.
So let's go enhance our UI to do that.
>> [COUGH] >> All right.
Now, how do we do that?
Well, this cell right here needs to.
Actually, you know, it's time?
I'm going to do one other thing first.
Right now, it's only searching for #Stanford.
Let's make it so
we can type in what it's searching for, okay?
Setup is always looking for #Stanford,
let's go put a search field in here.
So, I'm going to put that search field as the table
view's header, remember I said the table view had a header?
So I'm going to put that there.
So I'm just going to go grab a text field, typeable
in text field like we've talked about, here it is.
I'm just going to drag it right
up here at the top of the table view.
Okay, here it is right here.
I'm going to make the font a little bigger,
20 point font right there.
I can also do things like put a placeholder text in here, so
when it's empty it kind of tells people what to do.
So this is a Twitter search query, right there.
So they know what to do.
And, then I can just wire up to this header view using
normal outlets.
So let's go ahead and wire this up to our table view.
I'll just control drag to probably a little.
Higher up here.
Yeah, right in there.
This outlet, I'm going to call it my searchTextField.
Okay? There it is.
My searchTextField.
Let's go back here.
All right.
So here's our searchTextField right here.
Now, when this searchTextField is set by IOS, I'm gonna set
myself as its delegate so I can start doing some of those
UITextField delegate things we talked about.
So I'm going to say here,
searchTextField dot delegate equals self.
Okay. Now it's gonna complain
because I don't implement the UITextField delegate protocol.
So I'm gonna say, okay, sure, UITextFieldDelegate.
So now I'm the UITextFieldDelegate, so
now I can implement some of those UITextFieldDelegate
things.
What's this one?
Oh, sorry, yes.
We want this in the did set.
I was trying to make that a computed property.
Okay.
So that's the did set.
All right.
So inside there we want to do something.
Right now our search is hard wired here to be #Stanford, so
let's make it so it's not hard wired anymore.
Okay? Let's have it search for
some search text.
Okay?
So I'm going to make a var up here, searchText,
which is gonna be a String.
We'll make it optional so
you don't have to set the string here.
Okay.
I get into that quite a bit, don't I?
It's because I got sticky keys on, and it gets stick.
Okay, and we'll still have the default be Stanford.
Okay, and we're gonna need some didset in here.
So here's our searchText.
And down here since it can be an optional,
I'm gonna say if the searchText does not equal nil
because I don't want to search for nil.
That makes no sense.
Okay. And this I'm gonna unwrap.
All right. So
now I've got the searchText, and we can search for it.
All right, we'll wait to do that in a second here.
[SOUND] All right.
Okay, so I got a searchText.
Now let's go back down to our searchTextField right here.
When that searchTextField is first connected,
I'm gonna set myself the delegate.
I'm also going to set my searchTextField's text
equal to my searchText.
Okay, so just in case someone set my searchText,
because I left searchText public.
Okay?
Okay? So if someone set it before my
outlets got set this would pick it up later,
so that's good.
Now let's implement this delegate method.
So, the one I'm going to implement is this
textFieldShouldReturn.
You can see there's quite a few textField things here.
So I'm gonna do this one, textFieldShouldReturn.
And, so this happens when someone clicks on the return
key of my text field.
So what is the return key of my text field going to be?
That's configurable so
if I edit this, if I inspect this text field,
I can actually control a lot about the keyboard right here.
So I'm gonna make this keyboard type be Twitter.
There's actually one for entering Twitter searches.
Okay?
All right?
So now somebody clicked the go button or
the search or whatever that's gonna be in that keyboard.
What am I gonna do about that?
Well for one thing I want to resign first responders.
So if this textField that's sending this to me
is my searchTextField, which it should be,
cuz that's the only one I have.
Then I'm going to have my textField
resignFirstResponder.
That means dismiss the keyboard.
If you don't do this, it will send this.
But it's gonna leave that keyboard up assuming that
maybe they wanna type another search right away.
But here, I want it to go away so
they can see the results underneath it.
M'kay?
So, what else do we need to do in here?
Well, then we just need to set our searchText
equal to the text that's in the textField.
Okay?
So someone hits search, I'm gonna set my search text up
here equal to the thing is in there.
And then I have to return true or false, whether or
not I want to let this return key do what it normally does,
which is fine.
I don't have target action set up so
it's not going to do anything anyway, but
we'll go ahead and say true.
Okay, now when my searchText gets set here,
I need to react to that by doing a new search.
So I'm going to go here in my searchText.
And whenever my searchText is set,
I'm going to basically clear out my table and then refresh.
So, let's go ahead and say tweets, removeAll.
Okay, so I'm gonna remove all my tweets that I have because
I'm dong a new search.
Then I'm gonna reload the tableView here,
reloadData in the tableView.
That's gonna blank out the tableView,
cuz I just set all my tweets to nothing.
Removed them all, and then I'm reloading, so it's gonna clear
out my table view while I'm doing my search.
Remember my search might take a minute if I'm on cellular.
So I don't want to be sitting there with the old results,
that'd be confusing, so I'm just gonna clear out my table.
And then I got to refresh my data.
So I'm going to call refresh and
take this code out of here and put it in another
method called refresh, func refresh.
Okay, I'm gonna do the same thing I was doing before.
I'm just gonna call it both in viewDidLoad when I start up
and also anytime someone changes my searchText.
In my searchText also,
if someone sets my searchText externally, I'm going
to update my searchTextField also if it's around.
Okay, so that way if someone's using my public API and
sets my search field, it'll appear in the text field.
I want it to show up in that searchTextField.
All right, let's see if I got everything here.
This works.
All right, here we have a #stanford.
That worked.
We searched here.
So maybe we could search for, I don't know, #grammys?
And there, we got stuff about the Grammys.
Okay? So that's good.
We got searching going.
So now, let's go back to do what I was gonna do,
which is let's make that row be a lot better than just
the tweet cut off and then the person who did the tweet.
Let's make it a much better UI.
So we're gonna do that with custom cells.
So I'm just going to select this cell right here, okay,
and change it from being a Subtitle cell to being
a Custom cell.
Okay?
And then inside this Custom cell,
I'm gonna build whatever UI I want.
And I'm gonna be able to wire up its outlets and
actions to a subclass of UITableViewCell.
So let's create that subclass of UITableViewCell.
All right? Again,
iOS source Cocoa Touch class, this time we don't want
Controller, we want UITableViewCell.
I'm gonna call this a TweetTableViewCell,
because it shows a tweet, 'kay?
Put it in the same place I always put everything.
[COUGH] Here's what it looks like.
I'm gonna delete these, 'kay?
So inside here is where I'm going to put all the code that
updates this custom UI that I'm gonna build over here.
Here's gonna be our custom cell.
Here's gonna be the code for it, 'kay, our UITableViewCell.
All right?
All right.
So let's set this cells right here,
the identifier of this cell to be our TweetTableViewCell.
Ok, if you forget this step then obviously you won't be
able to control drag between these two.
And then lets go ahead and build this UI,
actually we'll go ahead and get full screen for that.
I'm gonna build this UI.
What do I want this UI to look like?
Okay well, I want it to have.
Some labels, obviously, for like the person who,
sent the tweet and the tweet itself and
I'd also like to have an image of the person who tweeted it.
So I want an image view, there as well.
And I'm going to arrange all this, this ImageView,
I want it to always be a fixed size.
I'm gonna have it be 48 by 48, that's big enough to kinda see
it, but not big enough that it's dominating the space.
Because this is going to be,
each row each row is going to be a tweet,
I want to get as many of them on screen as I can.
So, I'm gonna set this thing to be 48 by 48.
I could use the dimensions inspector here to do that.
48 by 48.
There it is.
I'm gonna put this in the upper corner here.
I'm gonna do the auto layout for this really fast.
Okay? Because you're hopefully guys
are getting familiar with that.
And also we've got time constraints here so
I'm gonna put this thing in the upper corner.
Top space.
And leading space over there.
I'm also going to fix its width and height.
You can drag something onto itself and
then set things like aspect ratio or width and height.
Okay?
So I've set its width and height so that's good.
That guy seems to be happy there.
I don't see any yellow.
Let's put this guy.
This is going to be the name of the person who is tweeting.
Okay.
So I want that to be the whole width, right here,
and let's go ahead and hook that up so
that it's hooked up to this thing.
I'm going to hook up just the horizontal spacing there.
Let's also hook this up to the top,
and let's hook this over to the right.
Okay, so we've got that one hooked up.
That one seems happy.
Okay, this one is going to be the actual tweet.
Now, this one I want to be kinda big, okay,
I want it to use a lot of space here.
And, normally in a label, if you have more than one line,
it just draws one line and dot dot dot.
Have you noticed that?
So, there is actually a way in label,
if you inspect label, to say wrap.
And the way you do that is by saying how many lines you
want, and if you specify zero as the lines you want,
it'll use as many lines as it needs.
So it's kind of a cute way of doing that.
Another thing about these labels is they are currently
the system font.
That is bad.
Why is it bad that those are the system font?
Because the system font is not for the user's content.
Okay, I talked about this in one of the lectures.
User's content, you want to use the preferred font, which
you can get to by picking this little typeface here and
going down to text styles.
So this is the tweet itself so
that's kind of the body of the user's information here.
And this one which is the user who tweeted it.
That's kind of like a header or a caption or
header at the top.
So I'm gonna pick Headline Style for that.
So these fonts are going to be picked by the system
to look nice.
Also if the user goes into Settings.
And changes their preferred font size,
these will get bigger.
And since I'm gonna build my UI to be flexible,
my cells will just get bigger in that case, or smaller.
So it's all gonna happen automatically.
I don't have to actually do anything to make that happen,
except for do my auto layout right.
Okay, so I got that one.
Let's go ahead and Control + drag this one up to here.
Here I'm going to set both the vertical spacing.
I'm also going to line up these left edges.
Make sure the left edges of these two line up together.
I want this edge to be here.
I want this one to be, oops.
Down to the bottom here.
I think that's probably good.
Let's see if I forgot anything.
Oh yeah.
Two views are vertically ambiguous.
Okay? These two views
it says are vertically ambiguous.
That's again, our friend, the hugging.
Okay?
One of these two, these are both labels.
They both want to hug exactly the same amount.
If I look at them, you can see they both have a hugging
priority vertically of 251, 251 and 251.
So I have to pick one of these that's not gonna hug.
Now it's not gonna matter here,
actually, because my whole row is going to hug, so
there both going to get to hug.
But, I still have to pick one that has priority for hugging,
so I'm gonna make the big one here be less likely to hug.
So as soon as I change that,
now you can see only frames are the problem.
So let's go here and update our frames.
Okay, so it looks good, it's all looking good in there.
I actually was going to also put a little thing
here that says the time of the Tweet but
I'm going to skip that for time.
I'll do it in the code I post, I'll put it in there though.
All right, so we've got this UI kind of looking the way we
want it to look.
How are we going to hook it up to our table view cell?
Well, we're gonna do just like we do anything else.
Control dragging.
All right, so we've got our UI here.
Let's hook up let's say our image view, so
I'm gonna drag this in here.
This is going to be called my TweetImageView.
Going to show that.
And then, I'm going to drag this one, which is going to be
my tweetScreenName, I think I called that.
And this is going to be the actual tweet text.
tweetTextLabel.
Okay.
So I got my outlets in here, and so
now I just need the code that makes all these outlets get
updated when someone sets the tweet.
So I need some public API, which is going to be a tweet.
Okay. This is going to be the public
API of my TweetTableViewCell,
it's what I'm going to use in my self erode index path.
To set that up.
So when the tweet is set,
let's do a didSet right here and update our UI.
Okay, and in updateUI,
then I'm going to do all this.
So that's what I'm going to do.
Tweet created a label I decided we're going to save
some time and not do that but
I'll uncomment this out and put that in when I post this.
But all this does here is just sets the tweet's label
text label to the tweet's text.
It sets to screen name to the user and
it sets the profile image to the users profile image here.
Okay?
Now, notice this one right here, blocks the main thread.
So, in your homework, one of the required tasks is,
you can't block the main threads, so
you better fix this, okay?
I'm not gonna fix it, but you, you had better.
And anywhere else you block the main thread,
you're gonna fix, okay?
All right, so now, all we need to do is go back to our
controller right here and now our self erode index path is
going to be a little bit different because our thing is
not a UITableViewCell anymore, it's a TweetTableViewCell.
And we're not going to do these things right here,
the detail label and the text label.
Instead we're going to set that public API.
Which is cell.tweet = the tweet, which is actually this.
So actually, I'll make my code look nice and go like that,
get rid of that, get rid of that.
So actually our code got simpler here,
because we transfer a lot of the responsibility
to display the thing into our tweetTableView cell,
which is over here, all right?
Everyone understand we're configuring this cell by using
this public API.
It's gonna update its UI,
which is gonna set all these outlets.
Everyone cool with that?
All right, let's see if I forgot anything.
All right, look at this.
Okay, this is looking a little better.
It's still not quite right.
Because look, all these rows are the same height.
Even if the tweet inside is small.
Okay?
So why is that happening?
Well that's been happening because by default,
if you look in the storyboard, okay,
if you take a particular cell here,.
Okay, Ctrl+Shift, pick the cell, and
you inspect right here, you'll see its row height is fixed,
okay, fixed to 162 points high.
And I don't want that.
I want this basically to be the estimate,
this 162 I want to be an estimate, but I want
it to actually calculate it using the auto-layout.
So I'm going to fix that in here.
I'll do it in viewDidLoad.
Where's my viewDidLoad?
Up here.
I'm going to say that my tableView's estimatedRowHeight
equals the tableView's rowHeight.
So that's the height it has coming out of the storyboard.
And then I'll reset the tableView's rowHeight,
to UITableViewAutomaticDimension.
Okay?
So when you set the rowHeight to this automatic dimension,
that means calculate the size.
But it's gonna use whatever rowHeight is in the storyboard
as an estimate.
Okay. So, see if that works.
Now, if I got my, yeah, it looks like it works fine.
You see, this one's nice and small.
This one's larger.
Et cetera.
Okay.
Was there something there I'm going to have to bleep
out on iTunes U or something?
I don't know.
Be careful there.
Oh, look at this, let's see, look at that.
Nice, okay.
>> [LAUGH].
>> Now, your homework, your homework, Jessie,
is going to be a couple of things.
One, to highlight all these mentions.
The hashtags, users, etc.
And also, when you click on one,
you're going to segue to a new table view you're going to
write that's going to show all the images that are attached
and all those hashtags, etc.
And then you'll be able to click on those again to keep
navigating.
Okay?
That's the base of your assignment.
Now, the last thing I'm going to show here is
how to basically refresh this table, because tweets
are always happening as we notice right here from Jessie.
Maybe Jessie's still tweeting, I don't know.
We can't see the rest of her things without quitting our
app and restarting.
So what I want to be able to do is pull down on my table
view and have a little spinner come up up here.
And have it fetch again.
And when it's done, add that to my list.
So that's what we're gonna do right here.
First of all, how do you get that spinner?
Okay? Real easy.
You go to your storyboard.
You click your table view.
Okay? You go over here
to inspect it.
All right. And then the inspector,
actually you inspect the controller.
You look right here, it says, refreshing.
See, it says, refreshing disabled.
That means refreshing is not allowed in this table, so
I'm going to enable that.
Now, nothing appears to have happened.
You don't see the little spinner
appear here on the storyboard.
The place it actually appears
is over here on the document outline.
There it is right there.
Okay? That's the refresh control.
Now, that refresh control is a normal control.
You can Ctrl+drag from it to create an action,
which is exactly what I'm going to do.
I'm going to put that action right in my controller.
So here's my controller.
Let's put it,
we're going to put it up towards the top here.
Maybe right here.
Okay. So I'm going to Ctrl+drag
from the document outline, okay, over here.
And it's going to be an action.
I'm going to call it refresh.
It's going to have an argument which is this refresh control
itself.
You can also get this refresh control by calling the method
refresh, or the property refresh control,
in UITableViewController.
So here it is,
this is what's going to get called every time we refresh.
So just to show you what refreshing looks like
in the UI.
It looks like this.
So here it is, I want to refresh.
See that little spinner?
And I let go, and it's spinning.
Now, it never stops spinning here because
I don't do anything.
So it doesn't know when I'm done.
So what do we want to do when this refresh happens?
Well, actually, we want to take that search, whatever
the last search we did here for tweets, and we wanna get
a follow on search that says, give me more of those.
Well, TwitterRequest that I provided for
you has a nice property that if you give it a request that
you've already successfully made,
it'll give you a request to get more.
Okay? So that's exactly what we're
gonna do.
I'm gonna add a couple of new properties.
One is called my lastSuccessfulRequest.
Okay?
Which is gonna be a TwitterRequest.
'Kay, so that's gonna be the last one I successfully did,
and I'm gonna have another one,
which is my nextRequestToAttempt,
that's what I called it.
That's also gonna be a TwitterRequest.
And this one is actually gonna be a calculated property,
because I'm gonna be able to calculate the next one
based on the last one.
So that's simple, I say if I had a last successful request,
okay, that's, oh, sorry, let's say if I don't have one.
If I don't have a last successful request,
then let's make one.
We have that right here,
so I'm going to put this line right here.
So this TwitterRequest right here, this search,
I'm going to make that be my
request if the search text is not nil.
Then I'm going to return that as my next request to attempt.
And here I'm just going to do request,
next RequestToAttempt.
So this place where I was fetching before,
instead of always fetching the search text, instead I'm going
to do nextRequestAttempt, which, if we've never had
a successful request, is going to be that same search.
But if we have successfully requested something,
then I'm going to return our last successful request's
requestForNewer.
Okay?
And this exclamation point,
because I already checked that to make sure it's not nil.
Okay, everyone got that?
What's the problem here?
lastSuccessfulRequest!.reques- tForNewer.
Oh, yeah, let's make this be an optional right here.
Okay? So
that can be an optional too.
And since that can be an optional,
we'd better check it here.
If we can find a request, then we'll do this.
Well, you pay the price if you press the wrong key.
Okay, luckily, we have undo.
Okay, so there we go.
So that's it.
So now we are also doing it.
Now, the only thing here is,
otherwise we'll return nil.
The only thing here that we need to do is,
every time our search changes, we need to set our
lastSuccessfulRequest equal to nil.
Okay?
Cuz we, as soon as we're searching something new,
now our last request doesn't matter, so
we're gonna set it to nil.
And that's gonna cause this next request to make
a new search.
Okay? And then the last thing we
need to do is turn off that little spinner.
Okay?
So where are we gonna turn off the spinner?
Well, if we go off to do some searching, then when we
come back, we can have our refresh control turn off.
I'm gonna move this right down here into that target action,
okay, because I'll have my refresh control then.
So I'm gonna say sender?.endRefreshing.
Is that what it's called?
Oh, yeah, endRefreshing.
Let's go ahead and make this an optional.
Which you're allowed to do for a target action argument,
make that an optional.
I'm gonna say that.
The reason I'm gonna do that is because I still want
refresh to work.
When we call refresh from code, I still want that to
work, and I'm gonna do that by calling this refresh here
with my refreshControl as an argument.
So I'm just calling this one.
You see the little organization I did there?
And in fact, if we call from code,
I want that spinner to start spinning.
So I'm gonna say, if my refresh control is not nil,
in other words, unless someone's calling refresh
before my outlets are even hooked up,
then I'm going to start my thing spinning.
So I'm gonna say refreshControl?.beginRefresh-
ing.
Okay?
So here I'm beginning it refreshing in code.
Okay, here it's being sent target action.
So it's beginning by itself.
And either way, I'm ending it.
Now, what if their search text is nil?
Then I also want to end refreshing.
Because I can't actually search.
And everyone understands that
this is not gonna get called and this, right?
Because this is being called,
dispatched from another thread, okay?
This needs to be else.
Okay, so this is only going to get called if this is not
nil, okay?
All right, let's see if this all works.
All right, so that worked.
Did you see that little thing spinning when I
first launched?
So it worked to call it from code, that's cool.
Oh, look at that.
Now, I hope you guys will be nice to me,
you're not putting something.
There we go, we're getting more stuff.
Okay?
Now, just to be careful here, keep refreshing.
In fact, let's try something else.
Let's try grammys again.
Maybe people are still tweeting about the Grammys.
Okay, so here we go.
There we go.
See how we're getting newer ones each time we refresh?
Or maybe we could do gswhoops.
I think the Warriors are playing right now.
There we go.
Okay?
Well, nobody's too excited about it, though,
cuz they're not tweeting.
All right, so that's it.
That's all I wanted to do.
So you will get to start with this code
when you do your assignment.
Sorry for going a little long.
I'm here if you have questions.
>> For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.