[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Okay, welcome to Lecture Number 11 of
Stanford CS193P Winter 2015.
And today, we have a few topics to talk about.
I'm gonna start off by talking to you about your final
project requirements.
You know?
All the details of what you need to do, and by when.
Then we're gonna go over some topics briefly.
I'll get through as many of these as I
can fit the time of.
I might not, especially, the last one,
probably won't get to.
But that's okay, I'll just start off the lecture next
week because we don't have lecture on Monday.
So next Wednesday will be our next lecture.
All right, so start right into these
final project requirements and feel free to stop and ask me
questions if I say something or you don't understand it.
We ask everyone to submit a proposal for
what they're going to do.
And it's a simple proposal,
I am going to show you a sample proposal in a minute or
two so you can get an idea of what a proposal looks like.
Proposals, and please submit them in PDF format only,
not just sending them in an email or in Word format or
something like that.
Please, PDF.
And the proposal,
really you can have two big sections in it.
One is what you're doing, obviously, and
then another one is what parts of iOS you're going to use.
And again I'm gonna show you
an example of that in a second.
The project is going to be due on Friday the 13th.
[SOUND] Be ready for that, midnight on that day,
Pacific Time, yes.
Use the normal submission process,
there'll be an option in there for the final project.
You can't use any free late days.
We're already totally pushing this out to as late as we can
and still get them all graded and
by the time we have to get the grades submitted.
So lateness is very highly penalized.
Basically one letter grade per day
because we just can't afford it to be late.
Okay? So
if you have any free late days late
use them on assignments four and
five because you cannot use them on the final project.
I can't grant extensions.
There's just really no time for extensions.
So basically submit whatever you have on Friday the 13th
and see what happens.
If you don't like Friday the 13th,
you can submit in on the 12th, that'd be fine.
This is a three week-long project, right?
It's not due until, basically what, four and
a half weeks from today.
But you need a week to think about what you're gonna do.
You still have a couple of assignments left.
So it's basically a three week-long project.
So even though last minute if you're in an emergency it
shouldn't hurt you too bad.
So plan accordingly.
Start early and try to get it done early.
That way, if you have a problems,
you'll have time to go track things down.
If you don't start until the last week of the three week
project, your project's not going to turn out that good.
I can pretty much guarantee that.
People often ask,
can we work in teams on this final project?
And the answer is generally no, but
I do allow teams of two only
in these very specific circumstances here: Both
students have to be taking the course passment credit.
The homework grades for both students have to be
substantially similar and good.
No team can consist of anyone who's
basically been struggling in the course so far.
You have to submit a proposal and
your proposal has to be explicitly approved.
The rest of you are going to submit a proposal and
we're going to give you feedback on it.
But there's no process whereby we have to say yes this is
approved, now go forward.
You're just gonna get feedback.
But if you're doing the team of two,
you do have to get it explicitly approved.
And of course, that proposal would have to cover six weeks
of homework time worth of work because there's two of you.
Okay? So, that's twice as
much in there.
The proposal also not only is gonna have to show the things
I'm gonna talk about later but
it also has to include who's gonna do what.
And I really strongly encourage you to break up
the work that's going to be happening among two people
along class boundaries.
So, this class is being written by Joe, and
this class is being written by Jane.
Okay? So it's very clear who's doing
what, as opposed to oh, we worked together on this.
And then it's hard for us to tell who actually understands
what in here, okay?
Then when you submit your code,
you have to follow that up with a clear delineation,
this person did this, this person did that.
And again hopefully, that this class was written by this
person, this class was was written by that person.
So we don't end up with very many teams of two every
quarter, because of these strict requirements.
But if you wanna try and give it a try, you want to submit
your proposal as soon as you can put it together,
like in the next couple days.
And start getting your grader to give you feedback
on it as soon as possible so you can iterate and
make sure that you have something that's workable.
Okay?
Otherwise, I strongly recommend kind of
individual work.
I mean, this course is about learning to be an iOS
developer and if you want us to be able to measure your
success at that learning process, it's individual work.
Okay? Now, understand that when
you go out into the real world,
programming is never individual work.
It's almost, I mean, 5% of what's going on in the world,
programming wise, is some individual work, okay?
95%, you're working in teams.
And I wish I had more than ten weeks so
we could work on working in teams.
But we just don't have time for that, unfortunately.
All right?
You'll be graded based on your proper use of the iOS SD case.
So don't hack.
Okay? Make sure you understand.
You read the documentation of the classes you're using and
you use them properly.
The other thing I'm gonna say is that breadth is very,
very important.
Breadth meaning show me as much of the iOS API as you
can, rather than going really really deep and
doing one thing really, really, really well.
Some people are graphics wizes and
they go do these incredible graphics apps.
And I say to them well,
if this had been a graphics course,
you'd have gotten an A plus.
But unfortunately, it's an iOS Development course, and
you didn't show me much iOS.
You just showed me only the graphics part.
I don't know whether you can do table views and
all these other things.
What's going on?
So breadth is extremely important.
It's probably the most important.
And then the second thing is we're gonna ask you to do one
significant feature that I did not teach in lecture.
And that's because iOS is huge.
I only teach the tiniest little fraction of it.
I really just teach things that teach you the concepts
you need to learn other things in iOS.
So you really need to show that you can go to
the documentation, go on the internet,
figure out how to do something substantial on iOS without me
basically showing you and giving you a demo of it, etc.
So I put them in yellow there because those are really
the two most important things to get right.
You don't wanna get stuck down a rat hole, where you
just spend two of your three weeks kind of chasing after
one thing that never really pans out and
now you only have a week left to do a lot of breadth.
So if you start doing something and you're just
like, God I completely don't understand this or
I can't figure this out.
Just cut and run.
Go pick something else,
some other feature you can put in your application instead.
Notice that I don't say anything here that
you're going to be graded on how cool your app is.
Or how ready for the app store it is, or
how much money it's going to make.
None of those things are part of the requirements.
This is an academic course,
you're trying to show me your iOS capabilities.
That's the number one requirement, okay?
Now, if after this course you want to then
take some features out maybe that you threw in just to show
me that you knew how to do something in iOS.
Or if you wanna add some features because
there was something too complicated to do through.
Hey, that and more power to you.
Many, many final projects have
eventually ended up on the App Store.
But that is nothing to do with the requirements.
Not even, you know,
mention this part of what you're supposed to do.
Okay, I don't even care about that.
Okay? The scope of the project,
like how much work it is.
It should be three weeks of homework worth of work.
Especially three of the last weeks of homework, because
you're supposed to know iOS by the end of this quarter.
So if you took, take a combination of assignment
three, four, and five which is the graphing calculator, and
then the smash tag that you're working on now, and
there's gonna be an animation base thing,
you take that much worth of homework work,
that's about how much your final project should be.
Okay, maybe even slightly more because some of the stuff that
you're gonna put in your final project,
you already know how to do it in the assignments.
So it should be easy peasy for you, 'kay?
Just a reminder that everyone pass no credit or
letter grade you have to pass both the homework and
the final projects separately.
At Stanford a passing grade is a c minus or better, 'kay?
So we will tell you if you have not passed the homework
portion once we've finished grading homework assignment
five, 'kay?
So then you can just stop work on the final project at that
point, all right?
[SOUND].
>> [LAUGH]. >> Well,
you can keep working on it if you want, but you're not gonna
pass the course if you don't pass that part, okay?
'Kay, question about the scope?
Scope is important.
It's one of the things people fall down on.
They basically submit something that's kinda
two weeks of work, and so two weeks of work,
that's two-thirds of the, for total points.
That's not a very good grade, so
you wanna make sure you get your scope right there.
[SOUND] Do not just regurgitate your homework
assignments, okay?
I do not want to see smash tag too, okay?
And every quarter it seems like I always get a handful of
people who can't really think of something to do so
they basically just take smash tag or maybe the last homework
assignment and they just kinda change the names and,
you know, it's very, very similar.
Don't do that, okay?
Cuz then you'll have just shown us that you already what
you've already shown us,
which is you know how to do the homework.
Okay, great, we already, yeah, know how to do the homework.
Now show us different.
Basically one thing to think about is you wannna start your
final project from scratch.
You don't wanna start it with Smashtag and
then start changing it or with assignment five and
then start changing it or with a calculator and
then just start changing it.
Start from scratch, 'kay, that will help emphasize
you don't wanna just turn in a regurgitation of the homework
assignment and in fact,
whatever you do in your final project, try to do things
a little differently than we did them in the assignments.
Cuz if you do something exactly the same way we
did it in the assignment, like if you had a table view, and
if data structure is exactly the way we did it for
the assignment, it's kinda like, well,
we already knew they could do that, so don't do that, 'kay.
Pick a different instructor, something more interesting,
do a couple more features in table view,
do things that are maybe extra credit in the homework,
do those in your final project, those kinda things to
get some difference between your homework.
>> But, I guess I'm afraid that, how do I know what's,
you know, different, and what's like a hack,
like if I make my priority the structure, like a linguist,
for example, is that like a hack?
Or is that okay to use?
>> Okay, so the question is,
how do I know, if I do something different than what
was talked about in lecture,
if I'm not now doing hackery, okay?
And the answer is, well,
you're going to have to figure that out,
because when you go out into the real world and
build iOS apps, you need to not be a hacker, and the way
you figure those things out is by reading the documentation.
If you read the documentation of a method and it says,
this method works this way, and
you use it that way, then you're not hacking, okay?
If you go out on the internet, and it says, oh,
you can call this private method with this thing and
it'll work, then now you're staring to hack, right?
Or if you just don't read the documentation and
just start typing things in until they work, okay?
I used to have a great GIF, I don't have it now, where it's
just this GIF of this guy just banging on the keyboard and
then banging his head until he's just a bloody mess, and
that's a programming approach that doesn't scale very well.
So, you know, you'll know if you're hacking,
it'll be clear.
You can always ask your TAs, there'll still be office hours
all for the rest of the quarter, you can, you know,
go find out if you're hacking.
All right, so some examples of bad projects,
we already talked about Smashtag two,
that's a bad project.
Another bad project is one that has very little breadth,
like it's lots of MVCs being segued to each other but
all the MVCs are basically the same.
A bunch of buttons and text fields and labels and
that's it, there's no table views in there,
there's no animation, there's no custom view with drawRect,
you see what I'm saying?
It's all just the same thing over and over or
vice versa with the table views.
It's table view, after table view, after table view,
after table view, and there's nothing else,
just table views.
That's all that's in it, the whole app is table views.
Those are bad apps.
An animated game, like you're doing a game that's all video
game, a guy running around and shooting bullets and all that
stuff, that's bad too, because where's the table views?
And it shows me that you know the animation stuff, great!
But I need to see all the rest, text fields and
labels and segues, where's that if it's just this
one screen where the guy is running around jumping, okay.
Another one is some cool mathematical thing or
an image filter that uses your PhD research
to calculate something.
That's great that you worked your PhD research in there,
except for that's 90% or 80% of what you did, and
you're gonna get an F in this class,
because only 20% is going to be iOS stuff.
You want it to be the other way around, 90% iOS and
then you can only spend 10% of your time on doing,
putting your PhD stuff in there or
some in network resource or whatever, that's fine.
The aesthetics of your UI do matter.
Okay, we don't want these junky,
totally crappy looking things but
I don't expect you to be graphic designers.
You're programmers.
So that just basically means,
you know, do your auto layout nicely, line things up.
You know, those dash blue lines help you line things
up so things should look nice.
Also, don't be afraid to go out on the internet,
find some nice icon or something do in there.
You're really not even gonna have to worry about,
do I have the rights to use this icon,
because it's only for your personal work.
You're not gonna be shipping it on the App Store.
If you do ship in the App Store,
you have to change your icons, or either buy them,
or use stuff that's free to use, all that but for this,
you don't have to worry about that, so we do wanna see it.
By the same token this is not a human,
computer human interface class, okay?
So an app's not gonna be a primary thing.
I just want to make sure you don't turn into much of junk,
'kay, you wouldn't want that either.
You're final project has to work on hardware, 'kay?
And you have to demonstrate that to us.
So you're gonna have a final presentation which I'm
gonna talk about in a second, and if you do a live demo
on hardware, then you've satisfied that requirement.
If you don't, then you need to show your TA,
usually they'll hang around after the final project,
final presentation slot, or you could show it to them any
time before that, in office hours or whatever.
Show them your app working.
So that's the important part.
You can't just be simulator only.
And you're gonna that assignment,
I don't know if I made assignment four be
hardware required, I guess not, but
assignment five will definitely be,
this must work on hardware, 'kay?
Yeah, this is kind of a reiteration of my theory four
but don't get side-tracked on non-iOS code.
If you have something like a database that you're gonna use
or a login, a lot of people want to do a social networking
app which is great and you have to have a login,
or something like that, you know, you can fake it.
Fake the login, just have three users, and
that's all, right?
And it's some,
as long as you do it in a nice object-oriented way,
where that faked backend is its own object somewhere, or
whatever, that's the way you wanna do it, because again,
you wanna focus all your time on showing me as much
iOS usage as you can cram in there, 'kay?
So if you waste a week, hooking up to a network
server you've wasted a week, okay, now you have to cram
three weeks of iOS programming and coding into two weeks so
don't do that, 'kay, so be careful there.
All right, presentation,
this presentation I mentioned, so there's so
many of you this quarter, this is the max we've ever had.
Normally we have a two-minute
presentation where you get up here for two minutes and
you have to just basically tell us all about your app.
I call it sometimes the venture capitalist pitch,
imagining a venture capitalist here, and you're trying to get
them to invest in your company to build this app.
You wanna put your app in the best light and show it off,
and you wanna show off all aspects of it, so
should give a screenshot.
Do a live demo if you dare.
You can see I do live demos and they can be perilous.
Somehow, you know, pitch your app to us.
So, unfortunately we only get 90 seconds because they're so
many of you.
We only got three hour slot and didn't really want it to
spill over too much into the alternate final slot.
So 90 seconds. That doesn't seem like a long
time but actually you can say a lot in 90 seconds.
' Kay.
If you're, if you're very focused on what
you have to say, you can show your basically,
your entire UI in about 30 seconds.
Yeah? >> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Yeah so I think I say on here.
Maybe I get to second.
The question is can I just make a video and
get up here and press play?
And the answer is no, 'Kay?
I want you guys to have the experience of standing up in
front of your peers and having to talk to them.
That's a very, very important skill in your life, okay?
And so you need to do that, so no pressing play, 'Kay?
I need your slides before, because I'm going to put all
the slides in one big thing so we can race through this.
Okay, we got to get to a hundred people,
90 seconds each with like 10 seconds in between.
We're going to have to be really racing through.
So you're gonna give me all your slides,
I'm going to put them all in one gigantic presentation and
we're just going to be clicking through the slides,
person after person will have any switching time.
Please make your slides,
you haven't noticed by now, wide screen, okay?
1280x720. Do not send me 1024x768 or
800x600 slides.
They will look funny, 'Kay?
The slides are due to me the day after your final
project is due, so you can get your final project in and
then spend the next day if you wanna fax, you know,
craft your presentation, do some screenshots or whatever.
Whatever you present, though, in terms of slides or
UI on that second day, should be what you turned in.
So don't spend Saturday adding more graphics and
all that stuff and
then putting up slides that are not what your app is.
'Kay?
Your app is the presentation
you give has to be the app you turned in.
Make sense?
You submit the slides also using a normal process.
There'll be a different submit target for that,
final project slides, it'll be called.
And so, yes, that's the way you do that.
Now, I know some of you have a conflict with the final exam,
although I don't really know how that's supposed to happen,
because all the final exams are supposed to
not conflict with each other.
But I know you guys have other things,
you're in the GSB or something else.
So I am gonna have an alternate final slot if you
want, which is on the very last lecture of this course.
So you can do your presentation then if
you prefer.
And there will be a sign up for that but
it will be really easy.
I'll announce it on Piazza a couple weeks before.
Okay?
If you do the alternate time,
obviously I need your slide sooner.
So I need them by the Monday before actually.
Now in that case, you still get to turn your stuff in
by the Friday, so you're gonna have to be making your
presentation out of your apps not done yet maybe.
So, but you just gotta do the best you can if you
wanna go early.
Okay? But presenting early has no
effect on when the actual thing is due.
It's still due on Friday the 13th.
Okay?
The quality of your presentation,
people say oh does it matter?
Yes, of course it matters.
Okay? It matters for
you and your experience here at Stanford is to be giving
good presentations.
Does it matter to your final grade?
Yeah, a tiny little bit.
If you come up here and you totally bomb.
If you do a live demo and it's a complete mess,
we're not gonna go oh, that's a B for that guy.
No. But, still we want,
you can kind of impress us if you come up and
do a really great demo and it really shows our graph well,
we're more likely to walk away going wow,
that was a little better app than I thought.
Okay?
But, if you come up here and
you're terrible, then we might be like, which app was that?
I thought that was terrible.
Okay? So,
it matters a little because it gives us an impression, so.
And that 90 seconds is going to be strictly enforced.
I'm literally going to say okay thank you,
right at 90 seconds cause we just can not afford to go over
too many people.
Yeah, question, should I do a live demo?
I love live demos as you can tell,
I do a live demo almost every single lecture.
But I know that for some people, it's like, oh,
it's a little scary, it might not work,
especially if you're going out on the network,
maybe you can't get the network or something.
So, it's dangerous.
So, what I recommend is, live demos are pretty effective,
so, you know, try and
put a live demo together if you can but have a backup.
If you get up here to do your live demo, it's like,
it won't project.
Your device won't project.
Or the network doesn't work.
Or you have audio and it's not working.
Then just switch to your Keynote.
So have your Keynote slides as back up if you're gonna
go live demo, is my recommendation, 'Kay?
All right, so the proposal.
Sample proposal.
Here I'm just gonna show you what one would look like so
you can kinda get an idea.
My sample proposal is I'm gonna build a Shakespeare
director app.
So I'm a director of a Shakespearean play, and
I'm gonna have this nice iPad app to help me do that and
help my actors.
And so it's basically going to have a table for
choosing a Shakespearean play.
So you can pick a play, the one you're doing.
And then it will let you lay out, you're the director, so
you're gonna lay out the blocking,
which is where everyone stands on stage,
on a little kind of graphical stage.
So I'm gonna have a drawRect there.
I'm gonna have gesture, so I can move things around.
It's also gonna have a dialog learning mode,
where it's going to show the dialog line by line
so that actors can have their own iPad maybe while they're
learning their lines.
And they'll see their blocking and
their lines right there at the same time.
And they'll also be able to record the other people's
lines, so it'll prompt them.
So that they can sit there and
learn their lines and all that.
So you can see, it's a pretty cool app, right?
It's pretty good idea.
I'm basically explaining what it does in my proposal.
I'm talking about limitations, though,
like I'm saying that my custom view is only going to be
rectangles and circles and I'll let them set color.
So, the people are not going to be really great graphics.
I'm just saying that I don't want to spend all my time
doing that, so I'm just gonna make my, when I lay
out where everyone is on stage it's just gonna be block.
See? So, I'm kind
of explaining my proposal that I realize because if I don't
put that in here, then your TA's going to feedback and
say, whoa, you're gonna have this whole blocking thing?
How complicated is that gonna be?
What are you gonna allow?
You see what I mean?
So this heads that off by saying, okay,
I understand that mostly I'm focusing on doing draw rec and
gestures and things like that.
That's what I'm trying to show you with this feature.
But I'm saying here that I'm gonna be able to let you
take a photo of a person and put that in a rectangle so
that when you're blocking you can at least have
pictures of the people, maybe in their nice costumes.
And I'm telling you other things here, you know,
that sound recording sound is going to be possible.
I notice that I mention that it's iPad only.
Now, when I say iPad only there,
that hurts breadth, okay?
Because an app that works on both iPhone and
iPad has more breadth although it's pretty easy to make
an app that's just kinda works on both.
But you still have to make sure the adaptations
are working maybe and that when it rotates in both sides,
it does the right thing.
So it's a little more work.
So you just lost breadth.
I lost breadth by saying, iPad only.
But I decided that this app just doesn't make sense
without iPad.
Although i could, I could decide that maybe the blocking
part is not on the iPhone version just the dialog
warnings cause I could imagine the actors standing
here with just their iPhone learning their lines or
whatever so I could, I could if I needed the breath,
I could add that back in.
Okay, to here section one,
where I'm explaining what I'm doing.
Now here's section two, here's all the iOS API
that I'm gonna use to implement that.
I'm using TableView as a custom TableView cell.
A UIView with drawRect.
The camera.
Popovers.
I'm using scroll view to zoom in around in
the blocking view.
I'm using AVFoundation to do the recording of the sound.
I'm using timers.
I'm gonna use a thing called Core Data, which is an object
oriented database to store my data in there.
That would be a not covered in lecture feature,
cuz we're not covering that in lecture this quarter.
I'm also gonna make it so
I can print out my blocking on a printer.
That's also not covered in lecture [SOUND], okay?
So there I'm doing substantial
not covering in lecture futures.
I'm making it really care what they are in my proposal and
I'm talking about all the other things I'm gonna do.
'Kay?
That help you understand what's going on there?
Proposals.
Okay, so you submit those proposals as soon as possible,
but really no later than next Tuesday, please,
to your grading TA, whoever graded your last assignment.
And they have a lot of you to read, so they'll,
as quickly as they can, get some feedback to you.
If you don't give it to us by next Tuesday, you know,
still going to be beneficial for you to send it to us.
It's just that there's going to be less and less time for
us to give you any feedback, and
you're going to have to already have gotten started
pretty soon, by the end of next week, let's say.
You're probably really want to get started.
So it's really your own thing.
And again though it's not, you don't have to get it approved
to start on your project,
unless you're the two-man team, you do.
You don't have to get approval, but
you really do wanna get that TA feedback.
Cuz you don't wanna start off on a trajectory where the TAs
are like, you're not likely to end up with much of a very
good project here, cuz there's not gonna be enough breadth,
or I don't understand what your not covering lecture
feature is, or it's not a good enough one, or whatever.
Now, the other thing to note is that proposal is completely
non-binding, except for
a little bit with a two-man team.
But for everyone else, it's not really binding either way.
So if what you turn in is completely
different that your proposal, that's fine, okay?
We're not gonna go back and say, hey wait,
you said in your proposal you're gonna do it.
No, we will not say that.
But vice versa, too.
If we say in your proposal,
oh yeah, doing core data for that,
that sounds like a good not covered in lecture feature.
And then you go to implement it, and
you do such a trivial version of core data that's not
substantive enough, we still might ding you and say hey,
that was not a substantial not covered in lecture feature.
In other words, your proposal is not graded.
It's no part of the grade, we'll never look at it again,
it's just to get you started on the right track.
You are still responsible for delivering all
the requirements that I talked about today in your final
project, regardless of what's happening with your proposal.
So it cuts both ways.
We won't hold it against you, and, you know, but
you can't come back and say but you said that was okay.
All right?
Make sense?
Okay.
Last thing I want to talk about is collaboration.
So people ask me okay, but
can I work with someone else not in this class on it?
And the answer is absolutely you can,
in fact I strongly encourage that.
In fact, last quarter
I had a thing where it was a requirement
to go find somebody to work with outside of this class.
When I say that, be very careful,
I mean non-coding help.
Okay?
You can get someone to help you like a marketing person,
or a salesperson, or somebody who is kind of
a business development person, or an idea man, okay, or
idea woman, who's going to give you an idea.
That's fine for someone else to give you the idea.
But you've gotta totally be the coder and
architect of the solution, okay?
Because you are in an iOS development class so
you gotta do the iOS development part of it, okay?
Now, that other person who's helping you could also help
you with things, maybe giving you assets,
maybe they could give you some images or
they might give you access to a database or something,
or some network server that you're gonna oh,
perfectly fair game.
It's just they cannot help you with the actual
coding of your app.
And it can't be someone else in the class either.
Okay? It's gotta be someone
outside of this class.
Okay?
So I do have two people here, two Stanford affiliates,
who are going to get up and
talk a little bit about what they're doing.
And if you like what they're doing,
then you can contact them,
and maybe they would be your outside idea man or woman.
And you could work with with them to
understand more what they want.
Now what they want might not be suitable,
exactly, for a final project, because you know what
the requirements are, you've seen them all today.
They're specific academic requirements, and
you got to meet those.
But by the same token, what you do,
what their idea is might help guide you towards
putting together a lot of good features, and vice versa.
If you work with these people and
you find out this is great, this is really interesting
maybe then after the class is over you can say okay,
well now let's work together and
go do something really what we want to do,
based the specs of what the requirements are.
That make sense?
So back to learning about iOS itself.
The next thing I'm going to talk about is the unwind
segue.
Now this is kind of a weird thing,
because I talked to you about all this stuff about segues,
and then the unwind comes along and
unwinds a little bit of your knowledge about it.
The most important difference of an unwind segue versus all
those other segues that you know, the show segue and
the pop over segue is that it does not create a new MVC.
It is the only segue that does not,
in the process of seguing, create a new instance of MVC.
Okay?
It can only segue to an MVC that either directly or
indirectly presented the current MVC.
So the MVC that wants to unwind to another MVC has to
have been presented directly or indirectly by that.
So what's it good for?
What does this unwind tell you,
what do we ever use it for?
Well, it's really good for
jumping back the stack of the navigation controller.
All right, so you got the navigation controller.
You've got six cards, you know, things stacked on there,
and you want to jump back to number two,
or all the way back to number one.
Okay?
Well, in the navigation controller, each card down
is considered to have been presented by the previous one.
So it falls into this unwind segue thing where directly or
indirectly you can go back up.
Unwind up.
So that's one good thing about it.
Another one is you have an MVC that's modally presented.
Now again, I haven't talked really too much about modal
presentation.
I'm going to talk a little bit more about it today.
But modal, I told you what modal is though.
Modal segue means take over the entire screen.
Even a pop over is basically modal, because when
a popover's up you can't do anything except for
what's in that popover.
The only other thing you can do is dismiss the popover by
clicking somewhere else.
So that's kind of modal.
It puts your app in a mode where you can only work
in that one space.
So a lot of the time when a modal segue comes up
on the screen, when it's done it wants to
communicate some results back to whoever presented it, okay?
So an unwind would be great for
that because the only other alternative would be, like,
delegation.
And, yes, you can have an MVC delegate back to another MVC,
because we remember that delegation is our view,
talking back blind to our controller.
And remember that an MVC can be part of the view of another
MVC, so it's legal to use delegation.
But unwind, it's just a lot easier.
Okay, unwind provides a little pipe for the modal segue to
unwind back to the one that presented it and
communicate with it, okay, by segueing to it, basically.
All right.
So how does it work?
Instead of Ctrl+dragging
from something to another MVC, okay?
You can't really Ctrl+drag to the presenter.
It might be in weird places in your storyboard.
It might not make sense.
So instead, you Ctrl+drag to this little button at the top
of every view controller which is called the Exit icon.
You see it there, it has the word exit.
And when you Ctrl+drag to that exit, okay, to make the segue,
it's gonna say, okay, where do you wanna segue to?
And instead of specifying a particular MVC,
you specify a special IBAction, okay?
So my IBAction here I only wanna have is go back.
All right, that's the name of an IBAction method,
somewhere in some MVC out there.
Okay?
Now what's special about it is the argument of it,
is a UI storyboard segue.
The same argument that's given to prepare for segue, okay,
UI storyboard segue.
That's what makes it special.
So when you add an IBAction method to any MVC and
the argument of it is a UI storyboard segue,
then when people Ctrl+drag to their exit,
they'll see it in this list, okay?
So it can be any MVC anywhere.
Now of course if you try to unwind, and
you pick a method in an MVC, and
no MVC presented you that implements that method.
Then the unwind segue's gonna do nothing, okay?
Because it's not gonna be able to find a presenter who
implements this method, okay?
So, but let's say you do have a presenter.
Let's say you're in a navigation controller and
somebody who put you on screen has this method.
Go back.
You see it takes a UI story board segue there.
Then if I wire up my unwind segue to that then I am
basically going to be segueing back to that presenter.
Okay, so that's how you hook it up, basically.
All right, now what happens once you get this hooked up?
So there has to be IBAction and
there has to be UIStoryboardSegue.
Okay, otherwise IX code will not be able to detect
that possible unwind.
Okay, so when you segue, it is a normal segue
in that you get to prepare for segue, right?
So the guy on the right there, he gets to implement
prepareForSegue and when the unwind happens to his little
exit button, and he starts looking for
that go back method somewhere in a presenter.
He's going to get to prepare.
So you just implement normal prepareForSegue inside of
that guy, and the presenter, okay, is gonna get prepared.
And then the presenter's also going to have this go back
method called after he's prepared.
Okay?
So the presenter gets really prepared, kinda,
or gets information twice.
It gets it once when it's preparedForSegue, because
it's the destination MVC and it's going to get prepared.
Now it's already here so it's already pretty prepared but
maybe it gets prepared more.
And then when the Segue happens,
go back will be called.
And in the Segue that's passed as the argument there,
the presenter can find out who is segueing to me, and
what are they communicating to me?
What do they want to communicate to me,
in fact they can talk too, it uses public API to get
whatever information they want.
So basically it creates a link.
So you will be dismissed in the process.
When you unwind, when the user clicks on whatever you
control-dragged to that exit button, after this happens
you're gonna get always get dismissed.
Okay? So
if you're in the navigation controller,
the navigation will pop back up to the presenter.
If you're modal, you will go away,
you'll stop taking over the whole screen.
Okay?
So you are gonna unwind, that's why we kind of call it
unwinding, you're wound up and now you kind of get unwound.
So yeah, so Modal segues,
navigation controllers, exactly the same mechanism.
All right, so that's it for unwind,
it's as simple as that.
You could possibly use unwind in your assignment
four if you want.
I talk about it in the required task and the hints.
It's not a required task,
it's just a way you could do it, okay?
And you can decide whether you wanna use an unwind or not.
It would be a good experience for you to use an unwind.
Question. >> Is the default background
in the navigation controller actually doing that?
>> Yes. The question is,
is the back button unwinding?
And the answer is no.
That back button is wired to a method navigation controller,
called pop view controller.
And it just pops up,
so it doesn't get to do any of the unwinding.
It doesn't get to be prepared, you don't get the,
you don't have to implement that action with the,
so it's no, the answer is no [COUGH].
Okay any other questions about unwind?
Okay, next topic.
Alerts and action sheets, okay?
So there are two kinds of "pop up and
ask the user something" mechanisms in iOS.
One is called an alert, and one is called an action sheet.
And they use, actually, exactly the same API.
You set them up in exactly the same way and
I'm gonna show you how that works.
What's the difference between the two?
Okay. Alerts, first of all,
they pop in the middle of the screen.
They're both modal.
Okay? They're both basically modal
view controllers.
Okay? They're just kind of
drawn in a certain way, but they're really just a modal
view controller because they both take over the screen.
But the alerts takes over the screen and
comes up right in the middle.
And usually alert is gonna ask you a question,
ask the user a question where there is only, kind of, one or
two answers.
Like yes no, or do this cancel, or
something like that.
An alert also, by the way, can also have a text field, so
it could be like log in and
you have to type your password in there.
Okay or maybe even user name and password.
So it can collect text.
Action sheet cannot collect text from the user,
only the alert can do that.
But if you had a question that had more than two answers to
it you're probably going to use an action sheet.
Okay, so an action sheet.
It presents on screen a little differently.
It doesn't come up in the middle of the screen
like an alert.
It usually slides up from the bottom on an iPhone.
On an IPad we usually put it up in a popover and
I'm going to show you how we do that in a moment.
An action sheet is sometimes referred to as a branching
decision sheet, so where you're basically making
a branching decision where the user wants to
do one of three or four things and you're kind of picking
which one you're going to do, and you're gonna head down
that direction inside your app, okay?
So I think by example
is the easiest way to kind of see the difference here.
So, I took our Cassini out that we wrote, and I added a
little button on the top that actually controls Cassini.
Okay, it'll redeploy Cassini off to different places, okay,
Saturn or can send it off to Titan or
send it towards the sun, or whatever.
Okay so I added that little redeploy button.
You see it up in the right hand corner there?
It says redeploy.
So part of my implementation of allowing the scene to be
redeployed, I use an action sheet and an alert.
Okay?
So here's the action sheet I used.
When you click that redeploy button, it's gonna put up an
action sheet that says where do you wanna send Cassini to?
I'm sure the Cassini guys have an app just like this,
it's how Cassini is controlled.
But, our app only lets them send it to Saturn, or
Titan, moon of, is that a moon of Jupiter, I guess?
Or they can go take a closeup of the sun,
which is going to destroy Cassini.
Okay? Because it's too hot there.
Or they can cancel.
So that's the action sheet that I invented.
And then if you decide you want to go somewhere,
then I put up an alert that says oh, if you want to send
Cassini to Titan, you need to login and give your guidance
system control password or something, okay?
So this is my alert, okay?
So we're going to look at the code,
how I did this action sheet and alert.
Okay? So
let's start with the action sheet.
Now the code for both looks incredibly similar, so
what I'm teaching you here about action sheet,
almost can be 100% applying to the alert.
But basically in either case,
you create an instance of a UIAlertController.
This is just a UI view controller, okay.
It's a sub class of a UI view controller [SOUND] that,
you know, gets presented modally.
And that's basically it.
Okay, alerts and actions are basically a sub class of
UI view controllers that get presented modally.
They just happen to draw on these particular ways.
When you create your view control, you're going to give
the title that you can see where the title Redeploy
Cassini appears there in my action sheet right at the top.
And then the message,
which will appear right below it in non bold.
That's actually probably using preferred fonts.
So that's probably actually like a headline font and
a body font I'm guessing.
And then you specify the preferred style.
So this is how you decide whether it's an action sheet
or an alert.
So here I'm doing action sheet so
I say UIAlertController style action sheet.
So that means I'm making an action sheet.
So that's it.
I create my view controller.
Now I need to add some items into there like orbit Saturn,
explore Titan, close up of Sun, cancel.
How do I do that?
I do that by calling the method addAction on the alert
on this view controller I just created.
And the argument to that is a UIAlertAction,
which is another class that I'm going to create, which
really just kind of collects all of the information about
a particular action.
So here is how UIAlertAction looks like.
It's got a title.
That's like Orbit Saturn there or Explore Titan,
that's the title.
It's got a style.
We'll talk about that in a second.
And then it's got a handler, okay?
So here, you're starting to see closures again in
the iOS API.
This handler is just a closure, okay?
The argument is gonna be this action itself, so
it's basically like sender.
And inside this closure, you can do whatever you wanna do
when they click on that particular action,
like Orbit Saturn.
So the code in there would probably go off and
send Cassini instructions to go Orbit Saturn, okay?
So let's look at an example of one of these.
Let's look at Orbit Saturn.
The title is Orbit Saturn, the style is default, okay?
We'll talk about some other styles in a second here, but
default is just the default line,
this blue colored text right there, like Orbit Saturn,
Explore Titan, they're both that.
And then the closure I'm
gonna put is just to go into orbit around Saturn.
And similarly, Explore Titan would look exactly the same,
also default style.
And maybe Cassini's mission was I think to orbit Saturn or
go to Saturn.
So maybe if you're gonna switch it over to going to
Titan then you have to log in and do your guidance password.
Otherwise, you can always send Cassini back to
Saturn, I guess.
Okay.
So there's the example of the default actions.
So let's look at the next one, that Closeup of Sun.
So the Closeup of Sun is almost exactly the same except
for its style is not default, it's .Destructive.
Okay?
So .Destructive makes it show up in red.
So anything that's gonna really damage something,
like delete this entry, or something like that,
you can make it .Destructive and it will show up in red.
Okay.
Otherwise, it's exactly the same as the other ones.
And then the Cancel one also has a special thing, .Cancel.
All right?
And you can see that Cancel is
kinda separated from the rest of em?
It's down at the bottom, it's got a little extra space.
That's pretty much the only difference between Cancel,
cuz you still get a closure there you get to execute,
when it's clicked on.
Okay, so that's it.
So, alerts couldn't be any simpler to create, okay?
So that's how you create this view controller and
configure it with its actions.
Now, how do we put this thing on screen?
How do we get this alert to actually slide up
from the bottom?
Well, it's just a UIViewController,
we're gonna present it modally.
So, there's a method in UIViewController called
presentViewController.
I haven't really talked about it cause
we haven't talked about modal presentation.
But all presentViewController is,
it presents a view controller on screen.
And if it's a modal view controller like alerts are,
it'll appear modally.
Okay? It only has three arguments
which is the UIViewController to present,
whether to animate it so in the case of the action sheet,
it slides up from the bottom.
And then you also get a closure there,
completion, which will get called, this is closure,
it takes no arguments, returns nothing.
It'll have when it's done.
So when that thing has been finally presented on screen
and done its animation, boom,
you'll get your completion called.
You almost never do anything there.
It's really, doesn't make a lot of sense.
The things already up, it's doing its business.
There's really no business for you, as its presenter,
to be doing at that point, but you could, okay?
So that's it, UIAlerts are just UIViewController.
Just add actions to them, then you present them.
Now, what about this action sheet thing though on an iPad?
Okay? So here's same app in iPad and
I got that redeploy button up there in the right.
Now look what happens when I do redeploy in the iPad.
Same thing.
But it shows up in a popover.
Okay? It doesn't
slide up from the bottom.
It wouldn't look very good if it slid up from the bottom.
It would either be kinda silly narrow, or
it would be so fat and wide it would look ridiculous.
It makes much more sense to put it in a popover like that.
Notice that the popover is different in one big way.
No cancel button, okay?
And that's because you don't need a cancel button to
cancel a popover.
A popover is modal, and if you click anywhere else in your
app, boom, it's gonna cancel that popover.
But if you have a cancel action, like this one does,
its actions still will be called,
even in the popover cancel case.
Okay?
So that cancel thing is kind of still in play,
it's just that you access it differently.
Instead of hitting the Cancel button like the bottom of
the iPhone version, you just click somewhere else and
make the popover go away.
Everyone understand that?
All right, but how do we make this work?
Because this is not quite enough information
to present that popover, okay?
That popover needs one really important piece of
information, which is who is popping me up?
Because you see it has that little white triangle
at the top that's pointing to redeploy?
So nowhere here are we saying, oh, Mr.
Popover, point to that redeploy button, okay?
So we need to say that.
So that means when we put any action sheet up and it's
gonna happen on an iPad where there might be a popover.
We need to get a hold of the popover
presentation controller.
The same one we got ahold of, back when we were doing
the popover in the previous app, the psychologist app.
Same popover presentation controller.
We need to get it and we just need to tell it,
here's the button that's presenting you, so
you can point to it.
Okay?
So we do that like this.
First of all,
just have to say that the alerts presentation style,
its modal presentation style, is popover presentation style.
If we don't tell it that, then it will never make a popover
presentation controller.
So we can't tell it anything cause it won't exist.
But once we say that this UIViewController
modalPresentationStyle is a popover, now we can say okay,
well give me the popover presentation controller.
And the BarButtonItem,
which is that redeploy up there is this.
And so I point it to the redeployBarButtonItem, and
now when it pops over, when it gets presented modally here,
using a popover presentation,
it will point to the redeployButton, okay?
The cool thing is because of adaptive UIs,
which we talked about back then,
is that this code works exactly the same on iPhone.
So if you put in those three lines to make the popover
work, it won't effect the iPhone at all.
Because the iPhone already adapts popovers to present
over the whole screen, remember?
And in fact, we had to go do some work in psychologists
to stop it from doing that adapting.
So that it would show up in a little popover on the phone.
But if you don't do any of that work,
then by default it shows just like this.
Until it takes over the whole screen on the iPhone.
So that's why setting the modal presentation style to
popover still works on the iPhone because it adapts.
Okay?
Any questions about that?
So that's how you do an action sheet.
You're gonna do the same body of code you see right there
for every action sheet you ever do.
All right, now, let's go talk about the alert.
Okay.
The only difference in creating the view controller
is you say that its style is alert instead of action sheet.
Otherwise, it's exactly the same.
Okay, iPad different text here,
obviously login required and please enter your Cassini
guidance system password instead of the other things.
But, otherwise I'm just changing
the style to be alert.
I do the same thing with adding actions.
So, here I'm gonna add the Cancel button.
Okay, I'm gonna add the Login button.
Now the interesting thing about the Login button is when
I login I wanna get the text out of that text field
to use as a password for my guidance system, okay?
So how am I gonna do that, okay.
Well first of all we're gonna ask,
how do I put that text field there?
Okay, I've gotta put that text field in my alert.
So here's how we put a text field in alert.
Use simple method addTextFieldWithConfiguration-
Handler, okay?
When you call that, it adds the text field to the alert
and it calls this closure so
that you can configure the text field however you want.
So here my text field,
I configured it to say Guidance System Password
as the place holder text there in the background.
Remember in the smash tag,
I had my search field say Twitter Search Query.
Well, here I'm having
this one say Guidance System Password in the background.
And that's it.
So I could do other things to set the font or
whatever I want of the text field there.
And you can call
addTextFieldWithConfiguration- Handler more than once and
then you'll get more than one text field.
So you could have a login and a password field.
Now.
This is great, I've got the text field in there.
When I click log in inside the action for
log in, how do I get the text out of that text field, okay?
Well, that looks slightly more complicated than you might
like, it looks like this.
I'm going to let TF, which is going to be a pointer to that
text field equal alert.text fields.
Which is an array of any object
in its optional array, okay?
So, since it's an array, since it's optional,
I'm gonna put a question mark there so
that I can do this optional chaining and just fail.
So TF, let TF, that could be nil,
that could end up being nil.
That's a question mark, and then I'm gonna say .first.
If you remember an array,
the method .first returns the first thing in the array
if the array has anything in it.
If not, it returns nil.
So that's a great way to get something,
the first thing out of an array and
not have to check to see if anything's in the array.
And it'll just return nil if there's nothing in the array.
And then I've got to cast it to a text field because I told
you it was an array of any object.
Why is it an array of any object?
Don't ask, historical reasons.
It's a way objective C cat does things,
it's not quite as expressive as Swift.
But, anyway, too bad.
So you do this as ?,
so that also could return nil.
So, it's three different things that could return nil,
but if they don't, then I'm gonna get text field back.
And if I get a text field back,
then I can just take the text out of the text field and
log in.
Okay?
Any questions about that?
I know it's a little convoluted getting
that text field out of there.
All right?
So that's it for alerts.
Then you just present view controller exactly the same
as we did for action sheet or any other modal view.
And how about an iPad?
An iPad?
It looks exactly the same.
Takes over the whole screen.
No need to do any popover business with alerts on iPad.
Okay.
So that's alerts and action sheets.
Just UIV controls that you're presenting modally
that's all they are.
All right.
Next topic, NSTimer.
So NSTimer is a way to set up a timer
that will call a method periodically, okay?
Now, it uses technology called RunLoop,
which we're not going to talk about.
So suffice it to say, for you, in this course,
you always have to use timers on the main queue, okay?
Because the main queue has a run loop.
You can actually have run loops on other queues,
other threads, but we're not gonna talk about that.
So, main queue for you, NSTimer main queue.
And, so this timer, it's not really a real-time timer.
If you say go off every two seconds,
it's not going to go off every 2.00000 seconds.
And why is that?
Because basically it's just putting things,
it's kind of like it's putting things on the main queue but
not, not quite the same.
The runloop helps process things that are happening,
like interrupts or data that becomes available or whatever.
And it can't run in real-time,
because other things are on the main queue running.
Okay? Other
blocks of code and stuff.
So we can't quite guarantee it.
But it has a high priority, so,
as soon as the main queue becomes available, after
2.0000 seconds has happened, it's gonna call your method.
Okay, but it's not a real time programming thing.
I mentioned that for those of you who are like systems
OS people and you're used to real time API.
This is not real time but it's really, really,
really close to real time.
As long as you don't have any big things on your main queue
that are blocking it up which you shouldn't have any
way, right?
Never block your main queue.
Then your timer's pretty much gonna run when you want.
Okay?
Now this is not used for animation.
We're going to talk all about animation later today and
all of next week.
And your assignment five is
going to be all about animation.
Timer is more like a complement to animation.
Because when you're animating things sometimes you do want
to do things.
Something every second or every two seconds.
You're really not going to be, like,
doing something every 60th of a second.
Okay? 60 frames per
second animation,
you'd never do that with a timer, it's not for that.
Okay?
It's just for things like, maybe,
you have something where you have a score in a game and
you update the score every second.
Okay?
So that you're not constantly changing it,
something like that.
It's that kind of thing.
It's used for that kinda thing.
So run loops we're not going to talk about that.
Okay so how do you fire off one of these timers?
How do you make it work?
Well you do it with a class function in NSTimer.
It's called a scheduled timer with time interval.
Now be careful.
There are four methods in NSTime but it looked very,
very similar to this.
Okay? But
this is the one you want with this set of arguments [SOUND].
And the arguments are just,
the first one is how many seconds between firings?
How many seconds do you want to wait each time before you
call this method again?
The target is, who you gonna send the message to?
It can be any object.
Okay?
Remember, any object is not a struct or an enum.
Although, things like string and number, those are.
You're not gonna solve puzzles anyway but
those are essentially any object because they're
bridging over to NS String.
But anyway, any object, okay, is any object,
any class basically, and then selector is just
the method to call when the timer goes off.
User info is just like a cookie that you can
hand off here and then every time it fires you'll be giving
that thing back.
So, it's just kind of a way of passing this argument off
to your, so you don't have to keep it in a class,
in a variable in your class or anything like that.
You can just hand it off.
It's like context for the timer.
And then repeat is whether this thing just does it once,
or it keeps doing it every however many seconds.
Is it a repeating timer, or is it just a one time
do something in the future, and I showed you a way to do
one time thing in the future with dispatch last time, so
this will be another way to do something once.
Here's an example of calling it.
So here I have a timer.
It's gonna go off every two seconds.
It's gonna send this message to myself called fire.
Notice that, that method can be any name you want,
except it has to have a colon there,
because it's going to have an argument.
I told you that when you're specifying the name of
a method, if it has an argument,
you have to put a colon on the end.
OK. Otherwise it
thinks it's the method fire without an argument.
And then userInfo on passing nil.
I don't really want any information,
I could pass anything, any object I wanted there.
And then repeats equals true means it's going to fire
every two seconds.
It's going to fire in two seconds from now, and
two seconds after that, and two seconds after that.
Repeat it forever until I invalidate it, okay?
So let's look now at the fire timer thing.
It looks like this.
You can basically do whatever you want in there.
You're on the main queue so
you can do UI in here or whatever.
If you pass some user info, you can get it
out of the timer by saying the timer.userinfo.
Now you've got that info.
Okay?
Super simple to use these timers.
If you wanna stop a timer that's repeating,
it's going off every two seconds and you wanna stop it,
you just send it the message, invalidate.
If you say timer.invalidate, it will stop.
Okay?
Another thing you can do to make your system perform
better is put a tolerance in there.
What a tolerance says, is if my two, if I'm
setting something to go off every two minutes let's say.
Okay?
When the two minutes is up do I have to do it right away?
Or can I wait five or ten seconds?
If you let the system wait five or
ten seconds, it could pick an optimal time to call your,
a more optimal time, anyway, to call your timer.
So, my strong recommendation is, try to give a tolerance.
A tolerance is just a number of seconds that you're
willing to wait after it would normally fire.
Try to give a tolerance of like maybe 10% of your timer.
So if you have a two second timer,
give it a tolerance of 0.2 seconds or
something like that.
It'll let the system pick a more efficient time to run.
Like, for example, if your app, we didn't
really explain how this works, but your device can kind of
go to sleep a little bit when nothing's happening.
Nothing's drawing on screen, no network activity.
So it can kind of go into a little lower power state, and
then it comes back awake every once in awhile.
Well, if you give it a little tolerant,
it might be able to kind of go into that low power state and
then come back up in that little window.
But if you don't give it a tolerance,
it might have to stay awake to make sure it hits that timer,
the one you wanted.
You see?
So the tolerance is exactly what it sounds like.
A little bit of tolerance, give the system a little
better chance to manage your battery and all that.
Okay?
If you give it tolerance, it's not going to drift.
In other words, if you give a tolerance 2 minute timer and
you let it go an extra 10 seconds and
it waits an extra 8 seconds, the next one is not going to
be 2 minutes after that 2 minutes and 8 seconds.
It's still going to be 2 minutes after the first
2 minutes.
Do you see what I'm saying?
Within the tolerance.
So it's going to stay on a schedule of every two minutes,
even if it waits a little bit on one or two or three.
It doesn't drift.
Okay, that's timer.
Okay. Any questions about that?
It's a pretty cool little guy.
All right.
Animation.
So, this is kind of Intro to Animation,
this last ten minutes of today's lecture.
So, let me talk a little bit about the kinds of animation
that you can do in iOS.
One is to animate the properties of a view.
And that's what we're going to talk about today.
So that's one kind of animation.
Another one is animation of view controller transitions,
like in a navigation controller,
when you transition to the next card on the stack or
something like that.
Or even a modal view controller like the UI alert,
or the action sheet that slides up from the bottom.
Okay, that's another kind of animation, obviously.
Okay we're not going to talk about view controller
transition animation in this class.
It's not really that terribly difficult, but
it's just like I got to pick things to talk about and
that one, we're not going to talk about, okay?
But there is infrastructure for doing that.
There's also something called Core Animation.
Okay, Core Animation is this incredibly powerful animation
engine that underlies
all of this UIView animation that's going on.
And Core Animation can animate arbitrary properties
over time.
And it knows how to juggle them and
knows how to present them on screen over time.
It's really super powerful.
Unfortunately, I can't talk about that either.
Okay. Don't have time for that.
But if you're going to do something serious animation
inside views and you're not going to use the next kind I'm
going to talk about, Core Animation, know that it's
there because you will eventually have to learn it.
Okay.
And the last one's called dynamic animation.
That's physics-based animation.
So that's giving views gravity and collision boundaries and
other behaviors like friction and density, and
then saying, go.
Okay? And
then they'll just behave, okay.
So that's dynamic behavior based animation, and
that's what we're going to talk about on Wednesday.
And that's what your assignment five is
mostly going to be about.
Assignment five's going to do a little bit of
view animation, which I'm going to talk about today, and
then a lot of dynamic animation.
Okay?
And why do we have dynamic animation?
Why do we have this physics thing?
If you ever watch an iPhone app, you know,
if you flip things up and let them drop down.
Don't do it now, but if you get your iPhones out and
you go to the very front, even if it's locked, and
you pull down your notifications, you'll notice
they will kind of hit the bottom and bounce a little.
Okay?
It won't just kind of pull it down and
it won't just go clunk, it goes boom.
Okay? It kind of gives
a soft landing.
And that kind of animation turns out to
be surprisingly important for the user experience.
It makes the user feel a little more like oh, yeah,
it's kind of giving a constant warm fuzzy feeling about
what's going on, as opposed to feeling like a computer that
is slamming things around, okay.
So, dynamic animation is really important for
giving that really kind of homey feel to your UI.
Warm feel, okay?
So that's why we spend a lecture on it next time.
All right, so let's talk about animating view properties.
Only certain properties can be animated at the UIView level.
If you go down to Core Animation, you can do more,
but at UIView level,
you can really, the three that are most important to animate
are the frame, that means moving your view around.
The transform, that means rotating your view or
scaling it in and out.
And the opacity, the alpha.
Okay.
So you can use this kind of animation to
fade things out using the alpha or to move around,
although they won't move with this nice physics base.
So I kind of recommend the dynamic animation for
moving things.
But it's really nice for alpha for fading things around, or
if you're going to have rotating views,
views that rotate.
So how do we do this animation with these properties?
It's done with class methods on UIView and closures, okay?
So you have this class method.
You basically say what kind of animation you want,
how long you want it to take, things like that.
And then you just provide a closure, and
inside that closure you change these properties, frame,
transform, alpha.
Just change them.
Okay?
And then the system
will animate those changes over time.
Simple as that.
So here's what the method looks like.
It's called animateWithDuration.
There's a few different kinds of it, but
this is the basic one.
You can see that it takes a duration.
That's how long the animation is going to take.
A delay is wait.
Should I wait to start this animation?
Options, we'll talk about those later.
Then the block, okay?
Takes no arguments, returns no arguments there, that closure.
That's where you're going to change those view properties.
And it also has a completion closure.
When it's done animating, the animation actually completed,
it will call this and it'll let you know whether
the animation finished or whether it was interrupted by
another animation that tried to change that same property.
Okay, because you can have multiple animations going off
at the same time.
All right? So what does it look like to
call this?
Here's an example.
So this is going to, two seconds from now,
start fading my view out over three seconds.
And when it's done fading out,
it's going to remove it from the super view.
Okay? That's what this one
line of code does, okay?
It's got, I guess it's more than one of code,
cuz you've got the closures in there.
But it's what it does, okay?
So you can see here that I say I want three seconds, for
it to take three seconds, but
I want it to start in two seconds, so
you're going to take five seconds total.
Okay, it's not going to do anything for the first two.
And then in my block, I just change my alpha.
Right? From 1, which it started out,
I have an if that says only do this if I'm fully opaque.
So I just set it to zero.
That's all I have to do.
And then in my completion block, if I finished,
that's the if $0, that's the finish thing.
If I finish,
then I'm going to remove myself from the super view.
But if someone else animated alpha in between,
then I'm not going to remove myself from super view.
Which makes sense, right?
Because they probably changed the alpha to something
nonzero, okay?
Now, a very important thing to understand about animation,
all animation that's going on, is when you make changes,
they happen immediately.
The animation is just showing it to the user over time.
Okay? So in this code,
when I print myView.alpha equals myView.alpha,
that is going to print zero, because that closure changed
it to zero and it does it right away.
Okay. Even though the user doesn't
get to see it on screen for five seconds,
that's irrelevant.
The fact is, I just changed my alpha to zero.
Okay. It's very important to
understand and it will take some wrapping your head around
until you really understand and work with it.
But it's a little bit like multithreaded programming to
understand.
But really,
all animation is presenting it to the user over time.
It's not changing it over time.
Okay? All right.
So that's it.
That's how view animation works.
Here's all the options.
There's billions of them here.
You can change the curve.
So CurseEaseInEaseOut means that it starts slowly and
then speeds up to normal and then slows back down again.
So my fade, that's the way it worked.
It would start fading out slowly and
then normal speed and then at the very end when it's fading
out, fade out a little slower.
Okay?
You can also,
I don't have time to show you all these things, but
you can look at all these things.
BeginFromCurrentState is an interesting one because I just
told you that the change happens immediately.
But if you issued another animation that changed
the alpha and you had this BeginFromCurrentState on,
then that animation would pick up wherever any other
animation is.
So that other animation might be partway
through doing the alpha.
And then I do another animation with this
BeginFromCurrentState and it's not going to start with it
at zero, which is what alpha is now.
It's going to pick up the partial, okay?
So that's one way where you can actually kind of over time
get the value, by issuing another animation.
Remember, all these animations are happening in another
thread off the main queue.
They're all happening out of time for you, okay?
When you send that last line of code,
alpha immediately went to zero and you're on your way.
Your code is still going.
The fact that things are happening on screen over time,
it's kind of not relevant to you.
It's relevant to your user though.
Okay?
Sometimes you want to change an entire view and
you can do that as well.
I'll give you an example here of a playing card.
So if I had a playing card that has a back and a front.
I might want to flip that card over.
Okay, so I wanna change everything in the view.
I wanna redraw the view basically, but
I want it to flip over.
I don't want it to just boop change,
I want it to have an animation where it flips over.
So you can do flips over and curls up and dissolves, okay,
you can do all those.
The way you do that is with a different UIView class
method called transitionWithView.
You just give it the view, the playing card view or whatever.
You tell how long you want the animation to take.
What kind of thing you want like flipping or
dissolving or whatever.
You give it the animation.
Inside that animation you're changing your view,
changing the attributes in your view.
Like, if you had your calculator and
you wanted to change from one graph to another.
In here you would change the graph.
Okay, you would change it so when it draws the next time,
we draw something different.
And then it would animate it, dissolve it, or whatever and
show the new version.
In this closure you're changing anything you want
about the view, any attributes, any properties.
So the next time it draws, it will draw differently and
then this animation will kind of interpolate between those
two states, doing a flip or dissolve or whatever.
So that's another kind of thing.
Now this one you're probably going to be
doing in your homework.
Okay, I think I asked you explicitly to do some sort of
animation like this.
Either this one or the last one, either one.
So yeah, here's the playing card example.
You can see in the closure I'm just changing the card to
be face up.
And so the next time it draws,
it's going to draw differently.
Okay?
And again, this happens immediately.
That card is face up equals not card is face up.
That happens instantly,
as soon as I call this method, okay?
It's just that over time, on screen, it will happen.
But it happened immediately, right there.
If the next line, I say if card is face up,
it's going to be the changed value, okay?
These transitionWithView methods,
animated with duration, they return immediately.
They do what's in the enclosure and
return immediately.
Okay?
If you're animating changes to the view hierarchy,
like you're hiding views or
removing them from super view and that's all you're doing,
and you want them to flip over and
go away, then you can use this transitionFromView to view.
Okay? Otherwise it's
exactly the same.
It's just for things that change the view hierarchy but
it's basically the same.
So there's no closure there because
the change you're making is change in the view hierarchy.
You're not changing card that's face up,
you're actually changing whether the view is
in the hierarchy anymore.
Yeah. >> I'm just wondering, so.
If you want to specify several of the [INAUDIBLE].
>> Yeah.
>> [INAUDIBLE].
>> No, they are.
That's a good question in this particular API.
Ask me on Piazza and I'll try and
some APIs you specify as an array, some APIs different.
It depends but most times, Swift is an eNom,
so you are doing something like that or combining them,
so ask me on Piazza.
Okay.
So that's it for today.
On Friday,
we have a great section which is UICollectionView.
It's great because UICollectionView is very
similar to UITableView.
You'll really understand UITableView
if you go do look at this UICollectionView one.
Monday's a holiday and the next week I'm going to start
on that physics-based animation.
>> [COUGH] >> Thank you very much.
>> For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.