[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> All right, well, welcome to Lecture 13 of CS193P,
Winter 2015.
Today, we have three major topics.
One which is the Application Lifecycle, which is all about
we talked about the View Controller Lifecycle.
Where your view controller kinda is born,
does a bunch of things and then, dies.
Well, the same things happen for the whole application.
So we'll talk about that.
And then, I'm going to talk about Core Motion,
which is figuring out what the device is doing.
Gyro, and accelerometer, magnetometers,
all that business.
And then, I'm going to talk about persistence,
which is making things be stored on the internal hard
disk of your device.
Of course, it's flash memory, but
basically it acts a hard disk, a Unix file system even.
So we talk about how we do that.
All right, so let's jump right
into the application life cycle.
But we first, I need to give you a little side
lecture here on NSNotification.
And we actually saw this briefly
when I was talking about the keyboards.
And you get this notification when the keyboards show up.
But I decided I'm going to take a couple of slides here
and just talk about NSNotification and
how it works.
Because it's actually a fairly important part.
Not fairly important,
somewhat important part of the MVC model.
So if you remember back to our MVC slides.
I had a little kinda thing that looked like a radio
station.
It was broadcasting from the model.
And then the controller would tune into that radio station
to find out that changes were happening in the model.
Well that's,
one of the things that make that happen is NSNotification.
And so, it's the radio station or
one of the ways of doing the radio station in MVC.
And it's really for model to controller communication or
sometimes global to controller.
Cuz sometimes things happen globally in your entire
application, as we're gonna see in the demo today.
And you need to kinda broadcast that this global
thing is happening.
And then particular view controllers might
be interested in that.
They'll sign up to listen to that radio station and
they'll find out that global thing has happened.
So how does it work?
It's super simple.
There is a class called NSNotificationCenter
it has a class function called defaultCenter.
You get that,
that's this kinda shared notification center.
And you just send a message to it called addObserver
for name.
And you specify the name of the radio station you
wanna listen to.
Okay.
It has a couple other arguments which are,
is object.
Object is who's the broadcaster.
Who are you interested in broadcasts on this
radio station from?
And you can just put nil there if you're interested
when anybody broadcasts on that radio station.
But sometimes you'll specify I'm only interested if
this guy broadcasts on this radio station.
And then, notice that there's a queue.
And then a closure right after it.
Okay. Queue and a closure.
So the queue is just saying
what queue you want after this closure to be executed on.
I think if you put nil there you get I think
the main queue.
Possibly the current queue, but maybe the main queue.
But might as well just put it in there.
Now notice NSOperationQueue,
I briefly mentioned that earlier in the quarter too.
You're used to dispatch_queue_t, that thing.
NSOperationQueue is just kinda an object oriented API on top
of the whole dispatching business.
GCD, Grand Central Dispatch.
So, it's very thin layer looks almost exactly the same.
But object oriented APIs usually will ask for
a NSOperationQueue.
That has a couple of class functions like main queue,
where you can get the main queue.
And you can create your own queues by just saying
NSOperationQueue open parentheses
close parentheses to initialize it.
So anyway, specify the queue you want.
And then, what's gonna happen is,
if anyone broadcasts on that radio station,
the following closure is going to be executed.
And that closure only has one argument there,
which is an NSNotification.
That NSNotification has a few fields in it.
But the really only interesting field is
the field called userInfo.
And the userInfo is just a dictionary.
The dictionary of kinda old style, Objective-C dictionary
with NSObject as the keys, AnyObject as the values.
And every radio station it broadcasts
is going to have kinda different userInfo.
And when you go and look at the documentation for
that radio station.
Which is going to tell you the name,
that you're going to addObserver for name.
It's also going to tell you what it provides you in
it's userInfo.
Okay, so let's look at an example of doing this.
So you can kinda make it more concrete.
Which is finding out when the user changes their text size.
So in Settings, here I'm just in Settings on a phone.
If I go to General Settings right here and
I go down to Accessibility, then I go down to Larger Text.
You can see there's this slider here, which I can
use to set the size of the text that I want in my apps.
Well, if you have an app that has text in it, or
that is sized depending on the setting of this,
you might want to react to that.
Well the way you get notified of that is you get
a broadcast on a radio station.
The radio station is called the UI content size category
did change notification radio station, 'kay?
That's the name of it.
Radio station is just something I use.
It's not really called radio station, okay?
So, that's the name of it, and
it's sent out by the UIApplication object.
Of which there's this one shared application,
which you get by calling that method right there,
sharedApplication.
And I wanna hear about this on the main queue, okay?
So I have my block.
It gets this notification argument.
Inside the notification argument there's the userInfo.
And it turns out this radio station, when it broadcasts,
the userInfo contains the
UIContentSizeCategoryNewValue- Key.
And if I get that key out of the dictionary,
the value I get is the size.
And there's a bunch of enums or strings for
it like UIContentSizeCategorySmall or
UIContentSizeExtraLarge or whatever.
So that's how you get it.
And so this could come at anytime because the user could
go to settings and set this at anytime.
And you'll just get this closure executed.
And it can be executed multiple times once you
register this.
Then it's going to get called whenever that thing changes.
That make sense?
So there's a lot of radio stations in iOS.
We're going to talk about Core Data,
object-oriented database for example.
That got some very important notifications where it tells
you that things have changed in the database.
That's the classic model.
Communicating to the controllers.
And I'm going to do a little demo where we're gonna
broadcast on our own radio station.
And I'm missing a slide in here,
I noticed, which is how to broadcast.
But broadcasting is very easy,
you just create one of these NSNotification objects.
And then, you ask the defaultCenter,
postNotification.
So it's a method in the defaultCenter called
postNotification, you just give it a notification,
it'll broadcast it, simple as that.
So we'll see that in the demo as well.
Okay, so that's notifications.
And they're important in the application
life cycle as you're going to see.
So let's talk about the application life cycle.
Really your application gets launched.
The user is using it.
Then the user clicks to go to a different app.
And they come back to your app.
Maybe, your app starts using a lot of memory.
Or does something else, that the system doesn't like.
Or the phone runs out of power.
And you get killed, okay?
And so, that's kinda the life cycle.
And you go back and
forth between being in the foreground,
which means the user's using you.
And being in the background,
which means the user's using something else.
That's the green versus blue in this picture.
But you transition from these states in a very orderly
fashion.
And we're going to talk about that transition.
So.
In the green area, so
you start out not running, that's at the top.
Obviously, your app is not even running at all.
Okay? Then you move to this
foreground state where you're, you start out inactive,
which means you're running.
Your code is running, but
you're not getting any UI events.
Okay. You're not really displayed
onscreen and getting touch events yet.
But you started up, you started running.
Then you move to this state where you're active,
which is your view controller is on screen,
it's getting touch events.
This is normal mode.
Okay?
This is what you're used to.
This is where you are most of the time that your code
is running.
But if the user clicks on another app,
then you can move to this state called the background
where you'll run for a very brief period.
I could be incredibly brief and
then your code just stops running.
Now you're not, you haven't been killed, but
your code is not running.
So there's nothing you can do in this state.
Now when you transition to this background,
you can ask for a little more time.
But if you don't, you kinda quickly go to the state
where you're not running.
Okay.
That's the suspended state down at the bottom.
So you stay in this blue area for a short amount of time,
this background state.
Now you can be put into this blue area other times too.
Like there's a way to tell the system, hey,
I want to wake up every once in a while and
go and fetch something from the internet.
So that when the user does launch my app or
bring it to the foreground,
I have got the latest information for them.
Okay?
So the system can wake you up in the background.
You'll run for a very short amount of time while you go do
this little fetch and then you go back to suspended state.
Okay?
Now, while you're in the suspended state, okay?
Down here and your code is not running at all.
None of your code is being executed and
you could be killed from here.
So you wanna be careful when you move from the background
state to the suspended state to clean everything up and
get everything ready for your death.
Okay?
Cuz you might get killed.
That's rare to get killed, but you could.
Okay?
So you have to think of being in suspended state as
I'm suspended and I could be killed at any moment.
So [LAUGH] you can't run any code when you're gonna be
killed, so you better clean that up when you're passing
through the back, creating through a background.
Okay.
So let's talk about how you find out,
as you move through and you can only pass along the orange
lines to get from these states.
Okay? So
when you come out of the background,
you briefly will be inactive and then go to active.
Right?
So let's talk about how we pass through.
So launching is just a matter of moving into the foreground,
briefly inactive and then you're active.
That's your application being launched.
Switching to another app is you started out active,
you go inactive for a moment.
You come around, you're in background for a moment and
then you go suspended while the other app gets to run.
Okay?
So that's the flow of switching to another app.
Now every time you make a transition along these orange
lines, you get notified.
So let's talk about, for example, own's,
of course killed.
You can be killed, your code won't run.
Be careful, be ready.
All right. So let's talk about
these transitions.
So right there, the little yellow circle is talking about
moving into this inactive state from not running.
Okay? When that happens,
you get sent this message to your application delegate.
You remember that AppDelegate file that I always drag out of
the way every single time at the beginning of my demos?
Well, that file is an interesting file.
It actually has a class in it called your AppDelegate.
Your AppDelegate is the delegate of your UI
application object and the UI application object,
you never subclass it.
If you want to customize its behavior, you do so
by implementing methods in the AppDelegate.
So one of the methods you can get sent,
one of the delegate protocol methods for an application
delegate is application did finish launching with options.
And that gives you a dictionary,
which we'll talk about in a second.
And so that, so
you're always gonna know the first time you startup from
not being running at all to being in this inactive state.
Now what's in the [INAUDIBLE] by the way,
you get all these messages sent to you to your
AppDelegate, but you also a get a notification.
That we were talking about in previous slide.
So you can sign up to listen to the radio station.
UI application did finish launching notification and
when you launch, you'll get a message on the radio station.
Now that's only gonna happen once per launching of your
app, obviously.
And the user info in that notification,
of course contains the same dictionary that's being passed
to this method.
Okay?
So what's the difference between these two?
Well, you know, if you put the code in your AppDelegate to
find out that you've been launched, you know,
it kinda has to be global code.
Right? Because you're just,
it's in you AppDelegate, it's kind of in this global place.
Whereas if a particular view controller wanted to find out,
oh, I just launched.
Okay?
It can have its code in itself, so
it can be more object oriented.
Right?
It can have its reaction to launching be just in itself,
it doesn't have to be talking to some global thing
like the AppDelegate.
And in general, you wanna be careful about the AppDelegate,
cuz it is a global resource.
And as you know, from all your computer science training.
Globals can be bad.
Okay?
Globals are generally not the way you wanna communicate
information, but some things are global.
Okay?
Like when we talk about core motion and the phone,
there's only one gyro, there's only one accelerometer.
That is global, okay?
To your entire device, certainly to your entire app.
Okay.
So some things are global, but
don't use global variables basically through your
AppDelegate to circumvent that.
All right.
So what's in this past dictionary,
this dictionary that you get?
It's basically gonna tell you why you were launched.
Okay?
Cuz you can get launched for a lot of reasons.
The user might have just clicked on you, okay?
And launch you, but
it might be a situation where someone air dropped a file of
a certain type that you know how to open.
And the system will launch you to open that file,
which is kinda cool.
We're gonna hopefully do air drop in our demo today.
You might have setup some boundaries, and
your phone moved into that part of the world.
So, it's possible to actually setup s big region and say,
when this device comes in this region, run my app.
Okay?
And if your app is not running, it will get launched.
To go deal with the fact that you just moved near the dry
cleaners or
whatever you put in there as one of your regions.
In iOS8, you can start an activity like editing a file
on one device, like your Mac and then walk out the door and
pull out your phone and keep editing it.
Okay? So,
it's kind of like you can continue activities, so
you might get launched to continue an activity.
Okay? You could get launched,
because a push notification arrives.
Do you know what a push notification is?
Basically, this service where third parties can send you
notifications.
So for example, if you're playing a game,
maybe its a turn based game and its your turn.
You can go to push notification and
it might launch the game to take your turn.
Okay?
So a lot of reasoning could be launched and
that dictionary is going to contain information about why.
All right?
Now, it used to be that an application didn't finish
launching with options, you would build your UI.
So you'd instantiate a split view,
you'd instantiate a navigation controller.
You'd put in there with a master.
You'd put to create your view controller.
Okay.
We don't do any of that anymore and
when you're searching on the internet for how to do things,
you're probably gonna find some old stuff that says,
put this in application did finish launching with options.
I'm generally a fan of not putting that kind
of code in application did finish launching with options.
It's really not what it's for.
It's more for
handling all these other kind of global events,
like somebody wants you to open a file or whatever.
Okay?
It's not where you build your UI.
You build your UI in your storyboard as much
as possible.
All right?
Okay.
So now you are moving, so you've been active.
Okay? We haven't talked about this
getting too active.
But let's say you are active now.
And someone clicks on another app.
And you go to this inactive state.
You go from active to inactive.
You're going to get application will
resign active.
Now, what do you want to do in this method,
or when you get this notification?
This is mostly where you want to pause your UI.
Because you've just gone inactive.
Okay?
It might be that someone's going to come right back to
you and you want to continue.
Okay?
So in resign active, you want to pause.
This is I think of as the pause method.
Okay?
You're going from active,
where the user is using your to this inactive state, pause.
Okay? Now you might be on your way
to going to into the background, but
you might not be.
It might just be that a phone call came in.
When a phone call comes in, kind of the current
application gets put in the inactive state,
you answer the call, and
when you're done it goes back to being active again.
Okay, so you want to pause there.
Now, what about going back to active?
So you were paused and
you transitioned to active, or you were launched and
you transitioned all the way to active.
This is where you want to, kind of, unpause.
So this is where you
would undo whatever you did in Resign.
So Resign and BecomeActive obviously are paired.
Resign, you can kinda think as pause my state.
And BecomeActive, you can think of as resume my state.
Now, of course, when you're launching for
the first time, you go through the Inactive state.
You never resigned Active, so you never paused.
So there's never, no reason to resume.
Okay? You still might do some
of the things you do to resume in that case.
But obviously that combination can happen.
All right. So what about this state?
So now you've gone to background.
So if they clicked on some other app,
you go into the background.
Remember, you only go in here briefly.
Okay? This is where you wanna
batten down the hatches and prepare for your death.
Okay?
Because you could sit in background for
just a few fractions of a second, go into suspended, and
then you could be killed.
Okay? Without ever getting chance
to run again.
So going into the background stage application did enter
background.
That's where you want to batten down the hatches,
prepare for your own death.
Save any unsaved information although you should probably
be saving that.
Most of you don't.
Most of the things like here if you start off threads to go
do things like you have a background thread that does
some saving, make sure that thread is finished.
And it is possible in DidEnterBackground to ask for
more time.
Okay? UI application has a method
which I'm not gonna talk about, but you can basically
start up a background task and get some more time to run in
this background stage before you go to suspended.
If you abuse that.
OKay?
Like you try to stay active forever, or for many minutes,
the system will stop granting you that.
Okay? So don't do that.
System expects you, if you as for more time,
to quickly get that done with.
Or to time out whatever you're doing, do something.
Because when you go to the background it really wants you
to shut up, okay?
Be quite, because some other app is running right now.
Okay, so that did DidEnterBackground.
When you get activated again from the background
because someone clicked back on you, this is where you can
un-batten down the hatches, right?
This is where you can open things back.
Back up a bit.
You're back in the foreground, okay?
Maybe if you had something saved or
you threw away something from the heap,
you can load it back up, et cetera.
So, this is kind of getting yourself back to life
after battening down the hatches, okay?
So, that's it.
That's the cycle.
That's how it goes.
The AppDelegate does a lot more things than just that
cycle.
It handles notifications.
It can do this whole thing, a state restoration.
So there's a way, kind of a mechanism I will say,
which I don't have time to talk to you about,
where you can essentially, save the state of your UI, so
that if you do get killed while you're suspended,
and you start up again,
you'll start up in exactly the same place you were
instead of starting up like a fresh app launch.
So the AppDelegate is how you do all of that.
Look that up.
Data protection.
There's a mechanism for
saying, hey, the data that my app accesses should be
encrypted whenever the phone is locked.
That's great because if someone steals your phone or
tries to break into it, all of the data's encrypted.
They can't see your data anyway,
even if they hack into it.
But you need to find out in your AppDelegate when that
gets turned off and back on, so you can find that out.
Obviously, opening and closing files, right?
Not opening and closing,
opening files yourself, files that you know how to open.
The Delegate gets sent a message saying,
please open this URL.
You have to register with the system for
what kind of files you know how to do, and
we'll do that in the demo here.
But then this application delegate method is going
to ask you to open it.
And then I mentioned background fetching where you
can, essentially, tell the system you want to wake up
every once in a while and do some work in the background.
And that's pretty cool.
Again, you don't want to abuse it, or
the system will start saying, wow, that guy's really a pig.
Every time I wake him up to run in the background,
he uses all kinds of battery, so
I'm going to stop waking him up so much.
But it can do that.
So AppDelegate.
A lot of stuff in there.
You can just go look at the documentation for it and
see all the things it can do.
Now in addition, question?
>> Yeah. I was just wondering,
I had an app once which had music, and
when I pressed the home button or even locked the phone,
it would still keep playing.
Shouldn't it be like turning that off?
>> Yes, the question is, what if I have a music app and
I'm playing music and
I switch to another app, how does it keep playing?
Well, that's one of the cases where you are allowed to be
running in the background.
So that app is running in the background.
And you have to sign up and kind of requisition your app.
You have to set a capability to do that.
But you can do it.
And, you know, if your app is a bad citizen and
says it's a music playing app but
it's doing other things in the background.
Again, if it starts using a lot of battery,
it's gonna get killed.
Or it's not gonna be given an opportunity.
You might make it to the app store at the beginning.
But eventually they'll pull you if you are abusing
the backgrounding mechanisms.
Because there are other ways you can, you know.
Voip apps need to be able to stay in the background,
you're on a phone call.
There are reasons to stay live in the background.
Some people think, IOS not really multi-tasking.
It absolutely is multi-tasking, but
it has a philosophy which is the app
that the user is currently interacting with should get
almost all of the attention of the device.
That's just its philosophy,
which I think is a good philosophy.
So anything that runs in the background,
has to really keep it quiet.
But music is one where it can play in the background.
So in addition to the Application Delegate,
there's the UI application object itself,
which is the shared thing you call this class function
shared application to get it.
And it manages all the global behavior in your app.
You don't subclass it.
But you can send it a lot of messages to do various
things like open a URL in another app.
So we talked about how the delegate is used
to open a URL in your own app.
You can call this method open URL in application,
and you did that in your last assignment.
So you can open URL, and
it will figure out what apps on your device handle that.
And it will open that URL up.
You can also register for
push notifications or you can schedule local notifications.
So local notifications are just
notifications kind of like push notifications, but
they're totally local and they're timed.
So you say, send this notification to the user at
this time and it sends it to them.
And then push notifications, as we've talked about before,
are these things that come over the network when it's
your turn to play your game, or whatever.
So you can register to receive those in scheduled
notifications locally using UIApplication.
If you're doing this background fetching thing,
there's a very important function called
setMinimumBackgroundFetchInte- rval.
That by default is never.
So you might go to all this trouble to say yeah, I want to
do background fetching and all this stuff, and then if you
don't call this method to set your fetching interval to
something besides never, you'll never get woken up.
Usually you set it to minimum, this interval minimum,
which is like, wake me up as much as you can.
The system is kinda cool for this background fetching.
It kinda watches when the user uses your app, and
the more the user uses your app,
the more it's gonna let the background fetching happen,
because it's gonna figure the more it use.
It'll even kinda look at times of day.
This person runs this app every morning at 9:00,
between 9:00 and 9:15, so
we're gonna let this background fetch run at 8:30.
'Kay.
So it's pretty smart system for that.
I told you could ask for more time when you get
backgrounded, you do that with this method
backgroundTaskWithExpirationH- andler.
And so you get this background task.
You get to stay alive then until you call end
background task.
If you don't call end background task pretty quickly
after you call backgroundTaskWithExpirationH-
andler, it's going to say I give up on you, and kill you.
And also the next time you ask for
a background task with expiration it's gonna say,
no I don't give that guy ones, he doesn't end his.
So you gotta really be sure you call end background task
when you do this other thing.
There's a little spinner if you look at device well,
maybe we can see it in, I don't know, Safari maybe?
You see the little spinner up there?
Right by the AT&T whatever,
wireless thing there was a little spinner that spun.
That, you can control as well.
You can turn that on and
off if your app accesses the network.
Unfortunately, it's a boolean, so if you have multiple
places in your app that were accessing the network you have
to figure out how to turn it on and off appropriately.
Yeah?
>> I don't think your phone is plugged in.
>> Oh, sorry.
Yeah. Let's see here.
It's plugged in, it just disconnects every time it goes
into sleep mode here.
So, I don't know, let's search for something.
Okay, watch the status bar at the top there.
You see how there's that little spinner spinning?
Okay?
You can turn that on and off.
'Kay?
And yeah keep reminding me if I refer to this and
it's not up there.
You can also find out about things like,
that preferred content size category notification,
well you can also just ask UI application what that is
any time you want.
And you can find out what state you're in,
are you in the foreground, or in the background,
are you active, inactive?
You can find all that out as well.
So U application has a lot of cool stuff in it as well.
So there's another interesting thing called Info.plist.
Dot plist because it's a property list.
You remember a property list is any combination of
dictionaries and arrays and strings and dates, in datas.
And Info.plist contains a lot of settings in your app.
And you can actually click on it directly.
It's in that supporting files area and you'll see it.
What you're seeing up here is the x code's property list
editor, which lets you edit an arbitrary property list as
you can see there.
And it'll show you all the kinda setting,
some of the settings of your app.
You can even look at this in XML format.
If you right click on it and
switch to source code mode you can see it in XML.
So this is that exact same property list in XML, raw XML.
But you usually edit the Info.plist things in
the project settings, which you get by clicking on
the project in the upper left of the navigator.
You see I've clicked on it there.
And then you can see there's General Settings.
So, for example, things like what device orientations you
support, portrait or portrait upside-down, or landscape left
and right, which you can see there's a UI for there,
that's gonna set things in your Info.plist.
'Kay?
Now I'm gonna do a demo today and
in the demo I'm gonna add some stuff to make my application
know about a certain document type.
I'm actually gonna do it by editing the Info.plist
directly, because it's a lot faster and, you know,
we're gonna be time constrained here.
But you usually wouldn't do that.
Usually you would be clicking settings here in your project
settings UI.
So the Info.plist you can kinda look through and
see what's in there.
A lot of that stuff's kind of arcane,
you don't really even, hardly even know what it is.
It's just for the application.
But there are some things in there that
are pretty important, pretty obvious,
like what document types do I recognize, things like that.
Okay, capabilities.
So, some features in your app, quite a few actually,
require enabling.
In other words,
you can't use them in your app until you enable them.
Now, most of these are server features like iCloud or
Game Center, or they're interoperability features,
where you're gonna be inter-operating with other
parts of the system like the Passbook or things like that.
Okay?
So you turn these on in Project Settings under
Capabilities.
You get this list right here.
This is the current list as of the time I took the screen
shot a few days ago.
And you just switch those little switches,
the on off switches, on or off to enable this.
Kind of a little bit of a warning about here is that
some of these things, the server based technologies
require a normal developer program.
The free University program that some of you are on,
doesn't really support that.
So if you wanted to do some of these things for
your final project,
you might have to join the actual developer program.
'Kay, so this is an FYI there.
If you click on the little triangle to the left of any of
these things, it'll actually give you
a little description of what the heck this thing is.
'Kay?
So you can click on maybe In-App purchases and
it'll tell you, oh, this is what enables you to, the user
to buy things to extend your app internally, etc.
So I encourage you to look through all these things and
see what's available.
It kinda gives you a feeling for
how much stuff there is in iOS and how little we can really
cover in just basically nine weeks of this course.
But, it's still kind of fun to look at what's in here.
Okay?
And these capabilities, sorry, question back there.
>> So for the app [INAUDIBLE] map to run your app,
would that be supported in this, or
do you have to do a different thing to create another map?
>> So you're talking about maps?
So the question is, if I want to use a third party map
API or something, do I need to enable this or something?
No. This is just enabling what
your app can do, what it's capabilities are.
So for example if you're a map providing app, you would go
here and enable your, you know, turn it on and all that.
You see what I'm saying?
The end-user, they benefit from whatever capabilities
these apps have signed up for when they were built.
Right? So this is a build setting
essentially.
And it has a little bit to do with the coordination of your
bundle identifier with what's going on at Apple servers and
all that stuff.
So it's more than just turning it on, there's sometimes,
there's some payload that has to be kind of arranged.
All right?
So the demo I'm gonna do here is kinda setting us up for
Wednesday.
I'm gonna show you how to do AirDrop to drop something into
your app, 'kay, from the Mac.
Which is really kinda cool,
because you got this iPhone and let's say you wanna import
something, you know, an image or,
you know, any kind of file, a pdf file even, whatever.
You'd like to be able to just basically drag it, drag and
drop it from your desktop.
So the example I'm gonna do here is on Wednesday,
I'm gonna build an app that if you go on vacation, and,
let's say, you take a bunch of photos that are,
have GPS tags on them, and maybe you even go hiking,
and you have a little GPS monitor,
or let the iPhone keep track of where you go, and
you wanna draw the track of where you hiked, or whatever.
Okay?
So we're gonna build an app on Wednesday that does both of
those things.
Let's you take some information about photos and
their location or a track and draw them on a map.
Okay?
Now to do that app,
we need to import that vacation information.
Okay? I went on vacation,
I need the info.
And we're gonna do that with AirDrop and
we're gonna to do it, air dropping GPX files.
A GPX file is a file that just has a list of GPS coordinate
related information, like waypoints that you were at
where you maybe took a photo and
the track if you took a hike or whatever.
So that's called a GPX file,
it's just kind of a public file format.
It's XML, but it's XML with a certain extension, GPX.
And I'm gonna show you how you can make it, so you can just
drag a GPX file into your iPhone app from your Mac.
Okay?
So let's first talk about how that's gonna work here.
So on the Mac, you just go here to AirDrop.
You've probably, how many people have used AirDrop for
anything?
About only by half, okay.
Interesting.
So AirDrop's really cool.
So we got a lot of people here with various devices.
And here, I'm gonna turn this guy on and you're
gonna see that he shows up right here, CS192p iPhone6+.
Can you see that?
And so if I have a file, like my Vacation.gpx right here,
you see this is a GPX file.
I can actually just drag and drop it onto here.
Okay. To transfer it to my Mac or
to my iPhone.
But when I do that, sorry.
Cancel.
Its too bad this drops all the time,
its a little bit annoying.
So, I'm gonna drag it again.
Okay.
Drag it on here.
So what happens right now is it says, oh,
AirDrop someone wants to drag this GPX file to your Mac, but
you have no app that can handle this.
So it's saying,
do you want to go to the App Store to get an app?
Which I don't want to go to the App Store,
I want to write my own app that handles GPX files.
So that's what we're gonna do.
We're gonna write our own app here to handle GPX files.
All right. So let's go to Xcode.
So we're gonna create a new project here.
Now this project is going to show you how to do
the AirDrop.
I'm also gonna show you how to do notifications.
Okay? Cuz that's an important thing
to understand how to do as well.
So, I'm gonna call this app Tracks, because it keeps track
of where you go on your vacations or
whatever with GPX file.
So we call we're gonna put it in the place we always put
everything.
Okay.
Here it is, right here.
I am not going to move the AppDelegate out of the way
this time.
Okay? So the first time, yehey.
We get to actually do something with
our AppDelegate, but
I'm gonna move those things out of the way.
But we're gonna sneak in there and look at info.plist, so
kind of get both of those things.
All right.
So here's our ViewController.
How do we want to do this?
Well, the most important thing we need to do to make our app
be air droppable for GPX is to register with our app that we
know what a GPX file is.
Okay?
And we can do this in our project settings over here
in Info.
You see down here at the bottom of Projects and
Info is Document Types.
So these are all the types of documents I know about.
And then also Imported UTIs.
These are all the basically URL like descriptions of
a file.
So I kind of need to do both of those things.
I need to describe what a GPX file is.
And then I just say, yes, that's a type I support.
Now, I can do all this by clicking the plus sign
here and here.
But I want to show you another demo.
So, I'm gonna do this is kind of fast mode,
which I'm just gonna go to the Info.plist, because this
information's going to be put in the Info.plist.
And I'm gonna edit it in source mode.
So I'm just going here and saying,
edit it as Source Code.
Now you can see it's an XML file here.
And I actually prepped all of the stuff necessary here,
which you can look through later at your leisure.
Wait, for GPX files, but you can see
it's basically that I say that it's got file name extent,
file extensions GPX, but that it is a XML file.
All right.
And then up here, I'm saying, the documents I support.
I support this, which is my own private GPX type and
then that's linked to the type down here.
So, I'm just gonna copy this and go over here.
And actually,
just paste it right at the bottom of this down here.
Paste.
Okay.
So, I basically put that stuff in there.
I can even go back to Property List mode and
you can see that it added it here at the bottom.
Okay.
So here's my types.
And if I go back to my Project Settings,
I can see them here as well.
I can see now I have one document type,
it's a GPX file and I can import GPX.
So that's the key thing you need to do to make AirDrop
work, it's just define the document type you
are willing to have dropped on you.
Okay?
Now, once you've defined that, now the system,
any time someone wants to open a GPX file,
they're gonna ask me if I can do it in my app and
they do that here in the AppDelegate.
Now you can see the AppDelegate kind of gives you
stubs for didFinishLaunchingWithOptions,
ResignActive, EnterBackground, Foreground, even gives you
a little explanation of when you're supposed to use those.
We're not going to use any of those, so
I'm gonna delete that.
Okay?
So you can go look at that in any app that you build,
it's always going to put that, oops, those in there, so
that you can find out about it.
Don't ever delete this thing, though.
[LAUGH] Var window.
The AppDelegate has a pointer to the window where all your
UI is.
And it needs to have that.
It gets set when the storyboard gets loaded.
It is possible to reach into your UI here through this
thing and start talking to your ViewControllers.
I recommend against that.
Okay?
You do not want to be reaching down into there,
because if you ever went into your storyboard and
changed whether something was in a split view or
in navigation controller, now this code's going to break,
it's not going to work.
And it also is not very object orientated in that MVCs should
be their own thing and
they should kind of work on their own.
They shouldn't need some outside intervention to be
coming in and talking to them to make them work, okay?
You want to think of MVCs as these objects,
essentially kind of meta objects,
even though they're made up swift objects inside.
But they have an API and they work on their own.
They're independent.
They do what they do,
just like any other well designed object oriented API.
All right. So the method that we want to
implement in our AppDelegate to open a URL is called
application handle OpenURL, you see it right here.
There's a lot of other things you can see.
There's, look at all these things.
Many, many things we can do here.
But we want handle open URL.
And all we need to do and handle OpenURL,
we got this URL is go deal with it.
So right now, I'm just going to print it out.
So I'm gonna say, url equals url.
Okay? Just so
we can see that our AirDrop is working.
And then you return true or false, whether you handled it.
So since all I'm going to do is print it out,
I'm gonna say, true.
Yes, I handled it.
Okay?
So that's all I'm gonna do first here.
We're gonna run just that and then I'm gonna do another
thing with notifications in a second here.
So here's called tracks.
I'm running it on the device here, as you can see.
Now the first time my app is installed where it is saying,
it can handle these new types, the system's going to
recognize, oh, this guy handles GPX.
Okay? So here's my app,
it didn't do anything, but it did register itself.
So now, I'm gonna go over here to my AirDrop again and
going to, hope this guy shows up.
So let's go back to our app here.
We're gonna run our app.
It's registered itself.
It says, oh yes, I handle GPX files.
So now, if I take a GPX file here, like this, and
drag it on, okay, does the same thing, it transferred
over, but notice the difference this time.
Okay, this time it doesn't say get app, it says, do you
accept it in tracks, because I'm running tracks right now.
So I'll say, yeah, I accept it.
And when I do, we're going to watch our console here
and its going to say at the bottom, its going to print out
the URL of the file after its been transferred.
So I hit accept and sure enough, right here, you see,
it's created this URL.
So it's put it in this place in my sandbox called documents
inbox vacation.gpx which we're going to talk about,
the file system, a little later in this demo.
So, this file, GPX, was transferred over,
put on the local hard disk, flash drive of our phone,
and made available to this app.
So now, I can open this URL up and do whatever I want.
So that's it, super simple to do AirDrop, it's just a matter
of registering those document types.
But, in real world here now,
if I had dragged the GPX file on my document, I really need
an NVC somewhere that can display this GPX file.
Okay?
Now, I guess I could go look at my window, and try and
look in a split view inside a navigation controller, and
find a view controller that can handle this GPX file, but
that would be really, really bad.
Really what I want to do is just have a radio station
that says, anybody who wants to find out when a GPX file
has been loaded into this app, listen to this radio station.
And then we're going to send a message on the radio station
saying, up, one arrived.
Okay, so that's how we're going to do this.
So let's start with the posting side,
where we're going to post on the radio station.
Now, when you have a radio station,
you need to have a name for that radio station.
I'm just going to create that as this kind of global struct.
I'm going to call it static let.
I'll call this GPXURL.
Actually, we'll call it notification.
So this is just a string which is the name of the radio
station, which we'll call the GPXURL Radio Station or
something like that.
Okay?
And so, all I need to do to post on this radio station,
whatever, is to get that center,
the NS notification center, default center.
So now I have the center, because I have to have
the notification center to either post or receive.
And then, I just need to create a notification,
which I do by saying NS notification.
And if you look at the creation of it,
you can create it with user info or not.
And I do want user info because,
when I send out on my radio station, I'm going to send
the URL along as part of my user info, okay?
So I want this one, and
the name of it is GPXURL.notification.
The object is myself, I'm the one sending on this station.
And user info is going to be.
Well I need the key, GPXURL.key.
We'll have to define that.
And the value is this URL that was just passed through.
There's no space here.
Maybe we'll go to a larger font here.
How about this?
That better?
Okay.
So I need to define this key, so
I'll put that up here as well.
Static let the Key and this is just a key in that dictionary,
that user info dictionary, so I'll call this GPXURL URL
key or something, I can call it whatever I want,
it just has to be a unique key inside this user info thing.
Okay, so, I've created the notification,
now I just tell the center post that notification.
Okay, notification, and
that's going to broadcast on that radio station.
So, anyone who's listening is going to find out when a URL
gets dropped into this app.
So now, how do we listen to the radio station?
Well, who wants to listen?
It's going to be this view controller over here.
So, I've got my storyboard right here and let's put
something in our storyboard like, how about a text view.
Where's the text view?
Here it is. So I'm going to drag this text
view in here, put this somewhere, maybe right there.
Okay, let's make sure we do our constraints, sorry, set
the constraints, let's take a look at these constraints.
Actually, I'm going to have the top space be
the standard value away.
Okay?
So I've got this text.
Let's get that out of there.
I've got this nice text field.
Let's go ahead and create an outlet for
that into our view controllers, control drag.
I'll call that textview, okay?
We don't need any of this.
Okay?
So, that's that.
So, we've got our text view outlet right here.
Now, all I'm going to do is when that radio station
broadcasts, I'm going to put the URL into that text view.
Okay now, on Wednesday, we'll do much more.
We'll put a map and we'll draw all this stuff, but here,
that's all I'm going to do.
So, I'm going to put this in viewDidLoad,
super.viewDidLoad.
Don't forget, by the way,
in your view controller life cycle methods,
you need to call super.
I noticed a few of you not doing that.
So, to make this work, I'm just going to get my center,
NSNotificationCenter, default center.
[SOUND] Default center.
Okay, I've got the center.
You remember that I need a cue to put it on.
So I'm going to do it on the main cue.
So, I'm going to do NSOperationQueue.mainQueue.
And, I'm looking for this URL broadcast
from the app delegate, which I can get by saying
UIApplication.sharedApplicati- on().delegate, because the app
delegate is just the delegate of UI applications.
So, now I have all the information I need to do this.
I'll make this even wider.
And I'm just going to center, add observer for name.
So here's the add observer for the name, right here.
Just the one we want, the one that has a block at the end.
The one we want is GPXURL.Notification.
We're interested when the app delegate sends it.
We want the queue to be that main queue.
And we're going to use our nice swift thing
where we can put a closure after a method like this.
Okay?
Here's the notification, right?
So we'll just say notification,
actually don't even need to put this
void business in there.
So there's the notification.
So inside here, this is going to be called every time that
radio station broadcasts,
in other words every time a URL is dropped in.
And so, all I"m going to do here is I'm going to say,
if let the URL equal the notification?.userInfo and
we'll look up in there the GPXURL.key, and
notice I had to put some question marks in there
because some of these are optionals.
Okay, this is probably not actually an optional.
But, and then, that is an NSURL because, remember,
that this user info dictionary, the values are any
object, so I have to cast it to what I actually want.
And now, I'm just going to say
self.textView.text equals Received this URL.
Okay?
Any questions about that?
So now, when I run this Trax,.
Instead of it putting it on the console,
it's gonna actually put it in the content,
that text view of track.
So let's go over here again.
Luckily this time it's showing.
There we go.
So let's go over here.
I'm just going to drag it on here.
Okay, it's asking me if I want to accept it again.
I'm gonna say Accept.
And there it is.
It puts it on there.
Okay, now interesting see it says it's Vacation-1.gpx
this time, where it was just vacation before.
And if I drag it on again, it's gonna be Vacation-2.
Okay, so it's collecting these things.
See Vacation-2?
So now I actually have three of these things that
I've dragged in three times.
Okay?
So you can see now how this ViewController right here
in an object-oriented way is very self-contained.
It displays GPX files somehow, and all it does is sign up to
the radio station that says I received one.
And then it goes and does what it does.
And again on Wednesday we'll actually draw the map.
Okay?
Any question about that?
All righty, that is it.
Back to our slides.
Where's my slides here?
Slides, okay, all right.
So the next thing we'll talk about is core motion.
So core motion is what's happening with the hardware.
And the primary inputs to that are the accelerometer,
the gyro, and the magnetometer.
Not all devices have all those things.
Newer devices have them all.
But older devices, some of them don't have it.
The class that you use to get all the information about this
is called CMMotionManager, so CM is core motion.
That's the name of the framework this is all in.
And so the motion manager, you really only want to have
one of these per app, because you only have one gyro, okay,
and one accelerometer, one magnetometer.
So you really want one of these.
So you want to put it in some global space and share it,
like maybe your app delegate would be a good place.
The way you use the motion manager,
there's really two ways to do it.
Polling, which is, you create one of these motion managers.
You check to see what hardware is available like,
is accelerometer available, gyro, or whatever.
And then you just start asking for the value over and over.
Usually, we don't do it that way.
We do it the second way,
which is, we check to see what's available.
And then if it's available, we say how often we want to
receive an update, 'kay, how often we want to get
the acceleration from the accelerometer for example.
And then you register a closure, 'kay,
a block of code, that will get called each time.
'Kay, so that's a much more sensible way to do this than
polling, and so that's the way we're going to do this.
Notice that I had mentioned checking
the availability of it.
Well, because some devices don't have a gyro, for
example, you have to check.
And you do that by just asking the motion manager,
accelerometer Available?
And that will return true if it's available and
false if it's not.
Okay, you can do that for all the different hardware things.
Then you start the motion manager reporting to you.
Now, again, if you're polling, you can just say start update.
And then it will start updating it, and
you can ask for the value at any time.
Okay? But we don't usually do
it that way.
We'll talk about that in a second.
And you can also find out whether the device is
actually looking at the accelerometer right now,
if anybody's interested in it, by saying accelerometer
Active, or gyro Active, deviceMotion Active.
We'll talk about deviceMotion in a second, what that is.
And you can stop it also, and
it's very important to stop it because this thing
uses a lot of battery, okay, so you do not want this
happening unless you're actually using the data.
That is very important to understand,
and that's true of the GPS location stuff as well,
which we're gonna talk about on Wednesday.
You really want to turn this stuff off if
you're not using it.
You do that with just saying, stop whatever Updates.
Okay? And that's true whether you're
polling or whether you're using the block-based one.
All right, so let's look at the data structures here.
They're very, very simple.
So, when you get acceleration data, it comes as x, y,
z in g, g meaning acceleration due to gravity.
All right?
So If I have this phone sitting flat right here,
it's going to be having the z-axis this way so it can tell
you this way and then y is this way and x is this way.
So if you were to move it this way you'd get a lot of x
acceleration and deceleration.
If you move it this way you're gonna get a lot of z
acceleration, deceleration.
And if you just get the acceleration data directly,
it includes the acceleration due to gravity.
So this phone right here, z is going to be 1.0 right now.
'Kay?
If I turn it this way now, x is gonna be 1.0.
Cuz it's got acceleration due to gravity.
Now if you have a gyro, you can get the acceleration
without gravity, and we'll talk about that in a second.
If you get the gyro information,
then it's going to tell you about rotation rate.
And it's going to tell you how fast the device
is rotating in the x, y, or z directions.
Okay, that's what a gyro tells you, is the rate of rotation.
The magnetometer is going to tell you
basically the magnetic field,
around your device, in each of the directions.
Okay.
That's what a magnetometer does.
It tells you magnetic field.
That's how you can detect where true north is,
for example.
Now there's a very interesting one which is
CMDeviceMotion, okay?
So it's another thing like accelerometer, gyro, or
magnetometer.
But the CMDeviceMotion is actually a combination
of those things.
So for CMDeviceMotion, if you ask for
CMDeviceMotion updates, when you get to gravity,
it's going to give you gravity.
It's going to give you the user acceleration
without gravity.
In other words, it will separate gravity out, so
you can find out where gravity is, where that's pointing.
Right? Where is gravity pointing and
where is the user accelerating, separated?
And it can do that because it has the gyro.
Right? So
it know what's happening this way, so it can tell you
what's acceleration and what's rotation.
Okay? And similarly, for
the rotation,
it can give you unbiased data about the rotation.
Okay? Because it knows fixed points.
Maybe the magnetometer, for example,
can tell us fixed points.
And, so now you can get the attitude of your device
with roll, pitch, and yaw.
You all know what that is?
It's, kind of, an airplane thing.
Right, so roll is how much you're rolling the device,
pitch is how much you're pitching it up and
down, right?
And then, yaw is,
kinda, how much you're rotating this direction.
So it can give you that pure information unbiased if it has
both the accelerometer, so it knows where down is, for
example, or magnetometer.
And gyro has them all, can combine them.
So CMDeviceMotion is a really powerful mechanism to
kinda get real data.
And same thing with magnetic field, okay?
So how do you do this with not polling?
You do this registering a block.
You just say, for example, for accelerometer,
startAccelerometerUpdatesToQu- eue.
You give it queue, like the main queue, for
example, where you want this block to execute.
And then you give it the handler, and the handler just
takes an argument which is the data, the accelerometer data,
and an error, if it got some sort of error.
And you can get errors.
And similar for the gyro, similar for the DeviceMotion.
And some of the errors you can get are things like
this activity is not authorized.
Because the user can actually go into their settings on your
device and say I don't want this app to
get motion information from me.
Okay, and other errors there, like requires movement.
Obviously if you're asking for device motion and
the device is sitting on the tabletop, it's not moving.
It can't give you any information.
You set the rate at which this closure is gonna be
called by set accelerometerUpdateInterval to
whatever you want or deviceMotionUpdateInterval to
whatever you want as you might expect.
It's in seconds, all right?
So, you don't wanna set this to high a rate.
Like if you set this higher then,
maybe 30 to 60 hertz, it really can't
barely even give you that information that fast.
And you're gonna be calling your block a lot more and
you're gonna be using a lot of power.
And so you really want to be careful to kinda do this at
a rate that gives you smooth response for whatever you're,
however you're reacting, but not overly.
In fact, you might get a smoother response if you
slow it down a little.
'Kay?
Cuz if try to update too much,
it might be a little too choppy.
So be careful with that update interval.
You can call that start gyro update with this handler
multiple times and have multiple blocks going on, and
that's perfectly legal.
'Kay? Even though you only have one
gyro, the motion manager can still call multiple different
blocks if you want.
Okay, or accelerometer.
Any time I use an example, gyro, accelerometer,
magnetometer, device motion, they're all exactly the same.
Okay, so, the demo I have for this is called Bouncer,
and what we're going to do is we are going to do a dynamic
animation, but we're gonna use real gravity, as the gravity.
'Kay, we're gonna hook up a gravity behavior to
actual real gravity.
'Kay?
So how do we do that?
[SOUND] We're not actually gonna hook it up to real
gravity.
We're gonna hook it up to real device acceleration.
So the user can kinda move it around and
also will be using gravity as well.
So as I move my device around,
I'm going to be having my dynamic animator affected by
whatever acceleration the device is going through.
All right.
So let's go here to Bouncer.
It's a new project again, it's iOS apps,
single view, Bouncer.
Okay, and put it in the place that we always do.
Now, one thing I'm gonna do for
Bouncer to make it a little easier on myself,
is I'm gonna make Bouncer not work in landscape mode.
I'm sure you'd like to do this for
your homework assignment, as well.
But we are just going to make a portrait only.
Just to make the code a little simpler, cuz it's a demo.
But we usually wouldn't do that in an app,
making it not work in landscape.
Users kinda don't like that very much.
Okay. So,
I'm going to start right off the bat
by creating a dynamic behavior, okay?
Just like we did in the last one.
So it's gonna be UiDynamicBahavior.
I'm gonna call it BouncerBehavior, 'kay?
Cause I wanna capsulate all the behavior of the bouncer
into one class just like we did in Drop It, okay?
So here our BouncerBehavior.
I'm going to cheat and go over to DropIt.
And steal a lot of the code out of there, so
let's go over to DropItBehavior.
Here's DropItBehavior, so I'm gonna actually copy the whole
thing and paste it over here.
[SOUND] 'Kay?
Now the differences between drop it and
my bouncing behavior are kinda twofold.
Well, really, one major difference again is
the gravity is gonna be driven by real gravity.
But also I want the elasticity to be a little bit higher.
Also, as some of you have noticed, you really want
the friction to be off, and the resistance to be off.
Okay, you probably want that true for your breakout as
well, cuz you want the thing to bounce around and
flow naturally.
So we do that.
The other thing, too,
is I don't really wanna call these things drops,
because bouncer, they're not really dropping.
They're kinda bouncing around.
They're just little blocks that are bouncing around.
So I'm gonna change those things.
I'm gonna do Find and Replace in project here.
And hopefully you've found this little gem.
And I'm gonna replace drop with block.
So I wanna call these things blocks instead of drops.
So I'm just gonna Replace All.
We don't wanna do snapshots.
I'll do it for both cases.
Upper and lower case, Replace All.
So now I have this block,
this bouncer behavior that works on blocks.
You see addBlock, removeBlock.
But otherwise, pretty much the same.
'Kay. I'm just gonna tie its gravity
to the accelerometer.
Okay?
Everyone cool with where I am so far?
So let's go to, and I'm just gonna do this all
in this view controller right here.
I'm not gonna create a game view or
do all those things because we only have ten minutes left.
Wanna be able to do this whole demo.
So I'm just going to put it all in the top level view of
my view controller,
which you would never do, you don't usually wanna draw
directly in the top level view of your view controller.
The top level view of your view controller is for
subviews, okay, you put subviews in there.
But I'm gonna draw straight in there,
my bouncing ball, just for expediency sake.
So I need a bouncer, which is my bouncer behavior, 'kay, so
that's just one of those things I just created,
all right, that has the gravity and
collision behaviors and
all that stuff that I stole from drop it.
And of course, I need an animator.
So I'm gonna create a UIDynamicAnimator.
And do the same thing I did before which
is UIDynamicAnimator, referenceView.
Self.view.
Okay? Instead of game view into
self.view.
So I'm creating that lazy as we did before, so
I need to make this closure be executed to do this, okay?
It's the same as drop it.
Oops, this is, must be colon.
All right?
So now I've got my bouncer and animator, so
I'm just going to in viewDidLoad.
I'm just gonna say animator, addBehavior, the bouncer.
'Kay? So now I've got this going.
Course, super.viewDidLoad, I just talked about that,
so don't wanna do that.
All right?
So there we go.
So now we've got an animator.
Anything we add now to the bouncer is going to start
being affected by the bouncer behavior.
If you, which we mostly stole from DropIt.
All right, so how many?
Well, I'm gonna just add a block,
a little red block to my view which
I'm gonna then be controlling with the accelerometer.
So let's have a little function here called addBlock.
It's going to return a UIView.
Okay, there's a block that I'm gonna add here, so
let's create a new UIView, and its frame.
Let's start out.
Let's do CGRect.
We'll have its origin be CGPoint.zeroPoint,
then I'll move it in the second to the right place.
And we probably want a constant here for
the block size.
So let's put a constant here, struct Constants.
I really take the extra time to do this constants thing
because you really don't wanna have magic numbers spread
all out through all your code, okay?
You really wanna have your constants put into structs or
grouped, or name space or something to get them so
that they're not scattered about your code.
Otherwise, people won't know what's really going on.
So, I'm gonna let BlockSize equal CGSize.
We'll just have block be 40 by 40.
That's a good starting size.
We can see if we don't like it later.
So now, let's move the block to where we want, and
I'm gonna start the block out
right in the center of the view.
So that's just CGPoint, and, we'll say,
view.bounds.midX and view.bounds.midY.
Again, notice that I'm using the bounds, not the frame.
The frame would be my views,
super view which like the window or something.
So I'd only use frame there.
Then we'll add that SubView(block), and
we'll return the block.
Okay, so now I have a way of basically
adding a block to the center of my view, okay?
So now that I have that, let's go ahead and add the block.
And I'm gonna do that,
I'm gonna add that block in my viewDidAppear.
So as soon as my view appears if the block has not
been added, I'm gonna add it.
Okay, and that's a common thing,
again, to wait until view did appear to do something,
because you don't want to waste your time doing it until
it's actually gonna be on screen.
So in view did appear, here.
I'm gonna call super dot view did appear.
And I need a little variable for my block.
I'm going to make it be red, so
I'm going to call it red block.
UIView, okay it's an optional, it starts out nil.
And if my red block has not set yet, so if it equals nil.
Let em create my red block just by
saying red block equals ab block,
which is that function I just called, so now I created it.
We're gonna make my red block be red by Jane setting it to
background color equal to UI color red color.
So I created this red block.
I'm gonna add Red Block to the bouncer.
And it should start bouncing.
So let's go take a look.
This is all we really need to do.
We need to, exclamation point there, okay?
So, that should be all that is necessary to make this thing
happen, so let's go ahead and run this, all right?
Just in time, there's Bouncer.
And sure enough, bouncer is bouncing.
Okay, now, it's bouncing exactly like drop it,
because I stole drop it's behavior out of drop it,
and so it's just like that.
Now, if I move the phone, I pick the phone up here, and
I'm moving it around, nothing happens.
It doesn't do anything, right,
because gravity is just set to be down at the bottom of
the screen which is the default for gravity behavior.
So what we want to do here is link the acceleration of
the device, the accelerometer to the gravity, okay?
So that when I tilt it this way,
this thing will slide down that way.
And if I tilt it this way, it'll slide over that way, and
I'll kind of, I can move it around that way.
All right, so how do we do that?
It's quite simple, actually.
First thing we need is a motion manager.
And I told you that really wants to be a global thing
in your app.
So I'm gonna put it in a global place,
which is my app delegate.
So I'm actually gonna go over to my app delegate and
get rid of all of this.
Okay?
And I'm gonna put a struct in here which
I'm gonna call Motion and I'm going to have a static in here
which is the Manager equals CM Motion Manager.
Now look, I'm trying to type,
how come Xcode's not helping me here?
Well that's because the motion stuff is in a different
framework that has to be imported, okay?
So you have to import
core motion if you want to use any of that.
As soon as you do that,
it's going to start escape completing here, all right?
So I could put other things in this motion struct if I had,
maybe I wanted the rate at which I'm asking for
these things to be global.
Maybe I'll put that as a constant in here as well.
But here I'm just gonna have the manager.
So everybody in my app who's gonna use motion
needs to ask the app delegate for this motion manager.
And that way they'll all be using the same one, okay?
Now I could have put this struct actually outside of
the app delegate and just said motion.manager and
had that be it.
But here I actually want to kind of explicitly make it
clear that when you are in this app.
This is where this app gets its motion manager, 'kay?
And that might seem non-object-oriented,
except that for again, this is a global resource.
We want to explicitly be sharing it, okay?
So, that's why I put it in my AppDelegate.
So, now I can get it, here.
I'm gonna say,
let motionManager equal my AppDelegate.Motion.Manager.
Notice I made it capital because it's essentially
a constant.
Motion.Manager is essentially a constant.
And so I'm going set the update in a roll.
Well first of all I have to always check to make sure
I have an accelerometer, it might be working on
a device without it so I'm going to say.
Motion manager, accelerometer available, sometimes people
escape complete and they end up putting here active and
they're like, why doesn't this work?
Okay, active is whether it's actively reporting
the accelerometer.
Available is whether the hardware is actually
available, so be careful there.
So if it's available then I'm just going to
start getting updates.
So again I'm gonna go wide here, motionManager,
startAccelerometerUpdatesToQu- eue, which is right here,
this one, okay.
I have to specify what queue I want these updates to come on,
so I'm gonna do NSOperationQueue mainQueue.
And, again, I'm gonna do the swift, put the last argument,
if it's a closure, outside of the parentheses thing.
I think there might be a way to do that with some clicking
magic, but, anyway, here it is.
Put that up here.
Oh, I see why.
Okay.
So here is the closure, right here.
And the argument is just the data, so I'm going to call
that one data, that's the accelerometer data.
And the error, I'm going to ignore the errors here.
Probably you shouldn't ignore the errors, but
in bouncer if I get an error I'm just not going to be
setting the gravity.
But there's nothing for me to do, so
I'm just going to ignore that error, okay?
And, in fact, can I undo that?
And say error while you're already inside, okay?
So here I am.
Now I just need to set the bouncer behavior's gravity
equal to this accelerometer data that I got right here,
which turns out to be very,
very simple since they're both in G.
They're in the same units, so it's easy to do.
I'm just going to say bouncer.gravity,
which is my gravity behavior, .gravityDirection,
which is a CGVector.
Okay, so CGVector has doubles or floats.
The data from cell rom is actually doubles, not floats.
So I'm gonna set it as, this as double.
And it's just the data's acceleration in x.
I'm gonna set that to be the gravity's acceleration,
essentially, in x.
And same thing for y, except for y, since zero is up and
I want positive.
Gravity be down, I'm going to say minus data
acceleration y, okay?
So that's it,
I've just set the acceleration due to gravity in the animator
to the acceleration of the device, okay?
Now one very important thing to do is,
I'm starting updates.
Never put code in the start update unless you put some
code somewhere to stop it, okay?
And the place to stop here,
since I'm doing this in the view did appear the obvious
place to stop it is view will disappear, okay?
So whenever this view goes off screen it will stop being
the eyesore that I'm on which is exactly what I'm on.
So here I just say.
AppDelegate.Motion.Manager.st- opAccelerometerUpdates.
And if it comes back on screen,
they'll start up again because it's view to appear, okay?
So if I had like a settings tab and I was going back and
forth, it would turn it on and
off as we went back and forth, okay?
So, see how this works.
All right, here's our bouncer, okay?
And see how if I tilt it up, it goes this way.
And, now, I'm tilting it down, it's going down.
Right, left, right?
And that can even kinda use it to get it going faster and
faster by using the acceleration.
Okay?
So you could imagine, I think we might even have made it
extra credit, make it make your paddle in Breakout.
Be accelerometer based, right?
I get the paddle going there.
Or make the bouncing ball in break out be effected by the.
I mean probably not this much effect.
You know, full gravitational effect but somewhat.
And if I set this down, although this table, I think,
is tilted a little this way, but.
See what happens?
You can see it settling down.
It's setting down a little because my elasticity is not
one, it's .85.
So all these bounce offs are not getting full effect.
How do you slow this down, there, okay?
Any questions about that?
Now I was, I had on the agenda,
which I obviously didn't even get close to talking to.
I knew it was going to be a time constraint,
is persistence.
I'm actually going to wait, and
talk about that next Monday.
On Wednesday, we're going to do MapKits.
This Friday, the section is on AppleWatch.
Okay, so that should be a fun one.
And then next week, in addition to persistence,
I'll be doing modal segueway.
Which you already pretty much know how to do because it's
just alerts for example, or just like mobile segueways.
But also talk about the camera and then,
if we have time next week, we'll talk
about internationalization of your apps.
It's really important to open your app up to large markets.
And then settings,
how to do settings inside the settings app, et cetera.
So we got a lot of stuff to talk about.
I'll trying to get to as much of it as I can in
the last few lectures here, all right?
If you have questions, I'm here as usual.
>> For more, please visit us at standford.edu.