[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Okay, well, welcome to Lecture 15 of
Stanford CS193P Winter of 2015.
So my topic slide today, I actually have topics for
this whole week, the two days.
This is going to be kinda one continuous demonstration.
Where I'm going to go back to the demonstration,
back to the slides, back to the demonstration.
Although today,
I'm probably only going to cover that first slide point.
And then, I have a demo pretty much the rest of the way.
If I have time left, which hopefully I do,
I will do the slides for the camera.
And then, we can start off on Wednesday with the camera part
of the demo and then move on to the rest of the stuff.
But, it's pretty action-packed.
I have a lot of stuff to cover,
especially in today's demo.
It's gonna be a lot more even than just modal and
popover segues.
I'm gonna talk a little bit more about notifications and
adaptations, things like that.
So there's a lot to cover.
All right so I'm going to dive in here though with modal
view controllers and I intentionally put off
the modal segues until towards the end of the quarter.
Because when people see it early, they're like, oh, wow,
I'm just gonna put everything up modally.
It's just so easy to do a modal segue.
And it is easy to do a modal segue.
But it actually has to be used with care because since it
locks up, you're out,
basically until they deal with what's on-screen.
The users can kinda be a little bit disturbed by modal.
Generally users prefer more free flowing thing where they
can click on something and then move back and
things you know, flow a little better.
But there are sometimes when it just doesn't make sense for
your app to proceed without stopping the user and
making them answer a question.
So modal view controllers is what that's good for.
We've already seen modal view controllers, actually.
The alerts, the whole alert and action sheet thing.
That's nothing more than a UIViewController
that we put up modally.
Notice that it took over the screen, didn't let us do
anything until we responded to the alert of the action seat.
And modal view controllers are just creating your own
things that pop up and
don't let the user proceed until you deal with it.
So here's an example of a modal view controller.
Here, I'm in the contacts app.
And if I tap on that little plus in the corner,
it's gonna put up a modal MVC.
So I'll tap on it, then modal MVC slides up from the bottom.
This is an MVC that lets you add a new contact.
And so that's something that you wanna kinda get it all
the way you want.
And say, okay, add it,
rather than it being kinda partially added all the time.
So that's why they use modal here.
Although, you could probably even think of a way to do this
non-modally.
But it's not bad.
Now notice that there's no back button per se.
But a lot of times where the back
button usually would be is a cancel button, okay.
Which will take them back,
but it will cancel whatever they're doing in this
modal view controller.
And then, often, in the upper right, there is a button,
a done button, or save button, or something like.
That will usually commit the changes in the modal
view controller, and then dismiss it, okay.
Now, this particular modal view controller actually
can put another modal view controller up.
If you look at this button here,
add photo, if you click on it,
it's going to put another modal view controller up.
It slides up from the bottom,
asking you to pick a photo from your photo library here.
I don't have any photos so I couldn't do it.
There's no back button here because you
either pick a photo or you cancel.
Okay, so you don't need a dumb button.
I would have argued that that cancel button,
I kind of feel like should be on the left.
This is an Apple app, so I guess I'm wrong.
But to me I'm always,
kinda looking to the upper left for get me out of here,
get me back to what I was before, but anyway.
So if we do hit that cancel button you can see that this
modal view controller then will dismiss, and
the other one comes back.
And same thing here.
Once we're done in here let's say we Cancel or we hit Done,
either way.
And then, this one will dismiss and
it goes back to where you were.
So that's the way modal view controllers work.
They just take over the screen, you do something and
then when they're done they dismiss.
Now there's a lot of different ways for
modal view controllers to appear on the screen visually.
And we will talk about that.
So as I said, you want to be careful with these.
They do block your UI,
it will be completely only doing this one thing.
Again, sometimes that's what you want.
But don't jump to modal view controllers as your a1 first
solution to every time you want to put an MVC on screen.
You got navigation controllers,
you got split views, you got tab bars, stuff like that,
those are usually better solutions if possible.
All right, so how do we set up a modal segue?
Very, very simple.
You've got your storyboard, well,
sometimes you'll get a MVC, like the alert MVC in code,
and you put it up with that present view controller.
And I'll talk about that here in a second.
But if you're doing your own MVC,
usually it's in your storyboard, you've built
the MVC that you want to put up modally in there.
And then you just Ctrl + drag to it.
But instead of saying, show or show detail,
you say present modally, okay?
And that's just gonna make your MVC appear on screen and
take over and it's as simple as that.
You can inspect the segue.
Anytime you make a segue you can always inspect it
to set the style of segue modal,
or push, or you know, the shows, or whatever.
And you can also inspect the style or presentation of
modal, which we'll show you in a second as well.
So, if you need to present a modal view controller,
not from a button, so you want some other action.
Like, for example, you had a map view and
you wanted a call-out button to do a modal thing,
which is what we're gonna do today.
Then you can perform segue from code.
You already know how to do that.
Or if you actually have the view controller in your hand,
you got it cuz it's an alert view controller.
Or when we do the camera we're gonna understand that
the camera thing gives us a view controller.
We can actually present the view controller using present
view controller.
Same way that we did alerts.
And that's just going to present it.
How it's presented is actually determined by a property
on the view controller that's being presented.
So a view controllers gets to say,
here's how I want to be presented modally, okay.
And that property is called modalPresentationStyle and
it's an enumerated type.
And here are some of the examples here, .FullScreen,
which is the default,
where it just comes up over the entire screen.
There's .OverFullScreen, which is full screen, but
it doesn't block out what's underneath.
Okay, so things show through,
the thing that is coming up on top of shows through.
Now you can't interact with those things behind cause
you're modal but they do show through.
And then of course a .Popover is essentially,
a modal presentation style cause a popover takes over
the screen also.
It just dims out the rest, you're working in your popover
if you click anywhere else it makes the popover go away.
There's some other ones, like form sheet,
which I'll show you in the demo today for on the iPad.
Sometimes you want to present something but
you don't want it to be gigantic,
filling the whole screen,
you want it to be a little smaller.
So we'll show you how to do that.
You prepare for a modal segue exactly like any other segue.
I didn't even put in any yellow on this slide,
it's just normal code, there's nothing special there.
Some people ask the question a lot,
well how do i hear back from my modally segued to MVC.
So like, in the contacts for example, I added a contact.
Well when the contact is added,
how does it communicate back to me, here's the contact.
Well, actually the MVC that put that contact adding thing
up, is probably sharing a model with the other one.
Which is to say, the database of contact.
So when you hit, add contact and you hit done,
it probably just puts it in the database, okay.
So it doesn't really need to communicate back.
But if it did need to communicate back,
the way you would do that is Unwind.
Okay.
Remember the unwinding segues?
You would just make the done button or whatever in your
modal thing, Ctr+drag it up to that little exit button.
You define the special storyboard ID action thing and
you would unwind.
And that's how you would communicate back.
A lot of times though modally presented view controllers
they do what they do and then you just dismiss them.
Because either they're editing this stuff in real time or
they are sharing the model so
they can edit the model directly.
So then they'll just dismiss themselves.
So dismissing without doing anything or
unwinding is pretty much the way that Modally segued to
controllers come off screen.
So how do you dismiss it?
Well if you unwind it automatically dismisses.
As you know,
unwind always includes a dismissal of whatever
your controller is being unwound from.
But if you're not unwinding, then you're going to call
dismiss view controller animated which takes
the boolean whether you're gonna animate the dismissal,
which you're always gonna do, pretty much.
And this is sent to the presenting view controller.
The view controller that presents you.
'Kay? That is the thing
that is responsible for dismissing you.
Now if you accidentally send this to the presented
view controller it's gonna forward it on to its
presenting view controller.
Although it can be a little confusing if
you have a presented view controller that, itself, has
presented another one and you say dismiss view controller.
Well, do you mean to dismiss the thing it presented?
Or dismiss from the thing it was presenting?
So that's why with the rule is, the presenting
view controller is the one you should send this dismiss to.
So I, personally, think it's wrong code for
you to send dismiss view controller to the presented
view controller expecting it to dismiss itself.
'Kay?
The presented view controller can get its
presenting view controller at any time with the method, or
the variable, presenting view controller.
Okay, every view controller that's being presented
knows it's presenting view controller and
then it can just send this message to it.
So we'll see that in the code of the demo as well.
So how does the modal view controller appear onscreen?
You've seen it slide up from the bottom, right?
That's the default modal transition style,
which is called cover vertical.
And you, again, the view controller that's being
presented gets to say how it wants to appear on screen.
And so this is different than, you know, the modal style,
like form sheet or something like that.
This is how the animation happens, 'kay?
How the actual transmission happens.
And so, again,
there's another property in the view controller that's
being presented called Modal Transition Style.
And cover vertical's the default,
means slide up from the bottom.
There's also flip horizontal, which will just flip over.
Okay, take from the old, the view that's presenting view
controller and the presented view controller,
we'll flip over and exchange places.
There's also cross dissolve where they'll fade out and
the other one will fade in.
There's even partial curl where the bottom corner
will kind of curl up and show the new view controller.
That one's a little interesting there because
once you've done that one, you can't do any more
modal transitions because it would make no sense.
You've got this curled up kind of look and then you
plant something on top of it, that just breaks the illusion
of this being just a little piece of curled thing that
lifts up to show you this modally presented thing.
Obviously the partial curls gonna be small view
controllers showing.
It's kind of a fun one though sometimes like in the Maps app
if you want to set some setting, so
turn traffic on, it'll just curl up the map a little bit,
you set your settings, and it curls it back down.
Okay?
So kind of fun though.
All right, so the demo I'm gonna do today it's gonna show
you all this stuff, modals, segues, all this stuff.
It's probably gonna take us most of the rest of
the time here.
And I'll try to cover a lot of other things along the way.
I'm gonna start out by doing some draggable MK annotations.
I'm also gonna talk much more about notifications cuz,
really, the only notification we did so
far was where we notified ourself.
So I'm gonna show you
a little more sophisticated notification where system,
another object is notifying us.
Then I'm gonna go back and cover pop-overs some more.
We covered a little bit back, way back when, in psychologist
but we're gonna do a little more sophisticated popovers.
We're also going to talk more about adaptive behavior,
which is to say when you have a modal segway happening,
what if it's on an iPhone versus an iPad?
It doesn't always wanna look exactly the same.
And so we're actually gonna get involved in making it look
how we want.
And as part of that I'm going to show you another thing that
I don't have any slides on but it's very easy to use called,
which is visual effects.
So there's a way to get visual effects,
like blurs and vibrancy, things like that.
So I'll show you that.
So you can see, a lot of stuff to go through here.
And if we have time,
we'll get back and do through the slides and the camera.
All right so we're gonna go back to Trax and
what we're gonna do here in Trax is we are going to make
it so we can add our own Waypoints.
Right now, Tracks just opens up the GPS file and
shows you the Waypoints.
And I'll show you,
remind us what that looks like in case we've forgotten.
All right. Here's our Tracks.
And it shows us these nice waypoints down here.
And we have a nice image over here, and we have this little
button, disclosure button, which will show us the image
in more detail where we can scroll around.
Well, what we're gonna do now is make it so
that if we long press, in other words, we press and
hold, it's gonna drop a pin there for us.
And then we're going to be able to set
the little thing like Valley Floor there,
or the views are spectacular even from here.
We'll be able to set that for our thing.
And we'll even be able to set an image once we learn
about how to do the camera next time.
But in order to make this work I'm actually gonna change our
track slightly, which is right now to see this image in more
detail, I press on this little detail disclosure button.
I'm gonna change it so that you click on the image itself.
To see the image in more detail so that I can free this
up to be our, we just added a user waypoint and
now we want to edit it, button.
'Kay? So this is gonna be our
editable user waypoint editing button.
So I'm gonna make that change real quick.
So let's go ahead and do that.
That's really easy to do, it turns out.
Right now when we build our callout view right here.
'Kay? Here's a view for annotation?
Okay? Here's where we
build our callout accessory views.
Instead of using a UI image view to build it,
I'm just gonna make it be a UI button.
'Kay?
Now, of course, once I make it a UI button, I also have to
make sure that I load this UI button up properly, so
I'm gonna go down here to div select annotation view,
which is where we currently load up that left callout
access review.
I'm gonna change this from being a thumbnail image view
to calling it the thumbnail ImageButton
because it's an image button now instead of an image view.
And of course it's not a UI image here, it's a UI button.
And then the only other thing is you don't set a buttons
image by saying dot image equals image.
You call a method actually called SetImage.
Image.
And it has, for state, because the button has various states,
highlighted states, other kind of states, but we're just
gonna set it for the normal state of the button.
So that's the only change I need to make
to make this work.
So let's go take a look at this and
here we can comment out now our little
right callout detail thing.
We don't need that.
Bring it back in second here.
But here's our things.
And so now here when we click it notice we don't have
the detailed disclosure on there anymore cuz I commented
that out right here.
But this is now a button so
if I click it now I get to see my image, okay?
So I haven't changed the functionality of my app at
all, I just kind of moved it to be click on here as
opposed to having the detailed disclosure.
Okay, everybody cool?
With that.
All right.
So, now we've done that.
Now let's make it so that if I long press,
which means press and hold, it drops a new pin, okay.
So how do I do that?
I'm just going to go to my storyboard here.
And in my storyboard,
I'm going to add a long press gesture to my map view, here.
So let's go down here, pull this up.
I'm gonna search for, long press.
There it is, right there.
So I'm just going to drag this gesture out onto my map
view, okay.
You can see that it appears over here in my
document outline.
Now let's bring up the code.
Okay, I'll put this right here in the waypoints
section right here.
So I'm going to control drag from this long press gesture
into here.
It's going to be gesture.
I'm going to call it addWaypoint.
It's what it does.
It's got the long press gesture as the argument here.
All right, so there's that.
Let's go back here.
Let's go up to here, okay.
So here is, where is that?
Here it is.
This is the thing I just added,
this LongPressGesture right here.
So what do we need to do inside
of this LongPressGesture?
Really not a whole lot to do.
I'm gonna say if the sender.state,
that's the state of the gesture, basically.
If that equals UIGestureRecognizerState.be-
gan, now I could do this when this long press starts,
which is, I'm doing.
Or I could do it when the long press ends.
And long pressed by the way, you'll get changed, also,
as you hold it down, you'll get a change happening.
But I like to do it when I began,
because I want instant feedback.
The user holds the long press,
as soon as it's recognized as a long press and begins, boom,
we're gonna drop that pin down there.
So they don't have to hold their finger any longer and
they don't have to hold it down and
say, hm, where's that, nothings happening.
Okay, so that's why I decided to do it on began here.
And to create one we need the coordinates that they clicked
on, right, or that they long pressed, they held down.
We need to find out the CL location coordinate 2D.
Where in the world they just did that.
And to do that we're going to use this method in map view
called convertPoint, which takes a point, so
let's get the location of the gesture in the map view's
coordinate systems, okay.
And it converts it to the coordinate system of any view
you want.
Which we're going to actually convert it the mapView's
coordinate system which is not much of a conversion, okay.
So that creates a view.
So we've converted this gesture to this coordinate
in the mapView, so now we have a CL location coordinate 2D,
here I'll click on this so
you can see that's a CLLocationCoordinate2D,
that's where the person pressed down.
So now I'm just gonna create the waypoint, and we can
create the waypoint using GPX waypoint, it only has one
constructor which is the latitude and the longitude.
Okay, so now we've created a waypoint.
Maybe we'll set some things in the waypoint, like the name.
We just dropped this, so
I'm going to call this the waypoint dropped, okay.
And then let's just add this annotation
to the map view, okay.
So that's all we need to do to drop something on there.
So let's go take a look at that.
All right, so here's all our points.
And I'm just gonna long press, you see it dropped one there.
And if I click on it, it says, dropped.
Now, I don't have any image associated with.
I don't have any little sub-information info
field on here.
So, we need to make it so that it does that.
But first, I'm going to make it so
that this can be dragged.
Because what if I dropped it here, and
then I looked in here closer and I was like,
oh no I wanted to drop it on the other side of that road.
Okay, I can't pick it up.
So I'd like to be able to pick this thing up and move it.
So what do we need to do that?
That's very simple as well, we just need to make,
back here remember, here's our extension to GPX waypoint that
we extended so that it would be an MK annotation.
We just need to make this note be a get only,
it needs to be set and get.
That's really the only thing you need to do to make
something be draggable.
Now, I'm gonna do that in a separate subclass here.
I'm gonna call it EditableWaypoint, okay,
it's a subclass of GPX.Waypoint.
And all it's going to do is override that var coordinate,
and it's perfectly fine to override a var
in a subclass to turn it into set and get.
So the get is just gonna return supers version of this,
okay.
And our set, all I'm gonna do on my set, is I'm going to set
my latitude equal to the new values latitude.
And I'm gonna set my longitude,
equal to the new values longitude.
Okay, and remember that latitude and longitude,
these are just properties in GPX waypoints, okay.
Well it has links, you know,
to our thumbnail images and all that stuff.
But really, the main thing about
GPX waypoint is just the latitude and longitude.
So now we've made this new class, EditableWaypoint, which
is a GPX waypoint, but it has a settable coordinate, okay.
So down here, instead of creating a GPX waypoint,
when we long press we're gonna create an editable waypoint,
okay.
One other thing you need to do though,
is that pin annotation, okay, the little
pin, we need to say that it's draggable, so I'm gonna say
view.draggable to set this thing to be draggable.
But I'm only going to do that if the annotation
is an editable way point.
Okay, remember is is kind of like as, but
you're just testing it to see if it is,
rather than casting it to be something else, okay.
So that's it.
So, let's go back.
Now our user waypoints should be draggable.
All right, we'll drop one here.
And I can pick it up here and move it over onto the other
side of the river there, okay, anywhere I want.
Notice that these ones down here are not draggable.
Can't drag them because they're not of class
EditableWaypoint, they're just GPX.waypoint, okay?
So draggable is really easy to do.
So now I freed up that right detail disclosure call-out,
and we're going to turn that into our edit uneditable
waypoint, right?
Change the name field, change the info field,
add an image to it, all that stuff.
That's what we're gonna make that be.
So let's go back down here.
Here's the old code we had for
that rightCalloutAccessoryView, and
I want most of that.
But instead of adding that little detailed disclosure
when the waypoint has an image,
I'm gonna do it whenever the annotation is an editable one.
So if it's editable,
I'm gonna put that little detail disclosure there, okay.
So now, we have to modally segue because this new MVC,
we're gonna need a new MVC that lets us edit the name and
the image of a wavepoint.
We're going to do that modally.
We're gonna do a modal segue.
We just learned about modal segues.
How are we gonna do that?
Well this is the rightCalloutAccessoryView
here, so I'm gonna go down to where the CalloutAccessoryView
is tapped, and right now it just always does the show
image segue way, which I still want it to do if we tapped on
the leftCalloutAccessoryView,
but if we tapped on the right one, I want it to edit it.
So I'm gonna put a little if-then in here to
that effect.
So I'm actually gonna say, if the control that we tapped on.
As a button which they both should be buttons okay, but
I'm just gonna make sure here.
If the button type equals UI button type detail
disclosures, so if it's the detail disclosure button, then
I'm going to do my modal segue to edit my waypoint, okay.
Otherwise, I'm going to do a little more of a check here.
I'm going to say, if the waypoint equals the views
annotation as a GPX.Waypoint,
which it should because the only kind of.
An annotation that I even have,
aur GPX Waypoint annotations.
But in the future, what if I added something else in there?
So I'm just being a little careful.
I'm also gonna say, if the Waypoint.imageURL does
not equal nil, cuz if there's no URL in the Waypoint,
then I don't want to segue to that image showing
the image view controller, right?
So, I'm just protecting myself a little bit here to make sure
that I actually have it.
Cuz I might have a thumbnail but
I don't have the image, possibly, unlikely.
All right. So, how about edit waypoint?
What are we going to do in edit waypoint?
Well, we're just going to segue.
So I'm going to perform a segue with identifier.
I need a new identifier because I'm not segueing to
the image thing, I'm segueing to an editing waypoint thing.
So I have a constant for that,
actually, called EditWaypointSegue.
Okay.
So EditWaypointSegue is down in my constants sections here.
It's Edit Waypoint.
Okay, so this is what we're going to have to make sure
we put in our storyboard for that segue.
Just like we put this in our storyboard for
the image segue.
All right.
So it's at a waypoint.
And sender, again, we'll have the sender be the view.
Okay, the annotation view.
Cuz that's really who's kind of causing this to happen,
cuz we're in its call out so it's the calling it out.
Now the other thing I'm going to do here is I'm
actually going to deselect this annotation.
Probably I would want to unwind,
come back and reselect it.
But I want it to be deselected because it's currently showing
the current state of the annotation,
of the waypoint, and I'm going to be changing that.
So when I come back, I don't want it to be there.
Okay, it's showing the old data I wanted to be,
I either want you to have to force you to redisplay it or
maybe, if I were going to add more code,
I could make it so that it redisplayed.
But, in any case, I definitely want this annotation to be
deselected when I segue it to go edit it.
Okay?
All right, so that's it.
That's all we need to do here.
We just need to go to our storyboard now and
create that new MBC that edits this thing and add this segue.
So let's do that.
Let's go to our storyboard, and
we're gonna be segueing from our map view again.
Inside one of the call-outs we're going to be segueing.
So just like we have this segue right here,
that came from this little thing.
Our new one's gonna come from this little guy, too.
So let's go ahead and get one.
Let's go down here and add a new view controller.
So I'm creating a brand new view controller.
We'll pop it up here.
Okay? Move it out of
the way a little.
And I'm gonna segue,
just the way I did before, from this thing.
Control drag.
Okay, to segue to this.
But this time I'm going to do present modally.
Last time we did show, we were in a navigation controller
down there, but we said show.
So this time even though I'm in navigation controller,
I'm still going to say present modally,
which is going to cause this new view controller to come up
over the whole screen.
Question? >> If you worked in
a navigation controller letter and if not,
which one would you suggest using?
>> Yeah, so the question was,
if I wasn't in a navigation controller.
If you look here.
See this guy right here?
He's in this navigation controller right here.
If I weren't in a navigation controller, would it make any
difference to this modal segue and the answer is no.
Modal segues don't care where you are.
They're going to take over the screen and show themselves.
Okay.
And the question of is it better to be or not to be,
if you're presenting modal it really doesn't matter.
But if you're in a navigation controller it's nice because
you can have this kind of segue which is pushing, okay.
And you could argue this whole editing of the waypoint,
maybe that should be a push.
And you go push to a place where you edit it, and then
you hit save or done, but it's kind of ambiguous then unless.
When you edit it, you're going to change it live,
like we're going to do our modal one.
So, I'm showing you this to show you modal segues, but
I actually, if I were really writing an app,
I'd probably push to this and
have it be live editing, where if I change something,
it's changing that thing in real time.
Cuz that's how I'm going to do this modal anyway.
The modals, actually, may be better when you are presenting
something that you're going to allow them to edit, and
then hit cancel, 'kay?
Versus Save.
That modal might be better for that, but
here I'm just trying to show you the mechanics of modal.
So here's out modal segue right here.
We gotta make sure we put its identifier,
Edit Waypoint, we're gonna call it.
You can see that segue says modal.
And I told you here that you can control things like
the presentation style of it.
And I'm going to show you that when we
go look at this on an iPad in a moment here.
But for an iPhone it doesn't really matter because it's
always going to slide up from the bottom.
That's the way iPhones present modal segues by default.
Okay, so we have this nice thing, so let's go ahead and
run this and see what this.
What we made happen here.
All right, so now I'm going to add a new thing here.
It's dragable, right?
I can pick it up, put it somewhere else.
It's here. It says dropped.
And now, when I click on this, notice that these guys,
by the way, don't have the editable thing.
They still have their image, okay?
But they don't have, they're editable.
But this one has this whole editable, so
I'm going to click on this and we'll see what happens.
Okay?
Perfect. Slides up from the bottom.
I'm this modal MVC where I can edit the waypoint.
Now we have a built-in UI to do that, but, here we are.
Kay?
So, now we're going to put our UI in here to edit this.
So let's do that.
That's right here.
It's going to be a pretty simple UI,
I'm just going to get a couple of text fields out here.
Okay, a text field for the name, a text field for
that little info field.
A label for each of those.
That's pretty much my entire UI.
One label is called Name.
I'm gonna add those, it will be my line.
The other one is called, let's call it Info.
Have that be right aligned.
We'll put this up in the corner here and
do all of our auto-layout constraints.
We'll put that there,
we'll put this one up in this corner.
Actually we'll have them align their baselines right there,
it's a good idea.
This guy.
Try and align.
Whoops.
Align his baseline if we can.
Yeah, there he is.
Yeah, there we go.
There and align the baseline.
Let's drag this all the way over here like this.
This one over here, we'll try to line these up.
Okay, one thing that I want to do here is.
So let's just set all our constraints here at all once.
I'm going to do it really quickly.
Again, you've seen so
many how to layout demos you don't see a little more,
but I'm going to left this guy to the trailing edge.
I'm going to hook this guy to the trailing edge.
I'm gonna hook this guy to the top.
I'm gonna hook this guy to the bottom, but
this is kind of an interesting one because I'm going to hook
him to the bottom with greater than or equal.
Because I really just want to make sure that he's
the standard value distance away from the bottom or
more, okay.
I don't really care,
I just never want him to smash into the bottom.
So we'll do that.
Let's go ahead and put this one here.
Leading space.
This one also, leading.
Let's put these two separated by a vertical space.
Let's separate these.
Let's separate this.
I want this one and this one, sorry, this one and this one,
to always be lined up their left edges.
Right, I don't want this to be ragged edged,
so I'm gonna line their left edges up as well.
So it looks like we got all of our things except for
vertical position for name.
Okay, that's because,
let's line up these baselines, baseline here, baseline here.
All right, so all gone, everything's lined up, okay.
Wow we didn't even need to update our frames,
we have this perfect looking UI here, okay.
Sound good?
All right, now let's wire these text fields up.
So to wire these text field up,
we need a custom subclass of UIViewController.
Right, cuz now this is just a generic,
if we look at its identity inspector,
it's a generic UIViewController, so
we need a custom subclass, no problem.
We'll do that, we know how to do that.
Okay, we're gonna call this our
EditWaypointViewController, cuz that's what it does.
This MVC that we're putting up, it edits waypoints so
we'll call it EditWaypointViewController.
Here it is.
Let's go back to our storyboard here.
I'm gonna change this guy's identity to be
EditWaypointViewController, okay.
So it's on automatic mode here so, we got our thing here.
I'm going to delete all but viewDidLoad, okay.
Let's go and hook these two things up, these text fields.
So, I'm gonna Control-Drag here,
we'll call this the nameTextField.
And we'll drag this one, we'll call it the info TextField,
okay, so there is our UI.
Now, we need to think a little bit at what's the model for
our EditWaypointViewController.
Can anyone think of what the model for
an MVC that edits a waypoint, what would be its model?
What does it do?
Edits a waypoint, right?
So its model might be a waypoint?
Yes.
Let's make it be the waypoint to edit, okay?
So it's going to be an editable waypoint.
It's gonna be the model for this viewController.
Anytime you're trying to determine, hm,
what's my model?
You always want to think,
what does this thing do, what does it operate on?
That's usually gonna be its model.
Okay, either how it functions or what it operates on,
that's usually gonna be the model, all right.
So this thing edits a waypoint, so
that's going to be its model.
So now, let's get some more space here.
Let's keep our view and model in sync, okay.
One of the first things we want to do actually when we
put a model in or add view is keep them in sync, so
that they're always reflecting each other.
So let's do that by having here, a div set
on the model that calls some update UI thing, okay.
And we'll do the exact same thing down here, as well.
So if you set either text field,
we're going to update the model.
What did I do wrong here, oh I don't have updateUI.
Okay, so let's go ahead and, func updateUI.
So we've got an updateUI, what do we need to do in updateUI?
Really, we just need to update our text fields from our
waypoints.
So I'm gonna say, nameTextField.text
= waypointToEdit.name, and
the infoTextField.text = waypointToEdit.info.
Okay, so that's it.
Let's also update our UI in viewDidLoad, that way,
if our model got set before our outlets were loaded,
this will catch them up to speed, okay.
So it's a very common pattern, here, to updateUI
when your model changes and also update in viewDidLoad.
Okay, because remember outlets are not set, unfortunately,
sometimes during prepare for segue, for example.
okay, so let's see what this looks like.
I'm actually gonna run this one on
the phone because I wanna show you
a particular problem we have with this UI so far.
Okay, let me put this on the screen here.
Okay, so here's our UI, I'm gonna just tap and
hold to drop here, okay, and now I'm gonna click on it.
I'm gonna press our new editing button and
here we have our UI.
That's good our UI's appearing.
A couple of problems here, one, no keyboard.
Okay, our UI has appeared here, but
if there's not keyboard that's not so good, but
if I touch on a text field it appears.
Okay, that's kind of good except for
when my the thing first comes up I probably want it to
have a keyboard.
So we're going to put in some code to become first responder
on one of those text fields, okay.
Right off the bat.
Another problem is,
I can never make this keyboard go away, okay.
No matter what I press, I press return, click on
[INAUDIBLE], and I can't make it go away, that's a problem.
Now, I don't have anything down at the bottom right now,
but when we start having an image in our waypoint editor,
then it's gonna cover up that image.
We need a way for
the return key on the keyboard that I'm pressing down here,
to make these things resign first responder, okay.
Let's fix those things really quickly, they're easy to fix.
Become first responder, we can just do in viewDidLoad.
I'm just gonna say, name text field become first responder,
so as soon as this thing is created it's gonna immediately
make that text field be the first responder, okay?
So that's easy.
Making the return key resign first responder requires us
to, if you remember from last time, become UI text field
delegates, and implement this method, text field should
end editing or should end return, here it is, okay.
So here,
when a text field hits the return key, I'm going to say
textField.resignFirstRespon- der.
And then we'll let it do whatever it normally does.
Okay, so that solves both of those problems.
Oh, whoops, one quick thing we need to do before
we do that is,
if we're gonna have this text field delegate method called,
we need to obviously make, oh, I did this totally wrong.
Sorry.
This should be, nobody caught me on this, but
this should be on the model, okay.
Add those on the text fields.
All right, it's the model that wants
to update the UI not the text fields, okay?
What the text fields want when they're didSet
is they want to set their delegates equal to self.
That's what they wanna do, okay.
Guys, pay attention.
I count on you guys to catch me doing these things.
Okay, everyone understand that?
The model setting that wants to update the UI, the text
field, just want to set themselves as the delegate.
See, you let me do another thing here.
Okay, there we go.
So now both text fields have self as their delegate, so
they're both going to call ShouldReturn, okay.
So let's try that.
Are we still up there, yes.
Okay. Again, here I'm gonna add one.
Click here.
Let's bring up our new MVC.
Here is is.
Keyboard comes up, excellent.
And if I hit Return, keyboard goes away.
And if I go to Back, it comes back.
So that's much more control.
And if you're doing this in the simulator, it seems like,
oh, this is all great.
But then when you run it on the device, you're like, oh,
well that's not very useable, okay.
So you've got to be careful to make sure things actually
are useable on the device.
All right.
That's that, so now we've kind of set up our UI.
But actually, there's one other problem with this.
Let's go ahead and take a look at this other problem we got.
Which is when I add a thing here is I might type in
the name, like I think I put that pin on the golf course
there or something.
Right?
Golf course, okay, snowed, whatever.
But now there's no way for me to get back.
[LAUGH].
You see?
How can I get back?
I've changed the things I want, now I want to get back,
I want to dismiss this thing and
get back, so we need some user interface here to get back.
The other thing is, when we make changes in these text
fields, it's not actually changing the waypoint, okay?
So we need you to fix both those things.
So let's fix the changing in the way point.
Now, this one I'm gonna use notifications for.
Because I want to show you a little bit more
about notifications that we really didn't cover
when we did the notifications last time.
So, text fields it turns out, they have a notification.
Okay, in fact they have a couple of notifications.
Three notifications, I think, even.
But one of them is ui text field,
text did change notification.
So you can sign up to hear from a text field whenever its
text changes.
Now, that's gonna be really valuable for us, here.
Because whenever the text field's text changes,
we can update our wave point.
Right?
So, how do we do that?
How do we make that work?
Well, turns out we want to put this in viewDidappear, so
in viewDidappear, okay, super.viewDidappear.
I'm just gonna call a method here,
called observe text fields.
Okay?
In an observed text fields, I am going to set myself up
to observe changes made in those text fields.
All right?
And, so I'm gonna do that with the notification center, so
I'm gonna get my center, which is NS Notification center.
Default center.
I'm also going to specify the queue I want this on which is,
of course, the main queue, so I'm gonna say, main queue.
And them I'm just gonna say, use that thing we had before,
Center Add Observer, for name which is this.
And the name of this notification is UI Text Field.
TextDidChangeNotification.
'Kay?
So, so far, this notification is nothing new to you.
Object is the object I care about if it changes,
which is, let's say, the name text field, in this case.
'Kay?
Queue is the queue, and the block, okay, I'm gonna do the.
Our magic trick here of
closing off the end of that, I'll get rid of that.
And then put our block on the end here.
So here are the argument, I'll just call it notification.
That's the notification that cames back, coming back.
And all I wanna do here is if I can let waypoint,
equal our waypoint to edit.
Okay, so we can get our waypoint.
Then, I'm just going to set the waypoint's name
equal to the name text field's text.
So every time the name text field changes here,
I'm just going to update the name of our waypoint.
And exactly the same for the info.
So all we have to change here is
info text fields coming in here.
And this is going to be updated to info.
And this is the info.
Now so far, so good.
You're probably like oh, okay it makes sense.
You haven't taught us anything new about notification.
But there's a very important piece of this
puzzle right here.
What happens when this MBC gets dismissed?
These observers are still trying to observe
those text fields.
Even those text fields could be have gone away,
they won't because these closures are gonna keep
those text fields in memory.
And also, self can never go away because
these closures are gonna be keep self in memory.
So this is a problem, so when you add an observer like this
and your NVCs ever going to go away,
which our last NVC never went away, it was the root NVC so
we added that observer for a name.
We probably could just leave it there forever,
because it's never going to go away.
Although good design,
maybe even that one would know how to go away.
But how do we go away?
And the answer is that this returns a little cookie, okay?
So it returns a cookie.
I'm gonna make storage for these two cookies.
One I'm gonna call it the name text field observer, and
it's a type NSObjectProtocol.
So NSObjectProtocol just means it's something
that used to be an NS object in the old world.
Okay, in the old, objective C world.
That's all that means for an NS object protocol.
We don't even know,
we don't care what's in the NS object protocol for
the purposes of this, because really, this is just a cookie.
It's just something that it gives us that we can give back
to it when we wanna talk about this thing.
So, here's this observer,
and I'm gonna say here NTF observer equals that.
I'm gonna say ITF observer equals that.
So I've added these observers and I got this cookie back.
Now, when I'm done observing,
I need to remove this cookie from the notification center.
So I'm gonna do that in view will disappear.
Okay, so, when my view will disappear, okay?
I don't need to look at those text fields anymore after I've
gone off screen.
They can't be changing because I'm not even on screen
right now.
I'm just gonna say
NS Notification Center default Center.
Actually, let's check and make sure they're not nill because
see I made these fields optional, so we'll say if.
Observer if let, let observer equal
the mean text field observer, than notification center.
Remove that observer.
So you can see how I've never had to actually look inside
and see what this thing is, I don't send it any messages,
I just get the cookie here and then I pass it along in here.
Except for this is observer, because I've lighted it.
Okay, so that's all we had to do.
Same thing here.
We'll do the same thing with the other cookie.
This is the ITF observer, info text field.
So this pattern by the way, of starting to observe something
in view did appear, and then stopping observing from it in
view will disappear is a very common way to do this.
Okay, because usually, any notifications like keyboard
will change, or something like that, there's keyboard will
appear, you don't care about that if you're not on screen.
So there's a perfect place to add and remove this.
Does everyone understand what's going on here?
You add to these notifications so
every time it checks changes,
it's gonna update our way point, but
we don't wanna be doing that when we're not on screen.
And we don't wanna have these closures,
this closure right here, and this closure right here.
We don't want them keeping self, and this text field
through self, we don't want them keeping them in heap.
When we, when our NBC goes away,
we want it to go completely away, out of the heap.
All right. So that's notification.
That's your little DL notification code.
Now let's fix that other problem,
the problem where there's no way to dismiss the thing.
It comes up and we can't dismiss it.
And there's a number of ways we could do that.
We could put a little Done button down in the middle
somewhere of that UI.
But actually, I'm going to do it by putting this
user interface in an navigation controller.
Now, why am I gonna put it in navigation controller?
Two reasons.
One, users are used to the look of navigation controllers
being the title bars and maybe there are buttons up there, so
it's a good place to put a Done button.
Also, it gives me a title, okay?
When this thing came up and
it was just a blank screen with these two fields,
it's a little disconcerting.
What's happening?
Whereas, if I have a title on top, like, Edit Waypoint,
it'll be clear what the heck is going on.
So I'm just gonna select this, right here, and
do Embed In Navigation Controller.
'Kay? So
it puts a Navigation Controller.
Now, I can, for example, put a title, Edit Waypoint, in here.
And, also, I can have a Done button here.
So let's go ahead and put a Done button in there.
Down here to Bar Button Item.
Here's a Bar Button Item.
We'll put it right here.
We'll call it Done.
And then let's go ahead and wire that Done button up.
Okay. We'll wire it
up at the top here, I guess.
Just Ctrl+drag from this right in here.
And, so when we hit Done, all we're going to do is dismiss.
So this is just going to be an action,
bar button item action, we'll call it done.
And, inside this Done, right here.
Sorry, we're going to go back to wide.
Okay?
Inside this done action when the done button is pressed,
I'm just going to say presenting
view controller.dismiss.
Okay? So, dismiss,
I'm asking the presenting view controller who presented me,
please dismiss whoever you just presented.
And, in fact, if my presenting view controller has presented
me and I've presented someone else, when I do this dismiss,
it's going to dismiss all of us.
Okay?
So, yes, we do want to animate it and, no,
we don't want to find out when the dismiss happens, okay?
Okay. So that's it.
So that done button will allow us to dismiss.
All right. So, let's take a look,
see if we fixed those two problems.
And we only have one more piece to go to wire this up
after this.
All right.
So, we're going to add, along with the long press,
I'm gonna click, I'm gonna edit it.
Here it is.
Notice now I have this nice title, Edit Waypoint.
I can set this to be again, golf or something.
I'm not gonna type too much because it's not gonna work
and you're going to see why in a moment.
But here it is.
Okay. We have this, we can return.
This is great.
Our NBC's exactly what we want.
Now, I'm gonna hit Done.
It dismisses it.
Now, let's look and oh, it still says Dropped.
Okay? Why is that?
That's because we didn't prepare that segue.
Okay?
And modal segue is like any other segue,
if you don't prepare it,
it's going to not going to know what it's working on.
So we need to set each modal, which is the waypoint to edit
and we do that in prepare for segue.
We already have a prepare for
segue in our GPX view controller right here.
Prepares for the image viewing 1, so
we just need to put another else if the segue's
identifier equals our new EditWaypointSegue.
Okay?
And in here, what do we need to do?
Again, just like any other one, we need to get the thing
we're pointing to, that we're segueing to and set it up.
So we're going to say if the, I'll go, what did I call it,
EWVC, okay, EditWaypointViewController.
If we can let the EditWaypointViewController
equal the segue's destination as and
EditWaypointViewController.
Okay, then now we've got this Edit Way View Controller.
We can set the EditWaypointViewControllers,
way point to edit equal to a way point.
So, we need to get our waypoint,
which I'm actually gonna steal from right here,
because we already have a nice line of code that does that.
Okay.
So there's our waypoint.
Now this, oh, sorry, this also.
Notice this is complaining.
See, this says error.
I'm trying to set the waypoint to edit to waypoint and
it's saying GPX waypoint is not an editable waypoint.
Ah-hah.
Because we declared Waypoint Edit to be an editable
waypoint, which is good, because it edits it, so
it better be.
And this is a GPX Waypoint, cuz I copied this line of code
from up here, where we're looking at the image URL.
So really easy fix, though,
we'll just set this to be an editable waypoint.
'Kay?
Now, this code will not work.
Any sharp-eyed people know why this won't work.
It's a problem we've had in other prepare for segues.
>> Navigation.
>> Bingo. Bonus points over there.
If I wereAron, I'd be throwing candy at you at this point.
Yes.
That editable waypoint view controller is
inside a navigation controller.
So the destination view controller is gonna be
that navigation controller.
So this is not gonna work, cuz this is gonna fail,
this as Waypoint finish.
Now, we've dealt with this in the past,
by putting a little if here, whatever.
It's so common to want to do that,
that actually I usually add an extension
to UIViewController that does that.
I call it content view controller, and
all it says is if I'm a navigation controller,
then return my visible view controller.
Otherwise return myself.
Okay.
So this is a nice little trick.
You can now, I can send to any view controller,
give me the content view controller.
If you are the content view controller,
you just give me yourself.
If you're a navigation controller,
then you give me the visible view controller.
So this is a really nice little extension to throw in
all your apps that are segueing to things that might
or might not be in navigation controllers.
So I use this by saying destinationViewController.con-
tentViewController.
'Kay?
Cuz I added this var to all view controllers.
In fact, I can do the same thing up here.
With this one, okay, our image one.
So, if we ever put our image, if we were ever transitioning
to show the image and it wrapped in a view controller,
we could do that as well.
So I almost put this in all of my
destination view controller segues.
Why not? Doesn't hurt, okay.
All right.
So now this will work.
Let's go ahead and run.
Okay, we add, we click, we edit, we go here.
Oh, notice now it says dropped.
Because we prepared it, so
it knows that it's the one that said drop.
So I'm going to change this.
Now we'll put back in Golf Course.
It's worse typing it in now that it's going to work.
Course.
Okay. And then we could say it's
under the snow, which it was when.
From this trip.
Okay, so here we are.
We've got this, and we hit done.
And now when we look at our waypoint, it's edited it.'
Kay?
All right.
Now, let's look at something else.
What's this gonna look like on an iPad?
It looks great on iPhone, really nice, okay.
But, let's take a look at iPad.
See what that looks like.
So I have an iPad here.
It's going to run on that.
All right.
There we go. There's an iPad.
Here's Trax.
Now Trax is incredible on the iPad because
it's got such a big screen,
we can really see all of our stuff very clearly.
And especially if we click and want to look at an image.
Wow, we got this really nice screen loading it up here,
but, whoa, look at that.
So it's a gray.
So it's actually quite great.
This is quite a great thing on the iPad.
But there's a problem with the iPad.
Watch this.
Let's add.
Okay.
Click on Dropped > Edit.
And we've got this humongous thing.
I mean there's no way we would ever use that much screen real
estate, okay?
So that's really not an appropriate UI.
Listen to me carefully.
That's not an appropriate UI for an iPad, okay?
And I know that some of you, who were putting on your final
project, oh yeah for breadth, I'm supporting the iPad.
And all you're doing is doing it on iPhone and
then hoping that this is okay.
But this is not okay.
Okay? This does not look
on the iPad.
So if you're gonna say I support the iPad, don't try
and swing this one by us, cuz we're just not gonna buy it.
Okay, we're gonna write down, doesn't really support iPad.
All right, so how could we make this UI look more
iPad-esque?
Well, there's a couple things we can do.
One is, we could go back to our storyboard and
we can change the transition style,
'kay, of this particular segue way that we have down here.
Where is it?
It's over here.
Here it is.
If, we can change, it's still modal, but we can change this
presentation, for example, to be form sheet.
So form sheet, it's iPad only.
This will be ignored if you set this on an iPhone.
The form sheet looks like this, and
it's a little better.
It's not enough better for
your final project, but it's a little better.
So here's what it looks like.
All right, so I'm gonna add one here.
Click on it, edit it.
See the form sheet, at least it's smaller, okay?
So it's a little better.
It doesn't look too bad.
It's almost good enough.
But really what the iPad wants is for
that to be in a popover, right?
I wanna be able to go here.
And when I click this little thing, I want a small little
popover that just has the name and info field.
And if I have an image, make space for an image.
That's the perfect thing for an iPad, okay?
So let's turn this baby into a popover.
And that's gonna break the heck out of our iPhone one,
but we're gonna go back and fix that too, okay?
But, first things first, let's make this into a popover.
So, how do we make this into a popover?
Well, I'm gonna get rid of this modal segue.
So here's the modal segue.
Let me zoom out so you can see it.
This is the modal segue that segues through this navigation
controller over to here.
So I'm just going to delete that by hitting delete.
I'm gonna have to move these over
closer because I have such a small screen here.
Then I'm gonna zoom in and then I'm just gonna make a new
segue from here directly to here.
I'm not gonna go through the navigation controller because
I don't want my popover to
have a navigation controller title bar.
Totally unnecessary.
It's gonna be nice, sleek, little popover.
So I'm just gonna go directly to here and
instead of present modally,
I'm going to do popover presentation here.
Okay?
Now when you do a popover, you notice I got an error here.
If I click on this and see what this error is, it says,
'Popover segue with no anchor'.
Okay? I've got some frames to
adjust here.
And we have this unreachable scene,
because of this navigation controller, but that's okay.
It's this popover error with no anchor.
So, what does that mean?
Well, when you do a popover, the little arrow on
the popover has gotta know where to point, okay?
Sometimes, it points to a bar button.
And here, I'm gonna have it point to the map view.
More specifically,
I'm gonna have it point to the little pin.
Okay?
So if we don't specify that then a popover can't work.
So how do we specify that?
How do we specify where, when this popover wants to popover
from this view controller, it shows up?
Well, one part of it we can do with dragging.
You see right here, in the inspector,
I've inspected this segue right here.
I clicked right on here.
You can see that it says anchor.
It says drag to select an anchor.
Okay, well, I'm just gonna drag over to my map view,
oops, except for I need to zoom in.
Okay? So,
I'm just going to select the segue.
I'm gonna drag to my map view.
And it says, okay, map view.
Great.
You're good to go.
And it game me no more error.
Except for this is not gonna work either because
I have to say where in the map view I want this to work from.
If I don't say where, it's gonna try and
point it to the edge of the map view itself,
which is gonna be off screen, which is useless.
I need to specify a little rectangle inside.
So how do I do that?
Where do I specify that little rectangle?
And the answer is it's exactly where we specify
anything having to do with configuring a popover.
Okay and we have already done this in this class but
you have probably forgotten, but for
your final project many of you are gonna do popovers.
So here is something to remember where you
set things for popover, and
that is in the prepare for segue for that popover segue.
Okay, specifically I'm gonna do it right down here, and
you wanna get the popovers presentation controller.
Okay? And you get the proper
presentation controller just by asking the,
make sure is it the right name for
these things that I call that PPC, I think I did yeah.
You just ask the thing that you're presenting,
give me your popover presentation controller.
Okay?
But you probably want to if let this, because you want
your code to work even if it's not in a popover.
If we change this back to be modal,
we'd still want it to work.
If you're not in a popover presentation this
will return nil, so you won't be doing the code in here.
So this code is only going to happen if this segue is
popover controlled.
So popover presentation controller, okay, if you look
at it in the documentation you can see that it's got, oops,
that's not a very good link to that is it?
Oh, maybe it doesn't return that.
Wait a minute. [INAUDIBLE] Okay,
PopoverPresentationController.
You can see it's got some things here like that source
view that we wired up.
Okay, it's also got sourceRect.
That's the rectangle inside the source view.
Or you can have a bar button item.
If you have a bar button item, you don't need both of these.
We've, so it's kind of either/or.
And also, it's got a delegate, which we're gonna use to
control our adaptive behavior and a few other things.
But, so that's what you can configure in
the popoverPresentationController.
So let's do that sourceRect.
Okay.
So the sourceRect equals.
We want this, basically a rectangle for
that annotation view so I'm going to say here,
the sender as an MK annotation view.
Okay, so sender, remember is this sender to the prepare for
segue which we passed the annotation view as the sender.
Okay? So
the sender is the pin that's causing all this trouble.
And I added a nice method to that called popover SourceRect
for coordinate point.
And you just give it a point, coordinate point.
And so let's calculate that point.
I'll show you that method in a second.
So we're going to let the coordinate point.
We're going to calculate the coordinate point by getting
the annotations coordinate and
using the map view to convert it.
So map view, convert coordinate,
and the coordinate is the way points coordinate.
And we're going to convert it to a point in the map view.
Alright, so here I'm just getting the point of our pin,
where our pin is on the map, and
then I'm asking the notation view, please give me
a rectangle that would be good for a popover to point at.
At that coordinate point.
And this code, this popover thing, is right here.
And it's really simple, really.
It just gets the width and height of our frame,
our little pin views frame.
And then it offsets it by the calloutOffset and
the centerOffset.
Don't worry too much about those.
But that's all it does.
So it's basically just putting a frame around itself so
that we can have the popover.
I just didn't wanna put that code in here and
mess it up for you, but that's all it does.
Now, we have this popover source rec.
Let's see what this looks like.
This is not gonna quite be what we want, but
we're getting there.
All right, [SOUND] Here we go,' kay?
I'm gonna long press to drop.
We're gonna edit it.
And we got a crash.
Okay. And, so why does this crash?
It's because we forgot to set our segue identifier for
the popover to edit waypoints, okay?
Probably you've all seen this.
No segue with identifier error.
That's easy to fix.
Let's go back to our storyboard.
Get our segue inspected.
And sure enough, look at that.
Edit Wavepoint.
All right, sometimes it's good when I forget to do
things like that because you get to see common things.
That's a common thing to do, is to forget.
Either to have the name be different or
you forget to put it in entirely.
All right, so now, here we go, like that, and Edit.
And we've got a popover.
Whoo!
It doesn't look very good, though.
Okay.
So, it's kind of close, but it's gigantic still, and
the whole point of this is to not use so
much darn screen real estate.
So why is that happening?
Well, that's because we do nothing to tell the system
what we would like the content size to be here.
And if you remember, the last time we did popovers,
we actually overrode the.
Property preferred content size and
return calculated content size.
Here I'm going to do it a different way.
I'm gonna actually set the preferred content size.
So I'm doing the same thing.
I'm just gonna set it, because it's a var.
I can set it, it's a settable var.
I don't have to override it.
So I'm just gonna set it to a size.
And so, what kind of size would be good there?
Let me make some more space.
We're still doing all this inside this popover-specific
code.
A good size for that would be, height-wise,
it would be if I just let the auto layout do it.
Wouldn't it be cool if I could just find out what
the auto layout thought the smallest size was?
Turns out, you can do that.
Watch this, let minimum size equal
the view controller's view.
I'm just gonna smash down the view controller view as much
as possible.
The name of the method is called
systemLayoutFittingSize.
And it takes a size, and
that size is the size it's gonna try to fit into.
And there's really two choices here.
One is, fit it into as small a space as possible, or
fit it into as big a space as possible, okay?
So I'm gonna go for small as possible,
cuz I want this thing to be small.
So that UI layout, fitting size, compress.
See, there's expanded and compressed.
So I want the compressed size.
So this is gonna give me the minimum size that that
view controller can be by using Auto Layout.
Okay, which is really awesome.
This is what the table U cells are using to size,
get the heights automatically with a layout.
It's a really, really great feature.
Now, I don't actually want it to be the minimum size in
width, though.
Because I wanna have some room for
the person to type in the name and the info that they want.
So I'm going to pick a size.
It's going to be a constant in my app.
So, I'm going to set my preferred content size,
equal BCGSize.
And the width I want is going to be this constant,
constants, whoops, width, constants dot, what did I
call it here, yeah, edit waypoint pop-over width, okay?
And that the height is gonna be the minimum size.
The height, okay?
So I'm using the minimum size for the height, but
I'm picking this, which I've set to be 320, which
is pretty standard width, and a pretty good width.
That's probably about the width of that is now.
But by setting preferred content size,
that tells the pop-over machinery
to make the pop-over be this size if possible.
It's only preferred, it might not be possible,
cuz the geometry of other views might get in the way,
can't do it, but this is,
it's going to try to make it this if it can't.
And usually, it can't.
So, let's go see how this works.
Okay, here we go.
Long press.
Top.
Edit.
Oh awesome okay, and now we can edit this right into
place here, golf course,
you know, foo.
Okay, and it's editing it on the fly, editing as do, so
if I click away and
then click back, I get golf course still, okay?
And, again, I can always go back, edit it again.
So this is really looking good.
It's not quite perfect.
It's kind of, if you look at the arrow that points down,
it looks like it's kind of see-through,
but the thing is white.
So, there's no reason that
this pop-over needs to be white.
It'd be really cool if it kind of, you could see back,
see-through it a little bit to what's behind.
Wouldn't that be kind of more iPhone-ish and kind of iOS-y.
So let's do that.
That's trivial to do that.
Let's just go into our storyboard and
have our view up here, our little.
Wavepoint editing view be transparent.
So I'm just going to select this thing.
Instead of its background being white right here,
I'm going to set it to be clear, okay?
So that's going to fix that.
So let's go see what that looks like.
All right, and click Edit, okay?
So you can see,
I don't know how well you can see it in that.
It might be washed out there, but I can, actually, see,
kind of, a blurred mountains there, scenery behind, okay?
And it, also, just kinda looks better,
the text fields stand out a little more.
It's all, just looks a lot better.
Okay, now, there's only problem with all of this,
which is the iPhone.
Okay?
Let's see what this looks like on iPhone.
Here it is.
Nice. Drop one.
Ooh, yeah, edit.
Look, yeah.
Okay.
So that looked absolutely terrible.
We lost our done button because we took it out of that
navigation controller.
And it's got this background,
just black, there's nothing there.
What's going on here?
Well, let's try to fix this iPhone thing.
One thing we can fix is that black.
The reason that that's coming black,
is because the default modal presentation style
is full screen, which means, take over the whole screen.
And it expects you to draw in the whole screen.
So it's just leaving that area black,
it's expecting you're gonna draw in that.
There's another kind of style which is over full-screen,
which just means draw on top of whatever is behind.
So anything that shows through,
you'll see what's behind.
And this is what alerts are using, things like that.
Even the pop-over was using that, it was blurring it, but
it was still doing that.
So how do we get that to happen?
Okay, well, to do that,
we actually need to use the pop-over's delegate,
which we did before.
So I'm going to set the pop-over
controller's delegate here to be myself, okay?
That means I need to go up here, and say, that I am a,.
UI PopoverPresentationController-
Delegate.
Be careful here not to say, UIPopover Controller Delegate,
It's PresentationController.
That thing is old, okay?
It's deprecated even.
So, it's this one you want, the long one,
PopoverPresentationController- Delegate.
And once I'm the delegate,
now I can control that adaptation behavior.
So why is that thing showing up
modal like that when we have it to be a popover?
Okay, we changed it to be a popover,
why the heck is it showing up modal?
Well, that's because of this adaptation,
okay, where the system is adapting to the fact that you
don't usually show popovers on the phone.
You show things full-screen modal.
So it's adapting.
So now that we're the delegate, let's go ahead and
implement the adaptive presentations style for
presentation controller, delegate method.
Thank God for escape completion there.
And all we need to do here is return the style, so
the modal presentation style I'm gonna return,
instead of fullscreen, is, overFullscreen.
Oops, not over [INAUDIBLE] overFullscreen.
Okay, so let's see what that did.
It's going to make it a little better, not a lot better,
but a little better, okay?
Here we go. Now,
at least we don't have the black, okay?
So we can see through, still not so hot.
We need that done button back for one thing,
without that done button we're done, okay?
So let's get that done button back.
And I'm going to do that by implementing another pop over
delegate method here which is called, I don't remember what
the thing is even called, oh yes, presentation.
It's this one right here,
viewControllerForAdapterPrese- ntationStyle, okay?
So this one right here is saying give me a view
controller to display this thing when I adapt, okay?
So what I'm going to do is,
I'm going to give it a navigation controller, and
tell it to use that instead.
So I'm just gonna say return UINavigationController.
The root view of the navigation controller wants to
be the thing I'm presenting, which I can get from
this presentation controller argument that's passed to me.
That's just controller.presentedViewContr-
oller.
ViewController, okay?
So that's it.
So let's see what happens now.
All right, we're here, we go here, we go here,
oh much better.
Now we have done, it still kind of looks terrible, but
we have done.
So we can say done, oh, excellent, okay.
So now, what are we gonna do to fix this see-through thing?
Well, I could just make it white again,
because now I'm returning the thing here, that view for
controller for adapter present thing.
I'm returning the whole thing, I can do anything I want.
But what I'm gonna use this to take advantage of is use
this chance to show you visual effects like blur.
Because we want really the same thing we had on the iPad,
where the pop-over comes up and it's kind of, you can see
the background through, but it's a little blurred.
We're going to do the same thing here, okay?
It's going to come up, it's going to be white, but
a little blur we can see what's in the background.
So how do we do that?
To do that, we, okay,
the way the visual effects work is very simple.
It's just a view, okay, a visual effect view,
and that view looks what's behinds it, what's behind it,
looks at what is behind it, and blurs it, and
then draws that as itself.
It's as simple as that, okay?
It's just, looks what behind you in the view hierarchy,
even if that's other views, or I don't care what it is,
it looks at it, creates white or even a dark color and
then blurs it, and now that's what it draws.
So all we need to do to make this blur happen is
put a visual effects view right at the top
of the navigation controller's view hierarchy
behind everything that it draws.
Okay, right at the top.
And we know how to insert something at the top of
the view hierarchy, right?
We just put it at index zero in the subviews list.
It'll be right in the back.
Okay, and everything else will be in front.
Now, if I put it right in the back of the navigation
control, the thing that's behind the visual effect view
is gonna be that map view.
Because it's clear and so,
we look back and whoa, there's map view there.
So it's gonna blur that, that's exactly what we want.
All right, so to do this we just need to say I'm gonna
let nav con equal this.
Okay, so there's your navigation controller.
And then I'm gonna say let a visualEffectView equal
UIVisualEffectView.
Okay, that's this view that does what I was talking about.
And it wants to know what effect you wanna apply.
There's a couple of effects, vibrancy and blur.
So we're gonna do blur.
So I want the blur effect.
And the blur effect I want is with style, extra light.
So, extra light is a very light colored thing,
almost white, with the blur in there.
There's also dark and just light.
Then I'm going to set the visual effect views frame
equal to the navCon's view.bounds.
So I want to totally fill the top level of the navigation
controller.
And then I'm just going to add this
thing to the view hierarchy of my navigation controller.
VisualEffectView, and I'm gonna put it at index zero.
Okay which means it's in the back of absolutely everything.
And then I'm going to return the navigation controller.
Okay, here we go, all right.
Click.
Boom.
Edit.
Blur.
So this looks pretty good.
This actually looks slightly better than being all white,
it kind of gives users a little bit of context to where
they were.
Still works perfectly fine here.
Our favorite golf course, it's under the snow, okay?
Hit done, go here.
It's working.
And just to make sure that we didn't break anything on
the iPad, let's go run it over there one more time.
Now, we can't possibly have broken anything here,
because, famous last words, but [LAUGH] we can't,
because all we changed was the adaptive stuff.
And on the iPad, it doesn't adapt,
because the iPad is regular in both width and
height, it never has to adapt to being in a compact space.
So here we go.
Click on here.
Bingo.
Okay, so that's it.
Perfect timing.
Almost.
Next time, we will pick up with slides that tell you how
to do the camera.
And then we'll enhance our editor here to let you take
a picture.
And we'll enhance our popover right here,
to show the picture right in the pop-over, okay?
And then after that we'll talk a little bit about
persistence, and we'll save the image in the file system.
Show you how to do that.
Okay, thank you very much.
I'm here if you have any questions as usual.
>> For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.