[MUSIC]
音乐
Stanford University.
斯坦福大学
Okay well, welcome to lecture 16 of Stanford CS193p,
好的，欢迎来到斯坦福 CS193p 2015 冬季课程，
winter of 2015.
第16课。
So today,
今天，
we're going to be talking about three major topics.
我们将要讲到三个主要的主题。
One is the camera, how to basically take a picture with
第一个是 Camera，怎么样基本的使用相机拍照
the camera or get video from the camera.
或者使用相机拍摄视频
Then persistence which is an important topic about how to
接下来是 Persistence，一个重要的话题关于
store stuff in the flash memory of your phone,
如何往你手机的内存中存储东西，
and a lot of you have already kind of dived into
很多同学已经钻研了这个
this as part of your final project, but I'm just gonna
在他们的 Final Project 中，但是我仅仅只是
kind of give you a tour of the various ways that can be done.
给你们介绍一下各种完成这个话题的方法。
And then the last one is kind of an interesting segue.
最后一个话题是关于一个有趣的 Segue。
I leave it for last because it's kind of requires you to
我把这个放在最后，因为这需要你们
be a little bit of a visual thinker, to see what's
有一点，是一个视觉思考者（Visual Thinker），来思考
happening when we do it, but it's called an embed segue,
我们在使用这个 Segue 时发生了什么，这个被叫做 Embed Segue，
which is where we basically take one MVC.
这个基本上就是我们拿一个 MVC，
And we embed its view into another MVC's view hierarchy
然后我们把它的 View 嵌入到另一个 MVC 的 View 中去
which is kind of fun.
挺有趣的。
So let's dive in right in to the camera.
好，让我们直接开始进入 Camera
The camera is accessed via this file or
Camera 可通过这个文件或者说
this class called UIImagePickerController.
这个被叫做 UIImagePickerController 的类来访问。
It is a UIViewController, sub-class actually of
它是一个 UIViewController，我认为
UINavigationController, I believe.
它实际上是 UINavigationController 的子类。
And it's very simple to use.
并且使用起来很简单
You really just configure it and
你只要配置好它然后
then you put it up modally.
把它设置成 Modally。
Okay?
So there's really nothing more to it than that.
真的没有其他要做的了。
We learned about how to put things up modally last time
我们学习了怎样把东西设置成 Modally，在上次
with presentViewController.
和 presentViewController 一起。
That's all you're gonna have to do.
这就是我们要做的所有的事了。
So, the process of using the UIImagePickerController
所以，使用 UIImagePickerController
to get something from the camera,
来从相机获得某些东西的过程，
is, you create it, and you set its delegate.
就是，你创建一个UIImagePickerController，然后设置它的委托。
It won't do anything without its delegate,
如果没有委托它不能做任何事，
so you have to set its delegate.
所以你需要设置它的委托。
Then you're gonna configure it, for you know?
然后你要配置它，比如说
Do you want just still images or video, or
你只是想要图像或者视频
that kind of stuff?
这些东西？
Do you want users to be able to edit the pictures they've
你想要用户能够编辑他们
taken before
以前照的照片
They import them into your app, etc.
他们导入以前的照片到你的 App，等等
Then you just present it with presentViewController.
然你你通过 presentViewController 展示出来，
And then you're gonna respond to delegate methods that tell
接下来你将要对委托作出反映，委托告诉你
you, okay, I took a photo, here's the image data,
我拍了一张照，这是图像的数据，
or the video, the URL of the video, that the user took.
或者是用户拍摄的视频，或者是视频的 URL
So that's pretty much it.
就是这么些。
Each device.
每个设备，
Kinda has different hardware, although that's becoming less
各种不同的硬件，虽然这个话随着时间的流逝
and less true as the years go by.
越来越不对了。
It used to be that there were some iOS devices that didn't
那就是有一些 iOS 设备
even have a camera at all.
根本就没有相机。
But certainly there were early on iOS devices that could
不过现在有一些早期的 iOS 设备
Do still images, but couldn't do video for example.
可以拍照但是不能拍摄视频。
So as with all the hardware things, whether it's you know,
所以对于这些关于硬件的东西来说，不管是
Core Motion or any of those things we always wanna ask and
CoreMotion 或者其他的，我们总是会先问问并且
see what we can do first.
看看我们能干什么。
So it's very easy for the ImagePickerController it has
这件事对 ImagePickerController 是非常简单的
a class function called isSourceTypeAvailable
它有一个类方法叫做 isSourceTypeAvailable。
And there's three different sources for images or
对图像和视频来说，有三个来源
video to come into your app.
来进入你的 App
One is the camera, obviously.
第一个显然是相机。
Another one is the saved photos album,
第二个是保存的图片专辑（Photos Album），
that's essentially the camera roll.
这个其实就是 Camera Roll。
Right, things that they've taken with the camera.
没错，就是那些早就被相机拍下来的东西。
And then there's the photo library,
最后是 Photo Library，
which is the same thing they see in the photos app, okay.
就是跟你在图片 App 里看到的那个是一个东西。
So you can kinda pick which one of those things.
所以你可以选择一个来源
You wanna get your image or video from and
来获得照片或者视频。
they're a little bit different.
他们有一点点的不同。
photo library and the saved photos album
Photo Library 和保存的图片专辑（photo album）
are treated pretty much exactly the same, but
基本上可以当作一样来对待
the camera is a little bit different in how
不过相机在如何展示出方面有一点不同
it's presented, so we'll talk about that in a moment.
所以让我们来讲一下。
Once you know your source type then you're gonna say,
一旦你之道了来源的类型，然后你会问，
what are the available media types, image or video.
可用的媒体类型是什么？图片还是视频？
Or both.
或者两个都是。
Now it's almost not even worth checking for image anymore.
现在你根本不值得去为图片检查。
Because if you have a camera, it can get an image.
因为你现在的来源是相机，相机可以拍照。
So, I think it'd probably be okay if you just never even
所以，我觉得这可能是可以的，如果你从不
called this available media types for source type,
调用这个 availableMediaTypesForSourceType(Camera) 方法
if you're trying to get.
如果你在试图获得
An image, okay, because it's gonna be there.
一张图片，因为图片在那会有。
But if you wanna get video, you definitely should call
不过如果你想要获得视频，你绝对应该调用
this in case someone has an older iPhone that won't,
这个方法以防某人的旧 iPhone 不能，
doesn't capture video.
无法拍摄视频。
Now these two types, the kuTTypeImage and
这两个类型，kuTTypeImage 和
kuTTypeMovie, which are basically strings that
kuTTypeMovie，实际上就是能
specify these two media types.
区分这两个媒体类型的字符串。
Strangely, they come from this
奇怪的是，他们来自一个
Framework that your otherwise never gonna import which is
除了这个情况外你永远不会想导入的 Framework
the mobile core services framework.
就是 MobileCoreServices Framework。
So if you wanna use those two types right there or
所以如果你想使用这两个类型
two constants KUTType images and movie.
或者两个常量 KUTTypeImages 和 KUTTypeMovie
You need to import mobile core services.
你需要导入 MobileCoreServices。
Okay?
I'm kinda lingering on this one because this is some
我讲这个讲了很久因为这是
people forget.
一些人经常忘记这事。
And they're just like what the heck?
然后他们会说一些比如 这是什么鬼错误？
Because if you search in the documentation it's kind of
因为如果你在文档中搜索,
hard to find.
这很难找到说
That you're supposed to do this.
你应该导入 MobileCoreServices。
Whatever.
不管怎么说
So I made a special slide and emphasize it there for you.
所以我做了幻灯片来强调这个事情。
You can obviously ask UIImagePickerController
你显然可以问 UIImagePickerController 要
for more detail even than this.
比这更多的细节。
Is there a camera and what kind of things can it take?
比如是不是摄像头？它可以拍摄什么，图片或者视频？
You can say, is there a front camera?
在比如那是不是前置摄像头？
Is there a rear camera?
是不是后置摄像头？
Which you might care if you have an app that's like selfie
你可能会关心这些如果你的 App
oriented.
可以拿来自拍。
It might wanna know that there's a front camera.
它可能想知道有没有前置摄像头
For that.
给它使用。
And you can also tell whether a flash is available on that
而且你也可以之道闪光灯是否是可以用的
device, etc.
在这台设备上，等等。
So there's a bunch of class functions in
所以有一大堆类方法在
UIImagePickerControllers.
UIImagePickerControllers 中。
You can find out what's going on.
你能知道发生一些什么。
So here's the code, typically,
这里是通常用来
to prepare to present the picker.
准备展示 picker 的代码。
You're going to create the picker.
你将会创建 picker。
You're gonna set its delegate.
你将会设置它的委托。
You're gonna ask if the camera is available.
你将会问它相机是否可用。
If it is, you're gonna set the source type to be the camera.
如课可用，你就会设置来源为相机。
Then you're gonna ask and see if, for example in this case,
比如在这个例子中
I wanna take a movie with my camera.
我想要用相机拍摄视频
So I'm gonna ask is that kuTTypeMovie available.
所以我问它 kuTTypeMovie 是否可用
Now, this line of code right there, if availableTypes as
现在，在这的这行代码，if (availableTypes as
NSArray).containsObject(kuTTypeMovie).
That's kind of a weird line of code.
真是一行奇怪的代码
Really, it doesn't.
它真的没有
Fit into the swift world very well.
很好的融入 Swift 这个世界
You just do it.
你只要这样写就好了
I's an old Objective-C based API.
这是一个 Objective-C 写的旧 API
And kuTTypeMovie is even kind of an older kind of string
而且 kuTTypeMovie 是一种比
even than NSString.
NSString 还要古老的 String
And, so.
因此
We kind of have to do this old style thing.
我们会写这种老旧风格的代码
I'm sure probably somewhere they'll probably come up with
我能肯定可能某些地方以后会推出
some new API for this whole camera thing that doesn't have
新的 API 来控制这些相机，没有这些
this old stuff, but for now you have to do that.
老旧的东西，不过现在你只能这么写
And then you just tell the picker the media types I want
然后你只要告诉 picker 媒体类型。
the user to be able to take is just a movie, so
我想要用户只能拍视频，所以
in this case they wouldn't be able to take a still image,
在这个列子里用户不能拍照片
they would only be able to take a movie, if you.
他们只能拍视频
Pass an array with just kuTTypeMovie.
只要你传入了一个只有 kuTTypeMovie 的数组
So that's it.
好。
You've configured the picker now, you just need to
你已经配置好了 picker，你现在只需要
present it with that present view controller.
用 presentViewController 把它展示出来
There are some other things you can kind of configure with
这里还有一些东西你可以配置
the picker before you put it up.
在你展示 picker 之前
One is editability.
第一个是 Editability
That's whether you're gonna allow the user to crop.
就是你是否允许用户去切割
The image or edit the video.
图片或者编辑视频
There's actually a video editor built in there
那实际上有一个内置的视频编辑器
that they can edit the video before it returns to your app.
用户可以编辑视频在返回你的 App 之前
You can also limit video capture, for example,
你也能限制视频的拍摄，比如
to be lower resolution if you're just doing something
降低分辨率如果你在做
that's gonna be in a little square somewhere in a webpage,
网页中的小方块
you can go low resolution.
你可以设置低分辨率
If it's something that.
如果有某些其他事
Maybe it's going to be Airplayed to a high resolution
可能是 Airplay 到高分辨率
device or something like that, and you can go for
的设备之类的东西，你可以
a higher resolution.
设置高分辨率
And of course high resolution, you're gonna use more memory.
当然，高分辨率会使用更多的内存
Etcetera, etcetera, okay?
等等等等
You present using view controller.
你使用 presentViewController 来展示
Now, the thing about this is interesting is
一个关于这个的有趣的是
when you're doing the camera.
当你在相机中时
You're always gonna present view controller.
你总是会展示 View Controller
It's always gonna be take over the screen even on the iPad.
这总是会占据整个屏幕，就算在 iPad 上也一样
So on the iPad when you do the camera,
所以当你在 iPad 上使用相机时
you're gonna have this huge camera taking picture.
你总会得到这个巨大的相机用来拍照
Okay?
The whole screen is gonna be the camera.
整个屏幕都会变成相机
However, on the iPad,
然而，在 iPad 上
if you're just looking at the photo library, okay?
如果你只是在 Photo Library 里查看
Or the camera roll you want to present that in a pop over.
或者是 Camera Roll，你会展示在一个 Popover 中
It's only gonna be fairly small,
它们只会有很小
like the 320 wide by I don't know how high.
大概320宽乘我不知道多高
600 or something.
600或者别的高度
So that's really something you're supposed to put in
所以这是你应该放到
a popover.
Popover 中的
Now an iPhone, it doesn't matter.
在 iPhone 上，这没什么关系
In both cases it's gonna be full modal,
两种情况都会是完整的 modal
take over the screen.
占据整个屏幕
Okay?
Cuz it's just too big to put any other way on the iPhone.
因为用别的方法展示在 iPhone 上都来说都太大了
Okay?
So, you present this thing, and it sits there on screen,
好，你展示了这个 picker， 它出现在屏幕上
and then, when the user use this photo, okay, or
然后，用户使用了这张照片，或者
use this video, this is gonna be called right here,
这个视频，这个会马上被调用
this delegate method: image picker controller did finish
这个委托方法 image picker controller did finish
picking media with info, and with info dictionary there,
picking media with info, 那里的 info 字典
has the results of what they did.
有他们做的结果
And when you get there,
当你到这个时候
we'll talk about what's in there in a minute.
过一会我们会讲到那有什么
But when you get this and you get your image, or whatever,
不过当你得到这个并且得到你的图像或者别的什么
then you wanna dismiss this thing.
然后你想让这个东西消失
And I've kind of put here a line of code,
我在这放了一行代码
presentingViewController.dismissViewControllerAnimated
Usually you're not putting the presentingViewCcontroller in
通常你不会把 presentingViewCcontroller 放在
there, because you are the presentingViewController.
这里，因为你就是 presentingViewCcontroller
You just presented this thing.
你只是展示这个东西
So you wouldn't need that part of it.
所以你不需要这个部分
But I just wanted to emphasize that again, you dismiss by
不过我要再强调一遍，你消失靠
sending a message through the presentingViewController,
通过 presentingViewController 发生一个消息
which is probably gonna be you
这个 presentingViewController 可能是你
And you'll see in the demo, we're gonna do this,
你将会在 Demo 中看到，我们会做这个
and we're just gonna call dismiss directly.
并且我们会直接调用 dismiss
We don't have to say presentingViewController.
我们不会在前面加上 presentingViewController
The other delegate method you're gonna get of interest is
另一个你会感兴趣的委托方法是
imagePickerControllerDidCancel
And that means they hit cancel.
这代表用户点击了取消
So now you don't want to use the image that they were taking
所以现在你不想使用用户之前选择的那张图片了
whatever
So in that case, you just need to dismiss, 'kay?
所以在这种情况下，你只需要消失
So that's it.
就是这些
Those are the two delegates methods you get.
你知道了这两个委托方法
So let's look in that info dictionary,
好，让我们来看看那个 info 字典
see what's in there.
看看里面有什么
All kinds of stuff in there.
里面有各种各样的东西
There is the image they took, obviously,
里面显然有用户拍摄的影像
if they're taking a still image.
如果用户拍摄的是照片
If you allowed editing,
如果你允许编辑
then it's gonna have also the edited image like cropped,
那里面也将会有被编辑过的照片，比如被剪裁过的，
right, if they picked a different space of it.
如果用户给照片选择了一个不同的大小。
Also if they cropped it,
如果用户剪裁了照片，
you'll get the rectangle that they chose inside the thing.
你会在这个字典里得到用户选择的矩形。
If it's a video,
如果用户拍摄的是视频，
then you're gonna get this media URL, okay.
你就会得到这个叫做 MediaURL 的东西，
It's just gonna be URL to some file somewhere in your sandbox,
这个东西就是一个指向你的沙盒里某处的某些文件的 URL，
which I'll talk about sandbox later today.
我今天晚点会讲到沙盒
It points to the video, 'kay?
它指向用户拍摄的视频
When you get this image or video you might wanna save it.
当你得到这个照片或者视频你可能会想要保存它。
We're gonna save it in our demo to a file in the file system
在我们的 Demo 里我们会把它保存到一个文件系统的文件里
cuz I wanna show you how the file system works.
因为我想要给你展示文件系统是如何工作的。
But really, most likely,
不过实际上，最最可能的，
you're gonna save it to the device's photo library, 'kay?
你将会把它保存到设备的照片库（Photo Library），
That probably if someone takes a photo and you wanna save it,
如果有人拍了一张照片，你想保存它，
that's likely where you would store, you might store in
照片库可能是你愿意保存它的地方，你可能会把它存到
the file system but more like in the photo library,
文件系统中不过存到照片库中是更加可能的，
you do all that with this, I'm not gonna, for time reasons, cover that,
你使用这个 ALAssetsLibrary 来做这些事，因为时间原因我不会讲这个
but,
但是
You can check out this class ALAssetsLibrary,
你可以去查看这个 ALAssetsLibrary 类，
it's pretty straightforward how you access the assets library,
使用它来访问 AssetsLibrary 是非常直观的，
and you can put things in the photo library there.
并且你可以用它来往照片库中放东西。
By the way,
顺便说一下，
the UIImagePickerController is kind of an old API,
UIImagePickerController 是一个老旧的 API，
it's a simple way to get things with the camera,
它是一个从相机获取东西的简单方法，
but there's a whole, much more powerful API called AVCaptureDevice,
不过有一个整得来说更强大的 API 叫做 AVCaptureDevice，
especially if you're getting video,
特别是在你获取视频的时候，
you might wanna check into that.
你可能会想要看看这个东西。
It's kind of a more powerful way to do the stuff that
它是一种更强大的方法来做那些
the UIImagePicker can do.
UIImagePicker 能做的事。
So I'm not gonna cover it, but just so
所以我将不会涉及到这个，但是
you know that it's there.
你们知道有这么个东西了。
If you're just getting simple image, or just a simple clip of video,
如果你只是获取简单的照片，或者只是获取一段简单的视频
you're okay with UIImagePickerController,
使用 UIImagePickerController 是可以的，
but if you wanna do more with that, then AVCaptureDevice.
不过如果你想要做的更多，使用 AVCaptureDevice。
The last thing about your ImagePickingController is that
最后一件事关于 ImagePickingController 就是
it does support putting overlays.
它支持放置透明层。
So when that camera is on screen
所以当相机在屏幕上
and the user's trying to take a picture,
并且用户准备拍一张照片时，
you can have your own controls on there, your own buttons
你可以有自己的控制器放在上面，你自己的按钮
or whatever you want, using an overlay view.
或者任何你想要的，使用一个 Overlay View。
The camera is always full screen, of course, so you need
当然相机总是全屏的，所以你需要
to make sure that the view that you're putting overlay,
确保你放置的透明层，
you know, matches up with that screen's bounds,
你知道的，对齐屏幕的边界，
which you can get using the UIScreen classes bounds.
你能使用 UIScreen 类的 bouns 来获得。
You might have your controls actually have the take a photo
你可能有让你的控制器有一个拍照
button.
按钮。
In which case you might wanna hide the Take a Photo button
在这种情况下你可能想要隐藏本来的拍照按钮
that comes with the camera, and you can do that with
你可以这么做，让
showsCameraControls equals false.
showsCameraControls 等于 false。
And then it won't show its Take a Photo button, but
结果就是本来的拍照按钮不会显示了
then you better provide one,
不过你最好再提供一个，
because you won't be able to take a picture otherwise.
否则的话你就不能拍照了。
And then finally, you have this cameraViewTransform.
最后，你看到这个 cameraViewTransform。
Normally, the camera maybe takes a square picture, or
通常相机也学能拍方的照片
it might take its picture, in any case, if the aspect ratio
或者它可能，任何情况下，如果纵横比
doesn't match the aspect ratio of the screen, but you might
和屏幕的纵横比不匹配，但是你可能
want it to basically take a full, you know, basically take
想要它拍一个完整的，你知道的，就是拍
the piece of it that is the aspect ratio of the screen.
一张纵横比和屏幕一样的照片。
And you can do that by controlling the transform of
你可以做这个通过改变
the cameraView.
相机视图。
So AffineTransform there, remember,
有个 AffineTransform 在那， 记住
AffineTransforms are scale, rotation.
AffineTransforms 是大小和旋转。
In translation, so
在转变中，
you can do the scale there to scale it up if you want to.
所以你能在那里放大它如果你想的话。
Let's do that, all right.
All right, so that is the ImagePickerController,
好的，所以这就是 ImagePickerController，
let's go ahead and go back to our tracked demo and
让我们继续，回到我们的 Trax Demo
use the ImagePickerController to make it, so
that if we have a waypoint, one of our custom waypoints
that we now can edit, that we can add a photo,
just by taking a picture with the camera, okay?
That's what we're gonna do here.
So let's go back to tracks.
Here we are in tracks.
Just remember where we are here.
We've built this thing that allows us to click on
the map and then we can see the images.
And we can also drop a pin.
And when we click on the little detail disclosure,
we bring up this little new controller right here,
where we can edit the name and the info.
So what I wanna do here is actually use this nice big
space we have at the bottom of our editor to show and
edit the photo, okay that goes along with this waypoint.
Now, you might think the first thing I'm gonna do here is go
down to my object palette and grab an image view, down here,
but I'm not gonna do that, 'kay, and
I'm gonna show you kind of a little bit of an interesting
trick about ImageViews.
One thing about ImageViews is that they have an intrinsic
size.
They're like labels.
They want to be the size of their image, okay, for
auto-layout purposes.
They strongly want to be that size.
You have a question, sorry.
>> [INAUDIBLE].
>> No, I'm not.
Close.
Let's see here, close.
[INAUDIBLE].
So you guys are only gonna get it from, starting from here,
cuz I'm not gonna go back to the start.
I'm [INAUDIBLE] much.
Okay, so if I have auto-layout and I drag an image view in
there, then when I set the image, it's gonna wanna make
the auto layout huge because the image is gonna be big,
especially if I have a high resolution photo, so
I don't want that to happen,
I want this image view to be the size I say it's gonna be.
Basically I want it to use whatever space is available
and no more.
So, well,
kind of a cool way to do this is to use a generic UIView.
So, instead of taking a UIView,
I'm gonna pull a generic UIView out here.
Now, by the way, when you put a generic UIView out,
sometimes it's hard to see what the heck is going on
because it's white on white.
So a lot of times when I do that, I think I might have
mentioned this before, I'll just set it to some other
color for a moment, so that while I'm editing it here in
the storyboard I can size it and set up its constraints and
all that stuff, and I can kinda see what's going on.
Okay, so let's put this thing in reasonable spots over here,
let's set some constraints for it, put some vertical
spacing to the top there, trailing over to here,
this guy over to here, and I'll put this one down to
the bottom, and we used to have a constraint
on this one to the bottom which we want to get rid of.
Where is that?
Bottom of space to bottom layup, it's this one.
And, we could also, while we're here,
make sure this is standard value, 'kay?
So that look's good.
This guy also standard value.
All right.
So, we've got this UIView in here, and really what we're
gonna do is put the UIImageView inside of it.
And I'm gonna manage it manually.
So I'm gonna size it to the right size
that I want in code, okay?
And that way, it'll never be trying to fight the auto
layout system to make things really big,
and smash other things off the screen, or
make my popover really gigantic, or things like that.
'Kay?
So, let's go ahead and do that.
Gonna go over here.
I'm gonna go back,
this is our editable waypoint view controller,
the view controller for this whole thing.
So I'm gonna go down here,
let's create a new little mark for images.
Okay.
So this'll be our image handling area right here.
So I'm gonna control drag from this generic view out here.
This is not my ImageView, this is my, what did I call this,
container?
Yeah, ImageViewContainer.
Okay, this is going to be just a generic UIView, see,
that contains my image view.
And so my image view is actually gonna be something
here that I create in code.
I'll just say equals UIImageView, actually.
Okay, so there's my image view and on my didSet here,
when this thing is set, I'll go ahead and put that image
view into this thing by just saying image view controller,
add sub view.
Image view, capitalize this for me.
Okay, so I basically just put that image view in there and.
Let's see, what's the problem here?
It's, oh, imageViewContainer, yeah, thanks.
ImageViewContainer, too used to typing in controller.
Let's make this bigger, too, by the way, so
we can see what we're doing.
Okay.
So, everyone see what I did there?
I just created this generic UI View,
I put the image view in there.
I'm gonna have to manage the size myself, though.
I'm not gonna do autolayout in there, et cetera.
And, basically, I'm just gonna always set the image
view inside to be the right aspect ratio for my image, but
no wider than my container view.
And if my overall controller gives me no space for
the view image, then I don't get it, okay?
And also anytime my image changes I'm going to ask for
more space by resetting my preferred content size.
Remember preferred content size for the pop over?
And so I'm going to ask for more space.
I may or may not get it.
Cause pop over might be near the edge, but I'll ask for
it and we'll see that code in just a second here.
Alright, so I got that.
Here is some code.
Let's put some code in here to do that.
I have this extension that I added to my way point
controller and it has this method update image.
Now update image, the reason I snippeted this in here instead
of typing all into you've seen it all before, right?
I'm dispatching to another thread,
I'm getting the image data.
Here I'm getting the URL and getting the image.
I'm dispatching back to the main thread,
I'm setting the image in my ImageView so
this is just not worth our time to go through this again.
We've done this two or three times.
But I am calling this function here makeRoomForImage, and
all that makeRoomForImage is, it sees if the image is
any bigger than the last image we had.
And if so, it updates the preferred content size to
give it a little bit of a extra height.
And this extra height might be negative if we just set
the image to nil, for example,
it might try to collapse it back down.
So again, this is just pertaining to what we prefer
our overall content size to be.
And if we can get this space then my generic UI view that
contains my image is going to get bigger.
And there's going to be more space for me and I can make my
UIImageView bigger, see more of my UIImageView.
Okay?
So that's it.
So we do need to update this image.
We'll do it in updateUI, right?
So we have updateUI up here that updates the text fields,
so we also wanna update our image there in that as well.
Okay, so that's it.
That's how all that's necessary here to display
the image in my view controller and
keep it's size contained.
So let's go ahead and kinda put a test image into our
edited waypoints just to see if this is working.
So I'm gonna go back to GPXViewController and
where I add a waypoint here by dropping I'm gonna
say waypoint.links.
Let's append.
I'm gonna append a new GPX link,
that's the thing that has the reference to a URL,
to the image or whatever and so we'll do http
CS193p Stanford images panorama.
Okay.
I'm just picking one of the ones we had there at random.
So, now this waypoint has a link, okay?
Just like the waypoints that came out of that GPX file,
they have links also.
One other thing we're gonna need to do is over here in our
MK GPX right here, our EditableWaypoint.
Right now, it gets its thumbnail and
image URL by looking them up by this type thing.
Thumbnail type, large type.
And just for the purpose of the demo, I'm gonna make it
just return the first link in its link list of links.
So let's go down here and just say return links.first.URL.
And then we'll have the thumbnail be the same as
the image URL, so it won't have a separate thumbnail.
I'm just kinda cheating this really quick so
that we can see some image in our UI.
So let's go ahead and run this and see what happens this is
for, oh we got, what do we got here, oh sorry override,
we gotta override these.
Override.
Okay.
All right.
So I'm gonna run this here, in the simulator.
We'll switch the device in a second here.
All right.
So here we are.
You all remember this UI I've got here.
And I've got these images on the left, for there.
So I'm gonna go ahead and drop one for
an editable waypoint here.
So I'm gonna click on it, you can see.
And there it is, there's our panorama.
See, I used that as the default image, and
if I click our editor here, there's panorama, it appears.
Okay, so, that's kind of fun and
notice that that's a very wide aspect ratio, but it only made
enough space to do that, and so we can edit it.
So, now we want to be able to change this view.
We don't want it to be panorama.
I only just showed that to show you how this would work.
So we need to go back to add some UI,
some button that lets us take a picture with the camera and
put that here instead.
Okay, so that's what we're going to do now.
Let's go to our storyboard here.
I'm gonna put that button like right here, I think.
Let's move this over a little bit and
I'm gonna put it right in here.
I have a nice button for that, or image for
that with the camera.
So, let's go ahead and
get a button.
Okay.
Here's a button.
Okay so we'll put this button right in here.
Okay I'm going to set this image to be that camera, so
let's go ahead and drag that camera image into our
XC assets, so here's our image assets.
Drag this guy in here.
Okay.
We could put higher resolution versions in, et cetera, but
we're just gonna use that.
So let's go to Button here.
I'm gonna go to the button here and change its image to
be the camera, and I don't want the word button on there,
okay, so here's my button.
Now we'll do some auto layout here, to get this thing,
in here.
So I will put this up against this edge.
Let's put something between here the horizontal spacing.
Let's have these two be center Y.
We had another one in here that we'll have to delete now
because we used to have this thing on this edge, so
let's go find that.
That's trailing space to super view right here.
We'll get rid of that.
We'll make these to be standard spacing right there.
All the rest of it looks like it's standard,
must have lined them up perfectly there.
Any problems, oh, horizontally ambiguous?
Okay.
So this guy wants to hug, the button wants to hug itself
because this guy's willing to be as wide as we want.
It doesn't want to hug down but this one does and
the system has to know who gets the space there.
So now the frames will be different.
Okay let's go down here,
update our frames make sure everything looks good.
It does.
Okay, excellent.
So we've added this little button to our UI.
So now we're just gonna have this button.
When we click it it's gonna bring up the camera.
So let's go do that.
All right, I'm just gonna control drag from this button
right here, and here.
And it's gonna be an action, we'll call it Take Photo.
That's what it does.
And we don't need any argument, or anything.
There's Take Photo.
So, in here.
All we need to do is create that picker and present it.
And then we're gonna implement those delegate methods and
we'll be good to go.
All right, so what do we need to do in here?
First I'm gonna check and make sure I have a camera.
Actually I'm gonna, first I'm gonna go and
give us some space to work with.
All right.
So first I'm gonna check here, and
see UIImagePickerController.
If I have a camera available, so
I'm gonna say source type available camera.
Okay?
So if I have a camera,
then I'm gonna set my picker's source type.
To be the camera.
Okay?
What else have we got?
Oh, sorry.
I've got to create my picker.
So here I'm gonna say let the picker equal UI image picker
controller.
So when you create it, it's just parentheses, parentheses,
you don't have to specify any.
X-ray information when you're creating it.
So now I've set the source type.
Now here I would maybe, if I was doing video.
You know, I would check media types to make sure that media
type is available.
And then I would say picker.mediaTypes equals.
And then the types I want.
So, in this case I just want image only.
Okay?
And then we obviously need the picker to set its delegate to
be self.
Okay?
Without the delegate this thing does nothing.
We could also set some other fun things here like maybe we
allow editing.
True?
So we'll see what that UI looks like.
And then we can just present.
ViewController.
The picker.
Animated?
Yes.
And, we don't wanna find out that a capture has
been put up.
And, what else do we got in here?
Oh, okay.
So this is the famous, oh.
Where does this coming from?
So, we have to come up here.
Import MobileCoreServices.
That takes care of that.
And this one of course is we don't implement.
UI Image Picker Controller Delegate.
Okay, let's do that, UI Image Picker Controller Delegate.
Now what's interesting here is that we still have an error
once we put this UI Image Picker Controller Delegate
thing here.
It says.
Wave point controller does not conform to UI navigation
controller delegate.
Why the heck does it say that?
UI navigation hasn't got anything to do with that.
Well that's because the UI image picker controller is
a UI navigation controller, inherits from it, and
they use the same variable delegate.
To be their delegate.
So, we also have to come up here and say that we are a UI
navigation controller delegate, even though we don't
actually implement any of these methods in the protocol.
That's fine.
They're all optional.
Okay?
So, that's a little tricky thing sometimes people don't
understand with the picker, but.
You definitely need to do that.
So, that's all that's required to put that picker on-screen,
so it's gonna be on-screen and
now we just have to implement those delegate methods.
So, here they are.
This one, by the way, is deprecated,
don't use that one.
Here is the one where they pick something, and
here is the one where they cancelled.
Okay?
So let's do the one where they picked.
Something, so
I'm just going to say that the image they picked is the info,
that info dictionary that's being passed along here.
And there's a bunch of constants in
UIImagePickerController, and one of them here,
ImagePickerControllerEditedIm- age, so
that's the edited image, and I wanna get it as a UIImage.
Okay, because this info is,
AnyObject is the value, so I have to cast it here.
If I couldn't get the image, okay, the edited image,
then I'm gonna just try and
set the image equal to the unedited image, which is the
ImagePickerControllerOriginal- Image.
As UI image.
Now you might say, why am I doing this line of code right
here because I'm clearly allowing editing up here.
Yeah, we're allowing editing today but
if I some day just said, eh,
I'm not gonna let people edit and I change this to false,
well, all of the sudden,
this code would break if I didn't have this nice little.
Thing here.
So I'm thinking ahead a little bit to make it so that
a change somewhere else in my code won't break me here.
Okay?
And so I've got the image.
So I'm just gonna set the,
my image views image equal to that.
And I'm gonna make room for it.
Okay, that's this makeRoomForImage that I told
you I added down here.
Okay?
And that's it.
I've got everything, so I'm just gonna dismiss.
And notice, I'm not saying,
presenting view controller dismiss here.
Because I am the presenting view controller.
So I'm just saying, dismiss true.
And completion.
Okay?
We have to do the same thing here for the cancelled case.
But in the cancelled case,
I'm only gonna do this dismiss right here, okay?
Obviously, I'm not gonna grab the image or
anything if they cancel.
All right?
So let's take a look at this.
Let's look at this, let's go on iPhone 6 plus here.
There it is, okay?
Actually, let's go.
We still have our little panoram in here.
Let's go to that really quick.
That's over here.
So we'll just go back here and we'll comment this out.
So that if we're testing again in the future we can go
back to it.
All right.
But let's get this code back up on the screen here so
you can see it.
All right, so here's our photo stuff.
All right, so
let's run again.
All right so I'm gonna drop a pin.
Notice that we don't have an image right here.
Okay?
It took away that little test image.
And clicking our edit thing and
we've got this big space now.
There's that big grey box right there because I set that
UI image in my storyboard to be grey.
Right?
So let's go look at that.
See over here, this is gray.
So really, when I'm shipping,
I'm obviously gonna go here, and
set this back to its standard, which is clear basically.
Okay?
Back to our code.
All right.
So we're gonna take a photo here.
I'm gonna press that little camera.
Okay, camera.
And you can see camera comes up right here.
And this was helicopter skiing.
So let's look at our favorite hat.
Ski hat, we got our favorite ski hat.
It's R2D2.
Actually it's better than R2D2.
There a little San Francisco Giants R2D2.
Okay, so we're gonna take this picture.
Okay, so we can now crop it.
Okay?
We could zoom in on the really important part.
All right?
And then we can say Use Photo, and it comes back and
it appears in our thing here.
If we take a different picture,
maybe if we decide, okay, we want the whole hat, all right,
we'll zoom out there, and we'll use that photo.
We got it, okay?
Now, of course, this is not going to save this, so
as soon as I go away and come back, it's not there and
that's because we need to save that picture somewhere.
And we're gonna save that in the file system with our
next demo.
Let's take a quick look what this looks like on the iPad.
Make sure that it works over there as well.
All right.
So, we'll drop a pin here.
We'll go there.
Bring up our little popover.
Take a photo, again we get the huge size screen.
We'll have to do front facing camera,
because I got it on this thing.
Here we go, this R2-D2 hat there.
There we go.
All right.
And there it is.
And so we can put it into our little popover,
which is kind of fun.
And because we have that generic UI view, and
I asked for a bigger preferred content size, it made some
more size and then the generic UI image view got bigger.
And so then I was able to make the image view inside of it
bigger.
Okay.
Excellent.
Okay, let's go back to the slides, and
learn a little bit about storing stuff, and
then we can come back and store that image.
All right, so there are a number of ways to make
things persist on your device.
In other words,
some data that you want to live forever on your device.
Okay. Even as your application
is quit, the phone gets powered off,
whatever, you want that stuff to exist.
So I'm gonna talk about four different ways.
You already know one, actually,
which is NS user defaults.
Okay.
That's a really simple, kind of small amount.
This is for bigger data, these four things.
The first two, I'm just gonna really, briefly pass through.
I'm barely even gonna talk about them.
Because, really, you're certainly not gonna use them,
I don't think, in your final project.
Maybe some SQL master out there will be doing some SQL
thing.
But I don't think anyone will use that.
But then the File System and Core Data, I know a lot of you
are doing Core Data as your final project.
And that's a great,
not covered in lecture thing, by the way.
Even though I'm gonna talk about it today,
that doesn't mean I'm covering it in lecture,
I'm barely gonna talk about it.
But, so I know I lot of you are doing that.
And some of you wanna use the File System, also.
You're reading and writing files from the File System.
So hopefully, this will get you up to speed there.
So let's talk about Archiving.
Archiving is a way to store a graph of objects,
okay, on to disc.
And those objects don't have to be property lists.
So they don't have to be array, dictionary, date,
whatever.
Because that's all we can put in NSUserDefaults, right?
And NSUserDefaut is for small things.
But if we want to store big things, bigger object graphs,
and we want a lot more flexibility.
Well, that's where we use Archiving.
And, Archiving can archive any tree of objects as long
as all of them implement these two methods,
encodeWithCoder and an init method that reads themselves
back in from a coder.
So encodeWithCoder basically writes them out,
writes themselves out, basically as a dictionary.
Okay, and then encode, and then init will instantiate
the object when it gets read back in,
reading that stuff from that dictionary.
So where is this used?
Your storyboard is archived.
So all the things in your archive,
all of those ui views, all those ui view controllers,
they are all encodable.
Okay, they implement this NSCoding protocol.
And they all get written out.
Basically, when the storyboard is saved, this whole object
graph, the entire thing, all the buttons, everything in
there gets written out using this Archiving mechanism.
And that's why we have that weird init thing with UI view
controller and UI view where there was always this
required init coder thing.
That's because they participate in this Archiving.
Now, I would not recommend to you if you had a graph of
objects, you know like, I want to make them persist.
I think I'll archive them.
I wouldn't do it.
I would use one of the other mechanisms I'm gonna talk
about today.
Okay, this is really is great for story boards and
it really is the right thing for story boards but
I'm not sure that for
arbitrary data storage if it really makes a lot of sense.
Okay.
All right SQL, some of you are database experts and
there is SQLite on the iPhone.
SQL is for those of you who are not database experts,
SQL is basically a programming language for databases.
Okay, for creating tables and columns and rows and
tables and all that.
And you can, if you have a bunch of code lying around
that you had to write to a SQL database,
then you could certainly use SQLite.
And the next thing I'm gonna talk about, or
the thing I'm gonna talk about the end here, Core Data,
it uses SQL underneath, okay.
It's writing all its data to an SQL database as well.
But probably not gonna access it directly.
The interface,
the programming interface to SQLite is like a C API.
It'll work in Swift cuz Swift has compatibility with C APIs.
But it's a little hard to use cuz it's gonna have
weird things like, you know, pointers into memory and
things like that, that Swift doesn't really,
it has ways to adapt to this.
So that you can do it, but it's not really native,
it's not part of Swift's way of doing things.
So it'll be a little odd for those of you who are used to
Swift, to try and program this SQL API using Swift.
But it can be done.
And I'll have to look up how to do it.
All right.
So the last two things I'm gonna talk about is
the File System and Core Data.
So the File System is very simple, okay.
Your device, your iOS device, has a Unix filesystem.
Okay, because I told you the very first day of this class,
basically Unix is underlying a variant of Unix,
BSD, Mac is underneath all of iOS,
it's providing the kinda core OS services.
So you have the Unix filesystem there.
And if you want to store things in the File System,
you just store them in this Unix filesystem.
Now, kinda four steps to do that.
One is you have to get the root path, it's true,
some URL, file system URL, not HTTP URL,
that you're going to write or read from, okay.
So, you basically got to start somewhere in the File System.
Now, it's a Unix filesystem, of course it starts at slash,
but you can't write in slash,
that's the, you know, root directory.
You have to write somewhere down, slash, slash something,
slash something, slash something,
that's where you get to start.
So finding that root path is the first step and
we'll show you how to do that.
Then you're gonna append the path components onto that URL.
So, if you want to create some directories in that place and
then some files, you're gonna be using appends and
NSURL has some methods to do that.
And then you're going to read and write files from that URL.
And we'll talk about how you do that.
And finally, you're gonna manage the filesystem.
You might wanna remove a file, you might wanna rename a file,
you might wanna see what files are in a directory, and
that's all done with this class, NSFileManager.
Okay.
So that's it.
This is how the File System works.
So let's look into all of these steps.
So you see this File System, it starts at route.
It's a protected file system, though, so
you can't see most of the stuff that's in root, or
any of the system directories or whatever.
It's not readable by you.
So, there is a part of the Unix filesystem there, though,
that is your application's own, it's called its sandbox.
Okay, and this is the only place you can write.
Some of the places in your own sandbox, you can't even write.
Like the place where your actual application is,
you can't write there.
So you can't modify [LAUGH] your own code by writing
something in that directory or something.
Okay, but many of the directories,
subdirectories of your sandbox, you can write in.
So this is the place where you can write, and
you can read everything in your sandbox.
Then we'll talk about how you get a URL into your sandbox in
a second.
Now, why do we do this sandboxing thing?
For obvious reasons, for security.
You don't want to be able to look into other apps and
see what's going on over there, and you don't want to
be able to access the system directories and
mess up that iPhone.
So it's completely obvious, but there's one
slightly non-obvious reason to this sandbox,
is that since everything you are ever going to write on
the local disk is in this sandbox.
If the user deletes your app you know, they go over here
and hold down until the thing, it's the other one.
Which one are we showing?
Yeah, this one.
See them wiggling there?
So, if they hold down wiggle, if they were to press x to
delete it, it would delete your entire sandbox.
So everything you've ever written is gone.
Okay?
Also, that's true for backup.
If they backup their phone to iTunes U, okay, or
iTunes and iTunes U, iTunes, then it would back
up certain directories in your Sandbox, not all of them.
Okay?
So, that's another reason to have this Sandbox.
So, what's in there?
What's in the Sandbox?
There's various bundles, which are directories.
There's the application bundle I talked about,
that's where your actual app is, okay?
And everything there is read-only.
All your storyboards in there.
If you have JPEGs that are in your image assets,
they're all in there.
They're all read-only.
If you put something in there you needed to edit,
like maybe some SQL database or
something you put in there or some data file.
You would have to copy it out of the application bundle into
one of these other directories in your Sandbox, and
then you could edit it there.
Okay?
So, you can ship your app with things you're gonna edit, but
you just have to copy them out of your application directory.
And then, there's also other directories in there.
The documents directory, that's where you should store
what the user perceives as their data, okay?
The things they're creating and editing and
owning that they expect to be there all the time.
Even if you don't, kind of,
divide it up into a document in your UI, it's still,
that's what the documents directory is for.
There's also a caches directory.
This is for data that you could throw away.
So, it's some information you got from
the Internet that you can go back to the Internet, but,
it might be slow to go to the Internet, so you're going to
keep a local copy, but, you could throw it away.
That directory, for example, wouldn't get backed up
to iTunes, okay, if someone plugged their phone in,
because they figure you can recreate it, okay?
And there's a bunch of others,
there's about a dozen different directories.
And, you find all these directories by looking
in the documentation for the term NSSearchPathDirectory.
Okay?
And, I'll talk about that in a second as well.
So, how do you get the URL to these special
directories in your Sandbox?
You do it with this file manager class,
this NSFileManager.
Now, NSFileManager, there's actually a class
function called, DefaultFileManager,
that will give you the default NSFileManager.
The only thing to be a little careful about that one is,
NSFileManager is thread safe.
And a lot of times, you might want to read and
write a very large file in a different thread.
Okay?
And NSFileManager is completely thread safe,
but only for
an NSFileManager instance that is created in that thread.
In other words, you should never create an NSFileManager
instance in one thread and then use it in another one.
That's not thread safe.
Okay?
But, even if you're accessing the same files,
trying to remove or look at the same directories,
that's all perfectly fine,
as long as each thread has its own NSFileManager.
So the NSFileManager DefaultFileManager,
you'll see that in the documentation.
That one is kind of your main thread, DefaultFileManager.
If you're only gonna use it on the main queue,
then you can use that one.
Otherwise, just create an instance.
It's pretty light-weight to create an instance of
NSFileManager just like this, okay,
let fileManager equal NSFileManager().
So, once you have a file manager, then you can send it
this message, URLsForDirectory inDomain.
And that will tell you, it gives you, actually,
an array of all the documents directories,
all the caches directories,
all the application bundle directories.
Now, why is this an array?
Well, on iOS, it doesn't matter.
There's always only one thing in this array, okay, and
that's the user's documents directory,
the user's cache's directory.
And that's because on iPhone,
you only have the user's resources.
But this API works on a Mac as well, and on the Mac,
you might have the user's document history or
a cache's directory.
You might have the computers, and then you might even have
the networks, okay, the local networks.
That's why you might get multiple of these.
So, don't be freaked out by the fact that this returns
an array of NSURLs, there's always only going to be one.
You can just use the first one in there.
And, that is going to be a URL that points to this kind of
directory like the documents directory, or
the cache's directory, or whatever.
And, you specify which one you want with that first argument,
NSSearchPathDirectory.
And, you have to go look in the documentation and
see what the special names of them are.
But there's, like, NSDocumentsDirectory,
NSCachesDirectory, NSDocumentationDirectory.
By the way, be careful with NSDocumentationDirectory
versus NSDocumentsDirector.
I can't tell you how many final projects people post in
Piazza, and they'll say, I've been trying to write to my
NSDocumentsDirectory for days but it says not writable.
And it's because they've been trying to write to
the NSDocumentationDirectory, which is read-only.
Okay, that's documentation that ships with your app.
So be careful with the escape completion there,
NSDocuments is the writeable one,
okay, NSDocumentation is documentation.
All right?
So, now you have the URL to the root of one of these
things, like the document's directory,
the cache's directory.
And, now you want to write some files in there.
Well, you're going to use URLs, NSURLs methods,
URL by appending path component, or
URL by appending path extension.
Some extensions like .jpg, or whatever, .doc,
got some document format of some sort.
And so, that's how you're gonna do that.
And, by appending multiple path components,
you can build things inside directories, right?
So I can say a path component, today's documents.
And then path component foo, and that would be a directory,
today's documents, and inside foo, okay?
So that's how you build up the URL.
So, once you have a URL, you can find out some things,
like, about it, like, is this a file URL, or
is this a network URL?
Sometimes, you wanna know that because you're accessing
an image, and you wanna know whether it's on disk or
whether it's on the network,
you might put one in the thread.
Cuz some people ask,
should I always access my file system in the thread?
And the answer is, probably for
small files unless they're, you know, megabyte size files.
You're probably fine to access them in the main queue.
It's pretty fast, that flash memory,
pretty quick at getting the information back.
You probably don't need to do that.
It couldn't hurt, especially, if you already have
the code to deal with the fact that file might be over
the network, might as well do it for the local file, too.
There is also a very important method that's a little bit
buried in the documentation called resourceValuesForKeys.
This is how you get things like,
when was this file last accessed?
'Kay?
How big is this file in bytes, 'kay?
That's this NSURL thing, resourceValuesForKeys.
When you give it the keys, like files last change date or
whatever, and it's going to return in a dictionary,
rather, with those keys you gave and the values for
all those things, 'kay?
Permissions, all that stuff.
ResourceValuesForKeys.
All right, now, I've got a URL,
I want to to write to the file system.
How do I write something to the file system given the URL?
And the answer is usually,
you're going to use NS data, okay?
Might use the property list ones, like NSArray and
NSDictionary and write a property list out to it.
But you oftentimes can use NSData, cuz you have some
image data or some other data you want to write out,
sound files, something.
And so, you do that with NSData's method writeToURL,
atomically.
And so, writeToURL, you just give it a URL.
It will write that file out there.
And the atomically means, write a temporary file,
and then, remove the old file, and
put the new one in an atomic transaction.
Okay?
That way, if something happens in the middle of writing
the file, the file won't be half written.
Okay?
It'll be always a completely written file.
And it'll return a Boolean,
as to whether that was successful.
Okay?
So, that's the primary way you're going to write.
That's how we're gonna do it in the demo.
That's the number one way you're going to write.
I told you that NSFileManager could do other things, too,
manipulate the file system, create directories,
things like that.
You're gonna have to look at the documentation.
There's quite a few functions in there.
It also has a delegate.
Where it'll let you control things.
There's like, should write file at path.
Something along those lines where it's basically shoulds
that you can control whether something happens.
And, so you can look all that up on documentations really,
it doesn't make sense for me to go over it all here.
>> [COUGH].
>> Okay, so that's the file system, and
I will be demoing that in a moment in Tracks.
But first I want to talk about Core Data,
the last persistence thing.
How many people here are doing Core Data for
their final project?
Wow, okay, so half of you.
That's great.
I'm really, really, really happy about that,
cuz I didn't teach Core Data in detail this quarter.
So I was hoping a lot of you would do it as your
final project.
Cuz Core Data is actually an important thing to know.
Not just as a way to store data but
it's just conceptually understanding a little bit
more about how iOS works, and things like that.
Core Data, if you can figure out how to do that,
then you understood a little more about how iOS works.
So for those of you who are not doing Core Data, I'll go
through this quickly since most of you are doing it, but
what is Core Data?
It's basically a way to store your data in a sequel
database, basically, but in a totally object oriented way.
So you don't have to issue any sequel commands or
anything like that, create rows and tables.
It's gonna create all that for you.
It's completely object-oriented API.
It's a very powerful framework in iOS.
It has a lot.
Most of you are getting it for your final project,
even though you're only going to touch the basic thing of
setting properties and creating entities.
But there's a lot of really powerful querying things that.
>> [COUGH]. >> Can happen in there.
Most of the things you can do with SQL, you can do up in
the Core Data layer, things like optimistic locking and
all that stuff is all doable, so
it's a pretty powerful mechanism.
It is backed by SQL, but
it can also be backed by other things.
XML, or you could even actually get involved and
store the data in your own format, but
that would be very advanced usage.
So how does it work?
How does Core Data work,
you create this visual mapping in your schema.
Okay, it's not like the parse that you saw at the Friday
section a couple weeks ago, that's schemaless.
It's basically creating its schema on the fly, right?
It creates the rows and tables as you ask for them.
This one you define your scheme upfront.
What are going to be your objects,
and what are going to be the object's properties on those
objects.
And then basically tables are kind of like classes if you
want to think of it that way.
And then the columns and the tables are kind of like vars.
Okay and then coordinator provides a way to have these
@NSManaged vars, where literally you just set the var
and it's gonna be go set the information in the database,
and of course you can query on all this stored data as well.
You create the schema with this visual map.
You do new file and you create this thing data model.
You're gonna get this thing, it kinda looks like this.
Okay?
It's a graphical, piece of graph paper looking thing, and
you can actually create things that look like class like
photo and photographer here.
And then you can create the columns in the database, and
then you can create
relationships by controlled dragging between them.
So you're gonna create your schema totally
graphically there.
Then you get this UIManagedContext.
That's kind of your handle, your hook, on your database.
There's a couple different ways to do that.
There's some code that can be generated when you create your
project, you can click on the Use Core Data button and
it will create this code for you in your app delegate,
and then you will have a method in your app delegate
called manageObjectContext.
Now you have a handle to your database and
you can start creating objects in there or
setting the values of things.
There's also another class,
an important class called UIManagedDocument,
it's a way to encapsulate a Core Data database, okay?
What's really cool about UIManagedDocument, if you use
data approach versus the Use Core Data approach,
is that the iCloud side of it becomes a lot easier.
So if you wanted to have your core database work on
iCloud so that I could see it on all my devices, and
it would be automatically synchronized,
then you wanna use UIManagedDocument.
So maybe some of you.
Anybody trying to use UIManagedDocument?
'Kay, so that is kind of like the next step
you would think about doing in Core Data.
All right, so once you have this context,
the handle on the deck,
on this core database, you can create objects.
You do that with this NSEntityDescription class
method called InsertNewObjectForEntityForN-
ame, and you're basically just specifying the name of
the table, which is like a class, and
you give it the managedObjectContext, and
it will create a new instance, okay, a new row in that table,
to use the database terminology.
And it's gonna return to you this NSManagedObject, or
subclass thereof.
And it's with this NSManagedObject that you
can set the columns, set the values in that row.
You can also fetch,
you create these things called NSFetchRequests.
They basically specify what you're looking for,
pretty powerful predicates in there for saying,
well I want all things, all of the rows whose column is
called name starts with the letter a.
You can do that kind of fetch request and then you issue
the fetch request and you get it back as an NS Array.
This fetched object thing would be an NS array, or
an array, of NS managed object.
Okay?
And so that's kind of what you can do with a database.
Once you have these objects, these NSManaged objects,
you can use these two methods, the setValueForKey and
valueForKey to set and get the values in there.
Or even better,
you can create subclasses of NSManaged objects.
That have these apps on NSManagedObject vars, and
Core Data will automatically make it so
that if you set that var, it sets it in the database.
And if you get that var,
it'll fetch it from the database, okay?
So, you use normal SWF notation for that.
Okay, so that's kinda what Core Data's about in its core.
Pun intended, no pun intended.
Core Data is also really good at hooking up to table views.
Cuz you can imagine you've got these big tables of data in
Core Data, and it'd be nice to have a table view that is
displaying all the rows or
some subset of the rows based on some query.
In the table view, and so there's this class called
NSFetchedResultsController in iOS, a super simple class.
It basically, you give it a fetch request, and
you associate it with a table view, and then that table view
will always show what that fetch request would fetch,
even if the database changes out from under it.
'Kay, cuz you add something, and
the thing you added matches that fetch request, boom,
it will just automatically appear in the table.
'Kay, so you don't have to be doing all, basically,
the FetchedResultController will implement all of your UI
table of your data source methods for you.
How many rows in table, how many rows in section.
Give me the self or own index path.
You have to do your own self or
own index path to do the UI part of it, but
there's one method in the FetchResultsController that
will tell you which managed object is in this row,
in the table.
So if you're doing Core Data for your final project and
you're doing table views,
you definitely want to look up NSFetchedResultsController.
Okay.
All right, so the demo that I'm gonna do,
I'm not gonna demo Core Data, don't have time for that.
So I'm just gonna demo the file system piece.
And we're gonna do that by making our waypoint.
Store the image that we took with the camera as a JPG in
the file system.
And then we'll have a URL to it,
we can update the waypoint.
And our new edit away points will work just like the ones
that come in a GPX file.
All right, so what do we need to do to do this?
Really, all I'm gonna do here when I take a photo, okay,
and the information comes back in the delegate,
I'm just gonna say SaveImageInWaypoint.
'Kay, remember that this NBC, its model.
Is the waypoint that we're editing.
So, I'm just gonna have a little method here,
saveImageInWaypoint.
So let's implement that, saveImageInWaypoint.
And all we're gonna do here is we have the image,
we already got it, put it here in our UI view image, so
I'll just get it out of there.
And we're just gonna write it in the file system and
then we're gonna update the waypoint to use that URL,
simple as that.
So, if we can get that image, so
if our imageView has an image.
Okay?
Because they could be nil.
It might have been set to nil by some means,
then I'm gonna get the image data as a JPEG.
And the way you do that, there's this cool function,
UIImageJPEGRepresentatio and you just give it a UIImage.
Okay?
And you give it a compression quality.
So, I'm gonna do really high compression.
Okay?
So this is a quality between zero I think,
which is like the most compressed you can do to one,
which is like almost no compression.
Okay?
I think that's the direction it is,
I hope that is what it is.
But anyway, so you can look at the documentation for it.
But we're gonna turn our image here
into by doing this in NSData.
So this is going to return in NSData.
If we look at the up here, see that is NSData.
So, it's gonna turn our image into NSData.
It's kinda the opposite of NSData contents for URL,
which is the opposite it would take the URL for
some data and turn it into UIImage.
This goes back the other way for JPG.
So, if we're able to do that conversion, then I'm
gonna get the fileManager here as a local variable.
I could just constantly, I could use the defaultManager
by defaultManager you see I'm in the main thread.
But just in case I ever put this in a separate thread or
something, I'll go ahead and use an instance of it here.
So now I need to get the documents directory,
because these waypoints, really,
the user perceives them as their document data.
That's where you would want to store this.
It's not like a cache that we can't ever get back.
We need that photo if we lose it.
It's gone forever.
So, and again, we might really want to be saving this in
the photo library.
But I'm just trying to demo here how to do the file
system, so that's why we're doing that.
So, I'm gonna get the documents directory and
so here's a nice long line of code for you.
Take the fileManager, we're gonna get the URLs for
directory.
Okay?
The directory we want is the DocumentsDirectory and
the domain always on the iPhone is the UserDomain.
More space please.
The UserDomainMask here.
Okay?
So that's gonna get this array of URLs and
I'm just gonna get the first one out of there.
Okay?
And then I'm gonna make sure that it's cast to URL.
So, if all of this succeeds, then I got
the documents directory and what did I miss here?
DocumentsDirectory.
There we go.
Okay?
So this will end up being a NSURL that
points to the DocumentDirectory.
Okay?
So now I have a DocumentDirectory,
I need a unique name for this photo that I just took.
So, I'm gonna create that by just saying,
NSDate.TimeIntervalSinceRefer- enceDate.
So this is just a certain number of seconds.
This is just a unique number.
It's gonna be a double.
That unique identifies this photo, because it can't have
two photos taken at the same instance in time.
So we got that.
And then so
I'm gonna let the URL for my photo be the docsDir and then
URLByAppendingPathComponent and then I'm just gonna create
a string out of that unique and we'll say that it's a jpg.
Okay?
So now I've created a URL,
which is just this unique string with JPG on the end.
So now, if I can get the path to that URL.
So this is gonna take the URL and
turn it into a string, okay?
Cuz URLs are in this URL objects.
I want the string, you'll see why in a second here.
If I can get that, then I'm gonna take that ImageData and
write it out to that URL and I'm gonna do it anatomically.
Okay?
And if that succeeded,
if I was able to successfully do that,
then I can add it to the way point by saying, waypointLink.
And I'm just gonna replace all of my waypoint
links with a GPX.Link, which is href of that path,
the string version of the NSURL.
Because GPX.Link, it's a generic GPX parsing thing.
It takes strings, it takes URLs as strings here.
Okay?
Everyone understand all this code?
This is typical code for
writing something out into your file.
So come into your Sandbox, in this case,
the DocumentDirectory of Sandbox.
All right.
So let's go ahead and run that.
It's good being
on the iPhone here.
Okay.
So let's drop a pin here and can see that we have our
dropped there and we have no image yet, so
let's click on our little eye here and get an image.
So, I'm going to click the camera.
Let's get a picture of our R2D2 hat here.
There we go.
And we'll use that photo.
And now we have our image.
We can even, for example,
change our title here maybe to let's say, R2SF.
All right?
And click Done.
Now, if we click on our pin, we can see that the image
has been saved and we can see it there on the left.
We can even click on it, scroll around on it.
Okay?
Or go back and edit it and
take a different photo if we wanted to.
[SOUND] Okay.
Now by the way, to make this work I had to make a small
change to the code, which is right here and
didSelectAnnotationView.
We just want to make sure that if we have no call out
accessory, because we started without one when we drop a new
pin, like this.
We have no image and so,
it didn't add the left call out accessory in that case.
So just when the annotation's selected,
we're just gonna make sure that it adds it.
Okay.
Back to our slides.
All right.
Okay.
So the last thing is Embed Segue ways.
So, Embed Segue ways is just taking the view,
self.view, basically of an MVC and
putting it in another MVC's view.
Okay?
So, it's basically embedding one MVC into another.
It's a pretty powerful encapsulation technique.
The way you do it is really easy.
In the storyboard,
you just drag out this thing called a container view, okay?
You drag the container view out.
It's gonna be a little view and
it's gonna have a little MVC attached to it.
All right.
So, it looks like this when you drag it out.
That little grey thing's the container,
that's the thing I dragged out from the storyboard.
And then that little arrow there moving,
that's the Embed Segue.
And you can see there's another MVC there and that MVC
is the one who's self.view is gonna be embedded.
All right?
The timing of this, you've got to be a little careful on
prepareForSegue, because this embed all
happens before any outlets are set as usual.
And so, it's happening very, very early in the game.
So, usually in our Embed Segue,
what we do is we grab onto that MVC.
Okay, so that we have a handle to it.
We can talk to it.
We can prepare it, set it up, whatever want later.
So this is best shown by just demonstrating it so
I'm gonna demonstrate that by going to tracks.
And here's our tracks UI, so tracks right here.
This is our map view right here.
And when we click on the left edge of a call out,
it brings up this UI image view controller.
Right, which is currently fully contains an image.
And what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna embed in the corner,
a little rectangle down here, a little square that contains
a little map view, with just the pin for this image.
So that when I'm look in the image,
especially on the iPad where I've got a big screen,
I can see some context of where this image was taken.
Right?
So I'll see them both on time.
So I'm basically gonna embed another view controller into
this guy right here.
So what do we need to do that?
The number one thing we need to do when we have an embedded
view controller is we need to do this segue, and
we need this view controller right here to have
a little subclass to manage that.
So right now this view controller, as you know,
is an image view controller.
So if we select this,
you can see that its class is ImageViewController.
So I need to change this.
I'm gonna change this to be a waypoint image view
controller.
Okay?
So a waypoint image view controller's gonna be
a subclass of ImageViewController.
So it's gonna do everything this one does.
Plus it's gonna know about how to manage that embed.
Okay?
So let's create a new class.
All right, the Cocoa Touch Class.
It's gonna be a subclass of ImageViewController,
one of our classes.
And I'm gonna call it WaypointImageViewController.
Okay.
Put it in the standard place.
'Kay here it is, here's our WaypointImageViewController.
This WaypointImageViewController,
its model is the waypoint.
'Kay?
This guy's model, did everyone remember what
ImageViewController's model is?
It's just an image URL.
Right?
So we need a little more powerful model here in our
WaypointImageViewCcontroller, so
I'm just going to have var waypoint.
It's a GPX Waypoint.
It'll work with the editable ones or non-editable ones.
And when that waypoint is set,
I want to make sure that I set my super classes model.
So, I'm gonna say my imageURL equals that
waypoint's imageURL.
Okay?
So, here,
I'm basically setting my super class's URL there.
And what are we getting this about here?
Oh, okay, we're not there, okay.
And then I'm also gonna set my title equal to the waypoint's
name, might as well.
And them I'm just gonna update my embedded map, okay, because
the whole point of this guy is he has this embedded map.
So, we'll have a function here called updateEmbeddedMap, and
it's going to update that map.
And we'll talk about how that's going to happen
a little bit later.
This isn't optional, that's why, okay.
All right, so that's it.
So that's our waypoint image controller,
kind of its main thing.
So now we need to go back to our storyboard, and
I'm gonna make this image view controller right here be
a waypoint image view controller.
So I'm just gonna go here to its identity and
go down here and say now it's a WaypointImageViewController.
Also, I'm gonna fix this segue.
This is a segue from our map view.
I'm gonna just fix this one to prepare this guy by giving
his way point.
So that's over here in our GPXViewController,
down here in prepare.
Okay, here's where we're preparing
the ImageViewController.
Okay?
So here I'm going to say,
if I can let the waypoint image view controller equal
the segue destinationVewController,
contentViewController as a waypoint view controller.
So in other words if it's a waypoint image controller,
then I'm gonna say waypoint image view controller waypoint
equals my waypoint.
And actually I'll just go ahead and
leave this other code in here as an else.
Else if it's not a waypoint view image controller,
it's just a normal image view controller,
we'll still make that work as well.
But we could delete this code, and it would work fine now.
But I'll just leave it in there, just for reference.
Okay.
So now we need to go do this embedding business.
We need to put this thing in here.
Now one thing I'm gonna advise you to do, when you're doing
embedding, and kind of be a little careful of.
Is when you drag out this Container View,
which is at the very bottom, by the way, it's gonna want to
be a subview of the thing you're dragging it on.
So it keeps trying here to be a subview of that scroll view,
and I don't want it to be a subview, a scroll view,
because I want it to sit on top.
Okay, I want it to always be there, and
the scroll view is scrolling behind it.
I don't want it to be in there scrolling around.
Okay?
So it's really a bit of a pain to do that with this in way.
So you can just take something like your scroll view, for
example, and move it out of the way temporarily.
So I just moved it out of the way.
So now I can put my Container View in here.
I can put it where I want, probably not
in the very corner there, something like that.
I can do all my auto layout here.
Maybe we'll do this a little, do it higher, yeah,
let's do that, bottom space.
Probably, I want this container to be a fixed width
and height, okay.
I don't know what width and height I would want.
Maybe like, I don't know, let's say 200
by 200, sorry, double-click there.
So let's make it 200 by 200.
We could make it whatever size we thought was kind of most
appropriate for this space.
And then we could put this back, this scroll view back.
By the way, if you go over here to the document outline,
you can see the order in the view hierarchy.
Like this would be behind, and
this is in front of everything else.
Okay.
Scroll view the activity indicator in
this Container View.
Now, I dragged this in here, but if we look oh,
look at down here.
What's this guy?
Okay.
See that is the little view controller that could.
This is the little view controller that is going to,
whose self.view is gonna be in here.
So let's do this guy right here, and we need a view
controller class for this, so I'm going to create that.
This is gonna be the world's simplest map view controller.
I'm gonna call it, in fact, SimpleMapViewController.
It's gonna be a UIViewController.
And all this SimpleMapViewController is
going to do is to make its map view outlet be public.
So that other people can do whatever the heck they want
with the map view that's inside of it.
So let's put a map view inside of it.
Let's go back to our storyboard.
Get this little guy right here.
Okay, I'm gonna, first of all I'm gonna make him be
a SimpleMapViewController, like that.
And then I'm going to put a map view,
which is right here, inside of him.
Okay?
Let's go ahead and go, suggested constraints.
Probably, that'll be just fine, yep,
all looks good to me.
And so let's just create an outlet for that.
Whoops, get an outlet here,
small screen, there we go, okay.
Whoops, SimpleMapViewController,
there it is.
Let's Ctrl+drag here, mapView, 'kay?
So that's it.
That's the entire implementation of this class.
It's just gonna do that.
It does MapKit, so we have to.
Import MapKit, okay, so this just is public and
we can do whatever we want with this map.
So, what do we want to do with this map?
Well, we want this map to show our waypoint in our
waypoint image view controller, okay?
So, that's how we're gonna update this embedded map.
We're, can access the map view directly.
But, the one thing we need to do, first,
is we need to do this segue right here.
So, we need to give this segue an identifier.
We'll call it the Embed Map segue.
And we need to prepare this segue.
And we prepare it here.
We're going to prepare it by just by grabbing that map
view, okay?
Grabbing that controller, actually,
than grabbing the map view out of it.
So, I'm gonna prepare for segue here.
I'm gonna say, if the segue's identifier equals,
and we'll just, no constant here.
We should do one, but we're not gonna do.
So, it's the embed segue.
Then, actually, I'm just gonna create a var here,
which is the SMVC, the simple map view controller.
Which is a SimpleMapViewController,
optional.
And, I'm just gonna actually set it inside this prepare for
segue, so, smvc equals the segue's
destinationViewController as a SimpleMapViewController.
So, in the set prepare for segue,
I've just grabbed onto this SimpleMapViewController.
So, now that I have it, okay, let's go ahead and
update our embedded map here, and let's do the code for
doing the embedded map.
Very simple.
I'm just gonna say,
if I can get that map view out of that smvc.
Okay, then let's set the map view to be mapType Hybrid.
And, then we want to set the map view's annotations.
So, let's remove the existing annotations from the map view.
And then, let's MapView.add an annotation for our way point.
Okay, which remember, is an MK annotation, so we can do that.
And then, let's also zoom in on those.
So, showAnnotations, the map view's annotations and yes,
we want it to be animated.
Okay?
So, that's gonna update our embedded map.
Yes, Embed Map.
Okay.
All right, so, now that we're actually embedding the map and
doing that actual prepare for segue,
we should get this to work.
Here we go, and sure enough, there it is.
And, it's kind of hard to zoom out.
Actually, I'm gonna do this on the actual device
cuz it's a little easier to pinch.
>> [INAUDIBLE].
>> Oh, I didn't hit Play.
There we
go.
All right.
There we go.
Here or there.
We should have our nice image here.
And inside here, this MVC is a fully operational MVC.
It can be pinched.
It can scroll around.
It does all the things that it would normally do.
So, we can actually see that we're in
the Greenbush area of Greenbush Lake, all right?
Okay, and if we rotate or whatever,
a lot of layout works on it, et cetera.
Okay?
So, that's embedded segue.
Sorry to run a little bit long.
If you have any questions, I'll be here as usual.