[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Okay. Well, welcome to lecture 17,
Stanford CS193P, winter 2015.
Today, our topics are Internationalization and
Localization.
That's making your application so
you can ship it all around the world in different languages.
And then also, kind of a minor topic,
settings which is a way that you can add a little bit of
UI to the general settings application on the phone.
And I have demos for both of these things.
All right. So let's talk about
internationalization and localization.
Those are actually two different things.
Okay? Internationalization,
sometimes called I18N.
Because of 18 letters in there between I and the N.
That's the process of making your application localizable.
And then, localization is the process of actually
translating it to another language.
So internationalization.
That's work that you do as the developer.
Okay?
You have to take your app and do some things to it.
Not a lot, but some little bit of things.
To make all the strings that you have in there be pulled
out or pullable out of there so
that our translator can translate all of them.
And then there's a little bit of formatting as well.
Certain things, numbers, dates,
et cetera, look different in different languages so
you have to be able to do that.
And then localization is a process that.
A localization company usually does.
Someone else does that.
Someone who's fluent in both languages.
Maybe even someone who has a little bit of
domain knowledge about what your application does.
So if it's a social networking app,
they're familiar with other social networking apps, so
they kind of know what various words and phrases.
Would be in a UI like that.
And so this is kind of a two step process, and
so, you're always working on adding new features and
internationalizing those features, and
the localizer is pretty much kind of always getting a dump
of the latest strings from you, and
they are translating them and sending back to you and
you're checking to see if it looks okay in UI.
You're going back and forth, so
it's an iterative process back and forth between you
as the internationalizer and the localizer,
which is usually some third-party company.
There's plenty of companies out there that do it.
So, let's talk about your side of it first,
the internationalization part.
And there's really two places that you have strings
in your code,
strings meaning text that is going to appear in the UI.
One is in your storyboard.
A lot of strings in there, labels and all that stuff.
And for storyboards, the way we do internationalization
there is we.
Xcode knows how to reach in there and
grab all those strings and
pull them out in a way that you can give to a localizer.
And then we use Autolayout,
to make sure everything looks nice when these strings
come back cuz these strings might be shorter or longer.
And so Autolayout is an extremely important part of
internationalization.
Okay. It's just one word,
Autolayout, but
it encompasses a lot of the work that you have to do.
Cuz you have to build your UI to be able to
deal with these different length strings.
So that's the first part.
Now the way you get these strings out of the storyboard,
the very first thing you need to do before you do
any internationalization is register
localizable languages.
Languages that you want your app to be able to ship in.
Now. This isn't something you have
to do upfront and pick them all when you're done, this,
you can always add a new language along the way.
But, when you add a new language it's automatically,
the first time you add a new language it's
automatically going to make your story boards, so
that their strings can be pulled out.
Okay.
This is super easy to do.
You're just going to click on your project.
And when you click on your project,
you're actually gonna want the project, not the target.
Sometimes when you click on the project in the very upper
left of the navigator, it's gonna be selecting the target,
which is that thing that says autolayout
in the second column, the second autolayout down.
So you want the top one, which is your actual project, and
when you do, you're gonna have two tabs across the top,
info and build settings, you see those?
And you want to be in the info tab and
you'll see about halfway down towards the bottom there.
It says localizations and
there's actually just a list there of languages.
So here my app is going to be localizable into Chinese,
simplified and traditional.
Also into French and Japanese.
Okay. So you just keep
hitting plus button there.
It's just gonna ask what language you wanna add and
you add them.
Okay.
Now, you're gonna see why this is important later.
Now once you do this, the storyboards,
if you look in the Navigator in your storyboard,
it's gonna show all these localizations, right?
It's gonna have a list of all the localizations.
If you expand the little storyboard.
And also if you inspect the storyboard
in the file inspector.
Which is the left most tab in the utilities column there.
If you have a storyboard inspected,
it's gonna show you the localizations there too.
And so that's a good way to just double check.
Oh yeah, yeah, I've got all the localizations for
all these languages.
It's what I expect.
Usually you don't have to manipulate.
These two things in any way.
It's just there.
Usually you'll have it closed up.
You'll have the little triangle pressed
there by the storyboard.
You won't even see these things.
But that's just to show you what's happening
when you do that.
So there are other strings in your app, though,
besides those storyboard things.
Things in labels and stuff.
There are literal strings.
Strings that in your code you put into the UI.
And the way you localize those is by calling this function
NSLocalizedString, okay?
Very, very important function.
Every single literal string that's ever gonna appear in UI
needs to be wrapped in a call to NSLocalizedString.
So the arguments to this thing are,
the first thing is the key.
Basically this is the thing that uniquely identifies this
string.
Okay?
And this is usually the thing that you want to put on screen
in the language of the developer.
Okay, if English is your language,
then this would be in English.
If you're, you know, developing an application in.
Czechoslovakia and Czech is your language then this string
would be in Czech, okay?
Or whatever, is that a language, Czech?
I think so.
So that's what usually this is.
But it wouldn't necessarily be that,
because you might have the same word appear two places in
the UI and actually, possibly have different translations.
Because they might mean slightly different things.
So this key might not necessarily.
Be that.
If it's not, then the value option, okay?
See the third one or actually fourth one there value, that's
the thing that it will use if it can't find this thing.
A translator doesn't translate this key.
Okay?
Now the table name in the bundle,
that's a way of kind of organizing these localized
strings into groups.
You can put them in little tables.
The bundle thing is more for
if you're localizing maybe a framework versus your app.
We'll talk about those two arguments in a second here.
And then the last argument, comment, super important.
This is a comment that goes to the translator.
So this tells the translator, this is the context of this.
Now the translator when they're doing the storyboard,
they see your storyboard cuz you're gonna send them your
storyboard as well.
So they're gonna see the context.
Oh, this is a label for a field, I get it.
But here these strings are in your code, and so
they have no idea where this thing's gonna pop in the UI.
So you need to give very good comments here
to localize, you know.
This is the title I'm gonna work that comes up.
When this bad thing happens because the user did this or
whatever, so that they know what the best
translation of that word to put up is.
So in this localized string, you pass these arguments and
it gives you back a string,
and the string it gives you back will either be,
if there's no translation, the value there, or
the key itself if there's no value.
Or it's gonna be the translated string that came
back from the localizer, okay?
And then you're gonna use that string.
You can put it in the UI.
So you wanna wrap every literal string in this.
Now most of the time, the table name and
bundle are defaulted.
The table name is just gonna be Localizable.
Which is where mostly you put all your strings actually in
a table called localizable, and
the bundle's gonna be your main bundle.
That means your app, okay?
Now we haven't talked too much about bundles, but
when you have frameworks and other things,
you can have other bundles of code in your app.
And they might have their own bundles of strings, but
I'm not gonna really talk about that.
I'm just going to say that most of the time you're
just gonna call this version of NSLocalizedString that
only has the key and a comment.
Okay?
Because it's gonna use the key as the value
if there's no translation, and
you've gotta have that comment to the translator, okay?
So that 90% of the time you just skip it.
No NS localized string comma colon around your
literal strings.
And that's it.
That's all you need to do to get all those little strings
to be translatable.
All right?
Now, if you use a format string.
So this format string,
the result is %g or the result is %d, okay?
So you're using a format string.
You're gonna wanna use this string, class method called
localized string with format to create a string from it.
So it takes var args at the end for
all the %ds or %gs or whatever in the string.
And you would want that format string to also be
NS localized string.
Okay because the words in there, the result is,
those need to be translated as well.
But the reason you wanna use this localizedStringWithFormat
is because numbers are not always displayed the same
in different languages.
So you wanna give the system a chance to display any %gs or
%ds properly in there.
You're actually not even gonna
use this that much because you are gonna
use a number formatter which I'm gonna talk about.
In a second, and the number formatter does an even more
powerful job of making sure the number looks good.
If you have multiple percent things in there, %d, %g,
a lot of them, the localizer is able to specify the order.
Because, as you can imagine, as some languages,
the words might come in a little different order,
just because of the way phrasing works in a language.
And they are able to do that when they translate, so
no worries.
There.
All right. So that's strings,
strings in your storybook, little strings in your code.
Now, let's talk about formatters.
So, formatters work based on a locale.
So there's really two parts of what makes something
localized.
One is the language, Japanese or French or whatever.
But the other is locale.
And the locale is where in the world you are essentially.
So your language might be Spanish but
maybe you're in Mexico or maybe you're in Spain or
some other part of the world that speaks Spanish.
Okay.
So you would have a different locale, Mexico or
Spain, than your language which might be Spanish.
Okay? So
the formatters are gonna format things, numbers and
dates and stuff.
Currencies, based on your locale.
Okay?
And so what kind of formatters are there?
Well we've already seen number formatter,
actually we saw it the very first day of this class.
Number formatter knows how to take a number and
turn it into a string.
And we didn't really worry about locale when we
used it early in the quarter.
It was a little advanced topic at that time.
But it was using the locale even though we weren't
worrying about it, it was using it.
This number of format will also be used for
formatting currencies.
Okay, your local currencies.
And then dates is another one.
Dates are displayed myriad different ways across
the globe.
So you definitely need to use a date formatter if you're
gonna put any kind of date in your UI.
There's also date components formatter, so
date components are like the day of the week, the month.
Okay, those also are displayed differently across the world.
And there's even kind of some fringe formatters you wouldn't
think but you need to like byte count formatters, okay?
So if you wanna say 350 kilobytes left of 2 gigabytes.
Okay, those numbers look a little different in different
languages.
You can't just put the number in there and
put kb after it and expect that to be kilobytes.
It's not necessarily gonna be right.
So the byte count format I can help you with that, and
then in map kit there's the distance formatter.
So you can specify here's the distance between two places
because that also needs to be localized.
Health kit also has a number of things.
Like energy, calories used.
Those kinds of things.
Some of those are different in different locales.
So any time you're gonna put a number or
a date on screen, you're gonna wanna see if there's a proper
formatter to format this thing, okay?
So how do formatters work?
Let's look at a couple of them.
Let's look at NS Number Formatter.
Now NS Number Formatter.
A lot of API there.
You're really gonna wanna check out the documentation.
But I'm gonna look at the two most basic cases.
One is just displaying a number.
So you create an NSNumberFormatter
like we did in the calculator.
Then you set the style of the number.
So for example, decimal style or currency style.
There's also a style even spell out style that will
spell the number out, 3,000, T-H-R-E-E T-H-O-U-S-A-N-D,
right it'll set it out as words in the local language.
So there's a few styles in there.
Then you can set other things about the formatter,
how many digits you want before and
after the decimal point, how you want rounding to happen,
all that kind of stuff.
Set that all up and
then you just call formatter string from number.
You give it the number you want and it will return to you
a string that uses all those attributes that you set up and
be proper for the locale you're in.
Okay?
So that's that way.
And of course, think about the other way.
If you're gonna ask the user for
a number then, you better use a number formatter to parse
that number into a number from a string.
And, that's because, as you know, some parts of the world,
the decimal separator's actually a comma.
So if they type three comma two,.
And you don't use a formatter,
you're gonna look at that and say, oh.
They want, what do they want, three?
Or that's just not even a valid number, right?
But if they type three comma two and they're locale is some
place where that's the way numbers are expressed,
then that's gonna give you 3.2 back out of it, okay?
So displaying of parsing numbers main job event is for
number formatter.
But there's a lot more in there.
So you definitely wanna familiarize yourself with
that class.
On the date side.
Okay, formatting dates, very complicated.
Okay, how we as humans represent dates,
we don't do it in a simple way, unfortunately.
Luckily there's some built in, pretty simple styles for
showing numbers.
Short style, medium style, long style, full style.
And hopefully those will do what you want.
Cuz if you can use one of those, then the way to
do it is you just create an NS Date Formatter,
you set the time style and the date style to be one of these
kind of styles, and then you just get you string from date.
And now you'll have a string that you can put in the UI
that will be fully localized in the local language and
in the right locale.
Okay?
EY image, how about images?
Because some street signs or other things like that might
look different in other language.
And there's a couple of ways to do that.
If you put the JPEGs or the PNGs directly in your project,
in other words you don't put them in the images.xcassets
thing.
Then actually those can become localizable files.
And you just click on them, go to the file inspector, and
say make this localizable.
And you can have a different version for
every language that you want.
But maybe a better way to do it is put them in your
xcassets.
Put all the images from all the languages.
And give them names
that you can then look up using NSLocalizedString.
Okay? Okay.
And then your translators can translate the name of stop
sign to French stop sign, or something like that.
And then that'll be the name in the image.scs.
And then you can use some naming convention to group
them, or whatever you wanna do.
But that's probably a little bit better way to do it,
because then your translator has a little more
control of it.
Now you'll have to coordinate with your translator to
make sure you name the images in your xcassets to match what
they've translated them to.
But still a pretty straight forward way of doing that.
Okay, so congratulations.
You've done all those things, right?
You did the story boards, you added the languages,
you used NS localize string, you
put the formatters in there, now your app is localizable.
And now you wanna localize it.
'Kay, how do you do that?
Could not be simpler.
You just go to the project again,
the same place that you added the languages, and
from the Editor menu, you just say Export for Localization.
And it will export all the languages.
You can actually select which ones you want,
but it'll export all your languages in a format called
.xliff, 'kay, which is this international file format for
translators, 'kay?
They have tools, translators have tools that read .xliff
files and let them translate, and
then they press, you know, send or whatever.
It generates an .xliff with the translations in it.
So this is kind of the,
you know, industry standard communication mechanism
between developers and translators.
And so Xcode localization will generate them all.
And then your translator will use their tool, translate it,
give you an .xliff file back, and you will then,
in that same place, say Import Localizations, 'kay?
You can only import one .xliff at a time.
A single .xliff can have multiple translations for
multiple languages, by the way, and your translator,
if they're doing ten languages for you, they might give
you one .xliff with all the languages in there.
But anyway, you do import localizations, and
it will import it into your project.
And what's really cool then,
is if you then change some things and export again,
all of their translations will get exported, so that you
can just keep going back and forth, import, export, import,
export, and the translators doing the opposite.
They're importing what you send, they translate it,
they send it out.
When you send something new it has all the old work they did,
becaus export keeps that.
Okay?
So it's really super simple system.
It's totally built for
that iterative process, really well designed.
This is new for iOS 8, they did a great job with this.
Okay? So it's just import,
export, and that's all it takes, 'kay?
Once you have a localization back
you can preview it in really two different places.
One, you can preview it in Xcode, and
I actually showed you this earlier in the quarter.
There's that little preview pane on the right and
you can preview it, and in the lower right hand corner of
the preview pane, it actually has all the languages that you
have translations for.
You just pick it and boom,
right there in Xcode it'll show you.
Now that's only gonna show your static story board
though, it's not showing your app running.
You're not gonna see any of your NS localized strings
in there.
You're only going to see the translations that were made to
something in a story board.
And yeah, notice there's that nice little double length
pseudo language.
That's a good way to make everything really long and
make sure everything's fitting.
Maybe there's places you're out of layout,
you need to make more room, something like that.
So that's kind of a cool, it's not real language,
just doubles the length of every string, but
it's kinda cool.
The other way, and this is mostly the way you're gonna
test your app is you want to run it using the translations.
Now, it would be a pain in the neck,
if every time you wanted to run in Arabic
you had to go on your device or your simulator.
Go over here to, actually, here, let's put this up here,
and I'll show you.
Okay, so here's my device.
So if I had to go to Settings and go to,
I think it's under General.
And then go to, where is it.
Language and region.
And then go over here to my iPhone language,
go find Arabic in here.
If had to do that for all of the ten languages,
I would just be going crazy doing that.
So luckily, you don't have to do any of that.
All you have to do is create a scheme.
'Kay? A run scheme for
your app that sets the language.
So the way you create a scheme.
In the upper left hand corner of Xcode where you click run.
Right now you only ever see it say the name of your app.
But you can actually hold down on that, and
there'll be a little menu, and you can say edit scheme.
And edit scheme will bring up this thing that you see there,
the big window, and it's going to say what are the settings
you want when you build, when you run, when you test, when
you profile this app, when you're stack analyzing, etc.
And in the build, in the run section,
there you can see that there's application language and
application regions.
So you can set those to French or maybe Spanish and Mexico,
if you wanted a locale.
And then, it will make a new entry, okay?
Sorry, first of all, you duplicate an existing scheme.
You see that, lower left?
Duplicate an existing scheme.
Then you set all these things, and save it, and
now you have two schemes.
The original one, that doesn't have a language set, and
the duplicated one.
'Kay, that you've set the language in.
Now if you wanna run in that other language,
like French, you just hit that pop-up, pick French, hit run.
Okay? And it's gonna run using that
language and locale.
It's really cool, fast way.
You can check ten languages really quick.
You add in a new feature or a new translation came back,
you just click run, check it out, okay.
Click run.
Checking out, back and forth, okay?
So that's how you preview a localization at runtime, 'kay?
And I'll show that in a demo.
There's also this little localization debugging switch
you see in there, and
that's going to do a couple of things.
One thing is on localize strings from your story boards
will show up in all caps in your UI, so that's nice.
Also things that were not localized,
will spit something out on the console,
saying this string on localized, okay?
So when you're getting something back from
the localizer you wanna make sure they didn't make any
mistakes, although the import is gonna find mistakes,
I'll show you that too in the demo.
But if there's something else in there, you'll be able to
see it with this localization debugging on, 'kay?
And that's it, 'kay?
So all you gotta do is autolayout, get your localized
strings in there, use formatters properly, and
you'll be internationalizeable.
And then it's just question, go hire your localizer.
Back and forth with the .xliffs, all right?
So let me show you what this looks like.
Here, we're going to localize autolayout, okay?
Do you remember this app back when we were doing autolayout,
looks like this?
So we're going to localize this to a number of different
languages.
And I added one feature to this, actually,
which is this little guy right here Last Login.
So I just made it when you log in it puts a last log in
date in here,
because it's gonna let us talk about date formatters and
number formatters, things like that, in here.
But otherwise it works exactly the same as it always is.
We type the username and password, we hit log in,
we can do change security and
it'll change this word right here.
And that's it.
So, what do we need to do
if we want to make this localizable?
Well the first thing we wanna do
is go up to our project up here.
And again, you want to be careful here
not to have the target selected,
you actually want the project selected, okay.
Target, project.
In the project selection you're gonna have info and
build settings.
And, so let's create some localizations,
you see it down here localizations?
We don't have any currently, it just says English.
So I'm gonna create some, you know, let's do French.
That's a good one.
And it's saying here, what do you wanna make localizable?
And, yes, my storyboard, and also that launch screen, which
we really haven't [LAUGH] talked about in this class.
The launch screen, by the way,
is just this thing that pops up briefly while your app is
getting up and running.
You've probably seen that.
You can edit it and create, put an image there or
something like that.
But that's something you might wanna be localize both,
it has text or something on it.
So we gonna leave that.
So there's French.
Let's do, yeah let's do Chinese.
Let's do traditional also.
Let's do, I don't know.
How about something Arabic, how about is a good one.
How about Japanese?
Yeah, there's Japanese.
So I'm adding a bunch of languages here, and
when I now go here to this Editor menu and
say Export For Localization.
It's gonna say, where do you wanna put them?
I have a directory here called my L10N, my localization one.
And, I have this folder called To Localizer.
I don't have anything in there right now.
We're gonna put our auto layout stuff in here.
Here, you see, it's asking what languages you wanna
generate these .xliffs for.
So I'm going to hit save.
And it's going to generate .xliffs,
which we're going to go look at for all of these things.
Okay? So
here's all the files that are going to my localizer.
I'm going to send these to my localizer so
let's look at one.
It really doesn't matter because nothing's been
localized yet.
But here we go,
see storyboard, here's all this strings.
You recognize these strings?
Company, last log in, the log in button, user name.
Name, password, the change security button.
Those are all the strings that it extracted
from the storyboard.
I send these off to my localizer,
and they go work on them, and then we get some back.
So, okay.
Look, they just came back from the localizer, here they are.
So let's go ahead and take a look at the Japanese one.
So here's the Japanese one right here,
what does this look like?
So the localizer has put localizations for
each of these things into this X-look.
Now they didn't edit it here in text edit [LAUGH],
they have a tool that lets them do that.
And so let's go ahead and import that.
So we go here, and
we're going to import this localization for
Japanese from the localizer.
Japanese.
Okay.
Oh, there's a problem.
Okay, now if there's no problem, this just loads up.
And you're good to go.
But here there's a problem.
And when there's a problem it shows you in detail
what the problems are.
So here it says there's incoming translation for
one of the things in IB that was not done.
And you can see it right here, no translation.
So they didn't translate the word company.
Now luckily, company never actually appears in our UI.
That's just like the little thing like where you know,
Madison Bumgarner, and
it was were old champion San Fransisco Giants.
So company always gets replaced with whatever
the logged in user's company is.
So, whew, we're okay.
But you can see it's showing all the other translations.
And those look good, right?
So this one, this one, this one.
It's showing the translations.
So this will only appear if you've got something where
your translation company failed in their translation.
In this case, it's okay.
So I'm gonna accept this and import it.
Okay?
Now I can actually go to my storyboard here and
without even running my app I can make a second
window here and go down to Preview.
So let's preview what our main storyboard's going to
look like.
Of course, our S is cut off because,
if you'll remember from auto layout demo,
we put that in code.
We put a constraint for
the aspect ratio so that's in code so that's not here.
So here's what it looks like in English, right down here.
If I go up here and say,
well tell me what this looks like in Japanese,
then it will use those translations for Japanese.
Now notice company is in all caps,
that's because that was not translated.
Notice that they translated the word name to be the same.
If we look at the Japanese translation,
and we look at what they did for name, which is right here.
They said, oh well, there's just no word in Japanese for
that part of the UI so
we're just going to leave it in English.
Okay? They have that
option to do that.
But you might say, I don't want that and so
you can easily see that here.
Especially with a language like Japanese.
Versus some western script language like English,
you can see quickly, oh, whoa, whoops.
It's not there.
Okay. So that's great.
And if we run our app,
we could run it in Japanese as well.
And so let's do that.
Let's do this edit scheme thing.
So you see, I'm just taking this thing up here that
normally is always saying autolayout.
And I'm gonna say Edit Scheme.
And when I edit its scheme, I can edit scheme for
lots of different things, building, et cetera.
But I want it for running.
I wanna edit the scheme for running.
And I'm gonna duplicate this scheme, okay, and
I'm gonna call this my Japanese scheme right here.
And I'm gonna change the Japanese scheme so that.
It is Japanese.
And it's, Japan here.
But if we, if it wasn't there,
we could go look for it up here.
But here's Japanese.
And so now this is my locale.
And this is my language, okay?
So now, if I ever wanna run in Japanese,
now that I have this scheme,
you see that I have two schemes now.
Now that I have this Japanese scheme, I can just hit Run
with this scheme selected and it's gonna run in Japanese.
Let's go ahead and make this smaller.
Even smaller.
Okay.
So here's our app in Japanese.
And maybe we type, oh, and so I'm trying to start to type.
Notice that in my locale it's even bringing up
a Japanese keyboard.
I believe I can get an English keyboard here somehow.
There we go.
So, let's go madbomb and log in.
Here it is.
Notice this is not translated at all.
Notice this is not translated.
Okay because we put those in our code.
Those are not in our storyboard anyway.
So we're part of the ways down making this
internationalizeable.
We've got our storyboard.
So let's take the next step which is those strings,
like the passwords, secure password and oh,
I added one other feature to this app I'll show you.
Try and just make this wide cuz it makes it
a little bigger for you.
It's this. Is if you type a bad user name
and password, it says, Login Error Invalid user name or
password Try Again.
So this also needs to be localized to Japanese.
Okay? So
we got some strings here to work on, so
let's go work on this string and that alert string.
You haven't seen this code in a while but
here's what it looks like.
I'll show you all of the code I added, very simple.
I just added this which is doing that last log in thing
and I added this.
If the logged in user couldn't be found
then I'm gonna put up an alert.
Okay. Now that you know what
alerts are.
You didn't know what alerts were at the time that
we wrote this, so I can put it in.
But, now, you certainly do.
Okay?
And then, here's where we do that secured password thing.
This has not changed, from our last demo.
So let's fix this one first.
This is a pretty simple thing.
We got these two literal strings here, and
we need them to be localizable.
So I'm just going to create a little local here,
which I'm going to use NS localized string for, and
you can see here's that long version of it.
And first let's do password.
So I'm just going to take my literal string and
plop it right in here.
I don't need the table or bundle or value.
Okay?
And this is going to be a comment to the localizer, this
is something like, this is a prompt for the users password
when it is not secure i.e.
plain text.
Okay, so I'm trying to give the localizer as much
context there, as I can.
May, I might even put a much longer comment, there.
You really can't go wrong with nice long comments.
And then, the secure password.
We will just do another NS localized string, here.
We'll take this secured password thing out of here,
put it here.
Get rid of all this.
And we'll say, a Prompt for.
An obscured (not plain text) password.
Okay?
So that's it. So now,
these two locals here are just strings.
If we look at their type, they're just a string.
But they've had a chance to be localized by a translator.
So now I can say, if it's secure,
return the obscure password.
If it's not secure, then do the password.
Okay, simple as that.
And, you can put these things right in line, right here,
if you want.
Okay?
We could have even put this, obviously,
right here without even having this local, or I guess,
this right here, without having this local, but
it's kind of nicer to put them in here.
It starts getting a little hard to read
if we had all that stuff here, a humongous line of code.
But, it's perfectly legal.
One thing about these localized strings,
these do need to be literals, okay?
This and this, they need to be literals.
They can't be themselves variables, okay?
Because, obviously,
the code is being scanned to extract this out of here.
All right?
How about our alert down here?
Well, I'm gonna do this a little differently.
I'm going to put the strings into a little constant,
okay, a struct that's kind of like constants.
So, I have my struct alert strings.
Actually, I have a little struct inside of it called
the alert strings for
the login error alert, cuz I might have multiple alerts.
And, so then I have a localized string for
the title of the alert, a localized string for
the message in the alert, and a localized string for
the dismiss button of the alert, right?
Login error, invalid username, try again.
And again, I've put nice, long description here, so that
the translator can figure out what the context of this is.
And then down here, I need to replace these literal
strings with the things from my struct.
So this is the title, this is the message right here.
Strings.loginerror.message.
And here is our dismiss button.
Okay, so I replace that.
Okay? So now,
I basically got all my strings, except for
this last login thing,
which we're gonna do in a second here.
I pulled all my strings out into NSLocalizedString.
I don't have any other literal strings other than this
in my app that appear in the UI.
So, again, I'm gonna go back to my project, right here.
And, this time I'm going to send
out to my localizers again.
Now, this time when I send out,
so this is going to the localizer again.
So I'm gonna send it out, I can replace these.
If we look at what I sent this time to the localizer,
let's look at Japanese, you can see that, look,
the old things that that localizer did are in there.
So, that localizer hasn't lost any work.
But, down here is all the new things that we just added.
Invalid username and password, login error, password.
And, here's my nice comments to tell them what it is.
So, they'll bring this up in their tool and
they'll translate it, okay?
So, you can how, what I mean by,
if we can go back and forth and back and forth?
So, they translate it and it comes back.
So, here we are from the translator.
We'll say we did all of our languages.
So, let's go to a different language here.
Let's do Chinese, let's say.
Let's do traditional Chinese.
Okay, so here's what Chinese looks like here.
There's the storyboard.
And here, all the literal strings have been
translated, okay?
So, let's import that.
So, I'm gonna go here, Import Localizations.
From the localizer.
Want this one.
Traditional.
There it is.
Again, I'll make another scheme here, okay?
This one, I'm gonna call, Chinese Traditional.
Let's go ahead in the Run.
We'll change this to Chinese.
And, we'll set our location to be China, our locale.
Okay? So, now we have one for
Japan and one for China.
Okay?
So, let's do this and let's just run.
Okay? Gonna make this wider.
So, this is, here we have in Chinese now.
Notice that this is working.
Notice the auto-layout is adjusting just like it did in
English.
If we try to log in, we get our error right here.
Some of you probably speak Chinese, so
hopefully these translations are good.
I take full responsibility.
I don't know any Chinese.
So, I'll take responsibility if they're wrong even though
I didn't do the translations.
But anyway, there's that.
Now if I log in, so let's log in here.
That's MadBum.
Okay, I still don't have this thing translated, and
this is obviously content,
so that we're not going to translate Madison Bumgarner.
Okay?
Although we could I suppose, but we're not going to.
So, this is content just coming out of our database,
or whatever.
So, this is the last thing we need to do.
Now, let's look at this last login.
It's pretty bad.
Okay? This is bad even in
English, okay?
This is really ugly looking time and date.
I want this to be much nicer.
I'm gonna have it be,
last logged in certain number of days ago at this time.
Okay? 12 and
a half days ago at 4:15 or something like that.
So, if I do that, I need two things.
I need to format that time, the time you logged in and
I also need to format the number,
how many days ago you logged in.
So, I'm gonna use a number formatter and
a date formatter to make that work.
Okay? And then I'm also then gonna
use a format string, you know, something with percent this
and then present that in there, to do that.
And, that string,
of course, as a whole, is gonna be localizable.
So, a lot going on to localize this here, but
you're gonna see the code's not too bad to do that.
So let's go, whoops.
Let's go back to our controller.
Here's where that nasty, offending,
non-internationalized code is right here.
So, here, this is where I get the last login.
So this is an NS Date.
Right? This last login is
an NS Date of the last time this guy logged in.
And so, I don't really want this badness in here,
so I really wanna say something like,
Last Login %@ days ago at %@.
So, I'd really like to say something like that.
And, you know,
to do the format, I wanna make sure that I'm doing
String.localizedStringWithFor- mat, okay?
So, put this format string in here.
Okay? And, we need the arguments
here that correspond, so we'll call that daysAgo and time.
Those are the two arguments that are correspond to
here and here.
But, of course, this needs to, itself, be localized.
Okay? So,
I'm gonna call this lastLoginFormatString.
And we will put here let
lastLoginFormatString equal NSLocalizedString.
And then, I'll put that format string in there.
Again, I don't use this.
In the comment here, we'll say something like,
Reports the number of days ago and time that the user last
logged in, or something along those lines to make
sure that the localizer understands what's going on.
Okay, so that's it.
We've localized that.
All we have to now is the daysAgo and time.
And, these are both going to be strings.
And, we're gonna get each of them by using a formatter.
So, let's start with the date.
So, I'm gonna create a date formatter.
NSDateFormatter, okay?
If you just create one, no arguments or whatever.
And, now we're gonna configure this date formatter to
present the date.
So, I'm gonna say,
set the timeStyle of the thing to be kind of a short time.
Okay, this is just saying when you last log in,
I don't need the seconds and the time zone.
I just need, basically, the time is a short time, so
I'm gonna say NSDate.
FormatterSTyle.ShortStyle.
So you can see here's the styles.
Full style.
Long style.
Medium style.
I'm gonna go short style.
Now, I only want the time.
I don't want the date portion at all.
So I'm gonna say dateFormatter.dateStyle equals
NSDateFOrmatterStyle.NoStyle.
Okay, that means,
don't give me the date portion, I just want the time.
Okay?
So now that I've kind of configured this date
formatter, I can let that time string, this thing right here
that I want this percent at sign to correspond to.
I can say dateFormatter.dateFromString.
That's all right, other way around.
StringFromDate the lastLogin.
Okay? And that's it.
So I've just use the date former.
Now, not only is this going to put this is a nice format for
me for English, it's also going to work in the local
language, as you're going to see.
All right.
How about the number, how many days ago?
I said I only want it to be like 3.5.
I don't want it to be logged in 3.5876 days ago.
Okay?
I could maybe just go for three days ago, but
I'm gonna say 3 point one decimal digit just to show you
how to do that.
So, let's create a number formatter.
And again, we already did this back in the calculator days.
So we create this number formatter.
Then we're gonna configure it, and the only thing I'm gonna
say is that I want the maximum number of fraction digits
to be one.
Okay?
3.5, not 3.5267, okay, just one digit.
Then I'm gonna let that daysAgo thing equal
the numberFormatter.
A string from number.
And so, now I just need to take this login date and
turn it into the number of days ago.
Which I can do with
lastLogin.timeIntervalSince- Now.
Of course that's negative, okay?
Cuz that's gonna be in the past.
And we'll just divide that times 60, times 60, times 24.
Which is the number of seconds in a day.
Because the time intervals are seconds.
Okay?
Make sense?
All right.
What do we got here.
Oh, exclamation point, yeah.
So string from number [INAUDIBLE] is an optional.
It returns an optional string and you might say why would
you ever do that because this argument if it's a double,
it's always gonna be turned into a string.
But string from number also knows how to deal with
things such as Booleans and
things like that from the old objective C days.
So that's why.
Just so you're pretty safe to always go ahead and
unwrap the optional if that gets back if what you're
passing in here is a double or an int.
Okay? Or some number.
Okay? You could do if let if you're
a little worried about it.
But I didn't do that.
Okay?
So there we go. Now we've got the date and
the time.
And again, like you say,
localizers won't be able to change the order of these two
things if they're a sentence in a different language.
Makes sense to do that.
All right?
Let's go back to our project again.
Let's go ahead and export this.
Okay?
So I export this to localizer.
Replace all that.
All right. We've sent them out there.
Let's go take a quick look at what that looks like.
We'll look at oh, yeah, let's look at French.
Okay, so here's French.
If we go down, here's the last log in.
Notice here's the dollar one and dollar two.
That's how they can control which one is which and so
they need to translate though, this into French.
Okay? So
let's go ahead and have that happen.
Okay.
It happened.
Okay. Now let's load it in.
Okay. Import localizations
from our localizer.
Let's go ahead and let's do French.
Okay?
So let's edit a scheme here for French.
I always like to do the edit schemes because
you're always gonna come back to it.
It's not like oh, you're only ever gonna run French once.
You're gonna run it multiple times.
So here's French, and we'll make it in France.
Okay.
So let's run.
See if we got this right.
Oops.
All right, so this all looks like French.
Okay? That looks like in French.
Yeah, there's some French.
I don't know if it's right French but
oh, again my keyboard is French.
So let's go ahead and bring up our keyboard so
we can see that.
Okay? Yeah,
we got our French keyboard here.
So, I'll type it here.
Mad, madbum.
Oops.
Madbum.
How do I back up?
There we go.
[LAUGH] Madbum and here we go.
Foo. Hopefully, I typed that right,
but there we go.
All right. So there's madbum.
And you can see [FOREIGN].
Whatever.
Okay? [LAUGH] So
there's the time and date and
you can see it's put a comma there.
Okay? Not 10.7, but 10, 7.
It's like those French have a different word for everything,
but they also have a different way to put the number there.
Okay? So there's French.
Now I'm gonna show you one other language which is kind
of a fun, different, interesting language,
which is Arabic.
So let's go ahead and import Arabic.
Those of you who know anything about
languages will know why this is an interesting language.
So let's duplicate it.
Arabic.
And okay, it's Arabic.
We'll have a country.
We'll have it be Egypt.
They speak Arabic in Egypt.
All those okay.
So now, let's run this in Arabic.
And, whoa, it broke my UI.
Look at that, it put those things over on the right side.
And, what's going on here?
This changed securities on the wrong side.
This was supposed to be over.
So, Arabic is a right to left language, right?
The text flows from the right hand side of the page to
the left.
Not from left to right.
So, not only does that mean the text needs to flow right
to left, but my whole UI needs to flow right to left.
Okay?
So labels need to be on the right with the text going to
the left.
Same thing with these buttons.
Okay? They need to go
for right and left.
So, this is in here.
I have an English keyboard so
it's gonna be left to right typing here.
But if I had an Arabic keyboard,
it would be typing right to left.
So let's go ahead and log in.
That's [LAUGH] this one.
Not this one.
There it is.
And here's our last log in.
Whatever that is in Arabic and here's the time in Arabic.
Okay, from right to left, so it's all right to left.
Okay.
Even this got made right to left.
And, that happened automatically.
Notice I didn't absolutely nothing whatsoever
in my entire storyboard to make that happen.
But if we look at our constraints,
like we look at this constraint right here.
This guy.
Let's look at his constraints.
You see it's trailing space to super view.
Trailing space.
Not right edge to super view.
Okay? So that's just
saying that we wanna be attached to the trailing edge.
And if we're in a right to left language,
that means the other side.
So, this auto layout did the right thing.
It attached this edge over to here.
Because this is the trailing edge.
Everyone understand that?
Okay?
So when you go and do a right to left language, probably
when you run it's not gonna work as nice as this one was.
I was actually very.
Pleased that it just worked, okay?
But sometimes it'll be like oh, oops,
I made an assumption there that was also going to be
left to right, something smashing into each other,
so I really always strongly recommend doing at
least one right to left language, Hebrew or Arabic or
something that tests out that part of your user interface.
Okay?
So that's it for localization.
Pretty powerful system.
Pretty easy, really, for you.
Apple's made it actually quite easy for you.
For the translators, depends, sometimes it's easy for them,
sometimes it's a pain in the neck trying to figure out what
it is you're actually trying to
say to them about where this word appears.
You'll get some funny translation back sometimes
when they don't really understand
what it is you're saying.
But these underlying system is pretty easy to
iterate with them.
Okay. Any questions
about localization?
Okay.
Let's go back to our slide.
Oops.
Slides are here. All right.
Okay.
So, the next topic is Settings, all right?
So the settings is a.
Let's go back here, and let's show this on here.
Okay, so the settings app, every device has a settings
app, it's this little icon right here.
Okay? See that icon right there?
So, I'm gonna click on that and this gives settings for
the whole device.
Okay? We were earlier,
we were looking for example, inside General so that we
could find the Language & Region and all that.
But there's more than General settings here.
There's also application specific settings.
You see them right here?
Mail, Notes, Reminders, Phone.
Those are settings for those apps.
Okay?
And even all the way down at the bottom here, okay?
There's one of our apps that has setting.
Trax?
I don't have, remember doing a settings for Trax.
But that's because Trax used photos library,
used the Camera, etc.
And so
it has some settings that were automatically built into it.
Okay?
But what we're gonna do today is add settings,
specific to our app that would have, you know, some setting,
that's just only our app has that setting.
How do we put the UI in this
general settings app right here?
Okay?
So in the slide here you can see some examples of some app
settings, Maps and Safari have lots of settings, et cetera.
You're gonna build this UI using something like
Info.plist.
okay? [LAUGH] So
it's not exactly gonna build this in your storyboard.
Okay? Very restricted,
can only do a few things but you can
build surprisingly a lot of stuff here with switches and
sliders and text fields.
But anything that's set in this UI is communicated
to your app via NSUserDefaults.
Okay? So
basically, this UI in the settings app is just setting
NSUserDefault in your app.
That's what it's doing.
Okay?
So let's look to see how it works.
You add a little settings bundle to your app.
That's how you get it to display some UI.
And you do that by saying New File and
you go to this place here, iOS, Resource, and
inside there you'll see, Settings Bundle.
'Kay? You pick Settings Bundle and
you're gonna get a sample Settings Bundle.
This is the best thing, for
something that's barely supported it seems like,
in some ways, this was the best thing they did.
Is they just gave you a sample one, okay?
And the sample one, at least as of this lecture, that they
give you has a little grouping there with the text field.
A little switch, and a slider.
And if you open up the, inside the settings bundle
there's this little file in there called, root.plist,
as you'll see.
And it's just a bunch of property list and
that's describing what's in there.
So, let's look at this thing on the right, the UI, and
what's corresponding on the left.
So look at on the left where it says Item 0 Group
at the top.
See that's making that little group.
The gray group thing.
It's just basically a static table view.
And, that is basically causing a static table view
section to be created.
And, that's the title of it, Group.
And then, see item 1, Text field, name?
That's got
things that describe what that text field is.
It's not just the title of the text field, which is name.
But it's also things like, what's the default value, and
what kind of keyboard should I bring up, a URL keyboard, or,
you know, just a normal alphabetic keyboard,
or whatever.
Then you see item two, toggle switch, all right?
It's got the toggle switch there.
Item three, is the slider, you've got the slider.
Slider very limited.
You can specify an image on the left, and
an image on the right.
Okay? That's the only thing you
can kind of customize about the slider.
So if you add a minimum,
maximum value you have to do it with images.
It is localizable.
I'll talk about that in a second.
And if you lookin all of them see number one, two and three,
they have a line there, identifier.
You see in item one it's called name preference.
In item two it's called Enable Preference
in line three is called Slider Preference.
That is the name of the NSUserDefault
that this is going to be set to, okay?
So every time that slider moves it's going to update
the slider under bar preference NSUserDefault in
this app, okay?
So, pretty straight forward and simple actually.
Localization is a pain in the neck for settings.
Okay? Because
the X lift stuff doesn't work with it.
You have to do it all manually.
You essentially create these directories inside the setting
bundle called a two letter code for the language, .lproj.
And inside there you're gonna put a strings file for
each page of your settings UI.
Now in the previous one, we just saw one page.
But it's actually possible to click and
transition into another page of settings, okay?
You see this in a lot of settings.
That's where they're kind of going down multiple levels.
So you can do that.
And so for every level you've gotta have a strings file.
The strings file looks like this.
And you have to send these off to your translator and
they have to translate them as well,
in addition to the x-lifts.
So this is a pain.
I'm sure Apple eventually will
integrate into the x-lifts system.
However, it's a little bit showing you that settings is
not a primary user interface for your app.
You really wanna use it sparingly.
You don't want people to have to go to Settings unless
you know, there's setting something that's really gonna
be set once and maybe never changed again.
Okay?
Or, something that they set and then,
it only changes in the future because something big happens.
Like, in mail, you set your accounts up once.
And they only change if you decide
not to use that email account or you change your password.
Maybe you have to go back in there.
That makes sense for
that to not be in the main user interface.
It may be off in settings.
Okay?
But you do not want to have the normal use of your app
require them to be going to settings all of the time.
Okay? If you have a setting that
people are setting
constantly you should have UI in your normal app for it.
'Kay?
This is just UI that you want to kind of get out of the way
of your main UI because people aren't going there very much.
All right? So that's what
setting's about.
So I'm going to do a demo with settings,
but since I won't come back to the slides,
let's talk about what's coming up here.
Wednesday is the alternate final as you know
I need your slides today if you want to present at
that alternate final.
No section on Friday but your final project is due 11:59 and
59 seconds on Friday night.
Okay? Pacific time.
Saturday your slides are due by midnight.
Okay?
Please make your slides 1280 by 720.
In other words widescreen format.
Do not give me those 1024 by 768s or 640 [LAUGH] by 480.
Okay?
Widescreen just like this, like you see right here
because it can be projected right here just like this.
Okay?
I prefer Keynote.
If you can do Keynote, please do Keynote because
what you see in Keynote is what I'm gonna get, and
what everyone's gonna get when I put it on screen.
If you send me a PowerPoint,
Keynote is really good at opening up PowerPoints, but
if you have a weird font in there,
it might get turned into Helvetica or something.
And then it's gonna looks like a mess.
Okay?
So if you can do Keynote, please do,
I understand not everyone has a Mac with Keynote.
Totally understandable.
So PowerPoint I will accept.
But please, if you can do Keynote.
And then, next week normal exam period.
I believe it's Thursday of finals week, 12:15 to 3:15.
If that's, anyone correct me if I'm wrong, but
I think that's when it is.
Then we will do the presentations.
There's so many of you,
this is the largest enrollment we've ever had, so
you'll only get 90 seconds each.
I know that sounds tight.
If we have a lot of people going Wednesday,
maybe I'll try and give you an extra ten seconds or
something like that.
But if you just do the math, a hundred people,
three hours, especially with the time to transition,
walk up and down and technical problems.
We really can't give you more than that, unfortunately.
Any questions before I do this last demo?
And then we'll be done for today.
Okay.
So, the way I'm gonna do the Settings bundle,
is I'm gonna add a setting to Bouncer.
Remember Bouncer?
Thing bouncing, the square, bouncing around?
I'm going to make it so
that bouncer, we can set its elasticity in settings.
Now, elasticity,
you're probably going to be setting a lot in Bouncer.
You want to set it to the way you like Bouncer to happen and
you're just going to leave it.
Okay? So
that's what we're going to do.
So let's go back to Bouncer.
Here's Bouncer.
That's where we left it off last time.
I'm gonna run Bouncer here just so
that we can remind ourselves what it looks like.
All right. So Bouncer,
remember this thing just bounces off the walls.
And it's pretty bouncy.
It's not super bouncy.
But if I take it up to the top and I just let it fall down.
You know, it bounces about half way back up, okay?
Slowly bouncing less and less.
And that's because we set the elasticity in Bouncer
over here to be 0.85.
So it's not full bouncing, okay?
It's 85% bouncing.
So it's losing energy with each collision,
but not too bad.
So this is the thing that we're going to have
set in settings.
Instead of being point 85 all the time we're going to set it
in settings.
So let's just add a settings bundle to our app.
So we go new file, we go IoS resource,
here's settings bundle right here.
Just double click, what do you want to call it?
We'll call it settings,
that what people usually call their settings bundles.
And here it is, our settings bundle right here.
If you click on the bundle itself,
you just get this little lego brick.
But if you go down here to root.plist, you will see
here is that default one I was showing you in the slide,
that it gives you.
And here is the strings that go along with this plist.
This is what you would send off to your localizer right
here for this particular plist file.
So we're gonna Run just to see this UI, which has got
a group with a text field and a toggle switch and a slider.
We're gonna see that in our Settings app.
So let's just Run.
Now, every time you Run, it installs the Settings
bundle into your system.
So here we go.
We have this thing, it's 0.85, so let's go over to settings.
Actually, let's make our slide a little easier here,
a little less swapping around.
Let's put Bouncer on this page.
Okay? So let's go to settings and
now, when we go down to settings, see we got Bouncer.
Okay, it added things for bouncer and
if we click on Bouncer.
There it is.
That name field right here.
And Enabled in this slider.
Okay? So that's a good start.
Now, let's change this UI right here to be what we want,
which is we just really want a slider for elasticity.
I'm going to keep this group at the top, but instead of
calling it group, I'm going to call it Elasticity.
Elasticity, okay?
And I don't need a text field.
We're not typing a text field.
So you can delete things by just hitting
Backspace to delete.
Same thing, toggle switch.
Delete, I don't want that.
But I do want the slider.
I'm gonna have the default value be the 0.85
that we have now.
Let's say the maximum is about 1.1.
If we start getting to more than 1.1,
in other words when it bounces off it gains energy,
that thing is going to be ripping around so fast.
So that's the maximum we want to allow.
The minimum, we don't really want zero,
that would be just death.
So let's make it like 0.5, which is pretty dampened.
But not complete death when it hits something, okay?
And then I don't really like this as my NS user default
name.
I'm gonna call it, how about BouncerBehavior, since that's
the class that we're gonna be setting this in, .Elasticity.
Okay? It's kind of decent name.
Okay? Comma name spaced name.
So now, we're gonna get a slider
with elasticity as the name of the group.
So let's take a look at that.
All right. So we go
back here to Settings.
And we look at Bouncer.
Here it is. Elasticity.
And we've got this on sliders.
Now as I move this slider, it is changing that
ns user default from 1.1 all the way down to 0.5.
Okay? 1.1, 0.5,
and everywhere in between.
Okay?
Now, it's only setting the NS user default at this point.
We're not actually looking at the value.
So when we go back.
Sorry. When we go back here to
Bouncer, it's still bouncing along at 0.85,
no matter what I set that to, okay?
So now, we need to look at the NS user default and
have it change the elasticity.
We can do that right here.
Nice and wide.
I set a 0.85.
I'm gonna say,
NSUserDefaults.standardUserDe- faults().doubleForKey.
And, we called it Bouncer.
I should probably have a nice constant for this,
but we'll type it in for speed here.
To behavior, that elasticity.
Now, this is a double.
And elasticity here is a CGFloat.
So we need to put that in CGFloat.
Okay?
And so, that's good.
So let's go ahead and now see what happens.
Okay. So
it looks like we have low elasticity.
See how it's barely bouncing?
'Kay?
And so let's go look and see what our elasticity is set to.
Bouncer, we have it right in the middle.
So let's set it to high elasticity.
And go back and see if that'll work.
So we go up to Bouncer.
And, oh. It's still low.
Well, what's going on?
Okay? Why didn't that pick that up?
That's because we only call this once when our app starts.
So whatever the elasticity was in the settings
at the time our app launched, that's what we get.
And if the user goes and
changes it, it makes no difference.
So, how do we make it so that the user can go to settings,
change the elasticity and come back.
And it will be different in Bouncer without quitting and
restarting Bouncer and all that stuff?
Well, the answer to that is Notifications.
There's an NS notification you get every time your NS user
defaults change.
Okay? That's pretty cool.
So, let's go NS Notification Center, Default Center,
add Observer for name.
The name is NSUserDefaultDidChange,
as you might imagine.
okay?
The object is I don't care, anybody can send me that.
The queue, we'll just do the main queue, and using
block this is what's gonna happen when things change.
And I'm actually going to do our closing,
trailing, closure notation here.
So here's the notification, this getting passed to me,
I actually don't even need to look at that.
And inside here I'm just gonna do this.
Okay.
So every time my NS user default change,
I'm just going to update the elasticity.
Okay.
Now really, to be a good citizen here,
I should be doing, let observer equals.
And somewhere else, I should be doing
NSNotificationDefaultCenter remove observer, this thing.
But the way our app is right now, pretty much Bouncer
comes up, takes over the screen and never leaves.
So it's probably okay to not be doing that here.
Besides, it's a demo so we're not going to do it.
But generally, when you add an observer,
you want to get that observer cookie back and
you want to remove it somewhere sensible.
All right? So let's see if this works.
Okay? Now,
last time we changed the elasticity to 1.1, I think.
Right. See? So look,
this guy's gonna go pretty wild, okay?
He's gaining speed with every bounce.
So let's slow him down.
Let's go over into Settings.
Notice that every time you install it,
it's gonna install it here.
So let's change our elasticity from 1.1 down to really slow.
Okay?
Now, we can go back to Bouncer and
the next time Bouncer hits, it slows down, okay?
See that? Almost dead.
Very little bounce.
Let's go back and change it again.
Go all the way back up to.
Whoops.
Up to high speed.
And the next hit gaining energy.
Oh, yeah.
Gaining more and more speed with every bounce.
Okay?
There we go.
I don't even need to look.
Okay.
[LAUGH] And it just bounced off and just disappeared.
Went into some ether.
Okay. [SOUND] That is it.
I finished early for once today, so thank you all for
coming.
And I'll be here if you have any questions.
>> For more, please visit us at stanford.edu