[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
Okay, well welcome to Stanford CS193p, Winter of 2015.
This is lecture number five.
And, today we're gonna finish up
what were talking about last time.
And talk a little bit about Objective-C compatibility,
because, of course iOS was originally written in
an entirely different language.
And so there's a little bit of
bridging between the Swift world and the old world.
And we're gonna talk about an example of
using AnyObject which is Property Lists.
And I'm gonna do a kind of a brief demo even,
showing you that.
Then we're gonna move onto a completely new topic,
which is views.
So, views on how we draw, and how we handle touch input.
In our UI and so we're gonna go over that, and
I'll be having a demo for that as well.
So, I'm gonna blast through these slides pretty quick.
As usual, the demonstration is probably
a little more elucidating then some of the slides, cuz when
you see it in action, it's a lot easier to understand.
Okay.
So, Objective-C compatibility, so, virtually all the iOS API,
this API that was written over the last, however many years,
in Objective-C, is available from Swift.
And you can't even tell the difference, okay?
It's just kind of, automatically made available.
And, when they designed Swift,
they went to a lot of trouble to make sure that it would,
could be done in a very compatible way.
So, that all of the iOS API, would work,
just fine in Swift.
There's few special data types though, that they've gone
to special care to bridge between the two languages,
and this makes using iOS API from Objective-C, much easier
in Swift, and so, I'm gonna talk briefly about those.
One is NSString.
That is the old way that String were represented,
in iOS, and that is bridged interchangeably to
Swift's String.
You can't really even tell the difference.
If you have a method that takes an NSString,
you can pass a Swift String in there, and vice-versa.
Okay, they're just automatically treated if
they were the same thing,
even though they are quite different things.
String in Swift is not even a class.
Okay, its just a struct.
So, they've done some miraculous work to
bridge these things.
NSArray, which is the old Array,
is bridged to Array of AnyObject.
Okay, so any time you see, an Array of AnyObject in
an iOS API, it's because it was an NSArray before, okay?
Then NSDictionary is an interesting one,
it's bridged to Dictionary where the keys have to be
subclasses of NSObject, and
the values are AnyObject, okay?
Now, you might think, that's gonna be a problem, and
I'll explain why that's not in a moment.
And then of course, Int and
Float, Double, Bool, they are all bridged to NSNumber.
We talked briefly about NSNumber,
we talked about the NSNumber format and all that.
So, NSNumber was the old Objective-C object that
just meant, any kind of numeric value.
And, so anything that used to take an NSNumber, you can
pass a Double, or Float or Int in there, and it'll just work.
Of course, coming back the other way isn't automatic,
because it doesn't really know necessarily what you want.
But you can use the methods like doubleValue or
Int value, like we use doubleValue, in the Calculator.
And of course, Int and Float and Double are also bridged to
the C types int, float, and double.
So, you have an API that takes an int, and hold a C int.
It'll be bridged to take capital I Swift Int.
So, this stuff, all just works completely automatically.
And you don't ever have to do anything.
And it just works.
However, if you wanna be explicit, about the type,
you can cast, okay?
So, it is perfectly legal to cast a Swift String to
an NSString, and it will always work, so
you don't need as?
Okay, it's all a hundred percent guaranteed cast.
And then once you do that,
you have an NSString instead of a String, and so
you can send it messages that are in NSString.
Although you wanna be careful with some of them,
like length, is an NSString method,
that doesn't exist on String.
It doesn't exist on String for a reason.
Because, we talked about this before, you know,
the length of a Unicode String, can vary,
compared to the number of glifs you'll see on screen,
and the new Swift String deals with that, and the old
NSString doesn't really deal with that properly.
So, you gotta be careful, when you start calling NSString
methods that, you know,
there's not, you wanna look for a String equivalent, and
use that if you can, because it's newer, and
it does thinks a little more accurately.
But NSArray is the same thing, you can cast from an Array,
that you have in Swift, to an NSArray, and
then you can call them methods in NSArray.
Like components joined by String, which is kinda cool,
it takes all the components in the Array,
sends them description, takes those descriptions and
joins them by the String you pass as an argument.
This is the same as the join method in Swift's String.
Okay, so, you can look at the documentation for
String and, NSString and NSArray, but
pretty much all the things you can do there, or most
of them anyway, are available in the Swift versions.
But again, if you're passing them back and
forth, it's all automagic, so you'd say.
Now, you might get a little concerned about Dictionary,
because Dictionary, the key has to be an NSObject.
And of course, we know that String, and Array, and
Dictionary in Swift, are not even objects, okay?
They're not AnyObject, or
they're, and they're not an NSObject for sure.
But you can still pass them anywhere you wanna pass in
AnyObject, or a subclass of NSObject, because they
are bridged to classes that inherit from NSObject,
because NSString, NSArray, and
NSDictionary all inherit from NSObject.
So, that means Strings, Swift Strings,
can be the keys in a Dictionary, an NSDictionary,
even though it requires NSObject, okay?
And of course, all three of them can be values,
because, even though they're not really objects,
they are structs, they are bridged to things that can be.
Okay?
So, it is okay to pass a String or
an Array to AnyObject.
You won't even notice this bridge isn't bridging 99% of
the time.
It just happens automatically.
But I just wanted you to know that's going on, so
you don't get kinda confused when you start
seeing NSString, NSArray, what's going on, okay?
They're just being automatically bridged for you.
All right.
So, we talked about AnyObject last time,
and now I'm gonna talk about a use of AnyObject,
which is called Property List.
So, Property List is not a type or
anything like that, it's just a term that we use.
And the definition of that term is, it's in AnyObject,
a Property List is AnyObject, that is known to be,
behind the scenes, one of those six classes.
NSString, an Array,
Dictionary, Number, Data and Date.
Or bridged too with Swift, okay?
So, why do we define this Property List thing?
It's in AnyObject.
It's kind of unwieldy, because you have to do a lot,
a fair amount of casting, ising and asing, cuz
AnyObject, of course, to use it, we have to kinda cast it.
And so, why do we have this thing?
Two reasons really.
One, Property List is used to pass data around blind.
It's like a cookie, right?
In a browser.
It's kind of this just bundle of data,
that only the creator of it knows how to interpret it,
because only they know what Strings, Arrays,
Dictionaries, and stuff are in there.
But to everyone else it,
just looks like AnyObject, so they don't know what it is.
So, all they can do, is pass it around to other things.
So, it's good for blind data passing, the other thing is,
a Property List can be used as generic data structures, okay?
Since it's got Arrays, and
Dictionaries, and Numbers, and Dates, and all that in there.
You can turn a data structure, like your r-ops stack,
in the CalculatorBrain, it has op enums in there,
that's not a generic data structure, but
we can turn it into a generic data structure, for example,
and then do things with it like write it out to disk, or
send it over the network, or things like that.
So, those are the two main reasons we use Property List.
And, a really good use of Property List in
iOS is NSUserDefaults.
So, NSUserDefaults is like a really tiny little database,
and it only knows how to store Property Lists.
Okay?
And it's really for things like settings, and
preferences, stuff like that.
You would never, it's not high performance,
you would never use it for big things like images or
anything like that, just Property Lists, you know,
Dates and Strings and Doubles, and things like that.
It can store and retrieve any Property List, and
it just stores it like a Dictionary,
as if the NSUserDefaults thing itself is a Dictionary.
And, it can store the whole Property List,
like setObject forkey: , that first method you see there.
And, repeat, retrieve all Property List,
or, it can just do little tiny pieces of Property List,
like it has a method set Double,
that will just set a Double for a certain key.
Okay? So,
it's like a Dictionary in it's key value, but
it only stores Property List.
And, the big thing about the way it stores them,
is that it persists when your app is gone, okay?
So, you know,
normally, a Dictionary is stored in the heap.
As soon as your app quits, it's gone.
But this, stays around, so
that when your app launches the next time,
all the data's still there.
So, that's why it's kind of like a database, but
it's very small, okay?
For preference and settings.
Here's how you use NSUserDefaults.
You use this type method in NSUserDefaults called
standardUserDefaults.
This gives you an instance of an NSUserDefaults.
You're always gonna use
the same instances like a shared instance.
You'll always to use the same one.
And then you just send it messages like, you know,
setObject forkey:, store this Property List, and
getObject forkey: to get it back.
Now, the changes you make in there,
are automatically saved, but, there is a method called
synchronized, which is kinda like save, which can force it,
to save out to disc.
Why do you ever need synchronized when it
auto saves?
Well, in auto save, when things happen like you app
stops being the front most app,
the user switched to another app.
So, your app is still there, but
it switched to the background.
It'll save then.
So, it won't always save when you want, and
especially when you're debugging, okay?
When you hit stop in the debugger,
it doesn't save, okay?
And so, you probably wanna throw some synchronizes in
there, to save this thing out,
especially when you're debugging.
It's not really that expensive to synchronize,
especially if there's not much data in there,
which there shouldn't be, because it's small.
So, it can't hurt too much to throw them in there.
Okay?
And yeah, synchronize return to Bool,
whether it failed or not.
But if it failed, there's really not much you can do.
So, a lot of times people don't even look at the return
values synchronize, they just synchronize, and they pray.
But, it's only not gonna save if like the disk is full or
something, that virtually never happens.
All right, so, I'm gonna do a little demo here.
And show you a little more about Property List.
And also AnyObject,
cuz you've never seen AnyObject in action.
And what we're gonna do, is add a property to our
CalculatorBrain, which gets its program.
Okay?
So, our CalculatorBrain has a program, especially your
versions, where you added variables to it.
It's got this kind of program,
it's almost like a little computer program.
You can execute that program, set its variables, it's great.
So, it would be nice if we could get that program.
But we don't wanna reveal our internal data structure, and
there's nothing anyone can do with that program.
So, we're really just getting it as a cookie.
And the only thing you can do with it, is give it back
to the CalculatorBrain, or another CalculatorBrain in
the future, and then say, evaluate.
Okay, so you see the value of having this?
So, basically getting the program out of
the CalculatorBrain and send it back.
But we're gonna return it as a Property List.
It's gonna be AnyObject.
People are gonna look at this var, and
it's gonna be of type AnyObject, and
all they can do is get it, and then set it back.
Okay?
So, what would that look like?
Let's go over here to our Calculator.
So, I've gone much bigger font here.
Hopefully everybody, is this big enough?
Yeah?
Okay.
All right.
So, this is Calculator as I last left it.
It doesn't have your enhancements to it for
the variables.
And I'm just gonna add a var here.
A public var.
Okay?
Called program, and
it's gonna be type AnyObject, but I'm gonna put comment here
that says guaranteed to be a Property List.
So, the callers know that this is a Property List.
So, for example, they could put it into NSUserDefaults.
Or they could write it out to disc.
I haven't taught you how to write it out to disc, but
you can do it.
So, they could do that with it,
cuz they know it's a Property List, okay?
So, this is going to be a computed property.
Okay, so we're gonna have a get and a set.
And when the get,
we're just gonna get some sort of Property
List representation of our internal data structure.
And when you set, we're gonna take that Property List and
turn it back into our private representation.
So, the get,
how are we gonna represent ourselves as a Property List
because this is really our internal data structure here,
it's Array of op, op is an enum,
clearly enums are not NSDates, or NSStrings, or NSArrays.
So, we can't just return this thing, okay?
Cuz that's not a Property List.
So, we need to return some sort of Property List.
And I'm gonna return an Array of Strings.
And the String is either gonna be the symbol of an op,
in which case I will look it up in known ops, or
the String will be an numeric representation of
the String of the operand rather.
Right? The Double will
turn into a String.
Which I happened to have a var that does exactly that.
Okay? This turns an enum op,
into a String.
And I know how to turn it back.
Because I know how to use a number formatter to turn
the String of a operand back into a Double and
obviously I know how to look up binary and
uniary operations in our known ops.
Okay?
So, we could say something along these lines.
Our get, I'm gonna show you a much better get in a second,
but one way we could do our get is we could just say,
we could make a returnValue that is going to be
an Array of String.
Okay, in fact let's just create an empty Array of
String here, and then we can just go through our ops,
in our opStack here, and for each op,
we can just say returnValue.append, an op's description.
On to the end of it, and then we could return, returnValue.
Right, makes sense, I just my internal data structure into
a Property List, because this is a Property List.
Notice I can return, this through AnyObject,
because Arrays are bridged, and
NSArray which happens to be an object.
Okay.
But this is an awful lot of code for this.
We can actually do this in one line of code, okay?
So if you paid attention in my last lecture, you'll remember
that I told you about this function called map.
And I can actually just return my opStack mapped,
so that each element description is returned.
So I don't need any of this, okay?
So everyone understand this line of code right here?
This is just a little closure that gets the opportunity to
convert every single thing inside opStack,
which is an op, these are ops, into a String and it takes
this String and maps them all and returns a new Array.
Okay?
So when you start getting familiar with Swift and
what it can do,
you'll start realizing a lot of things that take five or
six line of code, you can just do them in one.
Okay, but it does take some experience.
So now let's talk about going the other way.
So now we have, someone gives us back our program.
We wanna load our opStack back up.
Well the first thing we wanna make sure is that the thing
they're giving us back is an Array of these symbols.
Because they could just give me junk,
because it's AnyObject they could set it to anything.
So, I, I want to make sure that's what it is.
So what I'm going to do,
I'm going to let opSymbols equal newValue, right?
newValue remember we are in the setter here.
So, newValue is the newValue which is in AnyObject.
As an Array of String, because that's what it has to be.
If this thing that they passed in is not an Array of String,
I don't know what to do with it.
So really here what I wanna do is, if let as question mark,
because they could pass me anything.
And so, here I'm using the as to make sure this AnyObject
they pass me is actually and Array of Strings, okay?
If it is, now I can convert back, so
I'm gonna create something called my new opStack which
is just gonna be an Array of ops and I'm just gonna go for
each opSymbol in this opSymbols.
opSymbols is this thing right here, that's the Array,
that's the newValue, the AnyObject converted.
Into an Array of Strings, okay?
So for each one if I can find a known op,
that matches that symbol then this must be an op,
and so I will just add that op
to, to my stack, otherwise I'm gonna see
if I could turn that String into an operand, and I'm gonna
do that with if let operand equal NSNumberFormatter.
Okay, numberFromString, I'm gonna pass it
this opSymbol that I got out of that Array it gave me.
I'm going to use optional chaining here and
put a question mark, then doubleValue, okay.
Remember optional chaining, if you have an expression like
this, this whole expression, and if anything along the way
returns nil then this whole expression will return nil.
If you put a question mark after that term.
So, numberFromString can return nil if this is
not a String, that can be interpreted as a number.
So by putting a question mark here it says, okay?
If that's nil than just return nil back to here.
Otherwise keep going and send it doubleValue.
So this operand is either going to not get set,
because of the if let, or it's going to be a Double,
which is what this doubleValue comes out of here.
Okay, so that's kind of explaining from last week how
we did this number formatter thing.
So in this case,
I can just append onto the end of it that a new op.
So, we'll say dot operand with that operand.
So we're just putting a new op on there.
So now I've built a new opStack using all those Strings,
and I can just return that new opStack.
Not return it, sorry.
I'm gonna set my opStack equal to that new op
Stack, okay?
That's it.
Any questions about that?
>>Property List?
Like that's just because.
>> This is documentation,
this is a public thing, it's not private, and I'm just
documenting to anyone who's using it that this is true.
I can document this even better using a typealias.
So you can basically have a typealias,
which is an alias for a type.
It's just a way of another type, and
I could have a typealias called PropertyList,
which is equals AnyObject.
Then I could have this type be PropertyList, okay?
So I just created PropertyList as an alias for AnyObject, so
someone looking at this is gonna go,
whoa, what the heck is PropertyList?
Now they're going to look at this typealias, and
say, oh, that's AnyObject, but they're really going to
understand that I'm returning the Property List to them, and
the reason it's Property List, again, so
I can throw it again as user defaults or whatever, okay?
But otherwise, it's only good, the only thing it's good for
is giving it back to me to reset my program in
the future; that's all this thing is good for.
Now, you're gonna wanna add this to your assignment for
assignment three, okay?
So, all right, back to slides.
I'm not gonna, I don't have time to really run this
unfortunately due to in test code because we are
schedule constraint here.
So let's go back to here, continue.
All right, so now let's talk about, new thing here,
which is views, okay, totally new topic.
A view, that is to say,
a subclass of the class UIView in iOS
represents a rectangular area on the screen.
That defines a coordinate space to draw in, and
also to handle touch events, okay?
That's what a view is, and you are going to learn today,
how to make your own views.
The views are hierarchical, so,
views are within views are within views.
Any view only has one superview.
Right, it's only contained directly in one view.
But, it can have any number of subviews.
So in our Calculator, we had a top level view,
which I'm gonna talk about in a moment,
and then we had a lot of subviews, all the buttons,
the labels, those are all UIView subclasses.
Okay, so we made a whole bunch.
A bunch of subviews in that view.
But you can go even deeper.
It's hierarchical multi-layer.
We can go as deep as we want.
The two, you can see the two properties there for
getting your super view.
Notice it returns a optional, because you
can have a view that's not currently on screen.
It's not currently in the view hierarchy so that can be nil.
Your subviews, I show Array of UIView there.
Actually the subview's property is an Array of AnyObject,
again for historical reasons, but
there will always be UIViews in there.
So don't even worry about that, okay?
And usually in this class on the the slides.
If something's an Array of AnyObject,
if there's gonna be a certain kind of thing in there,
I'll say, Array of the certain kind of thing.
But when you write your code, then,
obviously, you might see, oh, that's Array of AnyObject, and
that's again, the bridging will work here,
automatically, so, no worries there. UIWindow.
There is a certain thing called a UIWindow.
It's a subclass UIView but it has no meaning in iOS.
There is a UIWindow it's at the very,
very, very top of each device screen but
you never send it any messages really.
You don't interact with it.
It's all about views.
On a desktop windows matter.
But on iOS, it's all about views, okay?
So don't worry about UIwindow.
This hierarchy of views, subviews and
superviews, is created usually, graphically.
You can drag things out in the StoryBoard.
You can drag views inside other views to
create your hierarchy.
But you can do it in code as well.
It's pretty rare to do it in code, but you can.
There's two methods here addSubview and
removeFromSuperview, addSubview is sent to
the prospective superview.
In other words to the place you wanna add your,
this view into.
And removeFromSuperview is sent to the view that you
want to remove.
So these are sent to different people,
okay, removeFromSuperview means remove yourself from
your superview.
So, where does the view hierarchy start?
Where is the kind of the root,
the top level of this hierarchy, and
the answer is very simple, but, for some reason,
students have a very difficult time understanding this one.
There is a property in your UIView Controller
called view, and
it is the top level view in the scene in the StoryBoard.
All right. So you have this StoryBoard.
You've got your scene that we've seen like your
Calculator one.
The top level one the place where you're going to add
your top level views is called view in your view controller.
It's just a property in UIView Controller.
So it really couldn't be simpler, okay?
Sometimes students they just forget that's there and there
like all right how do I add something to my StoryBoard?
You know in code or something like that.
Well you just you add it to the view of
your UIView Controller, okay?
So, let's talk about initializing a view.
As usual, as I've kind of recommended, you probably want
to avoid doing an initializer, if you can.
So, to initialize any properties in
your view hopefully using equals or
some of the other ways we've talked about doing it.
But, in UIView it's slightly more likely that you
might want to have an initializer.
So it's a slightly complicated thing.
Only slightly.
In that UIView has two initializers you
have to deal with.
And that's because UIViews can be created in
two different ways.
In code by just saying UIView and
this frame initializer, which is just the frame in the super
view coordinate system where this view is gonna live.
But then there's also this init with coder.
And I'm not gonna talk about coders and
archiving and all that.
But that is the initializer that is called when the view
comes out of a StoryBoard.
So, if you create a view by dragging on a StoryBoard,
its initializer is this coder thing, okay?
So, if you want, if you absolutely have to use
an initializer to initialize something in your UIView,
you're gonna want to implement both of these things.
And I recommend this kind of format here.
Where you override init with frame there.
That is a designated initializer in UIView.
And then, there's actually a required initializer,
which is the decoder one.
So if you implement the init with frame you have to
implement the coder one, it's required,
cuz as soon as you implement the init with frame,
you'll no longer inherit all of your designated
initializers you won't inherit the init with the coder.
So, basically implement them both, and
then just factor your initialization code into some
setup method or something, and call that, okay?
So, that's only if you absolutely have to
have an initializer.
All right, there's another alternative to initializing.
Which is if you can wait until the initialization is finished
but you want something really early in the view's life,
如果你需要在视图加载完成后立即执行一些操作，
you can implement this method awakeFromNib.
你可以实现awakeFromNib方法。
But that only works for
但是只有storyboard中的视图
views that come out of a StoryBoard, okay?
才会调用这个方法，记住了吗？
awakeFromNib means I just awoke from coming out of
awakeFromNib表示我已经从storyboard中
a StoryBoard.
加载出来了。
So now you can initialize me.
你可以对我做一些初始化操作。
So it's a little bit limited, because it only is good for
不过这个方法使用很有局限性，
views that come out of a StoryBoard.
因为只是针对storyboard中的视图。
But it is an alternative.
但是这的确是另外一种方法。
Now okay, so
好的，
that's all I'm going to say about that actually.
以上是关于视图初始化方面的内容。
Now let's go on to how do we.
现在我们来看看怎样在视图中
Draw and handle events in this rectangular area.
绘制和处理事件（触摸事件）。
Well we need a coordinate system to work in.
我们需要一个坐标系来完成这些操作。
So there's some data structures I'm going to
所以我会大致介绍一些
show you real quick to get us started here, that we're
我们在绘制和处理触摸事件中，
gonna use when we're drawing and handling events.
需要用到的数据结构。
First of all, all coordinates are gonna be CGFloats.
首先，所有的坐标系的单位都是CGFloats。
Okay, CGFloats is a type in Swift struct.
是的，CGFloats在swift中是结构体。
And always use CGFloat when you're drawing or
记住，在绘制和处理触摸事件的时候，
handling events in a view.
我们都用CGFloat类型。
Do not use Double.
不要用double类型。
Do not use Float.
也不要用Float类型。
If you use those in your homework,
如果你在课后作业中使用这些类型，
you're gonna get dinged, okay?
你就会死翘翘了，明白吗？
CGFloat.
只能用CGFloat。
Now Doubles and
你可以通过初始化方法，
Floats can be converted to a CGFloat using the initializer.
将Double和Float类型转换成CGFloat类型。
CGFloat has initializer for Floats and Doubles.
你也可以通过CGFloat的初始化方法
that you can pass and turn into a Float.
把CGFloat类型转换为double或float类型。
But, you always want things to be into CGFloat when you're
但是你在坐标系中，
working in the coordinate system, okay?
只会使用CGFloat类型。记住了吗？
Now, there's a couple other structures that
这还有一些比较重要的
are important here.
结构体。
One is CGPoint.
一个是CGPoint。
It's just two Floats, X and Y.
它由x和y两个Float类型组成。
Just defines a point in the coordinate system.
它用来定义坐标系中的一个点。
Couldn't be simpler.
很容易理解。
Okay? And there's also CGSize,
然后，另外一个是CGSize，
just defines a width and
它在坐标系中定义
a height in the coordinate system.
长和宽。
Okay, so these are just simple structs.
是的，就是一些简单的结构体而已。
That's all they are, structs.
他们都是结构体。
I don't know, certainly Point,
我不太确定，貌似
I don't think has any other methods on it or anything.
Point并没有其他的方法。
Size, maybe, I don't think so, though.
Size可能有，不过也不一定。
But these two are combined, the points and
Size和point组合在一起，
the size, to CGRect.
就是CGRect。
So CGRect is struct that has a point and a size.
所以CGRect是由point和size组成的结构体。
The point is the origin of the rect.
point是这个矩形的原点。
Upper left, which I'm going to talk about in a second.
它在左上角，我马上会详细解释。
And then the size is the width and height.
然后是size，它表示矩形的宽和高。
Now rect has a lot of methods on it, okay?
矩形结构体有很多方法，知道吗？
Rect has things like minX,
比如minX,
which is the left edge of the rect.
它表示矩形的左边界。
Or midY, which is the midpoint of the rectangle vertically.
又比如midY,表示矩形垂直方向上的中点。
Or intersects.
还有intersects方法。
And you pass another Rect, and it'll tell you,
你传递另外一个矩形进去，它会返回一个布尔值，
Boolean, whether it intersects that Rect, right?
来判断这两个矩形是否相交，明白？
The two Rects overlap.
或者说他们是否重叠。
Or, intercept, which says, take this other Rect and
intercept方法可以创建一个，
create a smaller rectangle,
更小的矩形，
which is the intersection of those two Rects.
通过两个矩形交叉的部分。
Or contains point.
contains方法。
Okay, we passed a point and
我们传递一个point进去，
it'll tell you whether it contains that point.
它告诉你这个点是否在矩形中。
So rect is this struct, but
所以，rect这个结构体，
it has a lot of cool methods in there.
有很多很酷的方法。
A whole bunch more.
一大堆。
You can just type a rect, type and
你只需要键入rect，
then a dot Xcode show you all the cool methods it has, okay?
然后打一个点，Xcode会提示出所有这些方法。
All right, so those are the types of data types we're
好的，以上所有这些结构体，
gonna use to talk about our coordinate system and
都是关于坐标系和在坐标系中操作
to write our code in coordinate system.
时所需要用的数据结构。
So let's talk about the Views coordinate system itself.
接下来我们看看视图的坐标系统。
First of all, origin upper left.
首先，原点在左上角。
Some of you might be used to origin lower left,
你或许遇到过原点在左下角的坐标系，
like Cartesian coordinates,
比如Cartesian坐标系，
the origin is in the lower left.
原点就在左下角。
But all this origin that you're using a view is in
但是view的坐标原点
the upper left.
都在左上角。
So, that means increasing Y is down the screen,
也就是说，Y轴向下延伸，
increasing X is across.
X轴向右延伸。
So, I put an example, 500 dot 35, 500 comma 35, over there.
比如这里有一个点（500，35）。
It's 500 across, and only 35 down, okay?
它相对于左上角
From the upper left.
向右500单位距离，向下35单位距离，明白吗？
The units that we're talking about here are points
在这里我们用的单位是点，
not pixels.
不是像素。
Okay.
是的。
Pick high, very high resolution displays have more
高分屏中，每一个点可能表示
than one pixel per point.
多个像素。
Okay, 'cuz they are able to draw very find curves,
这样就可以绘制非常平滑的曲线，
very fine text, et cetera.
文本等。
You don't usually care
你通常不需要在乎
about the difference between points and pixels.
点和像素直接的区别。
It's automatically handled for
因为在你绘制文本或者曲线的时候，
you because you're doing things like drawing text or
系统会自动帮你配置
drawing an arc and the system automatically uses as much
一个点到底应该占多少个像素
pixels as it can to make things nice.
才能使绘制更完美。
But occasionally you do care,
但有些时候你需要在意这些，
because maybe you're drawing something very finely detailed
特别是你需要处理和控制
and you want to control pixel boundaries.
非常精细的细节和像素边境的是时候。
And if you want to do that you can call this,
你可以访问这个属性
get this property in view called contentScaleFactor
contentScaleFactor
and it will return the number of pixels per point.
它会告诉你一个点占多少个像素。
So on a retina display, that's gonna be 2.
在retina屏中，一点表示2个像素。
On a non-retina display, that will be 1.
非retina屏中表示一个像素。
It could be anything, though.
当然在其他屏幕中或许是任意个像素。
Okay?
明白吗？
So you shouldn't write your code assuming it's 2 or 1.
所以你不能直接用2或1把代码写死。
You should just write your code, get the contentScaleFactor
你在写代码的时候，
and you'll know how many pixels per point.
应该用contentScaleFactor来获取这个值。
Okay?
记住了吗？
99% of the time, you don't have to worry about this, but
百分之九十九的情况下，你不需要担心这个问题，但是
in your assignment three, hint, hint, you might have to.
在课后作业3中，你可能需要处理这个问题。
Okay.
好的。
So what about the boundaries of where drawing happens.
那么，我们绘制区域的边界在哪里？
You've got this rectangular area.
你已经有一个矩形区域。
Well, there's a very important property called bounds,
另外，有一个非常重要的属性，叫做bounds，
which is a CGRect, which describes the area you're
他是CGRect类型，它定义了坐标系中
drawing in in your own coordinate system.
的绘制区域。
Okay? It's important that it's in
明白吗？需要特别注意的是，
your own coordinate system.
绘制是相对于自身的坐标系。
Because these views can be scaled and even rotated and
因为视图可以被拉伸，旋转
translated to other you know, coordinates systems.
或者变换等（父视图坐标系中）。
But when you're using the bounds and
但是你用bounds属性的时候，
you're drawing it yourself, you have this rectangle and
你是在自身坐标系绘制，你知道这个矩形
you know where it is.
的确切位置。
Now the origin of your bounds usually is 0,0.
bounds的原点通常是（0，0）。
But you could define it to mean something else, for
但是你可以更改它，
example, scroll views they define their origin to
比如，scroll view在scroll的时候会
be where they are in the thing they're scrolling,
更改它的原点至scroll的位置，
that's just what they define origin to be, but
这是scroll view定义bounds原点的方式，
90% of the time, your origin is just going to be 0,0.
但是百分之九十的情况下，bounds的原点是（0，0）。
So, the width and
宽和高
height is what you're going to care about,
才是你需要关心的，
how big a space am I drawing into.
我可以在多大的区域绘制？
There are two other properties that often get confused with
还有两个属性，容易和bounds混淆
bounds, but don't let this happen to you.
我希望你不会这样。
One is center.
一个是center。
Center is the center of your view rectangle in your
center是你自身视图矩形的中点，
superview's coordinate system, not in yours.
不过它是相对于父视图的坐标系，而不是自身的。
So if you write code that say, oh, I'm gonna start to
如果你这样写代码，我将在矩形中心
draw something in middle of my rectangle.
绘制一些东西。
I'll get center.
我会得到中心点。
Aah!
啊哈！
That's wrong.
这样会出问题。
Okay? Center is in your super view.
明白吗？center是相对于父视图的坐标系。
Center positions you.
center定义你在父视图的位置。
It has nothing to do with how you draw.
它和绘制操作没有关系。
It just says where you are in your super view.
它仅仅用来在你父视图中定位。
Same thing, frame, frame is a rectangle in your
同样，frame是父视图坐标系中
super view's coordinate system that contains you.
用来包含子视图的。
Okay, it contains all of you, of your drawing.
是的，它包含子视图的所有区域，包括绘制部分。
But it's in your super user coordinates systems so
但是它是相对于父视图的坐标系，
it's only good to position you, not for drawing.
所以它只是用来定位子视图，与绘制无关。
When you're drawing, you use bounds.
绘制的时候，你使用bounds。
To kind of give you a picture of this,
为了更形象地说明这个，
as better like you might think that
你可以这样认为
the frame size is exactly the same as the bound size.
frame的size和bounds的size总是相同的。
Right, if it's a rectangle that contains my rectangle,
不是吗？如果一个矩形要完全包含我，
it must be exactly the same size.
它必须和我的尺寸一样大。
But no, because view can be rotated.
但也有例外，因为视图可以旋转。
Okay? And
明白吗？
if you rotate your view like this green view,
如果你像这个绿色视图这样，旋转你的视图，
look how much bigger the frame is.
你可以看到，frame要大的多。
The rectangle that contains you is much bigger than you.
包含你的矩形，要你你自己大得多。
Because you're tilted.
因为你是倾斜的。
All right?
对吗？
Make sense?
明白吗？
So don't confuse frame and center, which are about
所以不要混淆了，frame和center是用来定位的，
positioning, with bounce which is your size and
而bounds，是为绘制操作定义的
area that you're drawing into in your own coordinate system.
自身坐标系。
Okay?
明白吗？
Okay, so creating views.
接下来，视图的创建。
How do we create views?
我们怎样创建一个视图？
Most often views are created by dragging them out to
大部分的视图是直接
the StoryBoard.
从storyboard中拖出来，而生成的。
That's 95% of the time.
百分之九十五都是这样。
And af, but
但是，
of course, your views aren't sitting in the Object Pallet,
官方视图可能不能满足你的需要，
there's buttons and sliders, but there's no your view.
这里有按钮，滑条等，但是可能没有你需要的视图。
So you have to drag it out of generic view.
这时候，你就需要先拖一个原始视图（UIView）。
It's kind of at the bottom of the pallet and
就在控件区的底部，
you just drag it out.
拖出来就可以了。
Once you drag it out though,
一旦你拖出来这个视图后，
you have to go to the Identity Inspector and change the class
你需要在它的Identity Inspector去
of that view that you dragged out, so that it's your class.
把对应的类修改你自己的实现类。
Okay? So it's a two step process.
明白吗？需要两步来完成这个操作。
You drag a view, your custom view out and then you change
先拖一个视图出来，
this class to view whatever your custom class is on rare
然后把对应的类改为你自己的类，
occasion, you might create an instance of your view in code.
只有在很少情况下，你才需要用纯代码创建视图。
Probably never in this class,
至少本课程上永远不会，
maybe in your final project, although I doubt it.
期末项目上可能会，但我还是怀疑。
You just do that using UIView's frame initializer.
你可以为构造器提供一个
Right? So you just say
frame值来
view equals UIView frame.
创建视图。
You can even do UIView with no arguments and
你也可以不传参数，
it'll give you a CGRect to zero which is a frame zero
这样视图的frame值就默认为
size and width and
then you could later set its frame to position the view.
So here's an example of creating a view in code.
I'm going to use UILabel.
UILabel is a subclass of UIView so I can send it.
UILabels parentheses frame.
So I just give it this frame which is kind of in
the upper left.
Notice I've created this view but it's not on screen yet.
Okay.
Assuming this code here is in a view controller,
I could then say view.addSubview.
Cuz remember view is a property in
my view controller which is that top level view.
And I could say add subview of the label and
boom, it'll appear on screen.
Okay? At 20,
20, width 100, height 50.
Okay?
So it is possible to create views in code.
We almost never do that in iOS.
We use StoryBoards.
Okay, so when do I wanna create my own UIView?
Right?
Well, when don't you want to?
Well you don't want to if you want a button or a slider or
anything where there's already an iOS view.
But if you want to do something that
those things can't do, draw something special or
handle touch events like swipes and
taps and pinches, differently or for a different purpose.
Then those things then you create your own custom view.
So, we're going to focus on drawing today, and
I'll do gestures in the next lec, in the next lecture.
To draw in your UIView,
all you need to do is override this method drawRect.
Okay, very simple method only takes one argument.
In the code, it's actually called Rect, but
I've renamed it to be regionThatNeedsToBeDrawn, so
that people understand what that argument is.
That argument is purely an optimization.
It's just the system saying, hey, draw yourself and really,
I only care about this rectangle of you.
But you can draw your, the whole self if you want.
But this is the only rectangle I really care about.
So if you had a View that knew how to draw parts of itself,
okay, then it could only draw the part that's in
this rectangle, but
you can completely ignore this rectangle if you want.
It's purely an optimization.
Okay?
This is very important to understand,
you never call drawRect, ever, never.
Never.
Okay?
If you call drawRect in your homework,
you're going to be a major ding.
Because I'm standing here in front of
you with red text on my slide.
Saying, never.
Okay.
Do not call drawRect, drawRect is called by the system.
Okay?
It's called by the system when your view needs to be redrawn.
How does the system know your needs,
view needs to be redrawn?
Because somebody called setNeedsDisplay on your view.
And you can call it on yourself if you want.
If something has changed about your view, some property or
something that would change the way it's drawn,
you call set needs display on yourself,
eventually the system will call your drawRect.
But it's got to set some things up first, okay.
There's other views around you.
That it has to get organized.
Okay, so never call drawRect, drawRect it's called for you.
When you call set in use display, you can specify I
really only need this rectangle redisplayed and
then obviously,
that rectangle's gonna show up in the argument to drawRect.
Okay, but if multiple people call set in use display with
different rectangles, probably the union of those
rectangles might get called here one time for drawRect.
Okay?
Make sense?
All right.
So, how do you implement this, pow,
all-powerful drawRect method?
You can use, kind of a C-like, function-based API,
called Core Graphics.
That's what it's all based on.
Or you can use a nice object-oriented, thing,
called UIBezierPath, which is what we're gonna use,
because we like object-oriented.
But since the underlying stuff core graphics is what
UIBezierPath is built on, I'm gonna kinda explain a little
bit about the concepts of Core Graphics.
How one draws in Core Graphics.
The first thing in Core Graphics that's important is,
you have to get a context to draw in.
Okay? So
if you're printing you'll have a printing context.
If you're drawing on screen you'll have a draw on
screen context, et cetera.
And inside drawRect, when you're drawRect is called by
the system it sets up the drawing context for you.
So it's automatically set up,
and it's called the current context.
The current drawing context.
And you can get it if you were using the C-API.
Or C-like APIs it's still Swift but it's functional.
Function API, you can get it
with this function UIGraphicsGetCurrentContext.
And it will return this cookie,
it's just this magic cookie.
You don't know what it is, but it is the context of drawing.
Because all of the C-like functional API take
a context as an argument.
Okay, BezierPath doesn't do that no worries,
but that one does.
So the first thing you need is a context automatically set up
for your when drawRect is called.
Then you create paths, you create paths with lines and
arcs and things like that.
Then you set the drawing attributes,
like the colors you want to draw in, the linewidths, and
things like that, and
finally, you stroke and fill those paths.
Okay?
And you can do either, or, or both stroking and filling.
So that is how, that is fundamentally how you draw.
Things like drawing text is just the fonts know how to
have the perfect path to draw beautiful letters.
And so, your stroking would outline the letters, and
filling fills in the letters, okay?
So even drawing text, is just stroking and filling paths.
Okay? Now, UIBzierPath, this object-oriented
thing on top, it always draws in the current context,
you don't have to worry about context.
It has methods, to do things like line two, arch two,
to build the path.
It also has methods for
setting a lot of these attributes like linewidth and
things like that and it has methods to stroke and fill.
So all those Core Graphics are put into one class.
Let's look at UIBezierPath, and
how we would use it to draw a triangle, let's say.
First we create a path, so we just say, UIBezierPath.
There are other initializers for UIBezierPath but
you could also just create an empty path, and
then you can start moving around.
So, here I'm going to assume this screen is 160 points wide
by 250 wide, and I'm gonna draw, this triangle here.
So I'm gonna move to 80 which is halfway across and
50 which is a little bit down,
and then I'm going to add a line down to 140, 150.
Then I wanna another line over to 10, 150.
Then I'm going to close this path.
Okay?
So that's it, that's how you can make a triangle.
Now, I'm kind of lying to you a little bit, because as you
execute these, nothing is appearing on screen.
The screen will be blank.
Okay, I was only showing them so you could understand what I
was doing there with the lines.
So it'd be blank.
To make it appear, you have to stroke or fill.
So, let's set the attributes we want.
So, I'm gonna set the color for filling to be green, and
the color for stroking to be red.
Okay, now notice that I set those with methods on UIColor,
not with methods on the BézierPath.
Okay, that's a little interesting but
that's the way that works.
But linewidth, I do step by talking to the paths, so
I sent a message to the BezierPath,
set line with the three.
So once I set up all my attributes, now I can fill,
for example by saying, path fill and
see, I get the rectangle filled in green.
Or, I can say stroke and it'll stroke the red line.
Okay?
Pretty straightforward?
Most of learning to draw is all about
understanding UIBezierPath and all the methods on it.
Question back there?
>> if I have two shapes onscreen,
how would I set the colors be different for each one?
>> If you have two what?
>> If you have two different shapes onscreen?
>> Oh, yes. So, the question,
if I have two shapes onscreen,
how would I set the colors be different for each one?
I would set the colors, stroke or fill one.
Set the colors on something else, stroke or
fill the other.
Okay?
Question.
>> If the path isn't closed, what does fill do?
>> So the question is,
if the path is not closed, what does fill do?
Well, it depends on, I think the winding rule, and,
other things about how it draws.
But, it will try to fill it in.
Okay. I mean a path could
cross back over itself.
Right? And so filling it
might be hard to understand.
And so there are rules for that.
I'll talk about that just briefly in just a second, but
it will fill.
But there are other things, if you don't close a path then
you can't do things like hit detection, right?
Detecting whether a point is inside it
because it's not closed, so there's no inside.
So you can, UIBezierPath also has kind of
pre-canned cool shapes like roundedRect, okay,
which is a rectangle that the corners are rounded off of, or
obviously ovals and circles, it has ways of doing that.
You can also clip to any arbitrary path.
So clipping,
hopefully everyone knows what that means.
That means, if I set it up, if I have a path, and I say clip.
If I say, addClip, then all drawing I do after that
will only show up if it's inside that path, okay?
So, for example,
if you were drawing playing card on screen,
playing cards have little rounded rects, so you might
draw your playing card in a big rectangle, and then clip
to a rounded rect, so that the corners get cut off, okay.
That's a simple to get a rounded rect playing card.
You can also do hit detection as I mentioned, the hit
detection and the filling depends on the winding rules,
and there's this usesEvenOddFillRule, property,
which is only yes or no to say which winding rule it uses.
And so people who don't know what that means,
don't worry about it.
In fact, don't worry about hit detection or
any of this stuff,
cuz you're not going to have to do this for your homework.
But I just want you to know that BezierPath has a lot of
other stuff besides just linetwo, linetwo,
fill and stroke.
Okay, it has other stuff.
And when you want to look at UIBezierPath,
check out its documentation and
kind of experience it in its full glory.
Okay, let's talk a little bit more about colors because I
used a color there, that green color.
UIColor is just an object.
It's really powerful.
Colors not only can be
standard colors like UIColor.greenColor, but
you can create a color from RGB, red, green, blue, or
HSB, that's hue, saturation, and brightness.
You can even set your color to be a pattern, so that when you
draw with that color, it actually draws some image.
Okay?
So that's kinda cool.
Views have a background color, which you can set on them.
Also colors can be transparent.
Okay?
They can be see-through, partially see-through.
This is called alpha.
So alpha is a value between zero and one.
Zero means fully transparent, so
you can see completely through it, and
it won't even show up on the screen.
To one, which is fully opaque.
It obscures anything behind it.
Anything drawn with this color.
And you can create a transparent color from
another color with this color with alpha component.
This would create kind of half transparent yellow.
Color to draw with, and you can draw in your view with
these transparent colors, okay?
Using these BazierPaths.
However, if you draw in your view with transparency,
you must tell the system that you are going to do that.
And you do that by setting this property on
your UIView called opaque to false.
And why is this required?
Well, because drawing with transparency is expensive.
Because the views behind you
are gonna start showing through.
Okay? So the system has to
blend basically the different views that are overlapping.
That's expensive in terms of graphics power.
And so it doesn't wanna do that if it doesn't have to.
If it can just draw the bit.
If you don't set this to false and
you try drawing transparently, it's not gonna work.
Okay?
Cuz it's not gonna blend with the things behind.
You can make your entire view transparent.
Okay?
It has its own property alpha,
which you can set to anywhere between zero and one.
It'll make your view,
everything you draw in the view will be
however much transparent you want it to be.
Okay?
What happens when views overlap and have transparency?
They're blended as I said,
remember that the subview's order matters.
Okay? The thing that is first in
the subviews Array is in the back.
And everything down the rye is in front.
So, when the transparency happens,
that's the order it's gonna happen in.
You can completely hide a view by sending it hidden equal to
true, and this is surprisingly common to just hide a view,
and maybe it appears when a certain condition is true on
screen, or whatever you can set up this view in
your StoryBoard and then set it to hidden, to true.
And so it comes up, it's not there.
And then in code you say hidden equals false, boom,
it appears, okay?
So that's a way to, completely hide the view.
A hidden view not only doesn't draw,
it doesn't receive any touch events either.
But it's still in the view hierarchy.
It's kinda there waiting.
Okay?
All right, drawing text.
So, usually you draw text on screen with a UILabel.
That's what you did with your display, et cetera.
But you might wanna draw in your drawRect and
you do that with this class called NSAttributedString,
which I'm really not gonna cover.
You wanna look at
its documentation if you wanna draw a text.
I'm not gonna do a demo of NSAttributedString, but
I'm gonna give you some code for
your assignment next week, and I'm
gonna use NSAttributedString in the code I'm giving you, so
you'll be able to see an example of how it's used.
But basically NSAttributedString is
a bunch of characters and
some attributes on those characters.
Now attributed String has a couple of interesting things
about it.
It's easy to use.
You can just create it, pass it a String, and
then say draw at point, and that will draw the String with
its point, its upper left corner at that point.
And you can even find out how big it's gonna be by asking it
the size of this attribute String.
So it's pretty easy to use in that way.
Mutability is not done with var and
let for NSAttributedString.
There's a different class
called NSMutableAttributedString.
Okay? And why would you
want a MutableAttributedString?
Well because these Strings,
what makes an AttributedString attributed,
is you can put attributes on the characters in this String.
And so a MutableAttributedString,
you can set the attributes.
You can get the String out as an NSString,
using the String property on NSAttributedString but
NSAttributedString itself is not a String.
It's not like a subclass of NSString or anything.
It's its own thing.
So you set
these attributes with functions like setAttributes.
It takes a Dictionary of attributes.
I'll talk to you about what the keys and
values are in a second.
And then a range.
That's an NSRange right there by the way, not a Swift Range.
And the indexing into these Strings is
the old style NSString version.
It's not the String.index stuff we
talked about last time.
It's literally which Unicode character are you
talking about setting an attribute at?
Okay?
So, this Dictionary has a bunch of attributes.
The attributes can be things like,
set the foreground color of this text.
Okay?
Set the stroke width.
Okay? Because remember,
text is just paths.
You can stroke them and to set the width or the font,
is a really important one to be able to say.
Set this text to have this particular font, okay?
And so you just set a Dictionary that has
the key NSFontAttribute and the value would be a UIFont.
Okay?
Now let's talk about UI fonts, briefly.
Fonts in iOS 7 and later, including iOS 8,
are very important to get right, okay?
Look at these screenshots.
Look how important the fonts are.
Okay? They're critical,
to making the UI look good.
Okay?
So, you've got to get the right fonts in your app.
And where do you get the right fonts?
Well, the number one place to get a font,
the right place 99% of the time, is this class function
in UI font called preferredFontForTextStyle, okay?
The text style is something like headline, or
a body, okay?
The body would be like the main content that your user is
looking at.
Headline might be like a title at the top.
Footnote might be a small little thing mentioned at
the bottom, okay?
And there's a whole bunch more of these text styles.
And so, you're gonna ask
the assistant give me the preferred font for that style.
The font includes a size.
Okay?
UIFont include the size, as well as the face.
And users can go into their settings on their phone and
change and say I can't see it anymore.
Kinda like me.
And they make their fonts bigger.
Okay?
And so this would
automatically get that new size.
Okay? So that's why you
always wanna use preferred font any
time you're displaying any user content, okay?
Now, it is possible to create fonts where you say,
give me Arial 15 narrow or what.
It is possible, but you really shouldn't be doing that.
You should be using this preferred font for style.
There's also a system font.
This is something that appears on buttons and
in things like segmented controls, things like that.
You never wanna use only the system fonts for user content.
User content you wanna use the preferred fonts.
Okay?
So yeah, other ways to get fonts, ignore them.
I'm not gonna talk about it, okay?
All right, how about drawing images?
How do you do that?
Well there is a UILabel for
images, it's called UIImageView.
And you can use that to put an image on screen, but
you might wanna draw an image, in your drawrect as well.
And usually you create an image by name, from that
Images.xcassets thing that we moved out of the way real
quick right at the beginning of our very first demo.
And if you click on that, it's pretty self-explanatory.
You can drag images.
You can have different images of different resolutions for
different devices.
It's really pretty powerful.
That's usually create an image.
By name and dragging into the images.xcassets.
You can create it in other ways from the file system,
which we haven't talked about, or even with drawing, but
we're not gonna talk about that either.
Once you have the UIImage, you can draw it by just sending it
the message, draw at point.
And it will draw in its normal size with that point as
it's upper left.
You can also say drawInRect, and
it'll scale to fit that rect, either bigger or smaller, or
you can draw a pattern in rect it'll tile it repeatedly to
fill the rect.
Okay?
So really easy to draw images inside your drawRect.
And the last thing I wanna talk about is,
what happens when your bounds changes in your UIView?
Like the, the user rotates the phone.
Now your bounds are wide and
not very tall, instead of tall and not so wide.
You might think,
oh my drawRect's gonna get called, and I'm gonna redraw.
But no, that does not happen.
Instead, the bits that were on screen get stretched.
Okay?
So, usually that's not what you want.
You can and
result in a very grainy, kind of bit stretching of your UI.
But that is the default,
is the bit stretching because it's higher performance.
Now, you control though, you can control what happens to
your view when the bounds change,
with this property in view called contentMode.
And here are some of the content modes you can set.
There's left, right, top, bottom, et cetera.
All these ones basically don't change the bits.
They don't re-draw, but
they just move your entire view to the left edge,
right edge, top, or bottom of the new bounds.
These are kinda strange ones.
You probably don't need that very often.
Then there's the scaling of the bits.
So here's the default, ScaleToFill.
'Kay, we'll scale the bits to fill the new bounds, but
you can also fill or fit the bounds and
keep it aspect ratio.
So that won't stretch your bits.
It'll still scale them, but
it'll scale them with your aspect ratio maintained, or
you can have the wonderous Redraw, 'kay?
This is the one you wanna set that says,
when my bounds change, call my drawRect again.
Okay?
With the new bounds.
So you're gonna want that quite often.
I'll show you that in the demo today.
All right, so let's get right to this demo.
Today, it's gonna be a little tight to do this in 20 minutes
but, cuz we're gonna cover a lot of stuff but
I think we can do it.
We're going to start by creating a new project.
So I'm just going to file a new project,
this is brand new.
Okay? We're going away from
the Calculator here.
And as always we're gonna be
using the single view application thing right here.
I'm gonna call this project Happiness,
because we're gonna draw a face, a smiley face.
Okay? And it's gonna be
able to smile or frown, depending on how happy it is.
Okay?
So that's why we're gonna call this Happiness.
I'm gonna put it in the same place I put my Calculator,
which is my home directory developer there.
Here it is.
As before I'm gonna move this AppDelegate out of the way.
I'm gonna move, actually let's take a look at image.xcassets.
So here's the appicon slots.
You can see that for any given image,
like the appicon, there's lots of different resolutions,
depending on the devices that you can provide.
Okay?
You don't have to provide all the different resolutions,
it will interpolate but you can do it.
So you just drag an image into here, and now you can get it
by name with that UIImageNamed function.
So we'll get that out of there.
We don't want the launch screen either.
So here we are.
I'm gonna show you something fun here too.
Here is my StoryBoard.
I'm gonna show you how to add a new view controller to
your StoryBoard.
And in fact, I'm gonna delete this one.
So, you see this one right here I've selected?
I'm just deleting it.
It's gone. I'm gonna delete its
code as well.
I'm gonna go here, and just delete, move it to the trash.
Now I have a StoryBoard with nothing in it, and
I've no view controllers.
Okay?
So, how do I add a view controller?
You go over here to your Object Pallet.
The very first thing is a view controller.
And you just drag it out, and boom.
You've got one.
Now, the class.
What class is this going to be though?
This is gonna be Generic UIView controller, so
it's pretty useless.
Okay? You can't add any outlets, or
have any actions because it's not a subclass of UIView
controller, so you can't put any of that implementation in.
So, we're gonna create a new subclass of UIView controller.
So let me show you how to do that.
You say New > File.
And last time we went to New > File,
we said Swift file to make the CalculatorBrain.
But now we're gonna go over here to Cocoa Touch Class,
which we do anytime we wanna create a subclass of
an iOS class.
And here I'm creating a subclass of UIView controller.
I need this.
So I'm gonna click on that.
Here's where I pick what I want it to be a subclass of.
You can see there's a lot of things in here.
I'm gonna say I want a view controller.
It wants to call it view controller by default.
We don't even like that for
the Calculator, let alone this.
So I'm gonna call this my HappinessViewController.
Okay?
So it creates that.
Put it in the same place all my other Swift files are.
Here it is.
HappinessViewController.
Again, I'm gonna get rid of this code.
Okay?
Just to make things a little clearer.
So here's my HappinessViewController.
It's just like the view controller you had,
that was called viewController in your Calculator.
It was called HappinessViewController.
But this guy right here,
is still playing old view controller.
How do I know that?
Well, it's this magic right here.
You see this Identity Inspector?
Okay. You can see the class of
this selected thing here, in this UIView controller.
And I don't want it to be UIView controller.
I want it to be HappinessViewController.
So, very important to understand that in
StoryBoards, everything is linked up to
your code by name.
Only by the name.
That is the only thing that links what's in
your StoryBoard with your code.
The names of outlets, the names of methods,
the action methods.
The name of your UIViewControllers.
The name of your UIViews.
Okay? It's all by name.
So you have to go to the Identity Inspector here and
make sure that name matches up.
So now, you can see
this says that it's a HappinessViewController.
So that's making me happy.
Okay.
Now, we want to put our custom view in here, okay?
So how do I add a custom view to my UI?
And the answer is, I go into the Object Pallet.
It's all the way at the bottom,
near the bottom somewhere.
Where is that thing?
There it is.
You can drag out a generic view.
So this is just a UIView.
Now when I drag it out,
I'm gonna put it right here with the dashed blue lines.
'Kay, because we know that that's a good thing to do.
And I want to set up the Auto Layout so
that this view always fully fills my scene here.
Okay? Now I could control drag to
the edges like I did before, but since this is already
perfectly where I want it, and I use the blue lines, I
can go down here and use Reset to Suggested Constraints.
'Kay?
Now, I'm only showing you dribs and drabs of Auto Layout.
I was gonna talk all about Auto Layout today, but
we need to move on to this.
But I will be having the lecture on Auto Layout,
probably week after next.
In the meantime I'm just gonna show you little bits of it and
you can explore.
I'm never gonna ask you to do a ton of it in your homework.
So this one I'm gonna Reset to Suggested Constraints, and
it added those constraints.
And I could go over here.
Let me make some more space here.
I could go look at them over here.
You've all determined that.
Another place you can see the constraints of a view is
here in the Size Inspector.
If you look towards the bottom of the Size Inspector-
Look, here's all the constraints, see?
Trailing, leading, top, bottom.
It added all these because these are the suggested
constraints based on the dash blue lines that I used.
Okay?
So, oftentimes if you put something in place perfectly
with the blue lines,
you can use Reset to Suggested Constraints.
We coulda done that with our display in our Calculator.
We couldn't do it with the buttons.
Cuz it just wasn't lined up enough with other things, but
we could have done it with the display.
All right? So now we have this.
Now, this UIView, let's look at its Identity Inspector.
It's just a generic UIView.
That's no good.
We need a custom UIView sub-class.
So let's go do that.
File > New File.
Same thing,
I'm gonna create a subclass of a Cocoa Touch Class.
This one's not gonna be a view controller,
it's gonna be a UIView.
Okay? I'm gonna call it FaceView,
cuz that's what it's gonna do.
It's gonna draw a face, okay?
Put it in the same place, put everything.
Here's our, my FaceView right here.
We'll get back to that in a second.
In our StoryBoard,
we wanna make sure that we inspect our FaceView.
Okay?
And change its class to FaceView.
By the way, it can kinda get tricky sometimes,
picking the right thing.
Like, sometimes you're picking the UIView controller,
sometimes you're picking the view.
One kinda cool trick, CTRL+ Shift.
If you hold CTRL+Shift and click, then it
lets you pick which thing you want, that's under the mouse.
A very important little trick, CTRL+Shift.
So here I could pick the view controller.
Now I'm seeing the Identity Inspector of
the view controller.
Or I could go here and pick,
this is the view property in my view controller.
The top level view.
This is my FaceView that I'm trying to create.
So I select this here, then I'm gonna go to
the Identity Inspector again, up here.
I'm gonna change this to be a FaceView.
Okay?
So now this thing is a FaceView, and so
when it's time for this thing to draw,
it's gonna call the drawRect of the FaceView class.
So let's go take a look at the FaceView class.
Here it is.
And here is drawRect.
Now, it's commented out by default.
Why is it commented out by default?
Well because having a drawRect costs system resources.
It thinks it has to draw this thing.
So you only wanna have a drawRect if you actually draw,
in your drawRect.
Don't have it just sitting there uncommented out,
if you're not actually using it.
All right, so, how am I gonna draw this face?
Let's start by drawing the outline of the head.
Just a round circle.
Okay?
Cuz that's pretty simple to draw.
And how am I gonna do that?
Let's start by creating a BezierPath.
I'll call it facePath which is, BezierPath.
And let's look at
all the different kinds of BezierPaths we can make.
Ovals.
We could use this one, ovalInRect, okay?
That's a pretty good one.
I'm actually gonna use this one,
arcCenter cuz I wanna show you a really bad error message
you're gonna get in Swift that I want you to avoid.
So I'm gonna use this one which lets you create an arc,
and I'm just gonna have my arc go all the way around.
Okay? From zero all the way around.
So, it wants to know the center.
So I'm gonna have to have my faces center somehow.
We'll define that in a second.
It also wants to know the radius, so
I have to have my faces radius in a second.
We'll do that.
It wants to know the start angle, to draw this arc.
Okay? So
I'm gonna start at angle zero.
The angle's in radians.
So I wanna go around to 2pi.
Going, I'm gonna draw an arc from zero,
all the way around to 2pi radians.
Hopefully everyone knows what radians are.
Okay?
So zero to 2pi that's good, and then clockwise or
counter clockwise,
I don't care cuz I'm going all the way around.
So I'll just say clockwise true.
Now, when I do this, well first let's do
our faceCenter and faceRadius here.
So I'm gonna make actually computed properties for those.
So the faceCenter is a CGPoint.
And really, it would be cool, yeah, I could do get and set.
It's gonna be Get Only.
Okay?
I'm not gonna allow me to set my faceCenter,
I'm almost going to calculate it.
I could make it settable, actually too, but
I'm gonna make it so it's calculated only.
When you do calculated only,
you actually don't need this part.
This get.
You can take that out.
And if it's returned Only.
So I'll say return.
Now I, you might be saying oh I'm gonna return center,
let's put the face in the center.
Did everyone understand why this is very bad?
All right, cuz center is not in my coordinate system.
It's in my super views coordinate system.
Luckily, I can convert a point from my super views coordinate
system using this nice method, convertpoint fromView:.
So I'm gonna convert center from my superview.
Okay?
That's gonna put my face right in the center,
cuz I've converted that center from my superview's coordinate
system to mine.
Okay?
So that's faceCenter.
Let's also do faceRadius.
So for the faceRadius,
I'm gonna have it be as big as it can be.
Okay?
So faceRadius is gonna be a CGFloat to all of
faceRadius 会是 CGFloat 类型的，
our drawing stuff is Float, and I'm gonna return as big as
所有的绘画元素都是 Float 类型的，在它不会被截断的情况下，
it can be without getting cut off.
我会让它尽可能大
So it's gonna be the minimum of my width or height.
所以让它成为宽和高中较小的那一个
So I'm gonna say, min of my bounds.
所以这里
Sorry.
抱歉
bounds.size.width, or my bounds.size.height.
bounds.size.width 或者 bounds.size.height
Whichever is less than that.
哪个短用哪个
Min is just a nice little function in Swift.
Swift 中的 min 是一个不错的小函数
And I'm gonna divide by two because this is a radius,
这里把它除以2，因为这是半径
not diameter of my face.
而不是脸的直径
This is the radius.
是半径
So now I have my center facing radius, but
现在我有了脸的半径
I still have an error here.
但是这里还是有个错误
Look at this error.
来看看这个错误
Even though I did my center, I did my radius.
即使我算好了中间位置，算好了半径
I still have an error.
这里还是有错误
What is the problem?
到底是什么问题？
Oh, extra argument radius in call.
extra argument radius in call
Huh.
That's weird.
这很奇怪
I didn't see any extra argument.
我没看到额外的参数
What the heck is that about?
到底出什么错了？
Okay.
You could waste a half an hour looking for this, okay?
你可能会花半个小时找错误
I was thinking, oh,
你可能会想
radius, there's nothing wrong with the radius.
radius，radius 这里也没什么问题啊
It's right.
是的
The problem for this has nothing to do with the radius.
radius 跟这个问题一点关系都没有
The problem is this.
问题在这
Okay?
So this is an error you get from switching occasionally,
这个错误你们可能会偶尔遇到
I'm sure they'll fix all these errors, but occasionally,
我确定他们会修复好这些错误
you get this very misleading error, and this is one.
但是偶尔还是会获得这些误导你的错误，这就是一个
The problem is that this-
问题在于
What type is this?
它的类型是什么？
It's a Double.
它是一个 Double
Yeah.
是的
And what type do we draw with?
但是我们绘画用什么类型的？
CGFloat.
CGFloat
So this problem is just that I need to cast this to
所以把它转型成 CGfloat 这个问题就可以
a CGFloat.
解决了
Okay?
That's gonna make this error go away.
这个错误就会消失了
It had nothing to do with radius whatsoever there.
跟 radius 一点关系都没有
Okay?
So, best warning, watch out for that.
这就是我给你们的提醒，以后要注意点
All right, so I have my nice facePath here.
我已经得到了 facePath
Maybe I wanna set my facePath's lineWidth.
在这里设置一下 facePath 的 lineWidth（线宽）
Something like three, something like that.
设置成3吧
In fact, maybe I even want lineWidth to
我想把 lineWidth 变成 FaceView 中
be something that's configurable in my FaceView.
可以设置的一个属性
So it's a CGFloat.
类型是 CGFloat
And we'll set it to default of three.
我们把它的默认设置为3
One thing that's interesting and
一个很有趣的事是
then we'll set this down here to lineWidth.
我先把这里设置成 lineWidth
One thing that's interesting about this is any time
一个有趣的事情是，无论何时 lineWidth 被改变了，
someone changes my lineWidth, I need to redraw myself.
我都需要把 FaceView 重新绘制一遍
All right?
So how can I make that happen?
我怎么做才能实现呢？
Well, I can use Property Observer.
我可以使用 Property Observer
Okay?
Anytime someone sets this,
无论什么时候，有人改变了它
I'm gonna call setNeedsDisplay on myself.
我就会在自己身上调用 setNeedsDisplay
Okay?
Bam.
I'm in it redrawn by the system.
系统就会帮你重新绘制视图
Okay? So anytime you have
如果在你的 view 中有一个
a property in your, in a view that changes how you would be
property 在改变的时候需要被重新绘制
drawn, just put a little Property Observer into
只要在 Property Observer 里调用
the setNeedsDisplay after it.
setNeedsDisplay 就可以了
And it'll get you automatically redrawn.
它就会帮你重新绘制
Maybe I'll have another property here,
在这里我还想添加一个
which is the color I wanna be.
颜色的 property
UIColor, we'll set the default here to be
类型是 UIColor，默认设置成
blueColor for example.
蓝色
But I want the exact same thing here.
但我也想像这里一样
Okay?
Someone sets it.
有人改变了它
I want it redrawn.
视图就会被重新绘制
And so let's go ahead and set our color.
现在设置一下颜色
Now I'm gonna do both my set, I could do setFill and
我既想 setFill 又想 setStroke
setStroke colors, but I'm just gonna do set,
我两者都想做，只要 set 就可以了
which sets both my fill and my stroke.
这样填充和笔画都会被设置
I'm not gonna be filling so it doesn't matter, but set to
这里不会被填充，所以调用 set 也没问题
both, and then how do I draw this BezierPath right here?
然后呢？我怎么绘制 BezierPath？
I just say, facePath.stroke.
facePath.stroke 就可以了
And that's gonna draw, okay?
这样就可以绘制了
So let's go take a look at this.
我们运行一下程序
Okay.
So, it comes up, it's blank.
运行起来了，它是空的
And not only is it blank, it's got some error down here.
不仅仅是空白的，这里还有一些错误信息
What does it say? It says,
它说
failed to instantiate the default view controller.
failed to instantiate the default view controller（初始化默认 view controller 失败）
Okay? Well that means that in my
这表明
StoryBoard, there is no scene that's specified,
在 StoryBoard 中，没有指定
as the scene to start in.
开始的场景
Okay? It has no starting scene.
没有开始的场景
The starting scene always has a little arrow pointing to it.
开始的场景总是有一个指向它的小箭头
Right here,
在这里
you've probably seen in in your Calculator right?
你们可能在 Calculator 中已经见过了
A little arrow that says this is the place to come in
当你运行程序时
when you start this app.
一个代表程序入口点的小箭头
You can set that arrow with the Inspector the regular
你可以在选中的 view controller 的
Attributes Inspector by selecting your
Attributes Inspector 里
view controller that you wanna be the one that comes in.
设置它为入口场景
And click. This little button here is
点击这里的小按钮
Initial View Controller.
Is Initial View Controller
You see that arrow appear?
看到剪头出现了吗？
You can also pick this arrow up and
你也可以把这个剪头选中
move it to another view controller.
把它移动到另一个 view controller 里
Okay?
So now we have a thing, oh all right.
好了
So we've got our face.
脸已经出现了
Now, one thing I don't like about this face is it goes all
现在我对这个脸不满意的地方就是
the way to the edges.
它太靠近边缘了
I want it to actually be 90% of the edges.
我想让它占据整个长度的 90%
Okay? Another thing I
另一件
don't like is this.
我不满意的事情是
Ugh, okay?
额
So my face is gonna be distorted every time I rotate.
每一次我旋转屏幕，脸都会被破坏
Why is that?
这是怎么回事儿？
That's this stretching thing I was telling you about.
这就是我之前告诉你们的拉伸的情况
We want our drawRect to be called again when we
我们希望每一个获得新的边界时（就像旋转屏幕）
have a new bounds like that.
drawRect 都会被再一次调用
So let's fix both of those things.
现在我们一起把它们处理好
We can fix that content mode redraw by selecting our view,
修改 Mode （重绘模式）的方法是：选中 view
going to the inspector up here,
去到 Inspector
the Attributes Inspector, and
Attributes Inspector
the very first one is the mode.
第一个就是 Mode
And you can see the default was scale to fill.
默认的是 Scale To Fill (拉伸以填充)
We want Redraw.
我们想要 Redraw (重绘)
Okay? So I'm gonna pick Redraw.
所以我选择 Redraw
So that'll fix that.
这样就修改好了
And as far as the 90%, I'm going to fix that in here,
至于 90%，我在这里修改
by having the, my face radius be times 90%.
把 face radius 乘以 90%
But really, I'd like this to be settable too.
但是我也想让它成为一个可以被设置的
So I'm gonna have var scale, CGFloat.
添加一个变量，类型是 CGFloat
Okay. And we'll start this out at
默认设置为
90%.
So I want that, and
我想让它
this one also, if I change, I want it to change.
在更改以后也重绘视图
Okay?
So now let's go try that.
运行一下程序
See what happens.
看看发生了什么
Okay? We got our 90%.
90% 已经实现了
That's good.
还不错
And when I rotate, it doesn't stretch it.
当我旋转屏幕时，也没有拉伸
Okay? And it's using the minimum of
它使用了宽度和高度中
the width or height.
较小的那个
Okay?
So that's good.
还不错
That's going good.
越来越好了哈
Now we wanna draw the eyes and the mouth, and
现在开始绘制眼睛个嘴
cuz time is running out here,
时间已经不多了
I'm actually gonna type those in super fast.
我将会用超快的速度输入
I posted for those of you who are trying to keep along here,
那些一路跟着我敲键盘的同学
which is probably impossible.
是不可能跟上的
To do that though, I need some constants.
为了实现这些，我需要一些常量
And this how we do constants in Swift.
在 Swift 中我们这样定义常量
We create structs.
创建 struct
Okay? And then use class, or
使用 class 或者
in this case, static lets.
在这里使用 static let 修饰
Okay? So this is gonna be
所以这个常量就是
a constant called Scaling.FaceRadiustoEyeRadius.
Scaling.FaceRadiustoEyeRadius
Okay. And
then I'm going to have a function here, that I'm
这里有个函数叫做 bezierPathForEye
gonna type in really, really fast, called bezierPathForEye.
我也会飞快地输入
And it's just gonna return a BezierPath that draws an eye.
它会返回一个绘制一只眼睛的 BezierPath
Either the left eye or the right eye.
左眼或者右眼
This says which one.
参数用来确定是哪一只眼睛
Okay? So it returns a BezierPath.
它返回了一个 BezierPath
Okay?
Then I'm gonna have another one, which is BezierSmile.
这里还会有一个函数，BezierSmile
We're gonna type that in real fast.
我们会飞快地输入...
Okay?
So here is BeizerPath for smile.
这就是笑容的 BeizerPath
And what this is gonna do,
这个函数会
it's gonna take a fractionOfMaximumSmile.
把 fractionOfMaximumSmile 作为参数
So one is full smile.
1 是最开心的笑容
Minus one is full frown.
-1 是最难过的
And everywhere in between.
其余的都在 1 和 -1 之间
'Kay? So that's what this does.
这就是它做的事情
And it returns a BeizerPath.
返回一个 BeizerPath
So now here in my drawRect,
在 drawRect 函数中
I can say bezierPathForEye, left eye.
调用 bezierPathForEye，left 作为参数
I got the BezierPath.
我获得了 BezierPath
I'm just gonna immediately send it stroke.
我立即用它调用 stroke
Okay?
And then BezierPath for the right eye.
接着是右眼的 BezierPath
I'm gonna send it stroke.
给它发送 stroke 消息
So I'm just gonna stroke the left eye and the right eye.
现在绘制了左眼和右眼
Okay?
Then I'm gonna do the smiliness.
接着处理笑容
So, I'm going to let smiliness equal some value.
先把笑容设置为一个值
Let's start it at 0.75.
从 0.75 开始吧
We're pretty, pretty happy to start.
这是一个很开心很开心的数值了
And then I'm going to create a bez,
接着，我用上面的这些给笑容
this BezierPath using this thing up here for
创建一个 BezierPath
a smile, which is bezierPathForSmile.
用这个函数 bezierPathForSmile
And we're gonna pass it the smiliness.
把 smiliness 传进去
And then I'm just going to stroke this smile path.
然后绘制这个笑容的线条
Okay?
And I hoped to have a little more time so
我很希望能有时间
I could have gone through this code, but
跟大家一起看看代码
it's a pretty straightforward code, really.
但是这些代码都很易懂
Here we're just using addCurveToPoint in
这里我们调用 addCurveToPoint
our BezierPath.
在 BezierPath 里
To draw a curve, which is the curve of the mouth.
为了绘制嘴部的曲线
And then here,
接着，这儿
we're just using BezierPath arcCenter again.
我们又调用了一次 BezierPath arcCenter
Okay?
To create the circle.
为了绘制圆
The eyes are just circles, okay?
眼睛都是圆的
That's really all those two methods do.
这就是这两个方法做的事情
There's nothing really special about them.
没什么特别的
And what do I have error here, which is, oops.
这里有个错误
Dot.
点
Okay?
That's not it either.
不是点
SmilePath oh, equals, not that.
SmilePath 等于，
Equals.
等号
There we go.
这就对了
Okay?
Yes?
有问题吗？
So let's run this.
运行一下程序
Hopefully, we'll have a smiley face.
希望我们能有一张笑脸
There it is.
来了
He looks pretty happy.
他看起来很快乐
We can rotate him.
我们可以旋转屏幕
He's very happy.
他真的很快乐
Okay, let's make him a little sad.
来，我们让他难过一点
How about minus 0.5?
-0.5 怎么样？
Minus 0.5.
-0.5
Pretty, pretty sad.
非诚非常难过
Aw.
呜呜
Okay?
Okay.
So now we have this nice FaceView.
FaceView 已经完成了
What we're gonna do in our next lecture, is we're going
下一次课要讲的是
to add a gesture so we can make him happy or sad.
给这个程序添加手势，我们就可以让他一会儿开心一会儿难过
Happy or sad.
开心或者难过
Okay?
We're also gonna put a gesture in there, a pinch gesture so
我们也会加入 pinch gesture (缩放手势)
we can make them bigger or smaller.
我们就能把他变大或者变小
Okay?
Then we're going to actually add a whole another MVC and
接着我们会添加另一个完整的 MVC
make a much more powerful application that just uses
使用 FaceView 制作一个
the FaceView.
更强大的应用
The HappinessViewController as a view in another MVC.
把 HappinessViewController 用作另一个 MVC 的 view
Okay?
So now we're going to do multiple MVCs.
我们接下来就会处理多个 MVC 了
So that's what we're gonna be doing on Monday.
这就是下周一要完成的事情了