[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Okay well, welcome to lecture six of
Stanford CS193P winter of 2015.
So today I am gonna do a little bit of
demo action right at the beginning.
I wanna show you a kind of a cool trick that you can do
inside your storyboard, and we also, last time,
didn't get to the point where we had actually a model for
our MVC, our happiness MVC.
We had worked on the face view and got that working but
we didn't have a model,
so I'm gonna just put that model in there, but then I am
going to jump right back into the slides and I am going to
cover a very important concept, which is delegation.
And I'll have to kinda go over Swift's protocol syntax, and
then I will do a demo to show you how delegation works,
then I'm gonna cover gestures, okay?
We know how to draw in our view now from last time.
So, now we're gonna then talk about how we handle gestures.
Pinches and pans and swipes and things like that.
And I think that'll probably use all of my time up.
But if I have a little bit of time at the end,
I'm gonna get started on the next major topic.
Which we're gonna spend most of Wednesday on.
Which is multiple MVCs, right?
We know how to build an MVC.
It's got a controller, it's got a model, it's got a view.
And now we're gonna build a bigger application by
combining MVCs, okay?
And that's critical, obviously,
to growing the capability of size of app you can build.
So I'll try and fit in five or ten minutes of slides for
that just to make sure we have more time on Wednesday.
Anybody have any questions about any of this?
All right.
So, let's dive into this demo first, before I talk about.
That, okay I am just going to bring up
happiness from where we left off last time.
And really all we had done here was the Face View,
we had not done our Happiness View.
In fact, if I switch over to our Happiness View controller,
you can see it is completely empty.
So one thing we're gonna do is
fix our model here but before we do that I'm gonna show you
something really cool that you can do in story boards.
So here we have our story board and it's pretty blank.
It looks blank there's this big blank square here.
This is our face view in here that I have selected.
You can see the little resize handles are selected but
I can't even really tell that's a face view.
It's hard to tell where it is.
It's just kinda hard to tell what's going on.
And it's actually possible believe it or not to have your
custom UI view subclasses draw in your story board.
Okay? So they can actually be
live drawing in your storyboard.
And it's really incredibly easy to do.
I'm just gonna go back to my face view.
Here it is.
And right before the class here I'm gonna say
at sign IBDesignable.
And if I put at sign IBDesignable in there,
then when I go back to my storyboard,
Xcode automatically notices that's an IB designable
class and it will draw it right here in the story board,
so now I can see much more easily what's going on with my
face view, where it is here.
And if I change something in my face,
like let's go change that smile so it's not a frown.
Whoops where is that, it's right here, minus 0.5.
Let's change that to plus 0.5.
Then you'll notice that this file has changed and
it will recompile it and redraw it.
Okay so you're always seeing the latest version.
Now another thing that would be really
cool here is just like if we have a button or a label.
When we bring up the attributes inspector here
we can edit attributes of a button or a label.
Right? Like its alignment or its font.
Well wouldn't it be cool if we could edit the attributes of
this face view here as well?
And we can do that too.
If we go back here to the face view here's some of
the things that are setable about a face view.
The line width, the color, and the scale.
And you can make any of these things editable inside of your
storyboard by just putting in here i b inspectable.
But I'd be inspectable before them.
Then interface builder,
which is the part of x code that is doing part of your
storyboard will create a new UI to make all those editable.
Here is our storyboard.
Now if you look over here you can see face view.
It's added things to be able to set these.
I can set things like my line width.
Maybe I want thicker lines.
Maybe I want a different color.
So we can go to the color chooser here.
We could pick green color or orange or something like that.
Tangerine.
It looks good.
And we can change the scale as well, too.
We can go down to 0.5, maybe we want to go 0.95, all right?
We can change that.
Now, these are not only changing here in
your storyboard, but they're actually setting the default
value so that when you run your application, so
let's go and run our application here.
It's going to use these values that are set in
the storyboard.
Just like if those were buttons or labels and you had
changed something about them in the inspector, it's going
to change the way it works in your program as well.
Yes, questions.
>> So that overwrites what's in your code?
>> Yes, so the question is does that overwrite what's in
our code?
So for example, back here.
We had equals three, we had equals blue color and
the answer is yes, it overrides it.
Basically, when interface loads it up it respects those.
It will use those but as soon as you start editing them,
then it's going to override them and
reset them to the editor value.
Any other questions about that?
Question?
>> Yes, so the question is are there some,
there's got to be some got-yous, or something.
Why wouldn't it just be the ideal design be the default?
And, yes, there are some gotchas.
There's certain things that, really, it can't do.
It can't load your code up, you might have dependencies on
other frameworks that it can't see, things like that.
So yeah, there are some gotchas,
I don't have time to go through them all but
I just wanted to show you that this is here for
most straight forward sub class UI view,
it works great without gotchas.
But yeah, there are obviously some times when it's not going
to work, because you could have a complicated view, so
any other questions about it?
That's all there is to know about that.
So let's go back to our model here, or
to our controller, and I want to put the model in here for
the happiness view controller.
So it's model, because this is demoed and
I want it all to be really quick and
you can even follow along with me, some of you.
This model's gonna be really simple.
I'm gonna have the model of and
a model you know the model is right?
Your calculator's model was a calculator brain so
it was a whole object that you created to be the model.
Here I'm gonna have my model be the happiness and
it's going to be the very complicated data structure of
an int.
Okay. So
we're gonna represent our happiness as an Int.
And I'm gonna start it out at 50.
And I'm gonna have my happiness mean 0 is very sad,
and 100 is ecstatic.
Okay?
So that's my model.
Super duper simple model, and don't get this model confused
with the smiliness in the face view,
that's a different thing, that's just the angle of
that arc in the face view, totally separate thing.
And you notice they're kind of on different scales anyways.
This is 0 to 100,
the smiliness is minus 1 to positive 1, etc.
And that's okay because one of
the things that controllers do, one of their jobs really,
is to interpret the model for the view.
Okay, or vice versa in what happens in the view.
And they have to figure out what to
communicate to the model.
That's a lot of what a controller does.
And so, we're going to have some coding here,
that does exactly that.
Interprets our 0 to 100 happiness into a smile or not.
Now there's other things that
represent happiness besides smiling.
You know, little crinkly eyes.
And other things that make you appear that you're happy.
But we're just gonna use our face view which only knows how
to smile or not.
Now one thing that we can do inside this model.
I put the curly braces here and
you might say why did I put that there?
That is because I want to use the property observer for
my model to, essentially, validate my model.
So you can use property observers to do evaluation,
really, of any property that you want.
So my happiness can only be 0 to a 100.
If someone passes me happiness minus 1 or
5,000 I need to kind of keep it in range to 0 to 100.
So I'm just going to say, in my setter here,
my property observer here,
I'm going to say min max of my happiness to 0 or 100,
so I'm just keeping it between zero and a hundred, right?
So no matter what someone passes me,
my happiness won't ever be outside of that.
Again, this is kind of a trivial example.
You might have a much powerful model that
needs much more powerful validation this,
but you can see this as a place to put it.
Another thing you might want to have here is if someone
updates your model, you might want to update your UI.
Okay, so I'm going to have update UI,
and I'm just going to have a function down here, update UI,
and it's going to do something to update the user interface,
and that's a common thing.
When your model changes,
you want your controller to cause the UI to be updated.
I think I'm going to put in here also is a little println
happiness equals back slash happiness.
Just so we can see our happiness changing in our
console all the time as we work the rest of the demos.
So we'll work on this update UI piece when we
get back to the demos.
I just wanted to show you the model of happiness.
Right now it's not hooked up to a it's UI.
So if I run my application,
you'll see that this is not happiness of 50.
This is not even looking at the happiness.
I could change this to anything that I want and
it's not going to change this.
And so later we'll show you how we hook up our UI
to our model through our controller,
that's one of the main things a controller does.
Okay, so let's go back to our slides though.
All right here, I'm going to start with this miscellaneous
topic here, kind of a bonus topic, which is extensions.
You read about in your reading assignments, so
you know what this is,
hopefully you've been reading those reading assignments.
But I'm discovering here in class,
not as much because it's an important feature per say but
it can be a little bit of a dangerous feature so
I wanted to cover it a little bit.
So an extension is really simple.
It's just a little syntax, to add methods and properties to
existing classes, structures, and enums.
Okay? You do not have to
have the source code to those things you're adding it to.
You could just add these methods and
properties pretty much at will.
There are some restrictions, one is that you can't add via
an extension a method or property that already exists.
So it's not a way to replace it, this is not sub classing,
you're not replacing or overwriting methods, so
this has to be something where the property or
method you wanna add to a class.
Does not exist.
The second thing is that any
properties you add cannot have any storage.
Okay so they can only be computed properties,
right the get, set, kind.
That's the only kind of property you can have.
Okay, but inside an extension otherwise it kind of
looks like you're in the definition of class.
You can refer to self if you want and
that will be the thing that you are extending.
It's a pretty powerful feature actually.
This feature is easily abused however people putting all
kinds of adding methods to classes making it so it's
completely not understandable of what that does anymore.
It's also whoever designed the class thinks a lot about it,
API and what should be in it and what shouldn't and
now all of the sudden things are being added.
That's kind of weird.
This is really best used for beginners like you
who are just starting with SWIFT to add little
helper functions to enhance the readability of your code.
Okay, so if there's something that it would be
really great if a cgrect could do this little thing, you
could add a little extension to a cgrect to do that.
Or maybe a UI view controller just once.
This extra little property that it can calculate
about itself.
That's the kind of thing that you could use it for.
Now extensions actually can be used by advanced Swift users
by architects, or
for architects, to really organize all your code.
Because you can
put almost everything into extensions, and
use extensions as basically groupings of functionality.
And so, it's really a powerful feature and
I don't want to make it sound like it's only for
little kinda drips and drabs and tiny little helper things.
It can actually be used as a core foundation of how you
architect.
But that does require some one to sit down and
have an architectural plan to do that and
you obviously a little early in the game to be doing that.
So I would say, when in doubt, if you're not sure whether or
not you should make something an extension,
don't do it for now.
And over time, you'll get more comfortable with it,
you'll understand what to do.
And again, the syntax for
it is all explained in the documentation.
Maybe in the demo here, I'll try and throw one in, so
you can see what it looks like.
That was just an aside,
now let's get back to the main guts, okay?
This very important feature called delegation,
I have to teach you about protocols first,
again you probably read about this in reading assignments,
but I want to go over it anyway.
A protocol is basically a way to express your
API a little more minimally.
Not to drag in so much API by, for example,
having an argument to a function be a class where now
you're passing an entire class into that function,
who knows what that function might do with that class.
It could access the entire non private API of that thing.
So really, the function just wants to use the one method of
a class.
Protocols are a way for
the function to express or really, I just want you to
pass me something that can do this one function.
Because that's what I'm going to call in here.
So, it's a way to kind of minimize your API.
A protocol is a type.
Okay, it's just like a class, or an enum, or a struct.
Okay. It's a type.
It can be used everywhere a type is.
A type of an argument to a function.
A var or a let can be a protocol.
Type. So it is absolutely a type.
The only thing that is interesting about it is it
has no implementation.
Okay?
In fact, it's kind of the definition of a protocol,
it's a type with no implementation.
It only has declaration.
Use a protocol to declare various properties and
methods but it has no implementation.
The implementation is provided by other objects that conform
to the protocol.
Okay, and there might be
hundreds of objects that will conform to a certain protocol.
Okay?
But the protocol when you use it looks just like a type,
exactly like a type as you're gonna see here.
Now there's three aspects to a protocol, to using one.
One is the declaration of the protocol.
This looks a lot like declaring your class or
an enum or struct.
It's just that there is no implementations for
any of the properties or methods.
Then there's the declaration part where a class or
a struct or an enum says, I will implement this protocol.
So it declares that it will conform to, or implement,
this protocol.
And then there's the part where that class, struct or
enum actually implements the protocol.
So, it implements that, all the properties and
methods in the protocol that's required, all of them.
Okay?
So we'll see what that looks like in some code.
So here's a declaration of a protocol itself, okay?
The protocol's called some protocol, all right?
This protocol has really what some might call
inherited protocols, or a protocol that inherits.
Which are other protocols that if you want to implement some
protocol you have to implement those too.
Okay that's what this colon thing, so
it kind of looks like this super class kind of thing but
there can be multiple of them, but it's not really
inherent in this, per se, like you think of in classes, it's
more just saying if you want to implement some protocol you
also have to implement inherited protocol one and
inherited protocol two.
If you don't implement those then you
haven't implemented all of some protocol.
Okay?
Now you have to specify, when you do a property,
you don't put the implementation there but
you have to classify whether this is a get only property or
it's a get and set, okay?
The system needs to know whether it's
a set because structs and enums are value types and
it needs to know when it's being mutated so
it can copy them and etcetera, okay?
Any functions that are expected to mutate also need
to be noted with this mutating keyword, okay?
You probably read that in the description,
you know that structs and enums,
insert value types, the system needs to know when a function
is actually changing them, so they can copy it on demand.
It is possible to limit your protocol to only work
with classes.
You put the word class right after that colon.
So SomeProtocol colon class means this protocol can
only be implemented by a class.
It cannot be implemented by a struct or an enum.
Okay? Then you wouldn't need
any mutatings because a class,
since it's a reference passed by reference all the time,
you can obviously mutate with any method or property.
Okay, you can even specify that
a protocol requires the class or
structure enum to implement a certain initializer.
Okay, that way you
know that you can create one of these things.
All right. So, that's kinda cool too.
All right, so that's how you declare a protocol.
See? It's pretty straightforward.
No implementations in here, right?
All right, so now let's talk about the part of it where it
says I'm an implementor.
I want to implement this protocol.
How do I tell the world I'm going to implement this?
You do that by putting at
the end of the declaration of the thing, so here's class,
SomeClass then it inherits from SuperclassOfSomeClass.
You just put a comma and all the protocols that
this class is claiming to implement, okay?
Now, obviously if this was a struct or
enum it wouldn't have that superclass name.
So it would just be colon and then the list of
all the protocols that it is claiming to implement.
So this enum says it's going to implement some protocol,
and it's also going to implement another protocol.
And once it says that, it has to do it or
the compiler will not allow you to compile, okay?
Same thing with the struct, all right?
So pretty straightforward syntax there.
The number of protocols is unlimited,
you can just keep putting more and
more protocols that you say you'll implement.
In a class, if you implement an init in a class,
you have to say it's required.
Okay?
So that's because you wouldn't want a subclasser
using the rules of inheritance of initializers which we
talked about in depth last lecture or the one before.
It can get to a situation where that init is
not even implemented, okay, in sub class.
And that would be no good because you're saying
you conform to this protocol and then that init is part of
this protocol so you have to make them required.
Okay?
You are allowed to add protocol compliance or
conformance with an extension.
And this is very common to do,
again, in a bigger architected system, is you will implement
the entire implementation of a protocol on some class or
structure enum by implementing it as an extension.
Now the only thing about that implementation is,
of course, no stored properties in there.
Only computer properties.
So you would have to be able to
implement that entire protocol without any storage.
But a lot of protocols can be implemented without storage.
Cuz they're fairly simple protocols, okay.
Here's what it looks like to use a protocol as a type.
So I've created a protocol called Moveable.
It has one function in it,
move to, which presumably moves the thing.
I've created two things,
a class called car which is a moveable.
So the car can be moved, and a class called,
or struct rather called shape which can be moveable, so this
might be a graphical shape that can be moved on screen.
Now you see that car and
shape are completely different kinds of things, but
they both could be moved, so they both could be movables.
And you can see that they both properly implement the movable
protocol and they both claimed implement movable.
Then I've created a couple of little variables here prius
and square which are just instances of car and shape.
Okay, so now let's look at some code.
I can create a variable called thing to move.
It is of type movable.
That's protocol, but protocols are types.
And I can set it equal to prius.
This is completely legal because a prius
is a moveable, right?
It implements the moveable protocol.
So I can set a variable that is moveable to a prius,
works great.
I can then say thing to move, move to.
Because thing to move is anything that implements
the moveable protocol.
However, I cannot say thing to move dot change oil, okay?
Change oil is a car thing,
it's not a moveable thing, okay?
So I can't send it to a moveable.
Even though, yes,
that thing to move happens to currently contain a car
it's still a compiler won't even let you put this in.
It'll complain.
It'll say, thing to move is a moveable.
Moveables don't understand change oil.
You understand?
I could then say thingToMove equal square.
That's perfectly legal as well cuz a square is a Moveable.
It implements that protocol so it can do it as well.
More interestingly I could let thingsToMove be an array of
Moveable, and I could set it equal to an array that
has a prius anda square in it.
So it's got a car and a shape, a class and a struct,
all in this array and it's perfectly legal because
they're both moveable so I can create an array of them
because moveable is a protocol It's just like a type.
It is a type.
Okay, make sense?
Why I can do that?
All right I can also have a function like slide,
let's say that slide something along the ground or
something, and you can take an argument which is unmovable.
And then inside of it I can say move to and
that works fine, and I say slide prius,
slide square, all works fine because.
They're all moveable.
It's actually possible to declare an argument like slip
and slide, that implements two, that takes an argument
that has to implement two separate protocols.
Moveable, but also something called slippery, let's say,
which I haven't defined.
Okay, so
this little thing where you say protocol angle bracket and
then as many protocols as you want closed angle bracket,
that says this argument to this function has to implement
both of those protocols.
Or all of those protocols.
And then if I tried to say slip and
slide Prius, not even compile.
Because while Prius is a moveable,
it's not as slippery.
And so it can't do that.
Can't be passed through that argument, okay?
Everyone cool with protocols?
Any question about that before I
start talking about delegation which uses protocols?
Okay. So
delegation is a very important use of protocols.
Delegation, if you remember back to our MVC talk right at
the beginning of the quarter, we had this big graph.
And one of the things we showed was how views need to
be able to talk back to their controller, okay?
But views are generic.
So, they can't know anything about the class or
the controller that's using them.
They're generic building blocks.
Okay? So how do they talk back?
Well, it turns out they talk back using protocols, okay,
and this is called delegation.
Okay?
So, let's talk a little bit about how that works,
how it plays out to do delegation.
First, you're gonna create the delegate protocol.
So, the delegate protocol is just gonna be protocol,
something with a bunch of methods and
perhaps even properties.
And it's going to describe what the view is looking for
someone else to do for it.
Okay?
It's gonna describe the responsibilities the view is
going to delegate to someone else.
Okay? So if this is a scroll view,
something the protocol might be, should scroll to point.
The view wants to know should I scroll to this point?
The user's trying to scroll to this point.
Should I do it?
And the view doesn't know because it
doesn't own its own data.
It doesn't really even know what it's scrolling on.
It needs to ask someone else.
So it's going to create this protocol.
Any time it either needs to notify someone else to
something interesting that is happening or
ask someone else for permission to do something or
to try to get its data, which is a common thing.
It wants its data that it's trying to draw but
it can't own its own data.
Remember views can't own their data,
the data is owned by the controller.
Really, it's probably in the model, but
the controller is responsible for dishing the data out.
So at first you're gonna create that protocol.
Then you're gonna create a property in your view,
okay, called delegate or sometimes it's called data
source if it's delegating the data.
And the type of that property is
this delegation protocol that you're gonna create.
Protocols are just types so
that's what the property type is gonna be.
Okay, then it's gonna use that property to go do all
the delegation.
It's going to send a message to
the delegate property saying, should I scroll to this point,
it's going to send a message to this delegate property.
Maybe it will be called data source in this case, but
it's saying hey, where's my data?
Give me more of my data.
Okay? That's what it's going to
send and it's going to send it to this object right here,
this delegate property.
And this delegate property, all it is is a protocol.
So all that, anybody who implements that
protocol can be set as the value for that.
Delegate.
All right then the controller is going to come along and
it's going to first say that it implements that protocol.
Okay, so it's a class thing, it's going to say, yeah,
I implement this view this delegate protocol.
Then the controller is going to
set it's self as the delegate.
So it's going to set that delegate property inside
the view to itself, which is fine because it just said it
implements that protocol, so that's good.
Then, of course,
the controllers going to have to implement the protocol, and
implement all the methods and properties required by
the protocol so that it conforms to that protocol.
Otherwise compiler is going to complain.
And you're good to go.
Now the view is hooked up to the controller, okay?
But the view still knows nothing about the controller.
It doesn't know what class it is.
It doesn't know what its purpose in life is.
It knows nothing.
All it knows is it implements the methods in its protocol,
in the views protocol.
That's all it knows and that's all it needs to know.
Okay? So that keeps
the view completely generic and allows the controller to
have complete control of this generic minion in its view.
Remember the view is the controller's minions,
it's how it's communicating with the user.
So that's how we do it.
So let's take a look at a demo of doing that in happiness.
We're going to have
the face view delegate getting its data.
Its data is basically its smiliness,
how much smileyness is going on.
It's going to get that from the delegate.
And, of course, the happiness view controller is going to
be the delegate it gets it from.
>> Okay.
Well, let's now use delegation to hook up our
face view to our happiness view controller.
And we're gonna do that by
starting here in the face view.
We're gonna go through the same steps we
just talked about in the slides to do delegation.
So remember the first step is that we need a protocol,
some particular way that the face view is going to talk to
whoever's going to provide its data, and
the face view's data is really it's smiliness.
So the face view has this data.
Now this is a very, very simple data.
Probably in real life if this weren't,
you know a demo where I'm trying to show you delegation,
you would probably just set this, you
can't own it's own data, it's such a simple piece of data.
But we're going to use delegation to
get this piece of data here.
Rather than have it be set right here.
All right, so
we need some sort of protocol that gets this smiliness from
someone and, so we're gonna type in here protocol and
I'm gonna call this protocol.
That I'm developing my face view data source protocol.
And sometimes we call these delegation protocols delegate.
Like face view delegate.
But when the only purpose of the protocol is to
get the data that the view is going to draw.
Because the view can't own its own data,
then we often will call the protocol datasource.
So this just needs to have whatever functions and
properties are required to get this used data.
Well such a simple view that it
just needs something to get the smile in some function so
I'm going to say smiliness for face view.
I have an argument here which is the sender.
Face view.
And this is gonna be myself.
So when I ask somebody else to provide my data by
sending them this message.
I'm gonna pass myself, this face view,
along as an argument.
And you'll see all throughout iOS when they have
a delegate or a data source.
They are always going to pass themselves along.
If you are trying to provide the smiliness for
this FaceView, you have a point or two to FaceView.
You know, which FaceView is asking you that, and
maybe if you need to ask the FaceView some other
questions to answer this, you can do that.
Now, this smiliness what is it going to return?
Now I'm going to have it return a double,
which is going to be that smiliness,
remember that smiliness goes from a plus 1 down to minus 1,
plus 1 that's very smiley and
minus 1 that's very frowny and so we made that double.
I'm also going to make this double be an optional.
And that's because if the data source, if I ask it for
the smiliness, and for
some reason it can't provide that smiliness, then I'm gonna
allow them to return nill, and just have no smile or
no frown, just flatlined mouth there.
Now we only by the way pass one argument here.
But we could definitely, if we were asking our data source,
we could have some more arguments in here.
And so that's perfectly reasonable.
You can have as many arguments as you
need to get this smiliness out of the data source.
Okay, so that's step one, we have this data source here.
Step two is we need to have a public var in our face view,
which I'm going to call dataSource, and
it's going to be of type FaceViewDataSource.
Okay?
I'm going to make that an optional as well.
So you can see here that I'm using FaceViewDataSource,
which is this protocol, just as a type.
And what this means is,
somebody who wants to provide my data,
who wants to be my dataSource,
all they need to do is set themselves as this variable.
And then I'm going to talk to them through this variable to
call this function on them.
Okay?
Now, why did I make this an optional here?
Because it's possible that
I can just live without a data source.
I will just always have a flat line, a flat mouth.
I won't be smiling or frowning.
And so this can be allowed to be nil.
Okay, now normally, this is not going to want to be nil,
because we don't want a face with no frown and no smile.
But, we'll certainly allow it.
So, allow that there.
Now one other thing we have to do about this data source here
is we really want to describe it as weak.
Now this is gonna be the first time we talk about
memory management in this class.
And really the memory's just been
managed automatically for you.
But here we have to be a little bit
careful with the memory management of this pointer.
Because, for example,
our controller is going to set itself as the data source.
So it's going to set this pointer back to itself because
our controller's going to be a FaceViewDataSource.
And, unfortunately, the controller also has
a pointer to this FaceView through the view hierarchy.
Because it's gonna have some outlet to the face view, and
so they'll be pointing to each other.
And since they're pointing to each other they're keeping
each other in memory at all times, so
that kinda memory cycle is really bad.
Because then the FaceView and
the controller can never leave memory.
They'll be stuck in memory forever.
So, by making this weak, if we put weak in front of a var
pointer it means that this pointer, this thing, whatever
this points to, should not be used to keep it in memory.
So the controller is gonna set itself as this data source.
This pointer, since it is going to be a weak pointer,
is not going to keep the controller in memory.
So the controller will be allowed to go out of memory.
And when it goes out of memory,
of course the FaceView loss will go out of
memory with it because its entire view hierarchy,
the controller's view hierarchy will go out as well.
And now you can see that we have an error here, okay?
And this error says weak cannot be applied to non-class
types, okay?
So FaceViewDataSource is a protocol, not a class.
So FaceViewDataSource could be an enum or
a struct and that's a problem because we really need this to
be weak because we
don't want that cycle things pointing back to each other.
So, we can actually make FaceViewDataSource, even
though it's a protocol, we can make it be a class type.
If you remember from the slides in our
protocol declaration, we can say colon class.
And that says that FaceViewDataSource can only be
implemented by a class, it cannot be implemented by
a struct or an enum, and that's perfectly fine and
usually that's what we're going to want anyway, but
we definitely need that so we can have this weak behavior.
So this data source, the pointer it has to whatever its
data source will not keep it's data source in memory.
As long as the dataSource is in memory,
this pointer will be good.
As soon as the dataSource goes out of memory then this
pointer will be set to nill automatically by the system.
So it's pretty cool, these banners are pretty cool.
We don't use them a lot you saw that we used them for IB
outlets and this is the second place that we have used them,
which is for delegation.
We're always gonna use a weak var when we have delegation.
Okay?
That just requires that we make our protocol,
you only work for classes.
All right?
Okay? So now we
have this nice data source right here.
Let's go ahead and go to the next step,
which to use the data source to get our smiliness, right?
So we have our smiliness right here,
it's currently at constant minus 0.5, so we're going to
get it from the data source by just saying to the data
source, please give us our smiliness for FaceViewSelf.
Okay?
Now when I type that in,
Swift automatically put this question mark here.
I didn't type that.
It put it in here.
Why did it put here?
Well it put it here because data source is an optional.
And it could be nil, okay?
This is an optional, it could be nil.
And so Swift is assuming that we wanna use optional
chaining here.
And just, if this is nil, then this whole rest of
this expression is gonna be ignored.
This whole thing would be nil.
And smiliness here would be set to nil, okay?
But smiliness, you can see this error here is
because smiliness, it can't be nil.
It has to be a double.
So we're going to use another cool little feature switch.
Swift which is the question mark question mark operator.
Now what this operator says is,
if the thing on the left-hand side of the question mark
question mark is not nill, then use that.
But if it is nil, then use what's on the righthand side,
and to the right hand side I'm gonna put 0.0.
So what that says is that if the data source is nil,
then we're going to use smiliness of 0,
which is not a frown or a smile, it's in the middle.
Now this is also gonna be working if
SmilinessForFaceView happens to return now because you
remember it is also an optional double right here.
So that'll work perfectly fine there as well.
So whether this returns nill or
whether this is nill, invalidating the rest of this,
we're gonna get no smile or frown.
So this is a cool little operator [INAUDIBLE].
Okay, so we've got our face view doing its part.
It's declaring this nice property,
this protocol right here.
It's got a property which less people set themselves as
the data source and
then it uses that data source to get its smiliness.
All right, so
now let's go back to our happiness view controller.
Okay? The controller has to
implement the other side of delegation.
Now you remember one of the steps it has is it has to
say to the world, I am HappinessViewController and
I implement the FaceViewDataSource protocol.
And it does that by just saying FaceViewDataSource.
Now as soon as I put this on here,
I'm going to get a warning right here,
an error that says,
HappinessViewController does not conform to that protocol.
And indeed it doesn't because we do not implement
that smiliness by anywhere in our class.
So, easily fixed though.
We go down here, now, since, we've already told it,
it implements this.
If I just start typing smiliness it's going to
automatically know to escape complete.
So I'll hit Tab.
I've got my nice method here.
So how am I going to implement this protocol?
Okay, this method in this protocol,
how am I going to implement that?
Well the happiness view controller is going to
interpret the happiness here.
Which is the model.
This is the happiness view controller's model.
It's gonna interpret this for the view, because the view
doesn't know about happiness, it only knows about smiliness.
Smiliness goes from 1 to minus 1.
Here, we're taking about the model which is happiness that
goes from 0 to 100.
So it's a typical job of the controller to
interpret the model for the view.
You also interpret the view for the model and we'll see
that a little bit later when we talk about gestures.
But, here we're going to interpret the model for
the view.
So, I'm just going to return.
Now, happiness is an int, and smiliness is a double, so
I am going to have to convert the happiness.
Also, the happiness is on a scale of 0 to 100, so
I am going to do minus 50.
Divide by 50 to convert it into that plus 1 to
minus 1 scale.
So here I'm just interpreting the model for the view.
Make sense?
Now the last thing that needs to happen here is
that the controller needs to set itself
as the data source of the FaceView.
Let's all go back to FaceView,
I'm going to show you a nice trick here.
Cmd+Shift+O will let you type in like, start typing
FaceView and you can see it appear right there, and
you can switch really quick so Cmd+Shift+O is a great way to
switch really quickly between files in your project.
All right, so we need to set this data source right here
inside of our face view to be the controller.
So for the controller to do that,
though, it needs to have a pointer to the FaceView.
And we do pointers to things in
our view using outlets, right?
So let's go over here to our storyboard and wire up
an outlet from this.
We'll go to automatic mode up here.
Remember, when you go to automatic mode you're
gonna see the controller that matches what you
have selected in your storyboard.
So here we can have that.
So I'm just going to take my controller right here and
I'm going to Ctrl+drag to create an outlet.
This is the same way that I create an outlet to buttons or
to the labels or whatever we've done.
It's exactly the same.
It's just a normal outlet.
I'm going to call it Face View.
So here's really nice FaceView right there.
Now where in my code should I go and
set this var right here?
Okay, this data source var.
Well a great place to do it since this is
the faceView we want to set that in,
is right here in the property observer for the FaceView.
This property observer is called when the iOS starts up
and loads the story board.
It connects this outlet.
It's going to set this variable.
And so it's a perfect time when this is
being set to go ahead and
say FaceView.dataSource equals self, okay?
This is the controller.
It's perfectly legal for
it to say this because it is a FaceView data source, right?
The happiness view controller is a face view data source so
we can say that it is the new source.
It's perfectly fine equals.
All right?
That make sense that we're doing that?
Okay, so now everything is hooked,
and how is this gonna work.
It's going to be very straight forward.
Every time that the face redraws itself,
it's going to look for its data source.
Which we have set right here in our controller to
be the controller itself.
It's going to get its smiliness from the data
source by calling the method in the protocol up here, okay?
We implement that method in our controller.
We interpret the model for the view.
And the FaceView's gonna be able to draw the proper value.
Now there's only one other thing that I wanna do here.
Which is every time something changes our model,
I wanna make sure the face redraws itself.
Of course, because we're representing that in the face.
So the best space to do that is in this update UI, so
every single time the happiness changes I'm going to
ask my FaceView to set needs display of itself.
In other words, to redraw.
Remember set needs display is the thing you do that says
hey, call my draw rect, redraw me.
Now if I didn't do this then every time I
set my happiness the FaceView would not draw, okay?
Now maybe if I rotated my device and
it redrew then it would show it but.
Otherwise it wasn't gonna show it.
We've got this hooked up, it really should be the happiness
that's showing in here rather than the smiliness.
So it shouldn't be a flat line right here,
it should actually show the happiness.
Let's go ahead run, see what we got here.
I knew we should get a happiness of 75,
which is a little bit happy.
Yeah. That looks good right there.
Let's go change our happiness here to be sad, like maybe 10.
Go ahead and re-run.
Okay, we're sad, all right and
let's go to the ecstatic and we're ecstatic, okay?
Or we should be ecstatic because we
successfully implemented delegation.
>> All right.
Let's go back to our slides and
cover the next thing here, which is gestures.
All right.
So we know how to draw inner view,
now we wanna handle these gestures.
Okay?
You know, pinches and maybe rotations, swipes, taps,
pinchsrotationsswipestaps
things like that.
Now we could get the raw data about every finger that
goes down, and where it is, that data is available, but
we never look at that.
First of all it's very difficult to
look at that raw data, and
see, is this a swipe, or is it just moving over to the right.
swipe
So iOS does all that for
ios
you, and that's the only way I'm going to teach you
to react to user touches is via gestures, okay?
So how do gestures work?
Gestures are recognized by UI views when
the gesture happens inside their bounds.
Okay, I told you the views are rectangular areas where you
draw and you recognize gestures so
this is how it happens.
There's a class called UIGestureRecognizer.
UIGestureRecognizer
It's an abstract base class.
You never actually create a UIGestureRecognizer base
UIGestureRecognizer
class, you create a sub class of UIGestureRecognizer.
And those subclasses are concrete in
that they know about certain gestures, swipes and pans and
swipespanstouch
touches, et cetera.
So there are two sides to using a gesture recognizer.
One is you have to add a gesture recognizer to a view.
That says to the view, start recognizing this gesture.
If you recognize this gesture, you let somebody know.
Okay?
And you do that with
a function on UIView called add gesture recognizer.
addGestureRecognized
Couldn't be simpler.
Then the second piece, though, is when you create the gesture
recognizer, you have to say, if you recognize the gesture,
who are you gonna tell about it?
Okay, you have to notify somebody and
say oh, I recognize that swipe.
swipe
Okay?
So there's the handler.
So you've got the recognizer, that's the view.
Okay, the gesture recognizer in association with the view.
And then you've got the handler that's who handles it,
and those are not always the same person.
Sometimes they're the same object, sometimes not.
Usually the first one, adding a gesture recognizer to
a view is done by a controller.
Although a view will sometimes add it to itself, for
example scroll view.
scroll view
Scroll view doesn't even exist without the pan and
pinch gestures, that's what it does.
panpinch
So it adds the gesture recognizers to itself.
But a lot of times other times you have a gesture that
you're going to recognize only if the controller wants you to
recognize it, so
you make some public handler possibly in your view.
And then your controller can add this gesture recognizer to
one of its views, one of its minions and say,
start recognizing this gesture and you can even handle it
yourself if you want, the controller might say.
Or the controller might say oh, and I'll handle it.
So the second thing, the handling is either done by
the view if it's a display-oriented handling
thing, or it's done by the controller if it's handling
model
something that's going to modify the model.
Okay? Or be something that's
complicated that's going to cause multiple views to
be involved and so the controller has to do it.
And it's perfectly fine to have either the controller or
the view handle something although you would
never have the view handle a gesture that is directly
modifying the model cuz a view can't see the model.
modelmodelview
Only a controller can do that.
model
Okay?
So how do you add a gesture recognizer to a UI view?
It's very simple.
I'm going to do it in a way that is very common, which is
to do it in the property observer of an outlet setter,
set
just exactly like we did when we set the face views delegate
face view
in the property observer, when the face view got set.
face viewset
We could do the same thing adding adjuster recognizer.
In fact, we're going to do that in the demo.
demo
So here I have an IV outlet.
IBOutlet
It's just a UI view.
In my story board.
storyboard
It's called pannableView and
pannableView
I'm going to make it so it can pan around in there.
All right, and in his property observer there the did stat.
didSet
I'm going to add this gesture recognizer.
I'm going to create a pan gesture recognizer and
pan
then add it to the view.
So here I'm creating it.
This is just
calling UIPanGestureRecognizer initializer here.
UIPanGestureRecognizer
The arguments to the initializer are who to
send a message to when the gesture is recognized.
When we start seeing a pan.
pan
And as the pan is happening we're gonna be
sending a message to this object.
In this case it's self.
self
So this method would obviously be in a controller, right?
Because controllers are the only
things that have the outlets.
outlets
So this thing's going to be
handled by the controller itself.
And then action is the name of the method.
action
It's just a string that is the name of
the method that's gonna be
called in the controller when this gesture is recognized.
Now notice there's a little colon on the end there?
That means that it's called a, it's gonna
call a method called pan that has an argument.
pan
That's what the colon means.
There's an argument there.
Okay, now you don't have to have the colon there if
you want, but if you don't have it there, then you
pan
won't get the argument when pan gets called and
the argument you get is the gesture recognizer.
GestureRecognizer
And for something like pan where you're gonna try and
figure out where the finger is,
you need the gesture recognizer so
it can tell you where the finger is basically, okay?
So we almost always have a colon.
The only place you
wouldn't have a colon might be like a swipe.
swipe
Because the swipe just got recognized,
you don't really need any information,
you just need to know what happened.
swipe
So you might have action, quote, handle swipe, no colon.
Then we just ask the view,
this panable view, please recognize this gesture when it
pan
happens inside your bounds.
Okay that's simple, that's like turning on,
this is the on switch, for
switch
turning on that pan gesture I recognized,
pan
by asking some of you to recognize it.
So now every time this view recognizes a pan going on
pan
inside its bounce it's going to send the message pan
with an argument to the controller.
pan
Everybody okay with this?
This is how you set up a gesture recognizer.
How about the handler?
So that pan thing with that argument, how do we do that?
For us to handle the pan we need information about
pan
what's going on in that pan.
Where are the fingers moving?
We need to know about that.
So the concrete subclasses of UI gesture recognizer like UI
UIGestureRecognizer
pangesture recognizer, they add methods that
PanGestureRecognizer
are specific to whatever kind of gesture they are.
So the panGesture one has a translation in
PanGesturetranslationInView
view which tells you how far the finger has moved since,
either since the panGesture was first recognized, or
since that last got reset.
And you can reset with this set translation which will
setTranslation
reset this translation to a different spot so
that the next time that you get notified,
it will be the distance between this.
So that's a good way to get incremental panning instead of
just the total distance that you've panned.
And then also I can tell you velocity,
velocity
how fast are you panning around?
Is the person kinda moving real slow, or
trying to put something in a perfect spot,
or are they kind of zooming it around, okay,
you might react differently depending on the velocity.
So those are the things that are very specific to Pan, so
pan
that's why these methods are in panGesture Recognizer.
PanGestureRecognizer
Now that last one is interesting because of
incremental translation
this incremental translation.
A lot of people really don't quite understand this.
But you'll see when we do the demo, we'll
demo
do incremental translation with our pinch gesture.
pinchincremental translation
And it'll make a little more sense what's going on there.
The abstract superclass UIGestureRecognizer.
UIGestureRecognizer
It also has a very important property called State.
state
Okay when you have a pan it actually goes through states.
pan
It starts out in the state Possible.
Possible
It's possible a pan can happen.
pan
Then if it were a swipe or
a discrete gesture, you would just get one state.
Which is I recognize this.
Recognized
So that's Recognized.
But if it's pan and
pan
continuous, then you're gonna get began.
stateBegan
Okay, recognize that the pan has started.
pan
You'll get that.
And then every time the finger moves,
you're gonna get another call to your handler saying,
changed, changed, changed.
Changed
And then when the finger goes up,
you'll get another one that says the state is now ended.
Ended
So this is basically a little state machine.
Obviously a pan goes through the state machine of possible,
pan
began, changed, ended.
All right?
There's also failed and
FailedCanceled
canceled, like you're in the middle of a pan and
pan
a phone call comes in, okay?
That's going to cancel that pan, alright?
pan
So sometimes you have to pay attention to cancellation like
that and sometimes not, it all depends on what you're doing
with your pan, sometimes your pan is updating.
Whatever's there is in real time and
if the phone call comes in it just stops doing that and
it's fine, everything is in perfectly fine state.
Other times it might be putting something in
some temporary state and
now it's interrupted it's gotta clean up, or something.
All right. So given this information,
what would the pan handler look like?
Okay? The pan
handler would be a method called pan.
It would take one argument which is
the UIPanGestureRecognizer itself.
You can see right there.
Okay?
We're going to look at the state machine and
say what state it's in.
So in my pan,
I'm only going to do something when the gesture moves or
the finger goes up.
I'm not even gonna do anything when it first goes down.
I can choose which things I wanna do.
But that's what I wanna do.
Hopefully you know about fall through.
You read that in the documentation.
Fall through is just a thing in switch that says
the implementation of this case is to go to the next one.
And do whatever the next one is, okay?
So it just falls through to the next case.
So in changed and
ended, I'm gonna do exactly the same thing.
What I'm gonna do is I'm gonna find out where
the pan is in the coordinates of the panable view, so
its coordinate system.
'Kay, that's translation in view.
I give it the view.
I want the coordinate system.
It's gonna give me the point in that view where the pan is.
Then I'm gonna update anything I want inside of my controller
cuz this is being handled by the controller.
So I'm gonna update anything I want based on that
translation, x and y, then I'm gonna reset the translation
and I don't have to do this but I'm going to in this case,
reset the translation back to 0, so
that the next time I get this called, in the next time it
changes it's gonna be just the difference.
Otherwise it's going to tell me from the time the gesture
was first recognized to where I am now.
So that'd be a big distance when I
just want the incremental distance as I move around.
So that set translation to 0 is optional,
you can do it if you want.
Okay? So that's it.
That's how we handle a gesture.
Very straight forward.
So let's talk about some of
the concrete gestures that exist.
There's pinch.
Okay? Pinch,
instead of giving you translation,
it gives you scale.
So when the pinch starts, the scale is 1.
If you spread your fingers out twice as wide,
the scale would be 2.
If you go down to half as wide, the scale would be 0.5.
Okay?
So that's how pinches work.
And it'll tell you the velocity.
How fast the person is pinching.
There's also rotation.
So that's a two finger thing as well.
You turn in a circle.
So it's like you're turning a knob.
It tells you how many radians the thing has been rotated.
Okay?
And it'll also tell you how fast in
radians per second the rotations happen.
So that's the way you can rotate.
There's also swipes.
Now, swipes are a little different.
When you create the swipe gesture, okay,
back in the property observer of the outlet,
I created a pan gesture.
But if I created a swipe gesture there,
I would send a message,
set the property of the swipe gesture,
number of touches required, or swipe direction there, and
that determines whether it's a two finger swipe to the left
or a one finger swipe down, or whatever.
You just kinda say what kind of swipe you're looking for,
and then your handler would only be called once,
with the state .Recognized when that combination
of fingers and direction happens.
So that's a little different than these other ones.
And there's also tap, a question.
>> Also for these gestures I said you can now test in
the simulator, right?
>> Can you test these in the simulator?
Absolutely you can test these in
the simulator, I'll show you.
>> How do you test more than one finger?
>> Yes, how do you test more than one finger in
the simulator, I'll show you how to do that.
Tap gesture is an interesting one.
It seems like it would be
discrete because it's kind of like swipe.
You set up the number of taps and the number of touches.
Except for that if you have a double tap it'll actually tell
you about the first tap and the second tap.
So if you're only interested in the actual double tap you
can just look at the state ending because
that's the end of that gesture.
But if you want to look at the intermediate states you
can actually look at the dot changed stated as well, so
it's not purely a discreet gesture tap.
Okay, so let's go look at how we do gestures by putting some
gestures in the FaceView.
So I'm gonna put two gestures in.
I'm gonna put in pinch to change the size of the face,
and then I'm gonna put in pan to control the happiness,
in other words, control my model.
All right?
With pan.
When I move up and
down it's gonna be happy is up, sad is down.
Not a swipe but actual pan so
I can move my happiness up in small increments if I want.
All right, so let's go back to here to do that.
So let's go get some more space here.
So we'll go here.
So we'll do the pinch first.
Let's do the pinch first.
So the first thing I'm gonna do when I
make my pinch happen is to add a gesture recognizer.
A pinch gesture recognizer to my FaceView.
And so a great place to do that,
as I said, is in the property observer of the FaceView.
So here I can just say, add gesture.
Whoops, sorry, FaceView.
FaceView.
Add gesture recognizer.
And this is just any kind of gesture recognizer.
I'm going to do a panGesture.
So I'm going to say UI Pan gesture recognizer.
And then you can see that it
has target in action are the arguments.
So the target I'm gonna have the pinch be handled
entirely by the view.
Because all it's doing is changing the view scale.
Its own scale.
So there's no reason I'm the controller I don't need to
get involved with that.
So I'm just going to have the target be the FaceView.
So the FaceView is going to handle this pan.
Or, sorry, we're doing pan, no, we'll do pinch.
So I'm doing pinch.
Your pinch first.
So we're doing pinch.
So we're doing the pinch of scale, not pan, sorry.
We're doing the pinch and I'm gonna have the FaceView
handle this because it's just gonna modify its scale.
And this action needs to be some nonprivate method
in my FaceView that I can call to handle it.
So, let's go ahead and go over to our faceview and
add such a thing.
So I'm going to call this method, what to call it?
Scale.
Okay?
And it's going to take a UI pinch gesture recognizer
as an argument, and we'll call that the gesture.
And all this is gonna do is modify our scale.
Okay?
Understand? You got this method here?
So how is this method gonna do this?
Well, I'm only going to adjust my scale when the pinch moves.
I'm not gonna do it when it first goes down because it's
gonna be scale of 1 anyway, and
I probably should do it when the fingers go up, but just to
make less code here I'm just gonna do it when it changes.
So I'm gonna say if the gesture state equals .changed.
Okay.
Then I'm going to take my own scale and
multiply it by the gestures scale.
Okay.
So if the gesture pinch scales out.
I'm going to make my scale bigger.
If it scales in I'm going to make my scale smaller.
Okay.
And I'm going to reset the gesture scale back to 1
all the time.
By resetting it back to 1 then I'm only getting the
difference between the last time it told me to update.
So that way I can update my scale every time it moves.
And since I keep resetting back to one,
I keep getting incremental scale.
It's gonna keep making my scale bigger or
smaller depending on whether the last movement of
the pinch was bigger or smaller.
This makes my code a lot simpler.
So that's it. That's all that's necessary.
And it's typical for gesture recognizers to be this simple,
to not require a lot of code.
So, this is the name of the handler.
scale  handler
So, let's go back to our controller and
put that in here, the action is scale.
action  scale
And it did take that argument.
So, I do need to put the colon there.
scale
Okay, and that's it.
That's all that's required.
So, let's go ahead and try it.
Now as was being asked here, how do I do two fingers,
I only got one mouse here.
And the answer is you hold down the option key.
option
You see when you hold down option, you get two fingers.
Okay, and they're evenly spaced from the middle, and
I can use them to pinch in and out.
Okay, there we go.
So you can see adding gestures really, really simple, okay.
You can do other things too.
If I can remember here I think Cmd, what is it.
There's other things too,
I can't remember offhand what they are but
you can take the two things and move them.
There we go. I'm using Shift.
Control  Shift
Now you can move them up here.
So that you can expand them out from here or whatever.
So you can control them a little bit.
Only two, you can't do three fingers or whatever.
So there's some limitations but
you can do some stuff there, all right.
So that's good. So
now let's talk about another gesture.
Let's do a pan gesture, where
Pan Gesture
if I pan up it's gonna make my guy happier and
if I pan down it's gonna make him sadder.
Okay.
So I can use a pan gesture for that.
Now, I could just go right here and
faceView  Pinch Gesture
do the same thing, I could say faceView.addGestureRecognizer-
faceView.addGestureRecognizer
(UIPanGestureRecognizer{target .
UIPanGestureRecognizer(target: ...
The target would be myself.
target  self
Because if I'm modifying the model with that pan gesture,
Model
my view can't do that.
View
The controller has to handle it itself.
And we can have the action of
Action
this thing be something like changeHappiness.
changeHappiness
Take that argument or something.
So I could do this.
But I'm not gonna do it this way, okay.
This would be perfectly fine.
But I'm gonna show you how
you can set up gestures in the storyboard.
Storyboard
So you don't even need this line of code, okay.
So here's how that works.
We're gonna go over here.
Let's get our storyboard.
Main.storyboard
And I wanna add a gesture recognizer to this view.
I do it by going over here,
same place where I add things to my view here.
If you go down towards the bottom,
you'll see that there's tap gesture, pinch gesture,
TapPinch
rotation gesture, swipe gesture, pan gesture.
RotationSwipePan
Okay.
So I'm gonna grab this pan gesture and drop it on this
view, which says I want this view to recognize a pan.
Now you might say, whoa, where'd that go?
I didn't see anything there what's going on?
Where is that thing, it's hard to tell.
Well, there's two places you
can find that thing you just dropped.
One is in the document outline.
Document Outline
You see it right here?
Pan Gesture Recognizer.
Pan Gesture Recognizer
Another one is, right at the top.
If you look at the view controller right here, you'll
Storyboard  View Controller
see there's a Pan Gesture Recognizer right there.
Pan Gesture Recognizer
Okay. Now all you need to do
to make this pan gesture recognizer be handled by your
controller is Ctrl + drag.
Control
So I'm holding down Ctrl and dragging in here, okay.
Let go.
It's an action kind of like target action for
Action Target Action
a button, but not quite exactly the same.
And I'm gonna call this change happiness cuz that's what
Action  changeHappiness
this pan gesture does.
Again, type I don't want to be any object.
AnyObject
This is gonna be the type of the argument.
I want it to be Pan Gesture Recognizer.
UIPanGestureRecognizer
If you leave any object in there you'll have to be
AnyObject
using as to turn it into a pan gesture recognizer so we can
as  UIPanGestureRecognizer
use it, but obviously a lot easier to just click it here.
The same as we had when we did button action.
So it can connect, okay, here it is right here.
Connect Action
Let's go look at it.
Okay, change happiness.
changeHappiness
And now we just need to implement this one.
So, what do we need to do to change our happiness?
changeHappiness
Well the pan is moving up and down,
so I can get the coordinates of the pan in the face views
faceView
coordinate system, but
I really need to turn that into a happiness change in
some interpretations.
So again the controller is now interpreting what's
happening in the view for the model, so it's going in
Model  View
the opposite direction of where we went before.
And again, that's the controller's main job,
interpreting the model for the view and
View  Model
the view input to modify the model.
So how's this going to work?
So again, I'm going to do sender.state = .changed.
if sender.state == .changed
I'm not going to do this because if I do this,
everyone out there is going to start doing the same thing.
So let's do a switch of this.
switch
I'm going to switch on the gestures, state.
switch gesture.state
I'm going to handle the case where it ended and
.Ended
I'm going to handle the case where it changed, okay.
.Changed
And I'm just going to do them the same, so
I'll do this fall through like we did in the slides.
.Ended  fallthrough
So, when this pan is changing or when the finger lifts up,
I'm going to try and change my happiness, okay.
happiness
So, first let's get the translation of the pan in
faceView
the face views coordinate system.
translation
And to do that I'm going to send a message to the sender,
Sender
you see sender right here?
That's the pan gesture recognizer that
is being handled here.
UIPanGestureRecognizer
We call this gesture in the other one and
sender
a lot of people like to change this to gesture,
gesture
which I think is perfectly fine to want to do.
So I'm going to ask the gesture,
gesture
tell me the translation in the face views coordinate system.
faceView
So now I know how much it's moved in
the face view coordinate system.
faceView
And so I'm going to let the happiness change, this is
happinessChange
the amount of change that's happening in my happiness.
happiness
I could just have it be equal to translation.y, probably
translation.y
would wanna be -translation.y because up means happy and
-translation.y
down means not happy.
But that's going to change the happiness a lot with very
small movements.
happiness
So I don't really want that.
So I really want to have, also it needs to be an int by
the way, so do that, because happiness is an int.
happiness
I really want this changed last so
I'm going to actually divide this by a constant.
-translation.y
So I'm going to create a constant here,
Constants.HappinessGestureS- cale I'll call it.
Constants.HappinessGestureScale
And we'll go back up here and I'll do the private struct
Constants  private struct
constants, and this is a static let,
static let
this thing which is a CG float.
CGFloat
Let's do four.
So for every four points we move,
we'll move our happiness by one.
happiness 1
Then we could play with this constant.
That's part of the reason I'm putting it out in a constant.
We could play with this number until we got the feel that we
thought felt right for changing our happiness, okay.
So we got our happiness changed.
happinessChange
So if the happiness change is not zero.
happinessChange 0
So if the happiness actually changed then I'm going to
happiness
change my happiness, happiness += happinessChange.
happiness += happinessChange
I'm also going to do that reset thing.
So gesture.setTranslation(CGPoin-
gesture.setTranslation(CGPointZero,
tZero in my faceView.
inView: faceView)
I'm resetting it because I'm changing my happiness every
happiness
time it changes, so I'm going to constantly be resetting it
so that it's incremental, okay.
And then of course we need to have the default case,
default
which is going to be cancelled or failed or
began, and I'm just going to do nothing in that case.
default
So any other state that gets thrown to me, I'll do nothing.
changeHappiness
So let's see if that works, let's run.
Here we go, so now up is happier.
Down is sad.
Up, good.
And we can still do this.
Okay, so these gestures, they don't look the same.
Okay, they don't start the same.
This one's a two-finger one,
okay, and this is a one-finger one.
So the system can easily tell the difference between
which one is going on and IOS is very good at
telling the difference between different gestures starting.
iOS
Okay? So everybody got that?
So we did a lot of different kind of
gesture handling there.
We added one in a storyboard.
Storyboard
We added one in code.
We handled one in our controller.
We handled one in our face view.
faceView
One is scaling and pinching, the other one was translation.
So hopefully between those two,
you can look through that code and kinda get a good feel for
how the gestures go.
Okay, good, so we do have some time left.
I'm going to get started on the next topic here.
Before I do that, because I'm going to get interrupted in
the middle, let's talk quickly about what's coming up.
So on Wednesday I'm going to continue the slides that I'm
Slide
going to start in a minute here.
About multiple MVCs and
Slide  MVC
then I'm gonna do a big demo creating multiple MVCs in
demo
our happiness controller, okay.
happiness controller  MVC
And again, time permitting, at the end of Wednesday I'll do
another topic view controller lifecycle.
view controller
Friday, hopefully, it will have this instruments thing.
instruments
And then next Monday I put auto layout question mark.
auto layout
Because I was telling you I was going to
do auto layout sooner but I keep putting it off.
And I might put it off again, we'll see.
But I won't be asking you in
your homework to do much sophisticated auto layout.
auto layout
So even it assignment three, there's very little.
Okay, so next topic, multiple MVCs.
MVC
So you remember this picture, I hope.
Which was at the of the MVC talk where I talked about how
MVC
if we wanna build a big app,
we're gonna do it by putting multiple MVCs together, okay.
MVC
So we're gonna zoom in here and
take a look at exactly how that's done.
Okay, how we're
gonna make multiple combine multiple MVC's.
MVC
Okay.
So you see that MVC right there the purple one
MVC
at the top, that's an MVC and you can
MVC MVC view
see that this view is actually made up of other MVC's.
MVC
So iOS provides some controllers for
iOS   MVCs  controllers
MVCs that have other MVCs as their view.
MVCs  controllers  view
And the three we're gonna talk about today,
controller,
by the way you can build your own.
BTW,  controller
I'm not gonna talk about that today.
controller
You can build your own controllers that have MVCs as
controller   MVC  view
the view, but I'm gonna talk about the three that are
controller  iOS
provided in iOS which you're gonna be using in this class.
Which is TabBarController SplitViewControllers and
controller  TabBarController SplitViewControllers
NavigationControllers, 'kay.
NavigationControllers
So these are just controllers,
controller
they're subclasses of UIViewController.
UIViewcontroller
And they draw a little bit in their view but
view
then most of their view is what other MVC's draw, so
view  MVC
the MVCs are part of their views.
MVC  controller
So let's look at TabBarController,
TabBarController
it's probably the simplest one of all these.
You've seen TabBarControllers,
TabBarControllers,
you see it's got the four tabs along the bottom on this one.
TabBarController  tab
This is the health app, I think.
And all that happens here is when you click one of those
tab button
tab buttons at the bottom, the top gets replaced with an MVC.
MVC
An entire MVC is controlling that top.
In this case, it's some sort of dashboard MVC or health
MVC  dashboard
dashboard is being presented at the top, right here.
dashboard
And the icon and
dashboard icon
the title that goes along with the dashboard down there,
title
is actually gotten from the dashboard MVC.
dashboard MVC
In other words,
icon  title
not a property you set on the UITabBarController MVC.
UITabBarController MVC  property
You actually just have a property on
dashboard MVC
your dashboard MVC, it's called tabBarItem.
tabBarItem
And inside tabBarItem, if you go look it up in the doc,
it's got things like title, icon, things that the tab bar
tabBarItem  titleicon
controller needs to put a nice tab on the bottom for
tabBarController  dashboard
your dashboard MVC.
tab
So, as you can see, it's very object oriented, okay.
Everything is contained in just this MVC.
MVC
And so, if you press on a different tab,
tab
maybe the second tab, then this is a totally
different MVC that takes over the top of this screen.
MVC
This would be Health Data MVC, and you can see that it's got
Health Data MVC,
a different icon and text down there, right?
icon  title
By the way, if there's too
many tabs along the bottom there, I think you get five,
tab5tab
if you go to six tabs then iOS will automatically let
tabiOS
the user manage which ones he wants down there.
tab
It's pretty cool, okay.
cool
So you don't even have to and
you can put as many tabs you want.
tab
I don't really recommend more than five
tabs here, by the way.
For users it's like, what,
I have to manage my tabs down there, I don't wanna do that.
tab
It's just that you're asking yours to do more stuff.
So hopefully you can fit it in five.
5 tab
And so we have other MVCs as well.
MVC
So there's the sources of health data,
health data
I guess, in your Medical ID tab.
Medical ID tab.
And so this is a very simple thing you can understand.
You've got this UITabBarController,
UITabBarController
it's a controller of an MVC.
MVC  controller.
The view is the little tabs along the bottom that it's
UITabBarController view  tab
drawing and the MVC's on the top.
MVC
Everyone understand what I
mean now about an MVC whose view contains other MVC's?
MVC  view  MVC
So let's look at another one that does that.
controller
SplitViewController.
So, SplitViewController takes two MVCs, and
SplitViewController  MVC
it puts them side-by-side, okay.
It puts the one on the left,
kind of a well known width there.
But, you don't care what that width is because,
hopefully, you've got auto-layout, and so
auto-layout
it could be any width you want, or
any height you want, like this.
And then it puts another one on the right.
UISplitViewController MVC
Now, we call the MVC on the left, the Master in
MVC  split view  Master
the split view and we call the MVC on the right the Detail.
MVC  Detail
Now here I've got a calculator and a calculator graph.
You assignment three is going to be to build this basically.
It doesn't have to look exactly like this, okay.
I've made a simple looking one here.
But it could look very much like this.
But you do have to use a SplitViewController.
SplitViewController
So this is what it looks like.
Now, this is only happening on an iPad.
iPad
Now, when we talk about auto layout,
auto layout
we're going to start talking about size classes.
size classes
So, different devices have been grouped into
iOS
size classes.
size classes
And the sizes basically are regular, so regular width and
size  regularregular width  regular height
regular height or compact width and height.
compact width compact height
So an iPhone, all the iPhones except for
iPhone
the iPhone 6+ in landscape,
landscape iPhone 6+
are compact both vertically and horizontally, okay.
compact
The iPad is regular width, okay.
iPad  regular width
Now, that's of the whole device.
But the MVC's inside also will have a certain size class.
iPad MVC  size class
So this side by side business can only happen in
MVC
a device whose size class is regular width.
regular width  size class
So that's the iPad in both landscape and portrait could
iPad  landscape portrait regular width
be that, and the iPhone 6+ in landscape, okay.
iPhone 6+  landscape regular width
So SplitView is only gonna do the side by
SplitView
side business there.
And if you rotate the iPad, then the Master disappears.
iPadMaster
But it can be swiped out.
Master
If you just swipe from the left, when you rotate the only
ipad  Detail
ones there is the Detail, you don't see the Master.
Master
But if you swipe out from the left,
then you get to see the Master as well.
Master
Again, side by side.
Master  Detail
Okay.
And if you touch the Detail, it'll make the Master go
Detail Master
back away and then you can swipe it.
So you can bring the Master out or not, okay.
Maser
That make sense?
So that's the SplitViewController,
SplitViewController
kind of how it's arranged.
But most importantly, I want you to understand that again,
it's two MVCs that are the view.
MVC  view
Now the SplitView draws nothing in its view,
SplitView  view
except for maybe that vertical separator line.
Okay, there's a vertical separator line.
That's probably drawn by the SplitViewController, but
SplitViewController
otherwise it's only drawing  whatever the MVCs draw.
MVC
So it doesn't even have any drawing on
tabBarViewController
the bottom like the TabBar has.
tabBar
Okay?
So the next thing I'm going to talk about, and
we're going to start this next time,
is NavigationController, which is a very powerful one.
NavigationController  controller
It draws at the top a little title and
title
some things, it can draw even around the bottom.
And then it can display any number of MVCs.
MVC
Okay, so we'll pick up the NavigationController next time
NavigationController
and in the meantime if you have any questions,
I'll be here as usual.
>> For more, please visit us at www.stanford.edu
>>  www.stanford.edu