[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
Okay, well, welcome to Lecture 8 of
Stanford CS193P winter of 2015.
Today we have two major topics we're gonna talk about,
one is view controller life cycle which is your view
controller gets born.
It lives and does a lot of things and
then it dies and so you want to be able to find out about
all those things that are going on and you can.
I'm gonna have a brief demo about that and
then we're gonna go into auto layout and
I keep promising we're gonna talk about it, so
I am gonna finally talk about auto layout.
Of course you all ready know a lot about auto layout and
I'm gonna review that.
Then we're gonna talk about an important piece of auto
layout that we haven't talked so far which is size classes,
and then I'll be doing a humongous couple of
demos on auto lab because, you know, it's the kind of thing
you're going to have to see it to really understand it, but
first, let's talk about view controller life cycle.
When we refer to the view controller life cycle,
we're just talking about a sequence of
messages that is sent to your view controller as it
progresses through its lifetime.
Why do we care about this?
Well because you very commonly wanna override these
messages that are sent to the view controller in
your subclass to find out what's going on, because you
might need to do things, make certain decisions or
whatever at certain points in your view controller life
cycle, so let's talk about the cycle and how it goes.
It starts off with creation.
99% of the time, this is from a storyboard, all right.
As you know, you create these scenes in the storyboard.
Those scenes have a view controller class associated
with them and you're just, you're segueing to an MVC,
even if you create an MVC in code, which I don't even talk
about how to do, maybe we'll talk about it a little later
in the quarter, but could look up in the documentation,
it's quite easy.
Even in that case, you're going to instantiate a view
controller using identifier in the storyboard, okay, and
that's how you're gonna get the view controller,
so creation is all most always from the storyboard, and
there is an init that gets called, it's kind of a weird
init, initWithCoder, I'm not gonna talk about it too much,
I mentioned it a little bit in the reading assignment,
number one or number two.
I don't remember, so there is an init but we try to stay
away from init so if we can, if they're somewhere else, and
in the view control life cycle there's a lot of
somewhere else's to initialize things besides in init, so
I'm not even gonna talk about the init right here.
Okay, what happens after that initialization though?
Well, the first thing is,
you get prepared if you're being segued to, all right,
the next thing is your outlets are gonna get set, 'kay.
It's just we're gonna wire up all those at sign IV outlets
that you have, and then your view controller's gonna
appear on screen and then it might disappear and
then might reappear and then disappear, okay, and
its geometry might change because of auto rotation or
something else happens and changes the geometry review,
so that's happening.
And then in obscure cases,
you might have a low memory situation on your device and
the system might try to get you involved to resolve that,
and we'll talk about that briefly, all right, so
that's the cycle.
So what are these methods that are involved in that cycle?
Well you know about the preparation that's prepared
for segue and some other MVC that's what prepares you,
and you know about outlet setting, right, just
system automatically sets your outlook from your storyboard.
So the next thing that happens is loading,
as your view gets load, well we call that outlet setting,
the loading process, and when it's done loading it sends you
this message viewDidLoad.
ViewDidLoad is an exceptionally good place to
put stuff to initialize your view, why is it so good?
Because you're prepared by whoever's segueing to you, and
your outlets are all set, 'kay, so you're in
great shape to go do things to initialize your view,
cuz you are all kinda set up and ready to go.
Now, when you override viewDidLoad, it's important to
call super.viewDidLoad and in fact in
all these life cycle methods you always wanna call super.
You can either call it at the beginning or at the end,
kind of up to you, doesn't really matter usually but
you definitely want to let super have a chance to do it,
'kay, so don't forget about that.
Now one thing that you often wanna do in vewDidLoad is
update your UI, okay?
Now you're gonna be updating your UI in the property
observers of all your things that change the model, and
you should continue to do that because your view
control might be on screen all ready loaded,
someone changes the model, you gotta update the UI.
But when you're first having your thing created and
you want to update your UI, it's kind of,
you know, your property observer's in your model, and
aren't really updating the UI because your outlets aren't
set maybe because you're in the prepare for
segue phase right?
So a lot of times, you get to viewDidLoad and
you haven't really been able to update your UI because your
outlets haven't been set, so
viewDidLoad is a great place to then update your UI.
So if you factor out updating UI into a separate method like
we did in the demo called update UI, but
you can call whatever you want, or
you can even have a couple different UI updating methods,
calling those in viewDidLoad is very common, 'kay,
cuz your view is ready to be updated, however, you have to
be careful here because your geometry is not yet set, 'kay?
You only get loaded once,
when you first come out of the storyboard and
you get prepared, your outlets gets set,
you get viewDidLoad, that's it.
That only happens once in the lifetime of a view controller,
but your geometry, like what your bounds are,
that has not been set yet,
that's not gonna be set till later in its lifetime, okay?
So do not do, I should have put this in red, do not put,
do geometry related things in viewDidLoad, 'kay,
you can do almost everything else in viewDidLoad, but
do not do that, 'kay, and we'll talk about where you do
do those things in a moment here, all right.
Next one in the life cycle is viewWillAppear,
'kay, so that's sent to you right before you're going to
appear on screen.
Now, that could be right after viewDidLoad or
it could be a long time after viewDidLoad.
It depends on what's going on in your UI,
okay, and viewWillAppear gets an argument, which is
whether it's an animated appearance or not, 'kay?
Usually you don't care about that.
And when would your appearance be animated?
Well you're in a navigation controller and
someone presses to segue you on screen,
you'll slide in, that's the animation, okay?
So, viewWillAppear,
this could happen all the time, this could happen
repeatedly in the lifetime of your view controller,
cuz your view controller can come on screen or go off.
Let's think of an example, split view,
the master of a split view.
When you first bring up your iPad user interface,
it's in portrait, you don't see the master,
you have to kind of slide it out to see the master,
you only see the detail, right, so it's not visible.
You rotate to landscape, now the master becomes visible, so
you're gonna get viewWillAppear.
You rotate back to portrait, it's off screen.
You rotate back to landscape, it's gonna appear again,
it's gonna send you viewWillAppear again.
So you're gonna get viewWillAppear every time it
appears on screen,
'kay, now what would you do when a viewWillAppear?
A lot of times maybe, if you have to do something very
expensive, like let's say you have to go out to the network
to get something, an image or something like that,
you might not want to do that in viewDidLoad because maybe
the user never turns view to landscape and never looks at
your master, maybe you've got an app where the details all
are that matters and people rarely pull out the master.
Well, you wouldn't wanna do
that expensive thing until the master actually appeared.
Now, you're gonna wanna do that expensive thing in
another thread, we'll talk about it on
Wednesday to keep the main thread active.
And, of course, when that master appeared, if
you're waiting for something on the network there's gonna
be a blank space or something that we'll fill in later,
maybe you put a spinning wheel, things like that, but
viewWillAppear since you know you're actually gonna get on
screen is a place we might kick off something that's
a little bit expensive, also your geometry is set here.
Okay, by the time you get view will appear your bounds,
your view's bounds, you're a view controller right, so
your view's bound, view.bound is set, so
you can do geometry stuff here.
It's legal and you might want to, 'kay, but
I'm gonna show you another place you can do that as well
on the next couple slides.
There's also a viewDidAppear in addition to viewWillAppear,
'kay, so
viewDidAppear gets sent to you after you are now on screen.
You are visible now, 'kay, pretty straightforward, and
similarly there's viewWillDisappear, so
you're just about to be taken off screen.
Again, you're the split view master in landscape,
the person rotates the portrait, you're gonna
get viewWillDisappear cuz you're going to disappear,
it's just going to show only the detail, 'kay?
Here you might clean up some stuff, you might get rid of
some resources that are expensive, like a big image or
something that you can reconstitute fairly quickly,
maybe from disk or something.
That's the kind of thing you'll do in
viewWillDisappear, and of course, there's a did version
of this too, viewDidDisappear, 'kay, so that will disappear,
will appear and will disappear in their dids, okay?
Now let's talk about geometry.
So when your geometry changes, when your bounds change,
the system knows that your bounds changed, and
it knows that you probably have to re-layout your user
interface, okay?
Now 99% of the time, that's gonna happen by magic because
you've set up your auto layout properly, right, so
you don't even have to do anything, but if for
some reason you wanted to do something,
you can override one of these two methods,
viewWillLayoutSubviews and viewDidLayoutSubviews,
so the system calls viewWillLayoutSubviews anytime
it wants to,
make sure that your views are properly laid out.
Now, when it calls, this is not viewsBoundsDidChange,
that's not the name of this method,
okay, it's a viewWillLayoutSubviews, so
your subviews can get laid out for lots of different reasons,
maybe one of your subviews changes in a way that causes
it to change shape and has to be relaid out, et cetera.
So, viewWillLayoutSubviews is sent to
you when someone inside your
view hierarchy or your top level bounds change in a way
where the system needs you to layout your subviews, okay?
Now, you can make this happen by calling, just like you
have set needs display you can say set needs layout.
You say set needs layout, then the next pass around the event
loop, the system will re-layout your subviews, 'kay.
Now this can be called, quite often this viewWill and
DidLayoutSubviews because changes are being made all
the time and the system doesn't
always quite know whether that affected your subview, so
it might ask you to just lay them out again, okay?
So don't be surprised when you get viewWillLayoutSubviews two
or three times when the bounds only changed once, let's say,
'kay, and you have to,
if you're gonna do something in these two methods,
you're gonna have to do the right thing,
even if like your bounds don't actually change.
This whole process of laying out your subviews,
the idea is to make sure that your subviews
are properly laid out.
Now again, most of that's happening with auto layout,
and the auto layout happens between these two methods, so
you get view a layout subviews, you do whatever you
wanna do, then auto layout happens, then you get
viewDidLayoutSubviews, 'kay, so your subviews might have
moved around between the two calls of these, make sense?
Any questions about that?
So, yeah, these things might be called quite a lot and
we'll see that in the demo that they might get called,
and called, and called.
Autorotation, really you wanna think of
autorotation primarily as just your bounds changed, so
autorotation is really a non-event.
As we have seen in all of our apps we have been writing so
far, we don't even think about autorotation,
it just happens our bounds change, auto layout works and
the world is good.
And that's the way you should think of it 99% of the time,
but if for some reason,
you care about the actual case where rotation is happening,
in other words, your device got turned and
so the bounds got to be wider than tall and when they used
to be taller than wide, then you can participate.
By the way, first line there says you can go to
your project settings and
prevent certain autorotation from happening,
and the default by the way is that portrait upside down
is prevented.
That's why you noticed your app,
you go in the simulator and you rotate it to landscape and
then you rotate it again to upside down and
it doesn't autorotate,
that's because in your private setting you said, oh,
portrait upside down is not a supported orientation.
So when you go to portrait upside down,
it just does not autorotate, and you can flip those four
switches for the landscapes and portraits any way you
want, okay, it depends on your UI and what makes sense.
Some UIs make no sense in landscape, some only make
sense in landscape, there might be a game or
something that just doesn't make sense in portrait, 'kay?
So, but if you want to participate in the
autorotation, 'kay, like you want to do some animation of
your own, because you notice that the rotation is animated,
right it goes from portrait to landscape, it kinda moves the
views around, it's hard to see cause it's happening so fast,
but it is animating it, and you can actually participate
that by this method viewWillTransitionToSize,
which is part of the life cycle.
And this transition coordinator you get,
now I'm not gonna talk about how to implement this,
I haven't even talked about animation,
we're not gonna talk about that for a couple of weeks,
but there is a method in that coordinator, for example,
called animate alongside, and you can specify what kinda
animations you want to animate alongside the rotation.
So I'm just telling you this now because it's part of
the view controller life cycle and
you should just know in your head that it exists.
Okay, it's a little bit of a complicated thing to use,
because when you rotate and you change bounds, really it's
container views that are most concerned with that, like
a split view, it needs to now put both things on screen and
put a line and when you switch the other way.
It's really about container views, a little less than
about leaf view controllers, but leaf view controller might
wanna know what's going on, all right, and
then low memory, you get this didReceiveMemoryWarning.
Here you wanna throw away anything in
the heap that's easy to reconstitute.
The way you throw things out of the heap, by the way,
is you just set all pointers that you have to them to nil,
okay, if you're not pointing to something,
then it won't stay in the heap, it gets thrown out.
That does not include weak pointers.
If you have a weak pointer to something,
it still gets thrown out, 'kay?
If the only pointer in the world to an image in the heap
is a weak pointer, it's gonna get pitched, and
that weak pointer's gonna get set to nil,
'kay, as we talked about when we talked about delegation,
'kay, that's the definition of a weak pointer, okay?
So, in low memory situations, you know, try to clean up.
You'll all most never get this,
you may never, ever get this.
If your app is very highly image intensive,
maybe it's an image processing app and
you've got a lot of images in there, then it's possible,
I suppose, but it's extremely unlikely,
'kay, there's a lot of memory in these devices.
Okay, now I'm gonna go back to awakeFromNib, which is not
really part of the view controller life cycle,
but a view controller,
just like any other NS object subclass that comes out of
a storyboard, will get awakeFromNib.
And there are some students, as a class in the past,
that have kind of abused awakeFromNib and they just
start trying to put everything in their initialization into
awakeFromNib instead of putting it into viewDidLoad or
viewWillAppear, or viewWillLayoutSubviews,
depending on what kind of thing it is.
And I'm just warning you here, don't abuse awakeFromNib, but
there are some cases where awakeFromNib is necessary.
For example, if you want to set yourself as the delegate
of the split view controller you're in, awayFromNib is
a good place to do that, because then it happens really
early and you'll start getting those delegate methods from
split view as you go through the rest of your life cycle.
Okay?
So there are some times when awakeFromNib is good.
All right, so here's the summary of the life cycle.
You get instantiated, usually from the storyboard.
You're gonna get awakeFromNib.
Segue prep is gonna happen.
Your outlets are gonna get set by the system.
ViewDidLoad is gonna get called.
View will appear and disappear.
It's gonna happen as your controller goes on and
off screen.
And as your view controller's geometry changes or
the subviews change in a way that needs to be re-laid out,
you're gonna get WillLayoutSubviews,
then autolayout, then DidLayoutSubviews.
So that could happen many times.
And if you get low on memory,
you could have this memory warning, okay?
So that's the View Controller Lifecycle.
There is actually one other one in here.
It'll tell you when your size class changes.
But I haven't talked about size class yet, so
I didn't put that in this list.
But there's one more, and
there will transition to traits or something like that.
All right, so I'm gonna do a quick demo here, super fast.
Let me get something to drink here, okay?
So I'm gonna do a quick demo.
And all I did is I took Psychologist from last time,
and I just put a bunch of printlns in all
these View Controler Lifecycle methods, okay?
So that it would just print out where it is in
Lifecycle all the time.
So, let's go do that.
Let's go run that.
It is here in Developer, Psychologist Lecture 8.
Here we go.
So you can see that in viewWillAppear() I
put a little log for that, disappear, all these.
So I'm just making it basically
logging all the things that are happening, okay.
So lets go, I'm gonna run this on iPad.
It's a little easier to make things happen here.
All right, so here's our Psychologist.
I haven't changed anything about the app.
I'm gonna make the console really big so
that we can see what's going on here.
All right, so notice we came up.
The detail is the only thing,
the detail is Happiness View Controller.
It's the only thing visible.
So what happened here?
The Psychologist got pulled out of the storyboard.
The Happiness got pulled out of the storyboard.
This zero is which instance of it.
Cuz we're gonna have multiple instances, eventually.
Then Happiness got awakeFromNib.
Then Psychologist got awakeFromNib.
The order of awakeFromNib is completely not determinable,
so you should not depend on it.
Then the master got viewDidLoad.
Even though the master never appears on screen,
it still had its outlet set, and
got viewDidLoad sent to it.
Then interestingly, the master was asked to lay itself out,
to lay its Subviews out.
Okay again, it hasn't appeared.
It hasn't even gotten viewWillAppear,
because it's not gonna appear.
But its Subviews wanna get laid out.
And why is this happen?
Well, you know, the system might be
preparing to animate it onscreen or something.
You just want to make sure.
This is not doing any drawing.
This is just making sure
the Subviews are properly laid out.
It happens twice here, maybe a before and after animation.
Who knows what's going on here,
it doesn't really matter.
The size didn't actually change.
Okay, the bound size didn't actually change, so
this second one probably did almost nothing here.
Then the detail, Happiness, it gets a videwDidLoad and then
it gets a viewWillAppear, cuz it's gonna appear onscreen.
The animated is false because it doesn't animate on screen.
It was the initial thing that shows up in screen, so
boom, it just pops up there.
It gets laid out and then it gets viewDidAppear.
And here it is, okay?
Everyone understand that?
Now I'm going to rotate to landscape, and
that's gonna cause the master to appear.
So watch this.
So we do rotate,
all these dash, that's what happened since I rotated here.
And you can see Psychologist and Happiness both got
informed that this transition to size is going to happen.
So they could have
participated in the animation if they want, and you're gonna
see the animation happen in a little bit down the road here.
The master got another chance to lay its Subviews out in
a little different size.
Because this size, it's only 768 high instead of
the full 1024, and it's a little wider too.
So it got laid out, then it got viewWillAppear.
So this guy was told it would appear, okay?
And this guy didn't get any viewWillAppear because it's
already there.
So it's not appearing, it was already there before.
So it gets viewWillAppear.
Now the detail gets chance to lay its Subviews out here at
a new size.
Because it used to be the whole screen,
now it's just this part right here, so it got a new layout.
And then the master was asked to layout its Subviews again.
So you see how I'm saying this gets called a lot.
So you just need to
make sure that if you're doing anything in these two methods,
that it's okay to be doing it over and over.
Here's where the actually animation happens.
And you can see that both the Psychologist and the Happiness
have been invited to animate alongside if they wanted to.
Then the master is asked to layout one more time,
same size.
That's the third time its been asked to do that.
And then the master gets viewDataAppear, okay?
Now the last thing I'm gonna do is click one of these,
which is gonna cause a segue which is gonna cause this to
be replaced.
So let's do that.
So we'll try the dancing tree here.
Okay?
So what happened here?
A new Happiness.
Happiness 1 got instantiated here, okay?
We have Happiness 0 up here and Happiness 1.
It got prepared with Happiness of a hundred.
Okay?
Then layout Subviews of the master again.
Then the Happiness 0 got viewWillDisappear.
Happiness 0, that old Happiness of
course getting pulled out and
replaced by the new one, so it got viewWillDisappear.
Then the master got laid out again, and
then viewDidLoad happened on Happiness 1,
the new happiness that's appearing.
Then it got viewWillAppear cuz it's going to appear.
Then it got a chance to be laid out.
The old Happiness disappeared.
The new Happiness appeared and then the old
Happiness got deinitialized, thrown out of the heap.
Because like I said, once you segue away from it,
boom, it's gone.
Okay? So that's all I
wanted to cover there.
Everybody cool with that?
Any questions about that View Controller Lifecycle?
It's pretty straightforward, but you can already probably
imagine in your head some things that you were
doing in your code that's like oh, I wish I had viewDidLoad.
That really could have
initialized some stuff there a little simpler.
All right, so let's go back to our slides.
All right, so you've seen a lot of Autolayout already in
this class, so
I'm gonna review briefly the things you should know.
One is you know about using the dashed lines.
Using the blue dashed lines is helping the interface builder.
By the way, when I refer to interface builder,
that means Xcode, the storyboard part of Xcode.
We call that interface builder for historical reasons.
So, when you're in the storyboard of Xcode,
the dashed lines are kind of telling Xcode what you want,
what you intend.
As best that you can, okay?
Then you know about Ctrl-dragging between views to
create relationships, right?
Like spacing, and hook this to the left edge, and
stuff like that.
You know about those in the lower right corner,
the "Pin" and "Arranged" popovers down there that let
you do things like set all the things to equal widths, or
create spacing between all of them, or
line up their left edges, okay?
You know about using Reset to Suggested Constraints.
If you use the blue lines,
sometimes you'll do Reset to Suggested Constraints, and
it will actually figure out what you want.
I'd say only 50 percent of the time,
but it's worth a try sometimes.
The Document Outline,
you know that on the left in the document outline,
all your constraints are listed there.
Okay. And also that's where,
if you've got problems, you can click on the little red or
yellow button in the upper right-hand corner of
the Document Outline and it'll tell you.
It might even suggest some ways to fix things, possibly.
And certainly will tell you if anything's misplaced.
And you know from there, you can also fix your misplaced
views by clicking on the little triangles in there.
You know about the size inspector.
If you inspect a view in your storyboard and
you look at the size inspector,
you'll see all the constraints listed there.
In there, all the constraints are shown with their details.
Okay?
What the constants are, all that stuff, is listed there.
And of course you can edit the constraints there.
You can also, you know that you can click on a constraint.
And bring up the attributes inspector.
And now you can inspect the constraint directly, okay?
It will be the thing that's selected so the attributes
inspector will let you set its attributes, okay?
So you know a lot here about autolayout.
And that is basically what autolayout is.
It's those things.
Okay, now again, as I've said many times,
mastering autolayout requires experience.
You gotta know how to use all these tools,
to greatest effect, okay.
You gotta familiarize yourself with what things can I
align to things, what things can I pin to here and there,
what things can I set as my constants that make sense.
You gotta learn all that by doing, okay.
I could spend many days going through every possible one.
Autolayout can be done in code.
There are objects, classes,
in iOS that represent what's going on in autolayout.
And in the demo I'm gonna actually show you an example
of doing that so you can get an idea of what it looks like.
But we rarely do that.
If we can do it in the storyboard, we do it there.
We only revert to doing it in code when it's like,
we just can't express that somehow in the storyboard,
which is extremely rare.
But I'll show you a case where that's true, but all right.
So what about rotation?
As I said, when you have rotation,
you're just going to rely on your autolayout to do that.
But occasionally when you rotate, things have changed so
drastically in terms of the shape that autolayout just
can't do it.
It can't move a view where you want.
So what's an example of that?
Lets consider our calculator.
Okay lets say we had 20 buttons in our calculator.
Okay.
Now in landscape,
I might want them to be five buttons across and four down.
But when I switch to portrait,
now I might want four across and five down.
Okay, there's no
way you're gonna write autolayout to do that.
Autolayout cannot make such a huge change like doing that.
Okay, so how do we deal with that?
We still wanna do that, so how do we do it?
It's not just in the case of rotation where this is
happening to.
It also happens, for example, in a split view.
When you have the master in the spilt view on the left,
it kind of is tall and thin, just like it was on an iPhone.
Even though it was on an iPad, it's kind of in a shape,
a space that's shaped more like an iPhone, right?
Lots of vertical space, but not much horizontal space.
So it's not just rotation where we
care about this size business, the relative size of things.
So the solution to this is called size classes, and so
your view controller always exists in
a size class environment.
For width and height.
And currently the size class can either be compact
or regular.
Regular just means it's not compact.
Okay, and so lets try and
understand what when you're in these different situations.
So for example the iPhone 6+ is an interesting device.
In portrait it's width is compact.
It's height is regular.
Okay so that's if you
had like a full screen view controller on an iPhone 6+.
When you go to landscape on the 6+ now it's compact in
height and regular in width.
That make sense?
All right, it makes perfect sense in that one.
But the iPhone is kind of an interesting one,
other iPhones besides the iPhone 6+,
in portrait it is compact in width and regular in height,
just like an iPhone 6+, but in landscaped,
it is considered compact in width and compact in height.
And that might seem non-intuitive,.
But it just turns out that a non iPhone 6+, the width of
it is just not quite enough to say this is a regular width.
Most UIs just will look better if you
consider it compact, okay?
Now the iPad is always regular in both directions.
Portrait or landscape, it's always so
big that it's just regular in both directions.
There's no compact on the iPad.
But again a particular view controller on
an iPad like the master of
a split view side by side that's going to be compact.
Regular height, compact width.
All right, this whole thing is extensible it's not kinda all
frozen in stone.
You if you have a view controller you can find out
your size class by using this property called trait
collection.
And inside traitCollection,
it's gonna return the horizontal size class and
the vertical size class,
and that's just an enum that's either .Compact or
.Regular, okay?
Now, you probably almost never need to do this because you're
gonna edit this in your storyboard, 'kay?
You're going to set up your storyboard to deal with
size classes.
And then your code, it's just all gonna work.
Okay as long as you got your
rest of your auto layout going.
So how does that work?
All right so here's the size classes right horizontal and
vertical, compact and regular.
See these four boxes right,
that's every possible combination.
Okay and so for my calculator for example here's what
my UI might look like in those situations.
Okay you see here that I've gone five across and four
down when I have a compact height and regular width.
But I basically anytime I have a regular width I'm gonna
go what did I do, every time I actually every time I have.
A regular height, I go five high.
Okay so lower right is regular height, it's five high.
Lower left is regular height is five high.
The top two are compact height,
I've gone to four high five wide.
Okay.
So it'd be kinda a pain though if I had to do all four of
these for every user interface I built.
So we actually have another size class called any.
And if you throw any into the mix,
now I can do this exactly the way I just said which is.
Any, first of all I'm gonna have an any any,
which is the middle, and that's gonna be my base UI.
So, if I don't specify any particular size class, it's
gonna look like that, which is four across and five down.
But in the case where it's vertically compact.
I'm going to go to five across and only four high.
And I don't care what the width is so
that's why it's any.
So now I only have to do two user interfaces.
My main user interface, the any any and one other one
which is I'm in a compact vertical situation so
I want to go four high.
Okay so this makes it a little easier now I only have to do
things and
still covers all the same bases as the previous slide.
And incredibly, Interface Builder will have a graph that
looks almost exactly like this slide that lets you pick
between these various boxes, and you can design your
user interface in any of these boxes.
Okay? And it will
just magically work.
So let's take a look at a demo here.
I actually have a couple of demos.
The one is called ShowSizeClass,
it's just an app that I wrote that shows the size
class of whatever device you're on at the time.
Okay?
And we're gonna take a look at the code for that.
And then I'm gonna do an app from scratch.
Which is called Autolayout.
That's the name of my app.
Add it's just gonna have some
very interesting autolayout things including
the size class problem that we're gonna have to solve.
Okay so it's kind of kitchen sink of that.
All right let's go and
look at this app I wrote called ShowSizeClass.
So here's ShowSizeClass, and
I'm just going to run this on some various devices.
Let's run this on an iPhone 6 Plus for example.
Here's an iPhone 6 Plus.
How do I make this small?
I guess I can't.
This is as small as I can make it.
You see how iPhone 6 Plus in portrait here
is horizontally compact.
And it's regular vertically.
That's what the green means.
Okay?
If I rotate it, it's regular horizontally and
compact vertically.
Everybody cool with that?
All right. Now,
let's look on the iPhone 6.
All right, iPhone 6 again,
regular vertically, compact width.
But if we rotate, it's compact in both directions.
Okay, let's go to like iPhone 4s or something like that.
Okay, so here's 4S.
It's also, even though it's kind of short,
it's still considered regular vertically.
And compact this way,
and compact in both directions just like an iPhone 6.
Okay?
And lastly, let's take a quick look at iPad2, or any iPad.
I do iPad too because it fits on this screen.
All the rest of them are too high of resolution again.
All right, look, see.
It's regular this way and regular both ways,
this way, okay.
So let's look at the app that I wrote to do that.
I keep going back here to iPhone 6.
Okay, let's look at the app that I wrote.
Here it is, ShowSizeClass.
It has a storyboard here.
Here's its storyboard.
Let's see if we can find anything in the storyboard.
There it is, okay.
Hm, nteresting.
This storyboard, there's no arrows.
There's the dot in the middle, but
where the heck did those arrows?
Oh, I must draw them in my code.
Let's look at the View control.
Oh, my View control had no code.
This app has no code.
How is it possible that it drew those arrows, okay?
Well, the answer is that those arrows are only drawn for
the SizeClass in question.
So for
example if I have something that is horizontally compact I
draw those two red arrows and where is that, well
look down at the bottom of the screen here it says any any.
So this is the user interface if you're in any any
the default user interface okay.
If I click on this right here I can pick any of
those nine boxes that I showed on that slide.
So for example look at this box right here.
This is any width but a compact height.
Now when I click here its actually gonna change my user
interface and show me what the user interface looks like on
a device that is any width but a compact height.
See, these are just two labels I threw out here that do
that and same thing let's say over here, any height,
compact width.
Or, over here we have regular width, any height.
And over here we have any width,
regular height, yeah, there we go.
So that's it.
That's my entire user interface.
I just put the arrows in whichever SizeClass was
appropriate there.
This is really cool to be able to go here and basically edit
your user interface in any of these circumstances.
Including specific ones,
like this Compact Width Compact Height.
That's basically, you're editing your user
interface for non-iPhone 6 Pluses in Landscape.
Because that's the only one that is both Compact Width and
Compact Height.
Okay?
So you could actually have a specific one just for
that circumstance.
Okay? But it's nicer to
have these Anys, to use these Anys out here so
that they'll work, and we'll see in the demo.
And one of the things I challenged,
I didn't really talk about it in the slides there,
but I challenged you to do is, I actually added this as an
extra credit to the homework number three, if you want.
Go back and
make your calculator user interface look different.
In different SizeClasses.
Maybe do five buttons by four instead of four by five,
okay, or something like that.
Or even, some ones have more buttons.
If you look at the calculator that Apple ships on
the iPhone, when you go to Landscape,
it has a lot more operations.
The buttons are all smaller, but
it has a lot of operations that aren't even there.
And you can do that with side classes as well.
Okay, alright so
now we're gonna write an app here from scratch.
And it is going to look like this.
Okay here's what it's UIs gonna look like.
It's very, very, this is a demo, okay,
so it's a very simple app.
It asks for a username and password up here, so
I have madbum, and password is foo.
Now, I can change the security on my password.
I can have it be secured so I can't see it, okay.
But when I log in, it's gonna show me.
An icon for the person,
the persons name, and what company they work for, okay.
Madison Bumgarner in this case.
And if I rotate it's gonna say the same information but
notice that this is not below here,
it's actually moved to be beside it.
Okay?
So, basically, on Sizeclasses that are regular height, or
have a lot of room, I put the words at the bottom.
I try to use this space to show their picture more.
And in other SizeClasses, I put it off to the side, okay?
And we have other users here, like, Same password.
Okay it's all got all the different icon or old j apple.
Okay John Appleseed.
Okay? In all of these cases
it's going to do that.
Okay so lot going on here to make this work with
auto layout.
Right you got
this thing automatically changing right here.
You've got this you've got this image here which you
want to be the right aspect ration.
You know we got he SizeClass things so
we can put the words underneath when it's tall etc.
Okay.
So that's what we're going to build.
Alright, let's go and we're going to start from
scratch as I like to do usually, so
it's creating a new XCode project, iOS application.
I'm going to call it auto layout, okay.
I'm going to put it the same place I put all of my
apps there.
Here it is.
I'm gonna move this app delegate out of the way.
And the launch screen out of the way.
For the first time we're actually gonna
talk about these image assets here today.
It's a good opportunity to talk about that.
Okay. And in my controller,
I'm gonna clear out this code.
Don't need any of that.
By the way, the things that I cleared out here,
you starting to recognize them?
View controller life cycle methods.
Okay.
But if I need those, I'll put them back but okay.
So, let's go to our storyboard and start building this UI.
Now this is gonna be a lot of clicking things around.
I'm gonna make this as big as possible for us here.
That's all right, that there.
Lot of graphical things happening.
Let's just do that.
Okay, so I'm gonna start with those text fields at
the top, right?
I need a username and password text field.
So I'm gonna go down here and grab a text field.
Okay, this is actually gonna be an editable one, so
I grab this one, text, not label, but text.
And I'm going to put it up in the upper corner to start.
Grab another one, put this here.
Okay, now, I'm gonna use some model layout stuff you
already know about.
I'm gonna use Ctrll drag.
Let's stick this one trailing space to that edge.
Let's stick this one with this trailing space to that end.
Let's get this one to the top.
Let's put a space in
between the vertical space between them.
You know about.
Doing all those kind of things.
Now one thing as I'm working with auto layout I
often like to click this little button right here.
Because this will
give you a little summary of what's going on.
And when all it's complaining about is that frames are gonna
be moved, a cool thing you can do is go down here
to this button.
The same one where we do Reset to Suggested Constraints and
Clear Constraints, there's this Update Frame.
And it will update all frames in your storyboard.
Now, it made those smaller because the text in
them is small, but don't worry about that.
We're gonna fix that later.
So I did Undo right there because I wanted them to be
a little bigger just as I work.
Okay? But I'll be going back to
look at this often.
And if I see it's just frames,
then I'll be doing Update Frames.
And if I don't like what it did I
can always undo, keep going.
All right?
So let's go and do our things here for
the user name and password fields.
So I'm just going to put some text in these.
Password.
User name, so
these ones I kind of want to be on the left.
Okay, if you remember.
So I'm gonna do the same thing here with control drag.
Let's set that leaning space.
Let's set this thing to the,
actually I'm not even gonna set this to the top.
Now this is an interesting one.
So I have these two guys right here.
Really what I want them to do is be lined up with whatever
the text is in here.
I wanna line them up by their baselines.
So I'm gonna control drag between the two of them and
go down here and pick Baseline.
So this is going to line up their baselines.
Okay?
Same thing here, drag this one.
And line up their baselines there.
Now, another thing I want is that I want them to be kind
of, well, I want these two guys, username and
password, to be the same width.
So, I'm control dragging between them and
saying Equal Widths.
You remember in the calculator we
did the equal widths down here with this thing, okay?
But, you can do it with control drag as well.
And then also I want these things attached.
So I want that thing attached to each other so
that its horizontal spacing is set.
And I want this thing attached to this,
its horizontal spacing.
Now I've done all this stuff even though
they're really not where I want them right now.
So usually you can kinda set things up and
then just go into the size inspector.
And inspect all of them and
get rid of every magic number you see.
If you get rid of every magic number you see usually it's
gonna do exactly what you want.
So lets go here, lets start with this one.
Lets find some magic numbers.
Look at this Leading Space Username.
[SOUND] Magic number.
Okay magic number means number in here,
anything that's a number get rid of it.
So 392 I'm gonna get rid of that,
I'm gonna do it by going up here.
Instead of having 392,
I'm going to pick Standard Value, okay?
So now it's gone.
So you can click on these things and
click Edit to get rid of these.
Even 8, which had got by the blue lines, okay?
I don't like that either.
I'm just going to go here and say zero, because
I want that to be right up against the edge, okay?
Oops. Sorry.
Same thing, oh, did I do the right thing there?
Leading space, username, yeah, trailing spaces, you're right.
How about this one?
Top Space to Top Layout right here,
I'll use the Standard Value for that.
Okay?
Oops, sorry, keep clicking there.
And then here, Align Baseline equals three.
Okay I want these baselines exactly aligned not three off
of each other so I'm gonna say zero right here.
So I've gotten rid of all the magic numbers in here.
Okay now lets do it for
this one, okay this one also has a magic number here,
lets change that to be Standard Value.
We got this one, Align Baseline.
We want that to be zero.
Okay? So we got rid of that.
How about this one?
Oh, this one's good.
No magic value.
And this one, also good.
Okay? All is good.
All is well with the world.
Okay?
But we still have this up here.
Frame will be different at run time, so
I'm going to go down here.
And update our frames and this looks good.
Now, when I look at this I'm like that's really not what I
want, so I must have made a mistake.
For example, I want this spacing in-between not to
be zero, so
I typed zero somewhere where I wanted a standard value.
So, let's go back here and see where that is.
Okay? It looks like it's this one
you can tell when you mouse over these, it tells you.
So here let's go back to here and
instead of zero, let's say Standard Value, okay?
And it moved it there for us.
Sometimes it moves it,
sometimes you need to do update frames.
It just kind of depends on
the character of the change you're making.
Okay?
Now, here's a really cool thing.
I want to see what
this looks like in portrait and landscape.
So yeah, I could go up here and hit Run,
but there is a lot faster way, which is to open up
the assistant editor here and instead of showing your view
controller, go up here and go down to Preview.
This will preview your UI.
Okay? And you can preview it in
either landscape or portrait.
You can also preview it on other devices like
maybe an iPhone 6 Plus, okay, which is kind of so
big that we can't barely even see it here.
Barely flip it around, okay?
Or you can even look at it on an iPad if you wanted.
Okay I think four inches works best for
this small resolution I have.
But this is really cool, now this can only preview your UI
for things that aren't running your code.
Okay so if you're gonna do something that you need to
run your code then you need to go run it in the app.
But if you just want to
see how is the auto layout gonna work.
You can do this.
Now another thing that's cool here is what's this gonna look
like when you give it off to your localization guys and
if this gets translated to German or something like that.
You can do that, you can kinda make sure that you
don't have any big problems by going down here,
see where it says English.
Sort of click on that.
And we can go to this double length pseudo language.
And all that does is doubles every text.
Okay? So even a long translation of
the word Username would fit there.
And my auto layout is working properly.
And so my translation is just going to work.
So Auto Layout is not just used for
landscape versus portrait or whatever.
It can be used for translation as well.
When you're localizing things,
you want auto-layout to make things fit.
Okay? Everyone understand that?
Okay.
All right, good.
So we're making progress here.
By the way, you probably don't wanna have preview open as
you're doing a lot of changes here,
cuz it's gonna be constantly previewing in real time.
So if you've got a really powerful machine,
it could keep up, but
you might be asking it to do a lot of calculations.
So I usually close that while I'm working, and
then just bring it back whenever I wanna preview.
So let's do those two buttons.
Remember, I had the button change security,
which changed this to secure, and
then I had the button login, so let's go ahead and do that.
Another trick I'm going to show you is, and
I'm always scrolling around in here trying to find things.
You can actually find things real quick by going down to
the bottom here and typing like button.
Now it's only going to show you the buttons.
Okay? We got Bar Button and
here's regular button, so I'm going to drag that out.
Let's get a couple of those buttons.
We'll call this one Change security.
We'll call this one log in.
Okay now where do these want to be?
They kind of
want to be underneath there something like that.
Definitely I like their baselines lined
up right there.
So let's go ahead and kind of put those in position.
I'm gonna set the vertical spacing between the login and
this guy right here and
then I'm control dragging here to set the baselines the same.
Okay?
Now, that has actually set the vertical position of both of
these things, okay.
Because the vertical position of these are set and so
when I tie this vertical position here and
the baseline which is a vertical positioning here but
if I go up here it says that the horizontal position of
Login and Change Security is ambiguous.
Which makes sense.
I haven't really specified where these
things are supposed to be.
Just because I put them on
the screen doesn't mean that there's an auto layout rule.
Now, what do I want it to be?
Well, I kind of want them to be some reasonable distance
apart so it doesn't look like, you know,
this is part of the same thing.
That would look like change security log in is one thing.
So I want them apart a little bit.
But otherwise I want them centered on the screen.
I want the pair of them centered.
Now, there's no auto layout rule that says that.
That's too complicated, okay?
But, I can easily do this with a little creativity, and
when you start doing auto layout,
you start realizing, hm, how can I do that?
Well, I need to be creative in how I'm gonna approach this.
[NOISE] And in this case what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna create two little spacer views on the side here.
And I'm gonna set them to be the same width.
Can you see how that's gonna make it so
these two kinda get pushed into the middle?
Right, by the same amount on each side.
So how would I do that?
So I'm gonna do that by just grabbing some views,
just generic views,
okay, this just a generic view like the one you do to
do your graph view or the face view or whatever.
When I'm working on it here, I'm going to give it
some background color so I can see the thing, okay,
now when I'm actually ready to go I will turn that back off.
And I'm just going to put them in here somewhere, copy and
paste another one, put it over here somewhere, and
then I'm just gonna wire these up to how I want them,
so I want this to kind of be on that edge,
I want this thing to be on that edge,
I want these two things to kind of be linked.
Okay.
Let's say I'll link their horizontal spacing.
Now here, I'm going to
set multiple things between these two.
I'm gonna set the horizontal spacing and
then notice I'm holding down shift.
I'm also gonna set the top and
bottom of this view to match the top and bottom.
Now, there's no base lines because this is not text.
This is just a generic view.
So I'm gonna move mine up the top and bottom.
So I can do Shift+click to do that.
Okay. And then same thing over here,
I'm gonna do the same thing with these two guys.
I'm gonna set the top whoops, sorry, control drag.
I'm gonna set the top and bottom horizontal spacing.
Okay.
Then I said I wanted to make this one and
this one be equal widths.
So I can just do that with control drag as well, so
I've set that up.
I want this to be stuck to this edge, trailing space,
I want this to be stuck to this edge, leading space, and
I want these two guys to have some horizontal spacing,
I'm not quite sure how much I want yet, but
I want some sort of horizontal spacing.
Now, I've done this, and look, the yellow thing went away.
It says, okay, I know exactly where to put these things.
Xcode
But this is really not where I want these put, okay?
Because I actually want this spacer right up against this,
and I want this spacer right up against this.
So I'm gonna go through that same process again of
getting rid of the magic number.
So let's start with this guy.
And get rid of his magic numbers in the size inspector,
so it's got this trailing space here,
let's get rid of that.
We want that to be a standard value.
Okay we got this one, we align the bottoms we want those to
be exactly aligned, so we'll do zero.
0.
Same thing with top we want that exactly aligned, so
I got rid of all of the magic numbers for this.
How about this guy?
Same thing.
Okay? We want this to be standard value.
Usually I always put it to standard value
unless standard value is not an option.
Then I usually pick zero.
0.
Okay? If standard value is
not an option I'll just make it zero.
0.
Then here, a line top.
Let's see. Standard value, nope.
Let's make it zero.
Okay?
So, no magic numbers there.
How about this guy?
Does he have magic numbers?
Yeah, he has this 87.
87.
That's this difference between these two.
That's okay.
This has a magic number here.
This.
Hello.
Standard value.
Okay. So now,
the only magic number we have is this 87,
which is this distance here.
Now, what's really cool about this is you can
double click on this.
And inspect it right in space.
So here I'm gonna make it be let's say 50.
50.
So this is a magic number right here, because there's
really no standard spacing cuz I'm kinda doing somewhat of
a non standard thing here.
Any time you do a non standard thing,
really ask yourself do I really want to be doing this?
Okay cuz I'm kinda going against the grain by doing
something against, you know, what standard values are.
In this case I'm gonna go ahead and do it, but I should
probably be asking myself if I really wanna do that.
And it might be a little confusing to users.
So let's go ahead and
look at this thing in the preview again.
So here it is, looks good, see,
it made those two things the same width,
put these things in the center.
Same thing here, put those in the center, excellent.
Okay?
So, that's good.
Now, I've got it where I want it.
So I can go back and
turn these things back to being non gray, okay?
Go back to the default.
Okay?
See how I built that UI?
UI
So those spacers, don't forget you can put spacers in.
They're perfectly legal to throw in there.
Question?
>> So what's the canvas option?
[INAUDIBLE] you choose the canvas value?
>> Okay. Yeah. When you have something selected.
Okay?
And you go over here and it says Edit, and
you can change to the Canvas Value,
that says whatever is actually here right now.
In other words, to what I moved it to, basically.
And when you first Ctrl+drag,
Ctrl
that's the value it's gonna have, okay?
Good question there.
Okay.
Now let's start writing some code, okay?
Cuz I want this change security button to
change security
change this to say secured password.
secured password
And I want this to
actually be a secured password in that case, 'kay?
So what is that code gonna look like?
Let's go here to automatic.
Here's our view controller here.
I'm gonna need some outlets to connect to these things.
outlet
So I'm gonna Ctrl+drag some stuff here.
ctrl
Let's control + drag that.
That is our login field.
Let's control + drag this.
That is our password field.
And let's control + drag over to this.
That is our password label, okay.
So we got that.
Now.
Lets say I'm going to do my viewDidLoad() here, okay, and
viewDidLoad()
when my view is loaded I'm going to update my UI,
UI
well first of all,
of course, I'm going to do super.viewDidLoad().
super.viewDidLoad()
Then I'm gonna update my UI.
UI
Gonna make this wider so
this is not jumping out on you so much.
I'm not gonna have a private func here to update my UI.
UI
And all I'm gonna do in my UI so
far is, I'm gonna have that password field.
I'm gonna set its secure text entry to true.
Or actually, I'm gonna set it to secure.
secure
And I'm gonna have a var for that.
So let's have a var here called secure.
secure
It's gonna be boolean.
Actually don't even need to say that.
Let's say it's false.
false
It starts out false and I'm gonna do a did set here and
falsedidSet
update my UI every time it changes.
UI
And I'm gonna allow this to be public so
people can set this boolean secure.
And what's the problem here?
Oh computer property must have that there's something
wrong there.
Well but that okay.
So, I'm going to let people set this secure thing externally, and
then that's going to change this to say secure password,
secure password
and it's going to start securing it here.
So, we're going to do secure text entry.
This is just a property in UI text field that you can set,
UITextField
that just makes it so
that when you type, you get the little dots instead of
seeing what the person is typing.
And then I'm also going to,
in the password label, I'm going to set its text.
If it's secure, I'm going to set it to be secured password.
secured password
And if it's not secure,
I'm going to set it to just be password.
password
Okay. So
that's this label right here.
I'm going to change that label depending on whether
it's secure or not.
Does that make sense?
All right. So let's go ahead and
run because now we need to run,
because we're going to be executing our code here.
Let's hope that when we click that button,
our autolayout makes it so
that everything kind of shifts over and
it doesn't because we need to have a target action.
target action
Let's do target action here, we want an action method.
We'll call this toggleSecurity.
toggleSecurity
Don't need an argument there,
connect, here's toggleSecurity.
connecttoggleSecurity
And this is secure equals not secure.
secure  !secure
Okay, we're just gonna toggle the security on that
when this button is pressed.
[SOUND].
Okay. So, change security.
Looks good. And see how it
moved these things?
We had equal widths set on these, so
when I changed security it makes these
be equal widths which moves everything else out of
the way as necessary and it works either way.
Okay? Everybody cool with that?
Alright, so next let's do login right here.
Okay, so the login is real easy.
I'm just going to go over here and Ctrl+drag for
ctrl target action
target action.
We'll call this login.
login
It's an action.
Oops, sorry got that wrong.
Let's us go over here.
Ctrl+drag, an action, called login.
login
We don't need the sender.
sender
Connect.
Now how am I going to do login?
Well, I actually have a simple user class which I
user
am going to drag into here.
Here it is right here.
User.swift, okay.
User.swift
So I'm going drag that into, oops.
Lets go here.
Easiest way to do this.
All right, so I'm just gonna drag User.swift in here.
User.swift
I'm gonna copy it.
There we go.
Okay, what does the User.swift look like?
User.swift
Looks like this.
It's a model class it doesn't has nothing to do with UI.
modelUI
It's just model class.
model
And it just has name, company, login and password.
And it has a function,
just a class function here that you can use to log-in.
And it has a little database of users like
Madison Bumgarner.
Madison Bumgarner
Okay. So that's all that's in there.
Let's go use that now, in our controller.
So when I log in,
I'm just going to set my set a loggedInUser so I need some
loggedInUser
var which is a logged in user, that's basically my model.
loggedInUsermodel
LoggedInUser, it's going to be a user.
loggedInUseruser
And I'm going to do the didSet.
didSet
Actually it's going to be user optional.
And I'm going to do my didSet here, and also updateUI.
didSet updateUI
So if anyone changes my logged in user externally,
loggedInUser
I'll let this be public, then I can update my UI.
UI
And finally, say loggedInUser equals User.login.
loggedInUser  User.login
And now I need to give it the login,
login
that's this field right here.
So I'm going to say loginField.text.
loginField.text
But this could be an optional.
Okay?
And the user takes a string.
So, I'm gonna say, okay, well, if it's nil, if
the log-in fill is nil, then just pass blank empty string.
Okay?
That's obviously not gonna log into anything,
but that's okay.
And then, same thing here; passwordField.text.
passwordField.text
And we'll have empty string there as well, kay?
So, that's how we're gonna log in, and
we'll have a loggedInUser.
loggedInUser
Once we have our updateUI here that's,
updateUI
actually we'll do that a little later.
Okay.
So, that's it, okay?
So, now we got logged in, we got this whole part of our
user interface working right here.
Now about the bottom part.
The bottom we had an image and
we had the name of the person and
the company they worked for.
So let's do the image first.
I'm just going to go over here and grab an image.
image
I'm going to go up here.
I'm going to type image, and this is a class,
image UILabel
kind of like a UI label for images, called image view.
image view
I'm going to put this in the corner down here.
And we Ctrl+dragged, leading space,
ctrl
Ctrl+drag, bottom space.
Now, you'd think, oh, I just set this here, it's ready to
go, but when I click this little thing it says, oh,
the size and vertical position are ambiguous for imageView.
imageView
And that's because we don't have an image in here so
it doesn't know what size it is.
Okay, so let's put an image in here and
I got some images we can use right here.
Okay, so I'm going to bring this image Stanford into my project.
This is the first time we have done this and
this is what this image.xcassests is for.
image.xcassestsapp
This manages all your images in your app.
Here's my app icon, I have not set it to anything so
app
those are all blank.
I'm going to to drag this Stanford image in here and
it creates it.
Now, notice this says 1x, so that means on
1x
low resolution devices this is the image it's gonna use.
And I could actually have
a different image on a higher resolution device.
Like maybe on a high resolution device I could do
this one with the Stanford tree.
I have more resolution, so
I can draw this little tree a little better.
Okay, and on a really high res device like maybe iPhone 6
iPhone 6 plus
plus I could put even higher resolution image in there.
So you can manage that.
You can also manage other things about the images.
I'm not really gonna go into this, but
you can manage them by size class.
size classes
Okay, this image appears on compact or
compact
regular or whatever.
regular
It also has vector graphics in addition to bitmaps.
It's a really powerful system for
app
managing all of your image assets here.
Now around here I'm gonna go ahead and
drag some of these other images I have in here as well.
Cuz we'll need those later.
Okay, here's all my images I have down here.
Okay, so I have an image.
So how do I set the image of this little thing in
my storyboard?
storyboard
Well, I just inspect this image view and go here.
imageview
And all the images I just loaded are gonna be here.
So I'm gonna pick Stanford, okay?
So, now that I've given an image, look No problems.
It just says the frame is wrong.
frame
So no problem, let's fix the frame.
Oops.
There. Update frames.
update frames
Oh, ew, that's no good.
Okay.
So we have a big image there, smashes on top of the other
thing, so how are we gonna fix that?
Well, a simple way to do that would be just to
Ctrl+drag between these two and set the vertical spacing.
Okay? And then I
can even double click this and
make this vertical spacing be a standard value.
Okay? Now, let's go ahead and
update frames.
And it doesn't smash into the ones on top.
Okay?
Simple solution there.
But we still have this right here.
Eight views are vertically ambiguous.
Oh my gosh!
What did I do?
It looks perfect to me.
Why is it saying that?
Well, when you get this kinda thing, it's time to go back to
our old friend, the document outline here, okay.
Let's make some more space.
In the document outline,
we can click on this thing in the corner here.
And look at all these problems we have.
Okay, you can see that it's all these vertical things
here, understandably, and look what it keeps suggesting.
Oh, set the vertical
compression resistance priority.
Set the vertical hugging.
What the heck is compression resistance priority and
vertical hugging?
What the heck is that?
Okay?
That has to do with this user interface is going to
be expanding and compressing vertically.
And when it does, who gets the extra space?
And when it compresses down, who allows themselves to
be compressed, and who can't compress?
Okay?
That's what this hugging and
compression resistance is about.
So, here we've got, these guys are all lined up.
This, okay, these two guys, and
this button, they can not be compressed.
If they get compressed,
their text is gonna get squished down.
So, we do not want them compressed.
But this guy, he could be compressed.
Because it's an image,
it can just redraw itself at a shorter height.
So, I need to set the resistance to being compressed
for this guy to be lower.
You've got to lower resistance to being compressed.
So how do I do that?
You do that in the Size Inspector.
If you select something, you'll see down here at
the bottom, Content Hugging Priority and
Content Compression Resistance Priority.
Okay? Now, these are priorities.
These are just arbitrary numbers.
Right now, this one is 750 in the vertical.
This one is also 750.
This one is 750.
They all have the same priority to be compressed.
That's why it's complaining, okay?
Cuz it doesn't know which one to compress,
cuz they're all the same.
So we can just go back to this one and say, okay well,
we're gonna lower this guy's compression resistance to 700.
Oh, all my problems went away.
Okay? Now I
have no yellow thing up here.
This resolved everything.
I had eight things that were ambiguous.
Now they're all fine.
Why? Because, when we compress now,
we're gonna know that this is the guy who gets compressed,
and these guys don't.
Okay? So that's what the compression
thing, and we'll see hugging in in a second, and com, and
more compression a little later, okay?
So that's what these are about.
A lot of people are, like,
well, I don't understand these.
But it's quite simple.
It's just how much is this view,
compared to other views, resisting being compressed?
And hugging priority is,
how much does it want to be its size?
How much does it want to be small, in other words?
So, like this guy always, that button always wants to
be only big enough to hold the login.
It does not want to be really tall or really wide.
It wants to hug.
So, it has a high hugging priority.
Other things, they might not care if they get bigger.
Okay?
Like this thing right here,
it really wants to hug vertically.
It doesn't mind if it gets stretched out horizontally.
All right?
Okay.
So, that's that.
Now, let's go to, what are we going to do next here?
Let's add a couple more fields.
That name, remember we had the name and the company?
Let's go add those and see what happens here.
So those are going to be text fields.
So they're labels rather, they're right here at the top.
So I'm just going to put these out here,
grab a couple of these.
We'll make this one be name.
We'll make this one be the company.
All right, now where do I want these to be located?
Well, I kind of want this to be right here.
I really want it to be kind of like right here.
Okay, not perfectly in the middle because I
am gonna put company right here.
So now it would be kind of offset down.
But I guess I can say all right,
I'll make these two things.
I'll have their horizontal spacing and
their Center Y's matched up.
The centers vertically.
It's kinda not exactly what I want, but it's close.
And then this guy, I will have his vertical spacing, and
his left edge lined up with the name.
Right?
That's pretty much what I want.
So that's not bad, but
really I don't want this lined up with the middle here.
I want the bottom of this lined up with the middle.
So how can I do that?
Okay, pay attention now.
It's very important to understand, because now
we're gonna start looking at how these constraints work.
So I'm gonna click on this constraint,
which causes me to inspect it here in the Inspector.
Okay? This is
what a constraint looks like.
Notice the constraint has two items, a first item and
a second item.
And, for each item, it says something about that item,
like its center, or its bottom, or its top.
Okay? If it had text,
it could be base lines.
All right?
So, each of them has something like that.
And then, it has a relationship between them,
which could be equal, less than or
equal, or greater than or equal.
So right now I have the center of this Stanford thing
equal to the center of the name thing.
But it's perfectly fine for me to say I want the center of
the Stanford thing to match the bottom of the name thing.
Okay?
Understand that?
And then, down here you have this constant.
Okay?
The constants, there's two constants.
One is a multiplier, and one is a constant.
Okay?
So the constant is always added onto the end,
and the multiplier is going to multiply the things that
are being compared.
So it really doesn't make sense too much to multiply.
But it kind of does.
Watch if I do four to one ratio.
It's putting this bottom of this
the ratio of four to one of the size of here.
Okay? And
this can also be like, 0.5.
Okay.
Which is really tiny, so tiny that it's one.
Let's say two.
All right? So these can be numbers, or
they can be ratios.
And then the constant is an amount added to it, like 50.
Okay, so I've just added fixed 50 pixels.
So it's just always added.
So constant is always added, multiplier is multiplied.
All constraints are this way, every single one.
Okay? And,
some make sense with center or top bottom.
Some of them make sense with width and height.
And when we do one in code,
you're gonna see we're gonna do width and height.
You know, but they're still in the same form.
They always have the same form.
That's why there's only one constructor for
these layout constraint in the code.
Okay, and it just takes all of these things.
The constant, the multiplier the first item.
Which thing on the first item?
The relationship.
And the second item, the second, and
the thing on that, okay?
So we're gonna see that.
So, lets see if this worked.
Just for fun let's go ahead and go back to our code, and
why are these things up.
Okay, so Ctrl+Drag.
That's alright, from the name.
oops, Undo, okay.
Ctrl+Drag from the name.
That is our Name Label and we'll go and
Ctrl+Drag from the company here.
That is our Company Label.
All right.
And in our Update UI,
sorry about the width here, let's do this.
In our Update UI here, we are going to update those.
So we'll just say that our Name Label that text,
equals our logged in user.
And if our logged in user is nil,
then we'll just set the text to be nil as well.
So I'm using optional chaining there.
But that's the name of the person.
And then, our company label's text equals the logged in
user's company.
Okay? Let's also set
that image view right there.
Okay?
So we'll Ctrl+Drag from the image view
that's just like any other thing.
I can Ctrl+Drag this thing over, so let's do that.
I'm gonna call it the Image View.
Okay. And
we'll set that as well in our Update UI.
Here by saying imageview.image equals the logged in
user's image.
Unfortunately, this is not gonna work.
And why is this not gonna work?
Because Image is not defined in User.
If we go look at User.
Okay, user can't have an image because it's a model.
It doesn't have any UI kit.
There's no UI.
And UI image is a UI thing.
Okay.
So we can't even model.
But that doesn't stop us from having an image
property MUser, because we can use extensions.
Okay.
So here I'm gonna make an extension to User.
Okay, it's gonna be a var called image.
It's gonna be a UIImage, UIImage, but I'm adding this
in my controller so that's fine because, it's extending
my model but it's not actually touching my model.
My model is still purely fine.
And to do this, I'm just gonna return basically a UIImage,
that is named the user's login.
Now notice, I can refer to login here because this
is user.
This is on user, so
login is a user thing, so I can refer to that, 'kay.
But this is saying no, because this might return nil.
So I'm gonna say.
If I can get let the image equal that,.
Then, I will return it.
Otherwise, I will return a UI image of some unknown user.
I have. A thing there I
put in there called, unknown user.
That's just an image that I put there.
And this, I'm gonna make this optional so
the whole thing can return optional.
Okay?
So now, this is implemented.
This might return nill but
that's okay, because this is allowed to be nill.
And all is well.
So let's go take a look,
now we should have our full UI functioning here.
Let's go on our iPhone here.
Oh, I know, right here,
okay, run, okay, here it is, so let's log in as madbum.
And log in, and there we go.
Oh, that looks terrible.
What's going on here?
Look at how it stretched this thing out, okay?
I want this hugging.
I don't like this.
This is not hugging, okay?
But there's another problem too,
we'll look at this in a second.
But let's look at it this way, though.
Same thing, it's no good.
Okay? So, we're getting close.
Why is this happening?
Well, the reason that this is happening is because we have
all these things attached to each other, and, so
we can fix this in two ways, actually.
One way is I can go here, and change this guy,
who's hugging priority can just be less so
that these guys will be more likely to hug.
Okay.
Down on their text.
So I'm gonna set this guy's vertical hugging priority
down to let's say 200.
The rest of these are at say, 250.
Okay, these are all at 250.
I'm gonna set mine down to 200.
Okay.
So we run, let's log in as mad mom again.
There we go, okay, so it didn't squish this,
although wow, now it's stretched this thing way up.
I don't really like that either.
Okay?
So why is that happening?
Well that's happening because of this constraint right here.
This constraint says,
that the distance from the top of the image to the bottom of
here has to equal.
The standard value equal.
I don't want equal.
I'm gonna say, if it's greater than or equal, that's fine.
Okay? So this is where you
would use a greater than or equals, because this spacing,
I just want to make sure it doesn't smash into it.
But if it's smaller, that's okay.
I don't mind that.
All right. So now, let's try madbum.
Madbum.
Okay, perfect, so now it's doing that, and
over here, oops, over this way, working fine.
Okay?
So we're getting good,
there's only really two things left that are problems in
this whole thing,
one is this guy getting smashed off, gotta fix that.
And we fix that.
You already know how to fix that.
I'm just gonna take this, and make it so
that this thing hooks to this edge.
And same thing with this thing hooking to this guy's edge.
And again, I don't want them to be anything but
a standard value here.
So I'm gonna have this one be zero.
And same thing with this one right here.
I don't like this.
Nonstandard values.
In fact, I've got a couple of them
left over from previous things here, so let's fix these.
Standard Values.
Okay?
All right.
Everything look good there?
No magic numbers?
Oh, here's the magic number.
Let's get rid of that.
Standard Value.
That it, okay, got all those.
Everything looks fine, it moved.
So now, we should be all fixed and ready to go.
Alright, madbum again.
Secure this time, don't want you to know madbum's password.
Okay, looking good, oh, still didn't quite work.
We got the name but why did this thing.
Not do that.
What's going on there?
Same circle Giants got put up.
The reason there is this guy's hogging priority is too
low, okay.
I'm sorry, his compression resistance, I mean,
is too low.
He's allowing himself to be compressed.
Okay.
So here, we need to have the horizontal compression
resistance of this guy be higher.
So I'm gonna set it to 800.
Doesn't really matter what we set,
as long as it's higher than.
The other things, like this one, which is 750, so
let's set this guy's also, oops, it's compression to 800.
Okay, so that prevents them from being compressed down so
that their text won't show.
Okay.
Oh, well, that's not so good.
Okay, so we fixed one problem, we introduces another one.
So we certainly-
There are two problems with this,
actually, number one, this is not the right aspect ratio.
This is not what the Giants logo looks like,
you can barely even tell it's the Giants.
And number two is, it's way too small, okay?
Look at all this empty space I've got up here, okay, so
we've got two things to fix here.
And then we're done.
One is make this aspect ratio be enforced, and
another one is put this in the right space.
In this size class which is I got a lot of vertical space.
So, lets go ahead and fix the aspect ratio one first.
You know that one.
We'd like to be able to just go here and
add some kind of constraint, but we can't actually do that.
And that's because if you remember, when we look
at a constraint, its constant and multiplier are constants.
And every time we get a new image,
it has a different aspect ratio.
Okay?
So, unless we wanted to force everyone's image to
be the same aspect ratio, we need code to
do this because we have to calculate that aspect ratio.
So, this is what that looks like.
I'm gonna go through this pretty fast because
we're over time already, so you can watch it here.
So, I'm gonna do this like this.
I'm gonna create a new var,
which is an aspectRatioConstraint(), and
it's going to be of type NSLayoutConstraint.
This is the type of those constraints.
All those constraints in there it is of this type, okay.
Now, I'm gonna create another var called image, UIImage.
And it can be optional, it's fine.
And it's just gonna be a computed property,
where I'm gonna get and set my image views properties.
So I'm really just gonna return imageView.image,
I'm gonna set her.
I'm just going to set it.
Let's go to wide here.
Wide mode.
Okay, in the center,
I'm just gonna set it imageView.image = image.
Now, why am I creating this little computer property?
Because every time I set my imageView's image I
want to update this aspect ration constraint, okay.
So, if I can let this constrained view,
this is the view I'm trying to constrain,
which is the image view.
If I can let it equal something.
In other words it's not nill, okay?
And if I can let the new image equal new value,
because this is, we're setting an image here, so
if I'm able to set an image in this constraint, screen view.
Then I'm gonna create this
aspectRatioConstraint equal to something.
If I can't set the new image, then I'm gonna
set the aspectRatioContraint equal to nil, 'kay.
So someone set my image to nil.
I can't have a constraint.
The aspect ration of nil image is nothing, so I don't,
can't even have a constraint there.
So how do I create this constraint in the case I
do have an image for imageView?
I just do it with a constructor,
NSLayoutConstraint, okay?
Here's what NSLayoutConstraint's
constructor looks like.
It's got all these things here,
let's go through them one at a time, and
it looks just like that inspector I showed you.
So one is the thing we're trying to constrain.
Which is our image view, what attribute of that, it's width,
how do we want to relate it to our constants and multipliers?
Well, we're going to do aspect ratio, so
we want the width multiplied times the height.
So the width is going to equal the height times the aspect
ratio, so this is going to be equal.
And what are we relating it to?
We could relate it to another thing, but
this is the imageviews own aspect ratio, so it's relating
it to itself, okay, and what attribute is it relating to?
It's height, and what is the multiplier going to be?
It's going to be that new image aspect ratio.
Okay? And then this constant gets
added in.
We don't want to add anything else in.
We just want to multiply.
So here I'm making this image view's width equal to it's
height times this multiplier.
Make sense?
That's the constraint I'm putting on it.
That's how constraints work.
That's all it is.
Now a couple of things are not good here.
One is there is no such method aspect ratio on UI image.
So I'm gonna go down here and do an extension for that too.
UIImage var aspectRatio.
It's gonna be a CGFloat.
I'm just going to return if my size.height is not zero,
because I don't wanna have to divide by zero.
Then I'm going to return size.width divided by
size.height, otherwise I guess I'll just return zero.
Okay, so I just added this var to UI image,
because I wanted it and
it makes my code read really nicely right here, okay?
Perfectly reasonable.
And the only other thing is, when I set this aspect ratio
constraint I'm creating it, but now I need to enforce it.
So how do you enforce a constraint?
If you have one in your hand, how do you force it?
And it's very simple,
you just add it as a constraint to the view.
So I'm in my view controller here, so
I'm going to add this constraint to my view.
So in didSet, any time this aspect ratio gets set up here,
this is where I set it.
Either to nil or this.
Then if I can let this new
constraint equal the aspect ratio of constraint.
In other words, if its not nil.
Then I'm gonna tell my view please add this constraint.
Now I also, by the way, when it set I want to
remove any old constraint cause I might already have
put a constraint from the previous image I was showing.
So I'm gonna say if let the existing constraint
equal the aspect ratio constraint and
this is my will set so this hasn't been set yet.
Then I'm gonna say remove the constraint.
Make sense? So that's it.
Okay, and that's all we need to do.
So let's go ahead and run here.
So I'm going to go back to this view here,
and select Storyboard here.
All right, so we're going to run this.
I haven't changed the storyboard since last we
talked, but now when we go madbomb here.
This thing, it didn't work.
So why does this not work?
because, sorry about this, forgot something.
When I set my image, I'm not calling my new image property.
I put all that nice code here inside this image
property, right?
Right here.
But I didn't call it.
So here I'm actually calling that, so sorry about that.
Why did I [INAUDIBLE] there, imageView.image equals
newValue, sorry about that, newValue.
Let's go back here, all right.
See, when I rush, then I make mistakes like that.
Okay, all right!
Whoo.
I think that's the Giants logo down there.
At least it's the right aspect ratio.
But clearly, it's terrible to have that thing there
because it's too tiny and we got all this space.
So last thing we're going to do is
use the size classes to put this thing up here, okay?
How do we do that?
We go back to our storyboard right here.
And right now, we've been doing all our
work in this any any.
Okay, and what we want to do is when we're regular height,
we're gonna put the name and the company underneath.
So I'm gonna go here to where it says any width,
regular height.
You see where it says along the top, any width,
See that?
I'm gonna click there.
Now I'm editing.
You see the bar at the bottom is bright blue.
That's to remind you,
oh hey, you are editing a specific size class here.
But we're editing any width, regular height.
And so here, this should be in red if I
was doing a slide, this would be in red, which is
when you go to another size class, and you're going to be
moving things around, remove the constraints on
the things you're going to be moving before you move them.
Because once you start moving them,
it's going to be hard to remember, what did that go to.
So here I am selecting these all and
I am going to go over here and remove the constraint,
clear the constraints, only from the selected views,
these three things I have selected.
So we're going to clear those constraints,
now they have no constraints,
now I am just going to move them around to where I want.
So I want that one there,
I want these down here at the bottom.
Put that in the corner.
I'll put that on top of there.
We'll put this down here like that.
Now we'll put the new constraints, so
now all new constraints that I'm making are only for
this size class.
Okay? Not for any-any anymore.
I'm kind of forked off here.
So let's put some new constraints on here.
This one is leaving space.
This one is leading space.
This one is bottom space.
We want these separated.
Vertical space.
We want these two separated.
We want this one over here leading space.
We want this to go all the way across, and
then go trailing space.
You also want this one to go all the way across, and
trailing space.
Okay.
Again, we would probably go here.
Let's see what we've got here.
Frames are different, that's good.
Let's go ahead and update our frames.
Okay, looks good.
All looks good.
Again, we would probably get rid of these magic numbers
like this.
We don't like that.
We get rid of that.
We did this one.
We don't like that.
We go select on this guy.
We've got this here, that.
Same thing this one.
Okay, he got none, so we're good.
We're good to go.
So now we've created this size class.
One has different arrangement of views and
different constraints.
So now when we run.
We'll see here.
Hit mad bum again.
There it is.
It's using this space much more
effectively keeping this in it's normal aspect ratio, but
in this way it goes back to the old way.
The any, any way, right?
Okay, and this is true if we go to someone else.
Hennessy.
There, okay, see how that keeps the same aspect ratio
and uses that space?
Really uses the space nicely here, no.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Now why did that happen, okay?
Because when I cleared the constraints here,
okay, to make this new space, I also cleared this little
constraint that went up here, this vertical spacing.
Right?
This vertical spacing here wants to be the greater than
or equal to, and standard value.
Okay? So sometimes when you
go to another size class, you delete the constraints,
you move things around, oh, you still have
to basically debug the new one just as much as the old one.
So here now,
let's go see if our illustrious leader's log in.
It's good and it is.
Okay?
All right.
Sorry to take so long.
Thank you.
I'll be here if you have any questions,
otherwise I'll see you on Wednesday.
>> For more, please visit us at Stanford.edu.