[MUSIC]
>> Stanford University.
Welcome to Stanford CS193P, Winter of 2015.
This is Lecture 9, I believe.
And today, we are going to turn on our clicker here and
then we are going to.
I'm going to show you a brief, very brief demo,
in addition to the Autolayout Demo that we did last time.
I challenged you in that one to add buttons to
your calculator, then I didn't show you how to do that.
So I'm gonna show you how to do that.
How, in a different size class,
you could add some views that aren't in another size class.
Then we're gonna talk about two big topics today.
One of them is ScrollView, okay.
And the second one is Multithreading.
And, kind of as a preamble to do multithreading,
I'm going to talk a little bit about closures.
Now, you should all have read your reading assignment, so
you all know about closures.
But, I just wanna emphasize something about them.
That will start to be more important as we
start using closures more for things like multithreading.
So, let's make a quick little detour here.
I'm just gonna open up Autolayout here.
So here's autolayout.
And what I wanna be able to do is add another
view only in one of my size classes.
So here's my Any, Any size class.
And let's say I go back to my Any Width,
Regular Height that we were working on.
And let's say, when we're in this particular arrangement,
we wanna have,
you know, an extra button up here or something.
And all we need to do that is to drag out whatever
the extra UI you want is, like this Button.
And if you inspect the button with the Inspector,
Attributes Inspector.
Down at the very bottom, you'll see, right here,
that there is some switches that control where this
button appears.
Now, since I dragged this button into this size class,
it assumes I only wanted it in this size class.
You see where it says Installed, right here?
I could put it in all size classes by clicking this.
That means it'll be in all size classes.
Or I could take it out of this size class only,
by unclicking this, okay?
And you can add more things.
I could say in Compact Width,
Compact Height, I want this button to be there or not.
Okay?
And that's true for constraints, as well.
If you have a certain constraint.
Like we've got constraints down here,
like this one right here, that are only in this size class.
Because these things are only down here in this size class.
So you can see that's switched.
So, whether something is even there and
also the constraints, you can control right here.
And someone asked me, oh, I did all this work in here, for
all this size class, but I changed my mind.
I don't want it to be different in that size class.
How would I go back and undo all this?
Well, the way you would do
that is bring up your document outline.
And you can select all your constraints.
You can actually shift > click to select.
I could select all my constraints.
And you can see over here, in the Inspector,
it's going to show me that, you know, some of.
It's got a dash here instead of a check.
So, kind of some of them are there.
And if just go here and say, boom, and remove that.
Now, all my constraints are only in my base class.
There's no constraints that are just in this one.
And, in fact, if you look down here.
Look, all these constraints are all gone.
So, in fact, if I go here and Update Frames.
Boom, it goes back to the way it was.
You see?
Everyone understand that?
So, Constraints and the Views can be turned on and off
by just inspecting them in the Attributes Inspector, okay?
That's all I wanted to show you there.
All right, back to the slides.
All right, so let's.
Talk about ScrollView.
All right so, you can see this iPhone right here.
This is like,
I don't know, iPhone 1 or something-looking thing.
But, I keep it around because it's a really cool example of
the power of ScrollView.
And what you can do with ScrollView.
Especially with ScrollViews inside ScrollViews.
So, watch this little movie here go as we scroll around,
up and down.
Okay, so that's just normal side-to-side scrolling.
But there's up and down within the side to side.
When I get to one, I can go up and down.
And then this app, at the bottom, I can scroll side to
side at the bottom and also up and down.
So, you see how the scrolling can kind of
go both directions.
Depending on what you've scrolled into view.
So, ScrollView is very smart about knowing which
way you're scrolling.
And having, you know, opposing ScrollViews and
stuff work properly, okay.
Now, we're not gonna be able to have time, in the brief
time we have here, to discuss how to make all that work.
But I just want you to know the power is there.
So, someday, if you wanna build an app that has some UI
like that, you know where to go, which is ScrollView.
So, we're gonna talk about the basics of ScrollView.
Kind of how to get a ScrollView to work.
First, let's talk about how we add subviews to
a normal UIView.
So, I got a normal UIView here.
This white view in my iPhone here.
And I wanna add a subview to it.
And so, you know, from Lecture 5, I think, that I just create
the frame which positions it and then I say add subview.
Okay, so I've got this view called Logo.
And it's just a UIView.
An image view, probably.
And, so I just add subview and, boom, it appears.
Simple as that.
It's really easy.
So, what is the analogy to doing this
for ScrollView, okay?
Let's go look at that.
So, in a ScrollView, if you wanna add a subview.
The most important thing you have to do is talk about
how big the area you wanna scroll over is.
So, you set this property in ScrollView called contentSize.
So, here I'm gonna set my contentSize to 3000
wide and 2000 high.
So, I'm gonna scroll over this huge space, okay?
Once you set the contentSize,
now you can add subviews just like you do a normal view.
So, here I got logo frame.
I'm gonna set the frame to way over on the left there and
I am going to add its subview.
So I'm adding that subview to the ScrollView.
But instead of it appearing onscreen there,
it's just kind of placed in this content area.
And so, I could add another one.
Here's a huge image, aerial view of Stanford.
And so, I'm gonna set its frame and
add it as a subview, okay.
So this is the fundamental,
this is all there is to ScrollView.
It's really simple, actually.
It confuses people for some reason, but
it's really just this simple.
You set the contentSize,
then you add subviews to the ScrollView.
Now, the ScrollView is just going to
be a window on that content area.
You see, it's just gonna scroll around,
looking in that content area.
And it'll see all the subviews as it
moves around in there, okay?
So, that's it.
That's all there is to it.
ScrollView is actually incredibly easy to use.
Now, you can reposition the views, anytime you want,
just like you could if they were subviews.
You can just change their frame and they'll move around.
Or change the logo's frame, move it around.
I can also change the contentSize.
[NOISE] And now it zooms down.
I can set the contentSize to be
the size of the biggest subview.
And now, again,
when I scroll around, it's just zooming around, okay.
So it's very common in the ScrollView,
obviously, to set its contentSize to be the size of
the biggest subview.
So that it exactly contains it.
Okay, now, as this thing moves around, you might wanna know,
where is it, okay?
What we are currently looking at in my content area?
And you do that with the property in
ScrollView called contentOffset.
And it's simple.
It's just an x-y offset from the upper left,.
Of the upper left of the,
you know, bounds of the scroll view.
Okay, now what about the actual rectangle
that's showing?
What is that?
That is actually the scroll view's bounds.
Okay, it's very important to understand that that is
just the scroll view bound, that yellow rectangle I'm
showing you there, that's the scroll view's bounds.
But if you want to know what that rectangle is
in the content, like, in that aerial view,
what is that rectangle, then you have to convert it.
You have to convert the scrollView's bounds using
convertRect, [COUGH] which is UIView method.
You have to convert it to that,
to whatever view you wanna convert it
to like the aerial view whatever that aerial view is.
Does that make sense?
So that rectangle is the scroll view's bounds.
Okay?
Questions?
All right. That's easy.
So that's it.
That's pretty much it to setting up a scroll view and
knowing where the thing is scrolling.
Couldn't be simpler actually.
How do you create a scroll view?
There's actually numerous ways to do it.
You can drag one into your storyboard.
That's what I'm gonna do in the demo.
You can actually select a UI view in your storyboard and
go up to the menu up there,
and say embed in scroll view, just like we did embed in
navigation controller in a previous thing.
You can of course create Scroll Views in code.
They're just views, so
you can write a UIScrollView frame whatever.
And boom, you've created a Scroll View.
So, they're just normal views.
And then the code if you wanted to
add those subviews in code would look exactly kind of
like what was on the previous slides.
Which is we might create an image view here,
the green is just creating UI image view,
and then I'm just calling addSubview.
But if you just do this, these three lines of code,
it won't work because you have to set the content size.
If you don't set the content size,
it starts out zero, until you bring your Scroll View up,
and they'll be nothing there.
Because you won't have that big white area to scroll
around in.
Okay?
So no matter what Sub Views you add,
if you don't have that big white area defined,
then Scroll View will not be showing anything.
Okay, so it's as simple as that.
This is a review of what I showed you graphically.
Now you can scroll around.
The user scrolls around by just using their finger.
Right? They pan around.
But you can scroll programmatically too by saying
scrollRectToVisible and this will take a rectangle in the
content areas view coordinate system, that content size.
And it'll scroll the Scroll View to be showing that.
And animated is whether it slides over.
If you don't say animated, it's just gonna jump there.
Which is kind of abrupt to the user, if it's on screen.
And there's tons of other things you can do
with a Scroll View that I'm not gonna really talk about.
But you can lock the scrolling direction, so
it'll only scroll up and down, or only scroll left and right.
It'll flash the scroll indicators if the content size
has changed.
You can control that.
There's a whole bunch of stuff you can look at
UIScrollView in the documentation.
Okay?
I'm going to have one thing important about
scrollview which is zooming.
Cuz so
far I just showed you kind of moving around and of course in
scroll you can also zoom in on the content area, okay?
Zooming in requires you to do a few things though.
One thing is you have to set the minimum and
maximum zoom scale.
So the zoom scale is just how much you'll zoom in.
So, if you have a zoom scale of 2.0,
then that means that you'll only zoom to twice the scale.
And if you're 2.5, it'll zoom down to half of whatever
the normal size is of the thing you're looking at is.
So you have to set these.
If you don't set these they'll be default to 1, and
it won't work because the scaling will go from 1 to 1.
Okay? And so
that means not scaling at all.
The other thing you have to do is use a delegate.
So here's the second time I've showed you a delegate.
Now I had you do all that work with a calculator to
do the delegate so that you'd be
ready to do things in iOS that use delegates.
And here's one.
'Kay. You've set yourself as
the ScrollView's delegate, and you implement this method.
You have to implement this method if
you want zooming called viewForZoomingInScrollView.
So the scroll view when it's zooming, it only zooms in,
in the coordinate systems of one of its views.
So usually it's kind of the background view.
Like in that aerial example,
it would be the aerial view that we would zoom in, okay.
But we're zooming the whole contents, so
everything gets zoomed,
全部都会缩放，
but that's gonna be the view that you're zooming in.
但是你需要在一个视图里进行缩放。
So you have to tell it which view that is.
你需要告诉系统这是哪个视图。
It's usually pretty obvious.
通常来说这是显而易见的。
Often times in ScrollView,
通常来说
you're only scrolling on one view anyway but
你只会在一个视图上滚动，但是
you still have to implement this, okay.
你依然需要实现这个方法。
You can zoom programatically once you've set those two
正确的完成这两步后，你就可以使用代码
things up properly.
来进行缩放了。
Then you can set the zoom scale, how zoomed in you are.
你可以设置缩放比例。
It looks kind of like this.
就像这样，
So, here I've got a picture.
这里有一张图片。
Let's say my zoomScale is 1.2.
我的缩放比例是1.2.
I go to zoomScale 1.
现在改成1
I zoom out, zoom back to 1.2 zoomed in.
然后再放大，现在是1.2.
Okay? And same thing with zoom rect.
缩放矩形也是一样的。
So if I had a little rectangle like that yellow area and
如果我有一个黄色区域这样的小矩形。
I said zoom to that rect, it would zoom to make that
然后我要缩放到这个矩形，图片就会缩放
rect fill the edges as much as it could.
到尽可能适应这个矩形。
Or if I have a rect that was really big, and
或者我有一个很大的矩形，
I said zoom it would zoom it down to fit.
图片就会缩小去适应它。
Okay?
So, zoomToRect means make this rect kind of either go big or
所以zoomToRect方法就是提供一个矩形，然后背景放大或
go small to fit.
缩小去适应它。
Okay?
All right?
好的。
There are tons of other delegate methods in
滚动视图有非常多的代理
scroll view.
方法。
One thing, when you start using scroll view,
这里有一个问题，当你开始使用滚动视图的时候，
you're going to ask me is,
你可能会问我，
hey, scroll view has 12 delegate methods.
滚动视图有12个代理方法。
And when I say I implement the UIScrollView delegate
当我要实现滚动视图的代理协议时
protocol, how come the compiler doesn't complain and
为什么编译器没有抱怨说我必须实现
say that it will implement those 12 methods because I
这12个代理方法？我认为如果我说要实现
thought if I said I implemented a protocol,
一个协议，我就要实现协议规定的
I have to implement all those protocols, okay?
所有方法。
The reason that that happens, that you don't get
编译器没有警告的原因是
a warning there is because there is actually, for
因为一些历史原因，
historical reasons, a different kind of protocol,
还有一种其他类型的协议，
which is an Objective-C style protocol.
也就是 Objective-C 的协议。
Objective C was the old language that iOS
Objective-C 是一种老语言，iOS就是用它写成的。
was written in and in the Objective C style protocols
在 Objective-C 的协议里，
some methods in the protocol were allowed to be optional.
一些方法可以是可选的。
Now that's not true in Swift,
Swift不可以这样，
but that's true in Objective C.
但是 Objective-C 可以。
So all these old delegate protocols like
所以像滚动视图代理协议这种老的
scroll view that have optional methods in them,
协议，里边都是有可选方法的。
Swift knows how to bridge them.
Swift 知道如何桥接他们。
You can actually create your own Objective C compatible
事实上你也可以自己写一个 有可选方法的 Objective-C 风格的
protocol with optional methods by saying @objc in front of
协议，只需要在协议声明之前加上
your protocol declaration.
@objc 。
So where you would say protocol face view delegate or
比如你可以写一个 FaceViewDelegate 或者
face view data source you would say
FaceViewDataSource，在声明的时候
@objc space protocol, whatever delegate, and
写@objc 空格 protocol,
then you could put optional in there.
然后你就可以定义可选方法了。
And you can read,
你可以在
this is all covered in the reading assignments, so
阅读材料里读到这些内容，希望
hopefully you've got that.
你们已经都看过了。
But that's the magic that makes it so that when you say
正是因为有这个魔法，所以在你
you implement the UIScrollView delegate protocol and
需要实现滚动视图代理协议的时候，你不需要
you don't yet implement all the 12 methods in there.
实现它里边全部的12个方法。
In fact you only need to implement the ones you
你只需要实现你想实现的方法，
want like view for zooming and scroll view.
比如缩放什么的。
That's why that works.
这就是为什么不会报错。
So anyway there are a bunch of
当然还有很多
other delegate methods in there.
别的代理方法。
For example scrollViewDidEndZooming.
比如 scrollViewDidEndZooming 。
So that will be sent to you when the user pinches and
这个方法会在用户用手指缩放完毕离开屏幕的时候
then they lift their finger up.
被调用。
'Kay? And it'll say oh,
它会知道
the user has finished zooming and
用户现在已经结束缩放，而且也能知道
this is the scale they left it at.
现在的缩放比例。
And you, at that point, might want to redraw your view to
在这个时间点，你可能需要重绘你的视图让它看上去
be less grainy, or something like that.
不那么模糊，或者类似的事儿。
If you do redraw your view at the new scale,
如果你确实要在新的缩放比例重绘视图，
you want to make sure you reset the transform.
那么你需要确保你重置了 transform 。
Okay. This property on
这是一个视图的属性，
view called transform is an Affine transform.
它是一种仿射变换。
Really that's all scroll view is modifying.
当你在滚动视图上滑动手指或者
When you pan around and
所缩放操作的时候，
zoom in, it's just modifying the property transform.
实际上就是在改动这个属性。
So, you can go look at the documentation for transform in
你们可以去看视图里 transform的文档去
view to understand what's going on there.
深入了解一下。
Yeah, it makes scroll view really easy in that it
这使得滚动视图的操作很好理解，因为都是
just is modifying this transform.
在改变这个属性。
All right, so that's scroll view.
好，这就是滚动视图。
So, I have a demo of scroll view.
下边有一个滚动视图的演示。
We're going to learn some other
在做这个演示的时候，我们还会学
things along the way while we're doing that.
一些其他的东西。
Okay, let's do that.
开始
Let's go over here.
这里
We're gonna start from scratch again.
我们从头开始做。
So I'm gonna create a new Xcode project.
建一个新的Xcode项目。
'Kay. It's gonna be Single View.
单视图应用。
Those of you who like to follow along are not gonna be
想跟着做的人今天可能
able to today.
不行了。
Sorry.
不好意思。
Because I'm going to be dragging in a file with some
因为我要直接拖一个有很多URL的文件
URLs in it.
进来。
I'm going to call this thing Cassini.
给项目起名叫cassini。
That's going to be the name of my app.
这个就是我的应用的名字。
And I'm gonna put it where I always put everything.
还放在原来的地方。
All right, I'm not going to be doing anything with the app
跟原来一样，我们不需要改动AppDelegate这个
delegate as usual.
文件。
I'm not going to be doing image assets.
这次也不改动图片库。
I'm not going to do the launch screen.
不改动启动屏幕。
So, here I just have a simple storyboard.
只需要这个简单的 storyboard。
I'm gonna also get rid of
这些关于视图控制器
all this ViewController life cycle here.
生命周期的方法也没用。
I don't need that.
这次不需要。
Get rid of that.
删掉。
And so here, simple storyboard only has this one
现在这个简单的storyboard只有一个叫
view controller here called ViewController.
ViewController的视图控制器。
And I'm not even gonna pay any attention to
而且我也不需要关注这个
this view controller.
视图控制器。
Actually, I'm gonna create a new view controller.
我要建一个新的视图控制器。
I'm gonna drag it out here and this new view controller,
从这拖一个出来，这个新的视图控制器
its only job in life it's going to display an image.
唯一的任务就是显示一个图片。
So I'm going give it the URL of an image, a JPEG file or
我可能会传递给它一个图片的URL，JPEG文件或者别的
whatever, and it's going to display it.
什么东西，反正就是显示图片。
That's going to be its job in life.
这就是它全部的工作。
So I need a new view controller for that.
我需要一个新的视图控制器文件。
So I'm going to call this new view controller.
我要给它起名叫。。。。
All right? I'm going here,
点这，
Cocoa Touch Class, it's a view controller.
Cocoa Touch 类，视图控制器。
I'm gonna call it ImageViewController.
起名叫 ImageViewController 。
Cuz that's what it does, it displays an image.
因为这就是它要干的活，显示一张图片。
Okay? Very, very simple.
非常简单。
I'm gonna put it where all the rest of my stuff goes, there.
把它跟我其他的东西放到一起，这。
All right? So here we go again.
好了，又要来一次，
Again, I'm gonna get rid of my
把所有的视图控制器生命周期
view controller life cycle there.
相关的方法删掉。
We're gonna actually add some of those back,
实际上一会儿可能会加一些方法回来，
cuz part of the reason I'm doing this demo, also,
这也是我们做这个演示的一部分，
is to show you a little bit where and
会给你们演示一些视图控制器生命
why, how we would use a view controller life cycle.
周期的内容。
So, my ImageViewController, one other thing,
还有一个事，
let me make sure in our storyboard here, we got this thing,
我得确认一下在storyboard里，
I'm gonna make sure I change the identity of it
我要把这个视图控制器的类改成
to be an ImageViewController.
ImageViewController
So this is an ImageViewController.
现在是 ImageViewController 了。
This is an easy thing to forget, but do that.
这个事情非常容易忘。
Okay, so what do I need in my ImageViewController.
在我的 ImageViewController 里，
Well, I need a UIImageView.
我需要一个 UIImageView 。
We saw that in the Auto Layout demo.
我们在自动布局的演示里见过了。
It's a just a view, kind of like a UI label for images.
它就是一种视图，一种显示图片的标签。
Obviously if I'm going to have ImageViewController,
显然如果我要做一个显示图片的视图控制器，
I'm going to need one of those.
我肯定需要一个这个东西。
Now, I could just drag it out into my story board, but
我可以从storyboard里拖一个进去，但是
I want to use this demo as an example to show you
我希望通过这个演示给你们看一下如何通过代码
how you create a view in code, create and use a view in code.
来新建一个视图并使用它。
So instead, I'm just gonna have a private var here.
这里我建一个私有变量。
I'm gonna call it imageView.
我叫它 imageView 。
And it's going to be a UIImageView.
类型是 UIImageView。
In fact, I'm just gonna create it right here.
我要在这直接新建。
Okay.
So I have this image view.
现在我又了这个图片视图。
I'm just calling it there.
我在这直接新建了。
Notice, I'm not using the frame.
注意我没用frame新建。
So it's going to create this image view.
所以我这个新的图片视图
It's going to be zero, zero, by zero, zero.
的frame就是
It's going to be, it's framed.
（0,0,0,0)
It's going to be, now it's not in any super view anyways, so
现在它不属于任何视图，
it really doesn't matter what its frame is yet.
所以它的frame 是啥也不重要。
Okay. It's obviously going to
当然，在我们让它显示
matter a lot once we start putting images in there.
图片的时候就很重要了。
I'm also going to create a little private var
这里我还要写一个叫 image 的
here called image.
私有变量。
And this is going to be a computed var.
这是一个计算属性。
I did this in Auto Layout as well.
在自动布局演示里我做过。
It's going to be a UIImage.
它是UIImage类型的。
And all I'm going to to here in the getter,
在 getter 方法里，
I'm just going to return the imageView's image.
我让它返回 imageView.image 。
And in the setter,
在 setter 方法里，
I'm basically just going to set the imageView's image to
我直接就写 imageView.image = newValue.
the new value.
Now, why do I do this?
为什么要这么做？
'Kay, I'm doing this for
我这么做的原因
the exact same reason that I was doing it in the other one,
跟我之前做的完全一样，
which is that when the image is set in my imageView,
我希望我的 imageView 的图片设定好以后，
I want to be able to do things, I want to intervene.
我可以对它做事，我可以干预它。
So I basically I want to kind of be able to do
所以我想要做一些
the did set kind of thing to make that work.
类似于didSet的事情。
So, what's my warning here, UIImage.
啊，这个警告是什么，UIImage 。
Okay, so here we go.
好了。
So in other words right here, when this is set,
换句话说，当这个设置的时候，
when this image gets set.
当这个图片设置的时候。
Setting this image just is going to set the image in
设置这个图片就是设置了imageView的图片，
the imageView, that's all it does.
这是这句代码的意思。
But I can put other code that I
下边我还想加更多的
want down here because I'm going to
代码，因为我希望在我的图片变更的时候
need to do some things every time my image changes.
可以做更多的事情。
I don't care about getting but every time my
我不关心 getter，但是每次图片设置了
image gets set in my imageView I need to do some stuff.
的时候我希望imageView可以做一些事情。
Let me see.
那么
Well, let's talk about what some of those things might be.
让我们看看可以做什么。
For example,
比如，
when I set it I probably want to do imageView.sizeToFit.
当我设置图片的时候，我希望做 imageView.sizeToFit 。
Okay. So when you change the image
当我们改变图片视图里的图片时，
that's in image view, this is kind of like saying label.text
这个就好像是 label.text 等于什么什么。
equals something, right, I'm changing the imageView that,
事实上我是在修改图片视图，
the image that the imageView's showing.
修改它的显示的图片。
When you change it, it does not change the bounds or
但是当我们改这个的时候，不会改变图片视图的bounds
the frames of the image view.
或者frame。
So, sizeToFit causes it to.
sizeToFit 可以。
So ImageView looks at the image, sees how big it is and
图片视图会观察图片，看它有多大，然后根据这个来拓展自己的
expands its frame to fit.
frame去适应它。
So that's clearly something I'm going to do every time I
这个很显然在我每次变更图片的时候希望
change the image I want to do that.
做到的。
So now you can see why I have this nice little convenience.
所以现在你知道我为啥要这么做了。
You can kind of think this is similar to
你可以把它想成setImage
having a function called setImage.
方法。
But it's just nicer to do it as a property cuz then I
但是把它当作属性这样处理更好，我同时有了 getter 和 setter，
get set and get and my code looks really nice.
而且代码更漂亮。
'Kay, so there's that.
这个完事了。
I'm also going to do viewDidLoad, okay?
下边我要实现一下 viewDidLoad 。
So viewDidLoad, we know that we of course need to call
首先，我们当然需要调用super,
super, and what I'm gonna do in viewDidLoad?
我要在 viewDidLoad 里做什么呢？
Well, I'm just gonna add my imageView to
我需要把图片视图加入到
the view hierarchy.
视图的继承树里。
Okay, I'm going to plop it right here.
我要把它放在这。
Again my storyboard, got this thing,
在我的storyboard里，要把这个视图
got my view as a top level view.
作为顶级视图。
I'm just going to add my view in here.
我现在要把图片视图加进来。
Now, I'm not doing a scroll view yet, okay.
到目前，我还没开始做滚动视图。
I'm going to do it without a scroll view, so
我现在要通过不使用滚动视图来实现，然后看看
we can see what that looks like.
是什么样的。
So I'm just gonna say view, addSubView, my ImageView.
我这里写 view.addSubView(ImageView)
Okay, and we know that this is fine to do because
这样做没有问题因为我们知道
viewDidLoad happens after pretty late in the process.
viewDidLoad 会在很晚才回被调用。
Now, I'm not doing anything here that's geometry based.
现在我做的事儿跟尺寸什么的没有关系。
I don't set any frames or anything like that, so this is
我没有设置frame或者别的什么，我就仅仅
just putting the ImageView in there with whatever frame it
把图片视图加了进来，并不管它的frame是多大，
has, either from the last sizeToFit that it got or
不论它从 sizeToFit得到的尺寸还是仍然是0，
it's still zero, zero because it's never been set.
0是因为它还没设置 frame 。
Okay.
So I'm just adding it as a subview there.
我仅仅是加了一个子视图而已。
Now, let's talk about what the model is in this
现在我们还看一下这个视图控制器的
view controller.
model是什么。
What is it's model?
它的model。
Look for the model right at the top here.
咱们把model加在最上边。
It's model is going to be into public.
model应该是公有的。
It's going to be a public resettable model,
应该是公有并且可以重置的，
which is an image URL.
它是图片的URL。
And it's just going to be an NSURL, so an NSURL is a class
类型是 NSURL，NSURL是用来存储 NSURL 的类，
that holds a URL, like http:// some Stanford.edu something
比如类似 http://Stanford.edu 的东西。
and that's going to be the model, and every time we
这就是我们的model，每次设置它的时候，我们就会得到
set the model it's going to get to that image and
它相应的图片然后把
put it in the view, okay?
图片放到视图里。
Everyone understand our nice model here.
大家都明白这个很棒的model了吧。
It's a very,
这是一个非常
this is a very well designed MVC it has a very clear model.
设计的非常好的MVC，有一个非常清晰的model。
It's clear what it does in its view.
model对于视图的作用也非常清晰。
So one thing that whenever our model is set,
只要我们的model设置了，
though, we want to make sure that we update our UI.
我们就希望UI可以确保被更新。
So when our, if we set a new image URL I'm immediately
如果我们设置了一个新的图片URL，我就会把现有的
going to set whatever existing image we have to nil.
图片设置为空。
Because we're changing it,
因为我们要变更图片，
and then I'm going to call a function fetchImage.
然后我要调用一个fetchImage方法。
Okay? And
fetchImage is just going to fetch the image that's in
这个方法会根据URL提取图片，
the URL, and load it up into my image view.
并把图片载入到图片视图里。
So, I need this private function fetchImage, okay?
所以我们需有一个私有方法 fetchImage 。
So let's talk about how we get an image from a URL.
下面我们看看如何从一个URL里提取图片。
If someone give me a URL, how do I get the JPEG image or
如果有人给了我一个URL，我如何才能得到JPEG图片或者
whatever that goes along to it?
里面的其他内容？
And it turned out to be quite simple.
非常简单。
First, I'm gonna make sure that my image URL is not nil.
首先，我要确保这个图片的URL不为空。
If someone asks me to load up nil,
如果有人要求我载入一个空的URL，
I'm not gonna do anything.
我就什么都不做。
So I'm just gonna basically ignore that.
忽略掉它。
So if it's not nil, so my URL is not nil, I'm gonna go and
如果不为空，我的URL不为空，我就要到
go out to the Internet, or if it was a local file,
网上或者本地，因为它也有可能是一个本地
it would be the local file, and get the image data.
文件，去拿到图片的数据。
So I'm gonna say imageData equals, and
这里写 imageData 等于
I can do that with the class NSData.
这里我要用 NSData 类，
And you'll remember NSData from a long-ago lecture,
也许你会记得 NSData 在很久以前的一堂课上讲到过，
maybe lecture three or four.
第三课或者第四课吧。
NSData is just a bag of bits.
NSData 就是一个装比特的包裹。
Right? So I'm gonna reach out on the
所以我现在要到网上
Internet and grab the bag of bits, which is this JPEG file.
把这个包裹抓下来，这个包里就是一个JPEG文件。
And I do that by using contentsOfURL initializer
这里用 contentOfUrl 这个初始化器
here, and I just give it the URL.
然后把URL传递给它。
So I can go out and get that.
然后我就在网上得到数据了。
Now this could return nil.
但是这个是有可能返回空值的。
What if I just gave it some bogus URL, 'kay?
如果我传递了一个假的URL呢？
There's no file there.
里边没有文件。
So let's check and make sure this is nil.
我们需要检查它是否为空。
So I'm gonna say if the imageData does not equal nil.
这里写 if imageData != nil
Why do I keep getting the caps lock there?
我怎么一直开着大写？
I'm not really sure what I'm doing there.
实在不知道我在干嘛。
ImageData does not equal nil,
ImageData 不等于空，
then I can do something about it, else, I can't.
然后我就可以对它做些什么了，如果为空，就不能。
So I could do if let, by the way, here, but
我可以写成 if let，但是我这么写
I'm doing it this way for a reason.
是有原因的。
You'll see a little bit later.
一会儿你就知道了。
So if the imageData's not nil, what am I gonna do?
如果imageData不为空，我要做什么呢？
Well, I need to turn that imageData, that bag of bits,
我要把imageData，装着比特的包裹，
into a UIImage.
转化成一个UIImage对象。
UIImage is the class in iOS that represents an image.
UIImage是iOS里展示图片的类。
So that's really easy to do.
I'm just gonna say,
in fact, I'm just gonna assign it to my image.
I'm sorry, we don't need self there.
I would say image equals UIImage with the data
being that imageData.
Okay?
Now, otherwise, I'm just gonna say my image equals nil, 'kay?
And, remember, this image equals something like this is
just calling this right down here to
set the image in our imageView or whatever, okay?
And then, of course, this needs to be unwrapped.
But we know we can unwrap it because I
checked to make sure it's not nil.
Okay, now, this line of code is a very bad line of code for
us because it might go out over the network.
Okay? I could be on cellular.
This might take ten seconds, or a minute, or it might just
fail because I have no network connectivity right now, okay?
So this is not a line of code we wanna be executing in
our program, but
we don't know what to do about it right now and I'm gonna
show you later in the lecture what we can do about it.
So, for now, we just got this kind of bummer line of
code here that's gonna be really slow.
Our app is gonna be really slow.
Although the network at Stanford here is so
fast that it probably won't even seem that slow, but
it will be slow cuz I'm gonna grab some pretty huge images.
All right, there's one other thing I wanna show here in
terms of view controller life cycle, though, which is,
if someone sets my imageURL, okay, and
I'm not on screen, do I really want to go and
start using up their cellular data plan, okay?
Probably not, 'kay?
You gotta remember that people don't have Stanford WiFi
internet everywhere.
Some people are using cellular, and it costs money.
So I am not going to actually fetch this
image unless I'm currently on screen.
So how do I tell if I'm currently on screen?
Actually I can do that with view.window does not
equal nil, 'kay?
So remember view is our top level view in our
controller's view ,and .window is the UI window it's in,
which will be nil if it's not currently on screen, 'kay?
But there's a little bit of a problem here,
which is what if I'm offscreen and someone sets my imageURL,
I don't fetch the image, and then I come on screen?
Aah!
Then I gotta fetch the image, 'kay?
So where does that happen?
Anyone wanna hazard a guess where I would put that code?
Nobody?
ViewWillAppear, exactly, very good.
So in viewWillAppear down here,
I'm gonna say super.viewWillAppear.
And then I'm just gonna say, if my image is nil,
then fetch the image, 'kay?
Now it could be that my image is nil because I
tried to fetch it and it failed, but
it's just gonna try again and fail, that's okay.
But, obviously, my image is not nil,
then I don't wanna fetch it again.
That would be wasting their cellular data even more, okay?
So here's a classic example of where we
would use viewWillAppear,
because we know it's worth it to go get that data,
because we know we're going to appear onscreen, 'kay?
Everybody understand that,
view controller lifecycle coming to life for you?
Okay?
So that's good. So let's go ahead and run.
So you, actually, let's go ahead and
put a default image in here.
I actually have some URLs.
I'm just gonna drag this DemoURL.swift in here.
And all this DemoURL.swift does is it just defines
a bunch of URLs that we're gonna use in our demo today.
So one of them is Stanford, right here.
So I'm going to load that up.
So in my viewDidLoad, I'm gonna say, if my image is nil,
then my imageURL equals my DemoURL.Stanford, 'kay?
So I'm just gonna,
in viewDidLoad, I'm gonna set my imageURL.
Now, it's not gonna actually load this until it
will appear.
That's okay.
But I'm just setting it right here, 'kay?
And I'm not, this is really for testing anyway.
I probably don't even need to do that just cuz we're gonna
remove this code once we start really not testing and
actually working.
So let's go ahead and run this and see what we got.
Oh, so it's not gonna work.
Okay, so this comes up, it's blank.
Why is this blank?
Well, let's look at our storyboard.
Here's the entry point to our storyboard.
It's this blank view controller.
Anyway, we don't want that.
Let's move them over here and have it
come into our view controller image view controller here.
Oh yeah, there we go, we got Stanford.
That's very nice, but can't scroll around, 'kay?
Oops.
I can't zoom, can't turn the pinch, nothing.
Okay, so I can't see it, 'kay?
Can't see anything.
So that's, obviously, we need a scroll view, all right?
So, let's go ahead and
first of all, actually, what should we do first here?
Let's do, let's enhance our user interface a little bit
more so we can pick other images.
I don't wanna just have this Stanford image, I wanna have
some different images that we can look around in.
So I'm gonna go over here and
drag out a split view controller.
Where's that split view?
Right here.
So let's drag out this splitViewController.
And, as usual, with the split view controller, I'm going to,
when I zoom out a little here, we can look at it.
I'm gonna delete a lot of the stuff that came with it here.
Keep that one.
We'll delete that.
I'm gonna have,
my image view controller is going to be the detail, 'kay?
So I made the detail.
I'm gonna make my entry point here be my
split view controller.
And I'm gonna have my master be this little one that was in
here before.
By the way, I just Ctrl+drag there and set this little view
controller that was there when we first started our app,
this blank view controller.
I can set it as the root view controller of
the navigation controller with Ctrl+drag and
pick root view controller here.
In your, in the demo and in your thing, we, you probably
did this in Editor > Embed In > Navigation Controller, but
you can also do it with Ctrl+drag, 'kay?
So now I have a nice UI here.
Comes up, shows my nice image view right there.
If I go back, here's my master.
So now, in this master, I'm gonna put some buttons so
we can pick different images to look at instead of
just looking at that Stanford thing.
So let's do that, really easy.
I'm just gonna grab some buttons here.
Let's do this.
Let's make the buttons really big,
maybe like 48 point, okay?
This button bigger.
And let's make three of them.
'Kay?
One of them is gonna be a picture of
the Cassini satellite.
Okay, that was sent out as Saturn.
Another one is gonna be a picture of Earth.
Another one is gonna be Saturn.
Okay?
So let's do a little bit of our favorite thing here,
which is auto layouts.
So put that one right in the middle.
Put that one right underneath.
This one right on top, 'kay?
I'm gonna try and reset to suggested constraints and
see how that works.
That didn't work very good, let's undo.
I think that's because,
let me make this thing be its normal size, that's why.
There we go.
'Kay?
Put these back.
Hopefully, this will, there we go,
Reset to Suggested Constraints.
Oh, still didn't work.
Okay, well, we'll fix them up, manually.
So this guy, right here.
oh, that's so bad, it's not even close.
Okay. So
I'm just going to do this all manually here,
going to uh-huh, sorry, wrong thing there.
Okay, Ctrl+drag, let's make it center vertically.
Let's Ctrl+drag and center horizontally as well.
Let's make this be vertical spacing.
We'll make this one be vertical spacing we'll have
these things share their center x, center x.
I think we're good to go there.
Yep, frames.
So, let's update our frames, less time.
Okay, there we go.
All right, so we've got some nice auto layout there, and so
now all we need to do is to segue when these are pressed.
We're gonna segue to our Image View Controller down here.
So let's set that up and just Ctrl+drag.
nope, Ctrl+drag, all right.
So I'm gonna show detail because in
the split view I want it to show up on the detail side and
on iPhone it's gonna push,.
So there's that one, let's go ahead and set its segue.
So this one I'll just call it Earth, 'kay, this one,
down here, show detail we'll call this one Cassini, and
with this one, show detail, we'll call that one Saturn.
Okay, so there we go, we've got a nice story board here,
we've got these segues all set up in here all
we need to do is prepare for these segues.
This View Controller right here, okay,
I'm going to select on this and go here to see its code.
So here's the code for that View Controller.
It's just this blank one that got created when we
created our app.
Okay, and all I need in this ViewController is
prepareForSegue, nothing more, so I'm gonna prepareForSegue.
Actually I'm going to make
this quite a bit wider here with these huge fonts.
And in here I'm going to see if it's a segue to
an image ViewController.
So I'm gonna say if I can let image view controller equal my
segue's destinationViewController as
an ImageViewController.
Okay, so we know we're segueying into
an image view controller.
Then if I can let the identifier equal
the segue's identifier, so the identifier's not null,
then I'm gonna switch on the identifier.
This code should all look very familiar to you,
and then in case of Earth, 'kay,
we are going to have to set the image URL, 'kay?
So ivc is an image view controller,
its public settable model is the imageURL.
So I'm gonna set that to DemoURL.NASA.Earth.
'Kay, I have a nice one ready to go there.
I'm also gonna set the title of that to Earth,
'kay, and then same thing here for Saturn.
It's image view controllers,
imageURL equals the DemoURL.NASA.Saturn.
ivc.title equals Saturn, and same thing for Cassini.
Let's see.
'Kay, and otherwise we will just break, and
do nothing, okay?
Everybody understand this code?
Hopefully it's completely familiar to you.
Nothing special there at all.
Okay, so I think that should work.
Let's try it.
Hopefully it didn't clean anything.
All right, so we go back, we've got these things.
Let's go ahead, oh,
my auto layout doesn't look very good there.
Probably messed that up, but anyway, close enough.
Let's go Earth, oh, it didn't work, okay?
That's because we have back here,
here in our engine controller, we have this test code here.
Let's get rid of that, right there.
Try again.
Right back now, let's look at Earth, and
look how slow this this, you see what I'm talking about?
Like, hello,
can't do anything, can't click on any buttons.
Finally, we get this and this does not look like
the Earth to me, looks like a bunch of dim photos.
I don't know what that is how about Cassini?
oh, we got the outer space part of Cassini right, but
that's all we can see because we need the scroll view now.
We absolutely have to have the scroll view.
These are big images so we can not see anything without it.
So let's go back and put our scroll view in here.
All right, so how are we gonna put the scroll view in here?
Well, I'm actually gonna put the scroll view in
using the storyboard.
So, I'm gonna drag a scroll view in.
That's kinda a simple way to do it.
So, let's bounce out here so
now we're back to our Image View Controller.
All right, this is our Image View Controller, and
I'm just going to drag out a scroll view.
I'm gonna search for
it, scroll, there it is, drag it out here.
I'm gonna place it so that it's right on the edges with
the blue lines right there.
I'm definitely gonna do Reset to Suggested Constraints.
I'm gonna make sure that works, which it did,
'kay, no magic numbers.
Everything looks nice right there, and now I
just need to put my image view inside this scroll view right.
So I got this scroll view here all I wanna do is put
the image view inside of it.
So how am I gonna put that imageView inside of it.
That's very, very, very simple I'm just going to
create an outlet to this thing.
Let's put the outlet right here.
Okay, I'm going to call the outlet scroll view, and
as soon as that outlet is set
in it's did Set I'm going to simply say to.
The scroll, well actually, we, you know,
we already added the scroll view.
Let me make this a little easier on you.
See right down here where we add the image view to
our view?
我们的视图？
Instead, I'm just gonna add it to the scroll view, 'kay?
相反，我只是把它添加到滚动视图中
So you can build your view hierarchy in view did load.
这样你可以在 viewDidLoad 中建立视图层次关系
It's actually a pretty good place to build it,
这里实际上是个很好的地方来创建它
cuz all your outlets are set, so we know this is set, and so
因为你的所有 outlets 都设置好了，我们知道这个已经设置好了
we can build our view hierarchy here, 'kay?
我们可以在这里建立我们的视图层次
So I just added the subview to there but I do actually need
我刚才已在那里添加了子视图，但实际上我
this didset here.
需要在这里调用 didset
I need again to make this wider so
我需要再次把这个变宽
you can see it because when I set my scroll view what's
这样你们可以看到，因为当我设置我的滚动视图时，
the most important thing to make a scroll view work?
让一个滚动视图工作最重要的事情是什么？
The content size, right.
contentSize，对吧
So when my scroll view gets set,
因此当我的滚动视图被设置了
I need to set the content size, so
我需要设置 contentSize
I'm gonna say scrollView.contentSize, and
所以我要设置 scrollView.contentSize
what size do I want it to be?
我需要设置怎样的大小？
Well I want the content size to be exactly the same size as
好吧，我需要 contentSize 和 imageView
the image view, so
的大小一致
I'm just gonna say imageView.frame.size.
我要设 imageView.frame.size
'Kay, now that's not, oops, equals.
这不是，等于
That's not the only place I need to do this, though, 'kay?
这里不是我需要做这个操作的唯一地方
Any time my image changes,
任何时候我的图片改变了
obviously my image view might change,
显然我的图片视图也可能改变
I need to change the content size of my scroll view.
我需要改变滚动视图的内容大小
So also here.
这里也需要
Inside the setter for image I need to set my scrollView's
在 setter 里面，我需要设置滚动视图的
content size equal to the imageView's frame size.
contentSize 等于图片视图的大小
Here I'm going to do something kind of interesting,
这里我要做些有趣的事情
which I actually did in auto layout demo after the fact
这是在我发布代码之后在自动布局
when I posted the code, but
例子中做的
I'm going to put a question mark right here.
但我要在这里放个问号
And the reason I'm gonna do that, it allows me to set my
我这样做的原因，我可以在内部设置
image internally, even if my outlets have not been set yet.
图片，即使我的 outlets 还没被设置。
I know that these outlets are implicitly wrapped optionals,
我知道这些 outlets 都是可选的
and of course that means that you can access them,
当然这意味着你可以访问它们
but the reality is you need to protect against the cases
但事实是你在这些变量可为
where those things might me nil.
nil 的情况下做些保护措施
Like setting your image,
比如设置你的图片
somehow, before that was your set.
某种方式，在你设置前
So, now I don't need to do it here,
现在这里我不需要了
because I'm in viewDidLoad.
因为我在 viewDidLoad
And I don't need to do it here because, of course,
我不需要在这里做这些，当然
it just got set.
它已经被设置了
But here, I'm going to do it just to be safe.
但这里，为了安全我需要做这个
Everyone understand that?
每个人都理解了吗？
Okay.
So, let's see.
让我们看看
It should work.
它应该可以工作
All right here we go, let's go try Cassini.
我们从这里，让我试试 Cassini
Slow, okay.
很慢
Oh yeah, look, oh stars.
看看，星星
Oh, what's that?
这是什么？
Oh, look at that.
看这个
Oh, sorry.
抱歉
There it is.
在这里
Oh, oh,.
It's a spacecraft of some sort.
这是某种太空船
Hard to tell, kay?
很难说清楚
We don't really get to see a lot of it, but
我实际上没看到它的大部分
[INAUDIBLE] Cassini.
Cassini
Okay, well obviously we need zooming, kay?
显然我们需要缩放
Because I can't see really what's going on here.
因为我不能看清楚这里所发生的
All right, so let's go back and add zooming.
让我回去，然后添加 zooming
Again, very straightforward.
非常简单
Remember, there's only two things you really need to do.
记住，实际上你只需要做两件事情
You gotta set that min max, and
你要设置 min 和 max
you gotta implement that delegate method.
然后你要实现代理方法
Great place to set delegate methods, of course,
这里是实现代理方法的好地方，当然
is in the setter of outlets.
在 outlets 的 setter 中
If you wanna set the delegate of an outlet, so
如果你想设置一个 outlet 的代理
I'm gonna set the scrollView's delegate to be myself.
我将设置滚动视图的代理为我自己
Of course I'm gonna have to say that I implemented.
当然我必须实现（代理）
That's the problem here.
这是问题所在
Okay.
We'll do that in a second.
我们一会就做这个
While I'm here I'm going to set the minimum zoom scale
这里，我将设置 minimumZoomScale
to 0.03.
为 0.03
This is a very,
这是张非常
very large image that we'll be able to look at here.
非常大的图片，我们可以在这里看到
And the maximum zoom scale to 1.0 and
然后 maximumZoomScale 为 1.0
maybe these don't wanna be magic numbers.
可能它们不想为神奇的数字
Maybe these want to based on the actual size of
可能它们想要根据图片视图的
the imageView.
实际大小
Okay?
So you might want to make it so
所以你可能想要让它
that you can perfectly zoom out to fit the scrollView or
完全缩小以适合滚动视图或
something like that.
其他类似的视图
But I'm just picking numbers here to
但我挑这些数字只是为了
make this code simpler.
让代码简单
So let's go fix the fact about the delegate here.
让我们修改下这里的代理
So I'm just going to go up here and say,
我要到这上面来，我要设置
oh yes, ImageViewController is a UIScrollView delegate.
ImageViewController 为滚动视图的代理
And, as soon as I say that,
一旦我设置了
this warning went away down here, but
这下面的警告就没了
I didn't get a new one that said, oh,
我没有另一个新的（警告）
you don't implement this.
你没有实现这个
And again, cuz this is the old objective C
因为这是老式的 objective C
style protocol where there's optional methods.
风格的协议，这是可选方法
So, I'm going to implement one of
我要实现它们中的一个
them though which is view for zooming in scrollView.
即 viewForZoomingInScrollView
Okay, as soon as I typed viewFor,
只要我输入 viewFor
it knew what I was talking about.
它知道我想输入什么
And I'm just going to return my imageView because that is
我只要回到图片视图，因为
the view that's inside the scrollView's content area that
它在滚动视图的内容区域中
I want to zoom on.
就是我想放大的
And that's it.
这就是了
That's all we need to do, so let's go run.
这就是所有我们需要做的，让我们运行下
Now we should be able to go and
现在我们应该能够
take a look at Cassini in all of its grandeur.
看到 Cassini 的全部华丽壮美
I'm just going to hold down Option so that I can pinch.
我要按住 Option 键，这样我可以捏（图片）
And I'm just pinching in here.
我在这里捏
Oh there it is. And let's go ahead and
这就是，让我们继续
rotate the other way.
旋转到其他方式
There we go.
我们看到了
So we can see it and zoom out a little bit.
因此我们可以看到它缩小了一点点
We can still scroll in addition to zooming.
我们依然可以在缩放的时候滚动
Okay? And let's go look at
让我们看看
this Earth thing so
这个 Earth 图片
we can figure out what the heck is going on with that.
现在我们总算清楚它在干什么了
So slow.
这么慢
Okay, so here it is.
这就是了
Oh, now we can move around and look at things.
让我们移动开，看看
Let's zoom in on this a little.
让我们在这里缩小一点
[INAUDIBLE] oh, whoa, it's the Earth.
它是地球
Woo, okay.
So, yes and as we can imagine, guess what this one is.
既然我们可以想象，猜猜这个是什么
Pictures of people.
很多人的照片
So this is actually made up of composites of images of
所以这个实际上是人们向 Cassini 挥手的
people waving at Cassini.
照片拼图
Kay they're taking pictures of themselves waving, see?
他们在挥手的时候拍的照片
Hello Cassini.
你好，Cassini
So that's what this composite is made of and
这就是这张拼图的内容
then I'll push in that Saturn out of there.
我要推动土星离开那里
'Kay so.
NASA, pretty cool.
NASA，相当酷
All right.
Okay, so that's good.
这很好
So that's all I'm gonna show for now.
这是我现在想演示的所有内容了
We'll get back and work on the fact that our app is really,
我们一会将返回，然后解决我们 app 相当相当慢的
really slow in a minute.
问题
Gotta show you some stuff first though.
先给你们看些材料
'Kay, any questions about that?
关于这个有问题吗
ScrollView's really easy to use, but you just
滚动视图很容易掌握，但你们
gotta know these particular things like the delegate and
要知道这些特别的东西，比如代理和
that min max zoom scale and that content size.
minmaxZoomScale 以及 contentSize
As long as you do those things,
只要你们做了这些事情
it'll work really great.
它就能工作的相当好了
All right, so a little aside here.
先把这些放一边
Just a two minute aside.
只是放一两分钟
I'm gonna rip through these slides about closures, but
我要讲讲这些幻灯片上的闭包
there's an important aspect about closure that
这是关于闭包非常重要的方面
you need to know.
你们需要知道
Kay?
Closures, when you have a closure in your code,
闭包，但你们的代码中有闭包时
it captures any variables that are used inside
它会捕获闭包中使用的任何外部变量
the closure from the outer scope, where the thing is,
这个是
which is a really cool feature.
是非常酷的特点
That's what makes it a closure really, okay.
这实际上也让它成为了一个闭包
Is that it captures them, okay.
闭包是这样捕获它们
You can make incredibly elegant code out of
你可以使用闭包写出难以置信的
this, okay.
优雅代码
Now here's where I'm going to
现在我要向你们演示
show you something about the calculator that if you
计算器的一些东西，如果你们
didn't do this in your assignment, that's good.
在你们的作业没做这个，没关系
Because in your assignment I wanted you to
因为在你们的作业中，我希望你们
use delegation, okay.
使用代理
However, sometimes closures can be a substitute or
然而，有时候闭包可以作为一种替代或者
a better tool to use than delegation.
是个比代理更好的工具
Lets look at this code right here.
看这里的代码
Lets say I have a class called grapher.
我有一个类叫做 grapher
I'm not going to say what kind of thing it could be
我不打算讲这是什么样的东西
because some of you haven't turned in your homework yet,
因为你们中有些还没把作业交上来
but lets say I had a grapher, okay.
但我有一个 grapher
And it doesn't have a delegate method or anything it just has
它没有代理方法或其他方法，它只有
a var called yForX whose type is a function.
一个变量叫做 yForX，它的类型是函数
A function that takes an x and returns a double.
这个函数有个参数 x，并返回 double
Okay?
Now that's an optional function.
这是个可选函数
That's fine, doesn't have to be set in this grapher.
这很好，在 grapher 中不一定需要设置这个函数
And then what if I just said,
然后如果我
well I'm going to let the grapher equal a new grapher.
让 grapher 等于一个新的 grapher 会怎样？
I'm going to let variable graphing brain be
我将让变量 graphingBrain 等于
a calculator brain instance I just created.
我刚刚创建的 CalculatorBrain 实例
Then I'm gonna set the program of the graphingBrain I
然后我设置我刚刚创建的 graphingBrain
just created to some other program that I wanna graph.
的程序为另一个我想要做图表的程序
Then I'm just gonna say yForX equals a closure and
然后我只要让 yForX 等于一个闭包
inside the closure it just says,
然后在闭包内部，只要
set the variable value to the argument to the closure and
将变量的值传递给闭包的参数
then return the graphingBrain at evaluate.
然后返回 graphingBrain.evaluate()
So do you see how by using this,
通过这个你们就知道怎么使用闭包
first of all we have grapher is completely generic.
首先，我们有一个完全普遍的 grapher
Knows nothing about a calculator brain.
对于 CalculatorBrain 一无所知
And yet we have this five line,
然后我有这五行
six lines of code to implement our graphing and
六行代码来实现我们的制图
it's all incredibly easy to kind of parse what's going on.
这一切都非常容易解析发生了什么
Now this works because the closure,
这个能起作用是因为闭包
that little thing in the curly braces,
即在大括号里的小东西
captured the little graphing brain that I created.
捕获了我创建的小 graphingBrain
Okay, so that every time disclosure is called,
因此每次闭包被调用
every time, you know, grapher one to yForX.
每次，你们知道的，grapher 一个给 yForX
It keeps reusing this graphing brain over and over and over.
它一直保持重复使用这个 graphingBrain
Which is exactly what I want because this
这正是我想要的，因为这个
graphing brain's got the right program in it.
graphingBrain 在它里面获得了正确的程序
It just keeps calling it over and over.
它只是保持不断调用它
It doesn't create a new one every time, it just keeps
它并不是每次都创建一个新的，它只是
reusing it because it captured it from the outer scope.
重复使用它（graphingBrain），因为它从外部范围捕获了它
Everyone understand what I mean by capture?
每个人都理解我所说的捕获了吗？
Now, this is really cool and really elegant,
这相当酷，相当优雅
it looks really awesome, it is awesome, but
看起来棒极了，太棒了，但
there are some dangers.
有些危险
Okay?
Capture danger.
捕获危险
The problem is, if a closure captures a pointer to
问题是，如果一个闭包捕获了一个指向某个东西的
something and that something has a pointer back to
指针，而这个东西有个指针指回
the closure, now you have a loop.
闭包，这样你们就有了一个环
A memory cycle that's going to keep them both in
一个内存周期，这将导致它们永远被
memory forever.
保留在内存中
Okay? Kind of
像
like the memory cycle we were talking about before.
我之前讲过的内存周期
This is easy to have happen in a closure.
这在闭包内很容易发生
This is what it looks like, so
它就像这样
here's another example here of closures.
这里是另一个闭包的例子
I've got this class called Foo.
我们称这个类为 Foo
It's got one property which is a function called action.
它有一个叫做 action 的函数属性
It's got another function called show,
它有另一个函数叫做 show
which takes an integer and shows it, prints it.
这个函数接收一个整型输入，然后输出它
And then it's got a method called setupMyAction, and
然后它有个方法叫做 setupMyAction
setupMyAction has a local variable, x,
setupMyAction 有个本地变量，x
which is an integer.
x 是个整型
That it assigns that action.
它分配了那个 action
[COUGH].
Function, property to a closure.
函数，一个闭包属性
Inside that closure it uses the x.
它在闭包里面使用了 x
That's cool, it captures x.
这很酷，它捕获了 x
This will actually work.
这将能工作
This will print 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
这将输出 1，2，3，4，5，6，7，8，9，10
You can see the doMyAction10times at
你可以看到下面的 doMyAction10times
the bottom.
函数
If you set up my action it will do it because the x
如果你调用 setupMyAction()，它可行，因为
gets captured by the closure and
x 已被闭包捕获，然后
every time the closure get executed.
每次闭包都被执行
[COUGH]. It increments that x and
它递增 x
counts to 10.
然后累计到 10
It's also cool because it's capturing self.
捕获本身也很酷
Because I'm using myself to show the number,
因为我使用我自己来显示这个数字
by calling self.show.
通过调用 self.show
But here's where the danger comes in.
但这也是危险的来源
Okay?
Because self has a pointer to the closure and
因为 self 有个指针指向闭包，然后
the closure inside has a pointer back to self.
闭包内部有个指针指回 self
Now, when you write a closure you'll notice that any
当你们写一个闭包时，你将注意到任何
time you call methods it makes you put self,
时候你调用方法，它都要你输入 self
makes you say self dot.
让你输入 self.
That's because it wants you to be clear.
这是因为它要让你清楚知道
You are capturing self when you call show.
在你调用 show 时，你正在捕获你自己
Okay?
Now, this is a problem, this class
这是一个问题，这个 Foo
Foo and this closure are pointed to each other, they
类，和这个闭包互相指向对方，它们
will stay in memory forever, they can never be released.
将永远保存在内存中，它们永远不会被释放
How do we fix that problem?
我们如何修复这个问题
Well, we can actually say,
实际上我们可以
when we make a closure, do not capture this variable in here.
当我们创建一个闭包时，别在这里捕获这个变量
Okay?
You do that by saying, [COUGH] unowned,
你通过使用 unowned 来实现
whatever the variables you don't want to be captured.
不管变量是什么，你都不想捕获
Okay? You just put it right at
你必须把它放在
the beginning of the closure, before the in.
闭包的最开始，在 in 之前
Okay? If you have arguments,
如果你有参数
you put it right before the, in, there.
你把它放在 in 前面，这里
That will make it work.
这样它就能工作
You can also say weak self.
你也可以使用 weak self
Which is a little different.
这个有点不同
That will make the self be a weak pointer in there.
这将使得 self 为一个弱指针
We learned about weak pointers in the lecture when we
在我们讲代理时我们学习了
talked about delegation.
弱指针
So weak would work, too.
所以 weak 也可行
It wouldn't do it.
它不能够
The difference between unowned is that pointer doesn't have
无主引用和弱引用的区别是，指针若不是一个
to be an optional that can be set to nil.
可选型，那么它可以被设置为 nil
It can just be anything.
它可以是任何东西
You just guarantee that self will never become nil.
你只要保证 self 永远不会变成 nil
So, for the lifetime of this closure,
因此，在这个闭包的生命周期
self can never become nil.
self 永远不会变成 nil
Okay?
Now, self can be released from the heap,
现在，self 能够在堆中被释放
which will release the closure now, from the heap.
这将从堆中释放闭包
That's great, but
非常棒，但
that closure can never be executed while self,
在 self，即 Fool 为 nil 时，闭包将
this Foo thing, is nil.
永不被执行
Which is fine, because it's only used inside Foo,
很好，因为他只在 Foo 内部使用
[COUGH] That would never happen.
这永远不会发生
Okay?
Unowned self.
无主 self
This is all covered in the documentation that you
这全都可以在文档中查阅，你们
were supposed to have read, but, you might have
应该读过了，但，你们可能
not really understood this, or glossed over it, so I'm
没真正理解它，或忽略了它，因此我
just revisiting it to tell you that [COUGH] It's important.
只是重新审视它，告诉你们这很重要
Okay. Because we're going to
因为我们将在这门课程中
start using closures more and
越来越多地使用闭包
more in this class and you will be capturing values and
你们将捕获变量
some of them will point back to the closure.
Okay?
[COUGH] Okay, that's it.
Next is multithreading.
Okay. Yes, question.
Is there an example, could you give
an example other than self where it would point back?
I think about that swift reference document has a whole
big, long example, so I would just refer you to that.
Any other questions about that?
[COUGH] Okay.
Multithreading, how many people in here have done some
programming in a multithreaded environment before?
More than half, that's more than usual, so that's good.
All right, then this will all be pretty easy for
you to understand.
Those of you who haven't, it will be a struggle.
The first time you do it, I'm sure all of you can attest,
it's a little bit harder to understand what's going on.
It's actually fairly simple.
What's going on here is, in iOS there are multiple queues.
A queue meaning like a queue at
the movie where people lined up to go see a movie.
A queue in a computer science sense is just a list of things
where things go into the front of the queue, go into the back
of the queue rather and they get pulled off the front.
It's a queue of functions, basically closures usually.
Okay.
That are sitting there waiting to run.
Each of these queues has it's own threads to run
these queues, to process the things on the queues.
That makes this a multithreaded environment.
Now, there's a very,
very important queue called the main queue.
This main queue is a serial queue, meaning it
pulls these functions off the queue one at a time.
It never runs [COUGH] Two of them at the same time.
Okay. They're serial, one at a time.
And all UI activity has to happen on the main queue.
So if you ever wanted to have a function or closure,
that is executing some code, that did anything with the UI,
you have to put it on the main queue.
It can only execute on the main queue.
This is how basically the UI is protected
from getting messed up in the multithreaded environment.
It has this main queue.
Okay? So the main queue,
very, very important.
The main queue never wants to
be doing anything that might block NS data contents of URL.
That should never be in the main queue.
So we're going to have to get that off the main queue.
All the code that you write normally in
your NBC that's all happening on the main queue.
View did load, view will appear, all that stuff,
all happening on the main queue automatically for you,
you don't have to do anything special.
Okay?
But, there are other queues that iOS will create for you
as you need, and we're going to show you how those work.
First of all, how do execute a function or
a closure on another queue?
Well, you do that with this function [COUGH] Called,
dispatch_async.
Okay?
So you say dispatch_async, the argument,
there's two arguments, a queue and a closure.
The first argument is the queue.
I'm using the trailing closure syntax here to
put the closure outside the parentheses there but
you just specify what queue you want to
execute the closure on and then you pass it to closure.
Okay? And the closure takes no
arguments, returns no arguments and that's it.
That's how you do it.
Couldn't be easier.
dispatch_async on the queue you want.
So how do you get the queue that you want?
Well, you get the main queue using this function
dispatch_get_main_queue and that returns the main queue.
There's also an object-oriented way to do it,
NSOperationQueue.mainQueue.
You got this queue and
here's an example of putting something on the main
queue dispatch_async, [COUGH] notTheMainQueue,
something, and then inside there [COUGH] You could
say dispatch_async_main_queue.
This is how you do multithreading programming.
Those lines of code right there.
I want to do something that doesn't block the UI, so
I dispatch it to notTheMainQueue,
some other queue,
[COUGH] I'll talk about how to get those queues in a second.
Then I do it, go do something like NSdata contents of URL,
blocks, whatever.
When it's done, I need to talk back to the main queue to
update my UI with the image I got or something like that.
The way I do that is [COUGH]
I dispatch back to the main queue.
So you nest these calls to the dispatch.
Okay?
You're basically running code on another queue and when
it wants to dock back to the main queue it just posts or
puts some code back on the main queue.
Now, the main queue might be busy.
But when it's done it's a serial queue but
eventually it will get to this block and it will run it.
Okay?
Everybody understand that?
That's it.
It's so simple really, actually when you see it,
it's almost too simple.
The code, when you write it, it's so simple you
can get confused and forget that you're in a multithreaded
environment, but this is really, those lines of
code you're seeing right there at the bottom, that is
the fundamental multithreaded programming syntax in iOS.
How do you get these other queues,
you don't want to run on the main queue.
You get a queue from the system by asking for
a certain quality of service.
And the four qualities of service,
there's user interactive,
which is I'm going to do something off the main queue,
but the user really wants this done fast, and
it's not going to take very long.
So do it right now.
Okay? So it's a high
priority queue for things that go really fast.
Then there's USER_INITIATED which is the user just
asked for this, but I know it's going to take a long time
fetching an image off the network,
we would USER_INITIATED, but it's still pretty important.
Then there's utility, which is I'm just doing something.
The user didn't just ask me to do this.
But it's just something I
need to do in the background processing things or whatever.
But it is something that matters right now to the user.
So it would be nice if it returned somewhat soon, but
it's not like got to have it.
And then there's background which is like things that
are not concerned with what the user is doing right now.
Like oh I'm pre-fetching some data, updating some database,
cleaning up a database, doing stuff in the background.
It really has nothing to do with the user doing now,
you understand what I mean?
Just background task.
So you create a quality of service,
you do that with this really odd int.
One of these constants above there,
.value, close parentheses, okay.
For historical reasons, they have them put a nice,
new UI in there Swift, which is interesting.
But anyway, you do that.
And then you just say,
queue equals dispatch_get_global_queue with
that quality of service, comma 0.
That comma 0 is reserved for future use, okay?
And that's it.
Now you have another queue.
You can now dispatch async to it, and
be running code off the main queue.
Simple as that.
You can create your own serial queues too.
I'm not going to talk about that really, but
you might have something where these queues that I'm
talking about at the top,
these quality service based ones, are concurrent.
So actually a single queue, like the user interactive
queue, could actually have multiple threads running,
working on it at the same time.
If you have a multi-core processor they can
even actually be working on them.
But mostly it's time sharing,
time slicing between the various threads.
But, anyway, you can do a serial 1.
And you would do that only if you wanted to do something off
the main thread that something depends on the next things,
depends on the next things.
So you want to want to do them serially or
you want to throttle.
Like you're fetching a bunch of images, but
you don't want to bombard, you know,
Flicker or whoever you're requesting the images from
with hundreds of questions.
You're just going to do them one at a time.
And they're going to appear in the UI one at a time.
So you can do your own
serial queues with dispatch_queue_create.
Okay?
You can also use the multi-threading stuff to
do something in the future.
Okay? You do that with
this dispatch after.
It's kind of odd again.
The arguments are kind of weird, you do this nth 64
delay in seconds times double insect per min insect per
milliseconds dispatch time now delay, blah blah.
You create this basically time dispatched_time t
that is in the future and then you just say
dispatch after that amount of time on to the main queue.
So you're almost always doing dispatch after on
the main queue.
It's rare that you'd be on another queue
because those other queues are kind of
concurrent running queues and such.
Anyway it's more likely, I want to put up an alert in
ten seconds if the user hasn't done something, or
something like that.
Which is kind of a weird UI, but anyway.
You never want to block the main queue saying oh wait,
20 seconds and then it will be able to do this.
But you want to be able to notify it.
And there's tons and
tons of stuff that I'm not even going to talk about, but
you can do readers and writers.
You can protect critical sections of
your code doing this.
You can do synchronous dispatch.
Okay, instead of asynchronously firing these
things off to put on the queues.
You can wait for them to execute.
All that stuff.
You won't need any of that for this class probably.
The things I showed you, that's the basics of it.
That's probably all you're going to need.
'Kay?
There are APIs in iOS that are multi-threaded.
So, you've got to be careful.
If you're doing something, and
it seems like this might be multi-threaded,
this seems like it might take a little while,
like it's gonna access the network or
something like that.
Then you want to read the documentation and
see, are you giving it a block, for
example, that's going to be executed off the main thread?
Because in that block, if you want to do something with
the UI you have to post back to the main thread.
Okay? So here's what
that looks like for example.
Here is an API, this is the NSURL session API.
The thing in yellow is all that really matters.
It lets you download a file from a URL.
And it does it asynchronously.
And you give it a block, which is the completion handler.
So when it's done, it invokes your block,
and it's got some arguments there.
It moves the file to a local URL that you can open.
You get HTTP response, you can get an error, et cetera.
So, you want to do something in there to update the UI,
cause you got the file back, and can you?
No, you can't, because that's not on the main queue,
however you can put dispatch async in there.
Okay, so this is exactly the same code,
I just add dispatch async in there.
All right?
So that's example where you dispatch a.
That is the exactly the same thing as I showed you on that
very first slide, it's just that it's wrapped inside an
iOS API instead of just your own dispatch to another queue.
Okay.
All right so.
Again, a demo's worth of vowels and words.
So let's go look what it looks to make an Imaginarium there.
Or Christini I guess I called it this time.
Let's make this thing be multi-threaded.
So we know that it's really bad UI, it blocks every
time we ask for these big images, it's completely stuck.
So where we fetch the image right here,
we need to be doing that on a different thread.
All right? So how are we
going to do that?
We'll we're going to do exactly what I
did in the slides there.
Which is I'm going to create one of these quality of
service things here, okay.
First of all, I don't need to do
anything if my image URL is nil.
So if it's not nil though,
then I'm going to let my quality of service equal,
let's go ahead and do this so you can see lots of code here.
All right,
I'm gonna select this quality of service to this weird thing
int and the quality of service I want is going to be this
user initiated because the user has asked for something.
It's not gonna be quick,
but I want it to be done as soon as it can.
Because the user's waiting for it basically.
So that's gonna be my quality of service there.
And then I'm just going to say dispatch, async.
The queue I want is a global queue, so
I'm going to say get global queue.
I'm gonna actually use a different one of these,
hold on.
Identifier global queue.
And use this one,
which is the one that takes the quality of service there.
So quality of service.
Not caps, Q O S, there we go.
The flags are always zero there, and here's my block.
All right?
So let's double-click to do that.
I'm going to put that outside, you know,
the trailing closure syntax here I'm going to use.
Now inside here, now I can do the things that slow.
So, let's put all of this inside here, to start.
Even though we know that's not going to be good.
All right?
So, I dispatched async in here.
Notice that it's already complaining that you gotta put
self in here.
That's because I put this inside of a closure.
And it's capturing self because I'm accessing my
image bar here.
All right, so I can fix that one.
Let's go ahead and do that here as well.
Extra parenthesis.
Okay, so that's good.
Now, this is fine,
this is that thing that's going to be slow.
It's happening on another thread right now,
that's great.
But this is not great because here, this is going to
cause UI stuff to happen all over the place, right?
Look at all this UI stuff it's going to do.
So I cannot do this on this thread.
So I just have to dispatch it back to the main thread.
The main two actually, and
again I'm going to use the trailing closure syntax there.
That's exactly why they designed it that way.
All right, so
now I'm dispatching back to the main queue.
That's good and all is well.
And that's it.
That's all it took.
So you can see the multi-threaded, it's like,
after you've made it, except for this weird end thing.
It made about the minimal amount of codes you could
possibly be.
All right, this is not quite right,
we're not quite done here, but
let's go see if this has fixed our problem at least.
So here we are, so I'm going to go Earth.
Now look, I can go back.
My UI is completely active.
I can do anything I want,
even though it's still loading that thing in the background.
And eventually, once it's kind of sucked it all down,
it shows it to me, and I can zoom in on it.
Here we go.
Okay, so that's exactly what we want.
And it took virtually no code on our part.
However, it's not quite right.
And if you have experienced multi-threading, you're gonna
immediately understand what I'm talking about here.
This is kind of lulls you into thinking,
oh I got this right okay ready to go next problem.
But what happens if this image data takes a long time to
come back and in the mean time the user asks for
a different image.
Well, we argue, I can't do that of course because we
segue to and from so we are always creating new nvc but
imagine a new nvc that stayed on screen.
And there was a way to click a button and
it would load a new image.
Well, this thing might come back after the next request
and show the user the old image they wanted instead of
the new one they'd asked for.
Do you see the problem?
So, this is where modern
threading gets a little hard on your brain.
It's like, oh, what?
These things are happening in a different order
because they're happening in different threads,
different threads of execution here.
So how do we fix that?
It's actually fairly simple to fix.
When this image data comes back, okay,
we're just gonna check and see if the URL that caused it
to be fetched is the one we currently want.
So I'm just going to go here and say, if the url, which is
this url right here, which was captured by this, okay?
So if this url up here equals self.imageURL, in other words,
the url that my user currently wants,.
Then I'm going to do this.
Otherwise I'm going to
completely ignore this response.
Okay, this JPG file came back but the user has moved on.
They don't even care about this.
So you see what I'm talking about, where you've got to
think a little bit with this multithreader.
You can't just throw the code in there and
go, oh yeah, it works.
You have to think about things might be happening,
taking a long time, cuz they're happening separately.
So that's good.
There's really nothing to show there because our UI doesn't
really allow us to specify a different image.
When we click back and forth in our UI,
we're creating a new MVC every time because we're segue.
So the new MVC is obviously got its own environment.
So the last thing I want to show you is our UI is not
very good because it has a lot of blank white screen in it.
Okay, right here, blank white screen, it's like oh,
blank white screen, what's going on?
Mm, I don't know, what's happening here?
I don't know.
You see what I mean, it's like
I can't even tell what's really going on in my UI.
It'd be nice if when I clicked here I
got like a spinning wheel that would say I'm working on it.
I'm trying to get that thing, okay.
So we want a nice little spinning wheel in here.
So how do we do the spinning wheel?
Spinning wheel, very easy to do.
We're going to go to our story board right here.
Screen realty management is a challenge on
this small screen.
And I'm just going to drag out a little spinning wheel
into my UI.
And this is a great chance for me to
show you a little bit of how to use the document outline.
And you'll see why.
So here the spinning wheel is called the activity indicator.
So I'm going to type activity, there it is.
Little spinning wheel, drag it out, and going to put it here.
Now when I drag that out, it kind of looks like okay good,
works, got a spinning wheel on there, I'm ready to go.
But actually,
something very bad happened when I dragged that out.
And if I look in the document line, I'll see what it is.
Which is that this spinning wheel
was added as a SubView of the ScrollView.
Because I dragged it out on top of the ScrollView, so
it added it as a SubView so
that mean it's going to be in that content area.
We don't want that, we want this thing to be floating on
top of the scroll view.
It's very hard to fix it in here.
Cuz it's like where do you drag it?
The scroll view's everywhere.
You can't get it.
So this is what the document outline is great for.
Watch this.
I'll take this right out of the scroll view.
Boom, it's out.
Now this puts it behind the scroll view,
because I told you the subview's list,
the top things are in the back.
So I'll just put the scroll view on top.
So now I have the scroll view in the back,
indicator in the front.
Okay?
What about constraints?
Oh, the constraints here are hard to put too,
because every time you kind of drag,
it keeps dragging it to the scroll view.
Well, I can do constraints in here as well.
Let's drag the indicator view up to
the view above the scroll view.
Right, our NVC's view.
And I'm just going to say I want this to be centered
horizontally and vertically in that view.
Boom, I've set the constraints now for
that totally using the document outline.
Now lets do one other thing with the indicator.
I'm going to inspect it over here and
you can see the indicator has some different styles.
We like grey because we
have a white background so that's good.
But it also has a couple buttons here and
this is a good one to click, hides when stopped.
That makes it so
when the spinner stops spinning it hides itself.
So it's only showing while it's spinning,
which is kind of a nice feature.
You can cause it to show and
hide yourself, but it's nice to have it hide itself.
All right, so we have this nice little spinner here, so
let's go ahead and hook it up into our UI.
And I'm just gonna Ctrl+Drag, even control dragging from
this can be a bit of a pain, because it's very small and
you got all these constraints in the way.
So you can actually Ctrl+Drag from over here.
All right so I'll Ctrl+Drag, I'll put it right here.
I'm gonna call it spinner.
I like to call my activity indicators spinners but
you could call it activity indicator too.
So here's my spinner and
what do I need to do with this spinner?
Well, I just need to
start it spinning when I make a request, and then I
need to stop it from spinning when the request is fulfilled.
Okay?
So I'm going to do that.
And I want to get lots of room here.
So I've got my spinner, well, where do I make a request?
Let's see, it's right here.
Right. This is where I dispatch
request so I'm just gonna say spinner, start animating.
But I'm gonna make that even better,
I'm gonna say question mark,
in case we're fetching an image before our
outlets are loaded.
For some reason, we don't currently do that cause we
only do it in view will appear.
But you know some day someone might write that code.
And then I could stop the spinner like down in here but
actually a great place to stop the spinner is as soon
as an image is set.
Anytime an image gets set I don't want to be spinning,
by definition.
Right?
So I'm just going to say spinner.stop animating.
Okay?
And that's it.
That's all it takes to the do the spinner.
So let's go take a look at the spinner spinning.
All right so the spinner didn't spin at
start because I haven't made any requests.
But here if I make a request there's the spinner spinning,
and yeah you can make the spinner larger if you want but
it's spinning, it's spinning cuz we're still working on
it and once the thing appears now my spinner's gone.
It's kinda hard to tell in the dark spots but here in
the light spots you can see that our spinner is gone.
'Kay same thing we come back, click on this one,
spinner comes back, right?
And I can't scroll it.
There's no scrolling or anything like that.
And then once our thing appears right here,
our spinner is gone.
Okay?
So that's it for today.
Questions?
What about the self referencing and.
Yeah so let's look at the self referencing thing.
Did we have a problem with
self referencing inside this closure.
That we did right here, and the answer is no,
because nowhere inside this closure do we refer to
anything that points to this closure.
Cause this closure just got dispatched a synced,
right it got put on some queue somewhere, but
we don't point to it anymore.
The queue points to it basically,
the queue owns this closure, we self don't.
So we're okay, we don't have to do any unknown.
But you'll start seeing the unknown thing when we
start doing animation.
When we start having actions in the animation that
are calling methods inside of our class to do animation, so
you'll see that there.
Okay? That's it, thank you.
For more, please visit us at Stanford.edu.